四

星期天一般被用来进行神圣的对三位一体的各种礼拜仪式，星期一用来礼拜圣灵，星期二礼拜守护神，星期三礼拜圣约瑟夫，星期四用来进行圣坛上最能得到神宠的圣餐仪式，星期五礼拜受难的耶稣，星期六礼拜受神恩的圣母玛利亚。

每天早晨他都在一个神圣的神像前或某种神秘的仪式上再次净化自己的灵魂。他每天一开始就英勇地把他度过的每一个时辰的思想或行动明确地提出，希望获得主教的关心，每天一早就参加一次弥撒。冷清的早晨的空气更加强了他的坚定的虔诚的信念。常常当他和很少几个礼拜的人跪在旁边的圣坛前，翻开自己的插着白页的祷告书，跟着神父低声念诵诗词的时候，他抬头看看站在象征《新约》和《旧约》的两支蜡烛间的阴影中的、打扮齐全的神父，不禁感到自己仿佛是跪在那里参加一次在地下墓穴中进行的弥撒。

他每日的生活都是在宗教气氛十分浓厚的地方度过的。通过向上帝的呼号和祷告，他毫不吝惜地为许多在炼狱中的灵魂争得了以日计、以月计或以年计的悔罪的日子，那些日子加起来都够好几百年了。然而他这样轻易赢来的难以想象的许多世纪的悔罪期使他感到的精神上的胜利，并不足以完全补偿他祷告时所付出的热情，因为他永远也不知道，他这样为那些受罪的灵魂代做祈祷，究竟能减少他们多少肉体上的惩罚。他担心在那和地狱之火的唯一差别仅在于并非永不熄灭的炼狱之火中，他的悔罪所能起的作用恐怕也只不过是杯水车薪而已，因此他不得不强迫自己的灵魂每天进行更多的超过上帝要求的善举。

他以现在看来是他生存所必须尽的责任来把他的时间加以划分，并让划分出的每一部分时间都围绕着自己的一个精神中心。他的生活似乎越来越接近永恒了，他的每一个思想、每一句言论、每一种行动和头脑中的每一个思绪似乎都可以在天堂中闪耀光辉了。有时他对这种直接发生反响的感觉是那样鲜明，竟使他感到他的无比虔诚的灵魂似乎已经可以像手指一样按动一个巨大的现金自动出纳器的键盘，并看到他直接送入天堂的财富的数量，但他看到的不是数字，而是缕缕上升的香烟的烟柱或娇嫩的花朵发出的气息。

他还经常念诵玫瑰祷词——因为他总把念珠拆散了放在裤兜里，这样他在街上行走的时候也可以祈祷——那念珠都变成了似非尘世所有的各种花冠，它们在他看来似乎不仅无名，而且也变得无色和无味了。他每天在神前念完他的三串念珠的祷词，以求得他的灵魂在神学所要求的三种品德方面能够一天比一天更坚强起来，一是加强对于曾经创造他的天上的圣父的信念，一是加强对于曾经为他赎罪的圣子的希望，一是加强对于曾经为他牺牲的圣灵的热爱。他通过圣母玛利亚，以她的欢乐、悲愁和光荣的神秘仪式的名义，向那三个神灵每日三次进行他的三重的祷告。

在每周七天中的每一天他都进一步向圣灵祷告，希望他的七种神恩之一能够降临于他的灵魂，并从他的灵魂中一天一天驱走过去使它堕落的那七种可怕的罪孽。他祈求每一种神恩都会在它指定的那一天降临，并且相信它一定会降临到他的身上，虽然有时他也觉得这似乎有点奇怪，为什么智慧、理解和知识在性质上竟要分得如此清楚，以致这三者都必须一个个单独地祈求。可是他也相信等到他的精神生活发展到将来某个阶段的时候，这个问题将会自动得到解决的，到那时他的犯罪的灵魂将会摆脱出从前的软弱地位，并得到至高无上的三位一体中的圣灵的启示。由于看不见的圣灵居住的地方是那样幽深和宁静，他因此对这一点更是怀着极大的敬畏，也更加相信。圣灵的象征是一只柔顺的鸽子和一阵猛烈的巨风，谁要是对圣灵犯下罪孽那是永远无法得到宽恕的，他是一种永恒的神秘莫测的神明，所有的神父每年都要像对上帝一样穿上绘着火舌的红色的袈裟为他举行盛大的弥撒。

在他读过的各种劝人皈依上帝的书籍中，他已经约略看到表现三位一体的三个神灵的性质和关系的形象——圣父像对着一面镜子一样对着永恒，默想着他自己的无比完善的神威，因而永恒地产生了永恒的圣子，接着圣灵也就从永恒的圣父和圣子产生出来了——由于这一形象具有神妙莫测的威仪，对他的头脑来说，比那种认为上帝从无限的永恒以来，在他降生到这个世界上来的几个世纪以前，在这个世界开始存在多少世纪以前就已经热爱着他的灵魂的那种简单的说法，似乎更容易接受多了。

他曾经听到过在舞台上和讲台上郑重其事讲出各种爱与恨的名称，他也曾看到许多书郑重其事地提出那些名称，但他一直纳闷儿为什么他的灵魂却任何时候都感到对这些名称难以容忍，也无法强迫自己口服心服地说出这些名称。他自己也常常被一种短暂的愤怒所笼罩，可是他从来也不能让那种愤怒变成一种长期包围着他的情绪，而总是感到自己很快就从那种情绪中解脱出来，仿佛那不过是自己身上很容易剥去的一层外壳或一层皮。他曾感到有一种微妙、阴暗、喃喃低语着的东西钻入他的生命中去，并在他的心中燃起短暂、邪恶的淫欲，这种淫欲常会逃过他的控制，使得他的心灵变得清澈而冷漠。这个，似乎是在他的灵魂中唯一可能出现的爱和恨。

但是既然上帝自己从无限的永恒以来已经用他神圣的爱一直热爱着他的灵魂，他现在不能再对爱这个现实加以否认了。慢慢地，当他的灵魂的精神方面的知识越来越丰富的时候，他看到整个世界已逐渐变成了上帝的神威和爱的巨大而匀称的体现。生命已经变成一种神赐，为它所经历的每一时刻和它的每一种感受，哪怕只是对悬挂在一根树枝上的一片小叶子的一瞥，他的灵魂也应对它的创造者表示无限赞颂和感谢。现实世界虽然具有那么多实在的物体，虽然是那样的复杂，而对他的灵魂来说，它除了作为神威、爱和无所不在的神性的表征而外，便不复存在了。他的灵魂对神意的各个方面的了解是那样完善和无可怀疑，他简直难以理解他还有什么必要再继续生存下去了。但那必然是神的意旨的一个方面，至于目的何在，像他那样一个对神的意旨犯下比任何人都更为深重的罪孽的人，又如何敢提出这个问题呢。他的灵魂由于意识到这永恒的、无所不在的、完善的现实，已变得更为温顺和谦恭了，它于是又一次负担起通过弥撒、祷告、圣餐和悔罪以体现自己的虔诚的责任，也只有到这时，自从他开始思索爱情这个巨大的神秘的主题以来，他才第一次感到有某种温暖的东西，仿佛是灵魂本身的新生的生命或某种新的品德在他的心中活动。对神圣的艺术感到狂喜的神态、微微分开举起的双手、仿佛一个快要晕倒的人的微微张开的嘴唇和眼睛，对他来说都变成了在造物主前变得十分谦恭和软弱的正在祈祷中的灵魂的形象。

不过，对于精神上的狂喜可能带来的危险，他是早就有所警觉的，他从不容许自己在任何时候对上帝的虔诚有些微的减退，并随时以强烈的悔恨来清洗自己的罪孽的过去，但他无意使自己达到充满危险的圣洁的地步。他尽力十分严格地约束着自己的每一种感官。为了制服他的视觉感官，他定下一个规矩，在街上走路的时候永远两眼看地，绝不向左、向右或向后看一眼。他的眼神永远避免和任何一个女人的眼神相遇。有时他还必须依靠自己的顽强意志来阻挠它们的活动，好比在一句话还没有念完的时候就得忽然抬起眼来把书合上一样。为了制服听觉的感官，他对他当时正好嘶哑的嗓子完全采取听之任之的态度，他既不唱歌也不吹口哨，而且对那些使他的神经痛苦不堪的噪音，比方在砂轮上磨刀，用煤铲在地上铲煤渣，或用树枝打地毯等的声音从来绝不逃避。他感到在制服味觉的感官方面遇到的困难更大一些，因为他发现对于任何难闻的味道他都没有本能的厌恶感，不管是外在世界的像粪堆和烧焦油等的恶臭，或者他自己身上的各种臭味都完全一样，对他自己身上的各种气味他已经做过许多离奇的比较和实验了。最后他发现使他的嗅觉十分反感的唯一一种气味，是某种像长久存放的人尿一样的腐烂的臭鱼的味道，因而只要情况许可，他就让自己老闻着这种难闻的气味。为了制服他的味觉的感官，他在饭桌上严格地坚持一套办法，对于教堂斋戒的规定一字不落地加以执行，而且尽可能分散自己的思想，使自己不要去注意任何菜饭的味道。然而，他的最突出的创造发明的才能还是表现在他制服他的触觉的办法上。他睡在床上的时候从不有意识地改换姿势，坐时也一定采取最不舒服的姿势，他带着悔罪的心情忍受着身上任何地方的搔痒和疼痛，冬天远离火炉，在做弥撒的时候除了宣布福音的那一部分之外他始终坚持双膝跪下，擦脸时总让自己的脸和脖子上有些地方不完全擦干，以便受到冷空气的刺激，以及任何时候如果没有数着念珠祈祷，他就一定让自己的双臂像长跑运动员一样僵硬地悬挂在自己身体的两旁，而不把它们插在自己的口袋里或者背在背后。

他并没有受到重犯那重大罪孽的诱惑。但使他吃惊的是他发现，在长时间采取这种复杂的表现虔诚和自我克制的活动以后，他却很容易犯下许多毫无意义的孩子的过失。他的祷告和斋戒对于压抑自己的愤怒的感情并没有任何帮助，常常因听到他母亲打个喷嚏或者有人打扰了他对上帝的祷告，他就会十分生气。常常需要使用巨大的意志力才能抑制住自己的冲动，不至于为这种可厌的干扰大发脾气。他过去常常注意到他的老师们因一点小事发脾气时的形象，比如像他们的扭动着的嘴、紧闭着的嘴唇和涨红的脸，现在这些又出现在他的眼前了，尽管他曾那样尽力深自贬抑，在两者相较之下，却仍使他感到十分沮丧。要让他使自己的生活汇入别人生活的洪流，对他来说比实行斋戒或整日祈祷还要困难得多，也正因为他常常不能做到这一点，因而对自己感到不满，所以最后在他的灵魂深处出现了一种精神干枯的感觉，同时也滋生了许多疑虑。他的灵魂曾经经历过一段困苦不堪的日子，那时候，圣餐仪式本身似乎都变成了已经干枯的源泉。他的忏悔变成了许多使他良心不安的未能悔改的过失得以逃避的通道。他实际接受一些圣餐，并不能使他经历一个使他心情豁亮的纯贞的自我弃绝的时刻，像他参加某些神圣的圣餐会，临近结束时有时获得的那种精神上的交流曾经带给他的那种感受。他在参加这种仪式时所使用的是一本圣阿方萨斯·尼戈里所写、长期被人忽视的很破旧的书，那书已是字迹模糊，纸张也都发黑并且满是黄斑了。在这本书里，赞歌的意象和圣餐参加人的祷告词交织在一起，他每诵读这本书，便似为他的灵魂召唤来一个充满爱的热情和纯贞感受的已完全凋枯的世界。一个听不见的声音似乎在安抚着他的灵魂，告诉她许多名字和光荣的事迹，告诉她站起来离开这里去寻求婚配，告诉她从阿玛纳和从豹群聚集的崇山中，怀着寻求配偶的心情向前观望(1)，而他的灵魂似乎也用一种同样的听不见的声音加以回答，并表示愿意献出她自己的一切：Inter ubera mea commorabitur．(2)

这种贡献自己的一切的思想对他来说具有一种充满危险的诱惑，因为他现在感到，他的灵魂又一次被一种始终不停息的肉欲的声音所扰乱，那声音在他祈祷和沉思的时候又开始在他的耳边出现了。这使他强烈地感到自己十分强大，因为他知道他要是愿意，他只要改变一下自己的思想，就能够马上全部推翻他所干过的一切。他似乎感到一个缓慢前进的水浪正朝着他的光着的脚边流过来，而他正等待着那微弱、胆怯和无声的浪花接触到他的发烧的皮肤。然后，几乎就在他接触到水浪的那一刹那，几乎就在他刚要罪恶地表示同意的时候，完全靠自己的意志作用或者说靠自己猛地一声惊叫，他发现自己已经远离那水浪，站在一片岸上了。接着，看到那水浪的银色的边缘已经离他很远，看到它又开始慢慢朝他的脚边流来，他知道他并没有屈服，并没有使自己前功尽弃，于是又十分激动地为自己的坚强感到颇为满意。

在他这样多次避开那洪流的诱惑之后，他的心情越来越烦躁，自己也弄不清他这样尽力不肯丢失的神圣是否已经一点一点被剥夺掉了。自信自己从此一尘不染的明确信念现在已越来越模糊，随之而来的是一种模糊的恐惧，他担心自己的灵魂实际在不知不觉中已经堕落了。为了恢复他过去相信自己正受着神恩庇荫的信念，他不惜费尽力气一再对自己说，他每次遇到任何诱惑的时候都曾向上帝祷告，相信他所祈求的神恩一定会降临到他的头上，因为在那种情况下上帝也不能不使他的祈祷得到满足的。诱惑的经常发生和它的强烈，最后都使他完全相信据说圣徒们都曾经受过各种考验的真实性。频繁和强烈的诱惑足以证明他的灵魂的堡垒至今还没有陷落，因而魔鬼才仍然不断对它进行攻击。

常常，每当他对自己的各种疑虑进行忏悔之后——说自己祷告时走神了，说自己在灵魂深处曾经因为很小的事发过脾气，或者在自己的言语或行动中表现了自己的执拗等——他的忏悔神父总要他把他过去的罪孽再拿出来说一遍，然后才为他进行赎罪仪式。他只得带着极大的羞辱重新述说一遍，并再次对那些事表示一番悔恨。特别使他感到羞辱的是，他现在看来，不管他过着如何神圣的生活，或者不管他在品德方面达到如何完善的境地，他都永远也不可能完全清洗掉过去的罪孽了。一种令人不安的犯罪感将永远存在于他的心中：他将忏悔、悔恨，然后得到赎罪，再忏悔，再悔恨，然后再得到赎罪，但永远也不会有最后结果。也许那头一次因为对地狱的恐惧逼得他匆匆做出的忏悔是不符合上帝的意旨的？也许当时由于他只是担心迫在眉睫的天罚，所以他对他的罪孽并没有表现出真正的悲伤？但是，证明他真诚忏悔以及他对自己的罪行确感深切悲伤的最可靠的证据，他知道，应该是在生活上的改过自新。

——在生活上我已经改过自新了，难道不是吗？他对自己问道。

那忏悔神父站在窗口，背向着阳光，一只胳膊靠在棕色的十字窗帘上。在他含笑低语，一边用手摆弄着另一个窗帘的绳子，用它套圈玩儿的时候，斯蒂芬站在他的面前，眼睛不停地看着外面屋顶上愈来愈暗淡的长夏的日光，或者看着那神父慢慢移动着的灵巧的手指。神父的脸完全隐在阴影里，可是从后面照过来的即将消逝的日光却正照在他深陷的太阳穴和两边弧形的头骨上。斯蒂芬也竖起耳朵注意倾听那神父断断续续的谈话声，他这时正在严肃而热情地谈着一些无关紧要的问题，刚刚结束的假期，国外教会学校的情况，以及教师们调动工作的情况。他用一种严肃而热忱的声音非常随和地讲着这类故事，而每当他停下的时候，斯蒂芬总感到自己似乎有责任提出一两个郑重其事的问题，让他再继续讲下去。他知道这些谈话不过是个序幕，他在思想上一直在等待下面的正文。从他一得到忏悔神父要他来见他的消息以后，他便一直绞尽脑汁想弄清他到底找他干什么。在他坐在大学的客厅里长时间不安地等待忏悔神父来临的时候，他的眼睛一直不停地观望着悬挂在四面墙上的一张张神态安闲的人的图片，从这一张看到那一张，各种猜想也一个接一个在他的脑子里闪过，直到最后，这次召唤他的目的他几乎已经完全明白了。接着，正当他希望某种预想不到的原因可能阻止忏悔神父前来见他的时候，他却听到了转动门把的声音和长袈裟摆动时发出的沙沙声。

忏悔神父一开始谈到多明我会和方济各会教会里的情况，还谈到圣托马斯和圣博纳凡契尔之间的友情。方济各会僧侣的服装，他认为，未免太……

看到那神父表示宽容的微笑，斯蒂芬的脸也对他露出一丝笑意，他并不想立即发表自己的意见，所以他只是表示怀疑地轻轻动了动自己的嘴唇。

——我相信，忏悔神父接着说，在方济各会的僧侣们之间，他们自己也在谈论要抛弃这种服装，也按照方济各会神父的样子穿上袈裟。

——我想在修道院里他们还会保留这种服装的，不是吗？斯蒂芬说。

——哦，当然，忏悔神父说。在修道院里那种衣服当然是可以穿的，可是在街上我想最好不要再穿那种衣服吧，你说呢？

——这衣服穿在身上一定让人感到十分麻烦，我那么想。

——当然麻烦，当然是。想一想我在比利时的时候，就常看到他们一年四季就穿着这种齐膝盖头的衣服到处转悠！那样子实在太可笑了。用比利时语说，他们叫它Les jupes(3)。

他在念这个字的时候把母音完全吞掉，几乎听不清他说的是什么了。

——他们叫它什么来着？

——Les jupes．

——哦！

由于神父的脸完全背着亮光，他并没看见他的微笑，但斯蒂芬仍然对他一笑作为回答，因为在神父低沉审慎的话语送入他的耳鼓时，他似乎感到在自己心灵中迅速掠过了神父鬼影一般的淡淡的笑意。他沉静地观望着眼前愈来愈暗的天空，凉爽的晚风以及可能掩盖住他脸颊上火烧一般的红晕的淡黄色的晚霞都使他感到很高兴。

女人所穿的各种服装，或者她们用来做服装的各种柔和纤细的衣料的名称，他只要一听到总仿佛立即闻到一种细腻的浸透着罪孽的香味。还是孩子的时候，他便一直想象驾驭马匹的缰绳都是柔和的丝带做成的，因而当他在斯特拉德河第一次摸到十分油滑的皮辔头时，他简直吓呆了。他第一次用他发抖的手指摸着一个女人的扎乎乎的长袜子的时候，他也同样感到非常吃惊，因为他过去所读过的一切东西，除了仿佛是他目前的处境的回音或者预言的那部分之外，他几乎全都忘记了。但对于具有娇柔生命的女人的灵魂或肉体，他却不敢设想，除了在轻柔的词句中或在玫瑰花一样的环境中之外，还可能在什么别的地方存在。

但出之神父之口的那句话显然是不诚实的，因为他知道一个神父不应该这样随便谈论这个问题。他所以随便这样讲显然是别有目的的，他还感觉到躲在阴影中的那双眼睛正不停地扫视着他的脸。不管他曾经在书本上读到，或者听人说过耶稣会会员多么狡猾，他一直都坦率地不予相信，因为他觉得没有得到他自己的经验的证实。他的老师们，即使他们中有些他也并不喜欢，他却觉得似乎都是些聪明和严肃的教士，都是些身体健壮和精神高超的教职人员。他想着他们都是每天毫不发怵地用冷水洗澡，并穿着清洁和冰凉的亚麻布内衣的男人。他在克朗戈斯或在贝尔维迪尔和他们一起生活的那么多年中，他仅仅挨过两次打，虽然那两次他都认为他们对他是很不公平的，可是，他也知道，他曾经好些次理应受到惩罚，结果却让他逃脱了。在所有那些年中，他从未听到他的任何一位老师讲过一句不负责任的话：是他们使他知道了许多基督教的教义，劝导他过着高尚的生活，而当他犯下了可悲的罪孽的时候，也是他们引导他又回到虔诚的生活中来。他在克朗戈斯长时期一事无成，是由于他们那些人的存在使得他对自己失去了信心，当他在贝尔维迪尔感到自己所处的地位暧昧不明的时候，也是他们的存在使他对自己失去了信心。这种感觉一直到他度过最后一年学校生活的时候，还始终存在于他的心中。他没有一次表示不服从，或者曾让那些爱闹的同伴引诱他放弃自己对一切都曲意服从的习惯。有时甚至他对某位老师所讲的话感到怀疑，他也从来没有公开表示过。到后来，他们的某些判断他听着觉得颇为幼稚，但那也只是使他感到某种遗憾和不安，仿佛他现在正慢慢离开他所习惯的那个世界，以后将再没有机会听到那个世界所使用的语言了。有一天，在小教堂旁边的一个棚子里，几个孩子围着一位神父闲谈，他听到那神父说：

——我相信麦考利男爵(4)这个人也许一生从来没有犯过任何重大罪行，我是说从没有有意犯过什么大罪。

有一个孩子问那神父，维克多·雨果是否可算得上是法国最大的作家。那神父却回答说，维克多·雨果本来是一个天主教徒，他后来却背叛了他的宗教，背叛以后他所写的东西的价值，和从前所写的相比，简直连一半也赶不上。

——可是，也有许多出色的法国批评家，那神父说，他们认为维克多·雨果虽然肯定是一位伟大的作家，可是和路易·弗尔约(5)相比，他缺乏一种纯法国风味的风格。

神父的暗示在斯蒂芬的脸上再次燃起的火烧一般的红晕现在又慢慢平息下去，他于是仍然抬起眼一声不响地望着窗外惨淡的天空。可是有一种使他不安的疑虑在他的脑海中翻腾。蒙上面具的回忆迅速在他的眼前飘过：那情景和人物他全都认识，然而他清楚地感到，他并没有能够完全理解他们的某些重要性。他看到他自己在操场上来回走动，观望着在克朗戈斯进行的体育活动，并用自己的板球帽装着一些稀薄的果酱在吃着。圆形的跑道上有几个耶稣教徒和几位妇女一起在散步。在克朗戈斯经常使用的某些特殊语言的回音，从他头脑中某些遥远的山洞里传了出来。

在客厅宁静的空气中，他正侧耳倾听着远处传来的回声，可是这时他注意到那神父开始用另一种声音和他讲话。

——我今天派人叫你来，斯蒂芬，因为我希望和你谈一个非常重要的问题。

——哦，先生。

——你一直以来有没有感觉到你得到了某种神示？

斯蒂芬微微张开嘴唇本来要说是，但很快他又把那个字吞了进去。神父等待他回答，接着又说：

——我是说，你有没有在内心深处，在你的灵魂中，感到有一种要加入教会的愿望？好好想一想。

——我有时候也想到过这件事，斯蒂芬说。

神父把手里的窗帘绳放开，让它落到一边去，然后他把两手交抱起来，支撑着下巴，严肃地思索着。

——在像这样一所学院里，他最后又说，总会有一个也许两三个孩子得到上帝的召唤，让他进入宗教生活的。这样一个孩子的特点是，他比他的同伴们都更虔诚，他给其他的同学做出了很好的榜样。他们都很尊重他，他的同教会的教友们也许会把他选出来当级长。而你，斯蒂芬，在这所学校里正可以算得上是这样一个孩子，你是我们圣母教会的一个级长。也许你正是这个学校里上帝打算要召唤去为他服役的那个孩子。

一种强烈的自豪感更增强了那神父说话的严肃性，这情况使得斯蒂芬的心急剧地跳动起来。

——接受这样一种召唤，斯蒂芬，那神父说，是全能的上帝所能加之于人的最大的荣誉。在这个世界上，没有一个皇帝或一位帝王具有上帝的传教士的权力。在天上，没有哪一位天使或天使长，没有哪一位圣徒，甚至连圣母自己都没有上帝的传教士所拥有的那种权力：他掌握着力量的钥匙，他有能力让人犯罪和清除人的罪孽，他有驱除邪恶的能力，他有能力从上帝创造的人的心中驱逐能用魔力控制他们的邪恶的精灵。他还有能力，有那种权力让伟大的天上的上帝来到人间的祭坛上，以面包和酒的形式在人的眼前出现。这是多么了不得的权力啊，斯蒂芬！

他听到这一段骄傲的讲话，恰好和他自己常有的骄傲的思想相共鸣，斯蒂芬的面颊上马上感到热乎乎的。他曾多少次看到过自己已变成一个教士，安详而谦恭地行使着连天使和圣徒都感到无比敬畏的那种可怕的力量啊！他的心灵一直都非常喜欢偷偷用各种假想来满足他的这种欲望。他曾经看到他自己变成一位年轻而态度安详的教士迅速地走进一间忏悔间，走上圣坛的台阶，点燃香，双膝跪下执行着一个教士的职务要求他执行的一些活动，那些活动使他很高兴，原因是它们很像现实而同时又离现实很远。在他所度过的这种冥思遐想的朦胧生活中，他曾经极力模仿他所见过的许多神父所使用的声调和手势。他学着某一位神父在跪下时微微侧着身子，又学着另一位神父在摇动香炉的时候摇得那么轻巧，在他向听众祝福后又转向圣坛的时候，他也仿照另一位神父的神态把他的十字褡一甩让它敞开。而特别使他高兴的是，在那些他所想象的模糊的景象中，他始终只担任着二号人物的角色。他完全不愿意享有主祭人的荣誉，因为在他的想象中，要让所有那些寓意模糊的仪式都由他本人来结束，他可很不感兴趣，再说他不愿意看到自己在那套仪式中随便就被委派一个如此明确的最高的职位。他愿意承担较低的神圣的圣职，在大弥撒中穿着副主祭的祭服，站在离开圣坛较远的地方，不为大家所注意，肩上披着长方形的丝披肩，手里端着用披肩掩盖着的圣餐盘，或者等到祭祀过去以后，他作为副主祭穿着金色的主教的法衣站在主教下面的台阶上，交抱两手面向会众唱着，Ite missa est(6)。如果说他也曾想象着自己是一位主祭，那只是在他翻开儿时的弥撒书看着上面有关弥撒的图片的时候，在那里的那个教堂里除了接受牺牲的天使以外再没有任何其他的崇拜者，圣坛上也光光的什么都没有，作为他的副手的也是一个几乎和他完全相像的孩子气的助手。只有在这些模糊的祭神和参加圣餐的各种行动中，他的意志似乎才真正和现实相接触。他过去或者用沉默掩盖着自己的愤怒或骄傲，或者遭受急于想和人拥抱而又不得其便感到的痛苦，至少部分原因是缺少一种他一直强迫自己躲避参加的既定仪式。

现在在这庄严的沉静中他听到那神父向他提出的请求，通过他讲的那些话他甚至还听到一个更为清晰的声音吩咐他走过去，提出要使他获得神秘的知识和神秘的力量。那样，以后他就会知道西蒙·马加斯(7)究竟犯了什么罪，以及对圣灵犯下什么样的罪行才是永远无法得到宽恕的。他将会知道许多其他的人，所有那些在神怒之下孕育和出生的孩子所无法知道的神秘的事情。他将会知道别人的罪孽、别人的罪孽的向往、罪孽的思想和罪孽的行动，听到妇女和姑娘们在阴暗的礼拜堂的忏悔间里忍着极大的羞辱亲口低声对他讲出她们的罪孽。而他自己经过那样被举手加封之后，便立即神秘地变得对一切罪孽都一尘不染，他的灵魂将会仍然保有原来的清白，再回到雪白的圣坛边去。他将举起用以掰开圣餐面包的双手是绝不会被任何罪孽所玷污的，罪孽也绝不会玷污他将用来祈祷的嘴唇，使得他把自己的一切天罚都吞下、咽下，不去管里面是否掺杂有上帝的圣体。他将永远像刚出生的婴儿一样纯洁无辜，因而也将永远保有他那秘密的知识和秘密的权力，而且根据最高神灵的祭司梅尔基塞德克的命令他将永远是一位教士。

——明天早上我准备主持一次弥撒，那位忏悔神父说，让全能的上帝可以向你透露他神圣的意旨。也让你，斯蒂芬，为你的神圣的保护神，那第一位殉道者进行一次九日祈祷，你的保护神在上帝面前说话是非常有力量的，他可以请求上帝让你头脑清醒。可是，斯蒂芬，你必须非常肯定，你的确是接受了神示，因为如果事后你发现你并没有得到神示，那将是不堪设想的。必须记住，你一旦接受了教士的职务就将一辈子是一个教士。你的教义问答也告诉你，对任何神圣的圣旨一个人一生都只能接受一次，因为你接受以后它将在你的灵魂中留下一个永不磨灭的精神的印记，这种印记是永远无法消除的。在事前你必须慎重考虑，不能等到事后。这是一个十分严肃的问题，斯蒂芬，因为这关系到你的永恒的灵魂是否可能得救。不过还是让我们一起来向上帝祷告吧。

他推开沉重的大厅的门，并向他伸过手去，仿佛他们在他们的精神生活中已经是亲密的伙伴了。斯蒂芬来到外面台阶上宽广的阳台上，明确感到一股柔和的晚风使他精神为之一爽。在芬勒特教堂那边有四个年轻人手挽手大踏步走着，领头的人正用手风琴演奏一支轻快的曲子，他们摇晃着脑袋踏着拍子向前行进。正和很多急骤的音乐的首段常会发生的情况一样，那音乐很快便侵入他的头脑，像一阵巨浪冲毁孩子们修建的沙楼一样，毫无痛苦地、不声不响地立即使他头脑中的神秘而复杂的结构归于瓦解。他转过在微风中含笑的脸，抬头看看神父，却在他的脸上看到了那即将消失的一天的毫无情趣的反照，然后他从那神父的手中缓缓抽出了他似曾默认某种伙伴关系的互相拉着的手。

他迈步走下台阶，从学校的大门前看到了那即将逝去的一天的毫无情趣的虚假的反照，这情景终于消除了他混乱的思绪。接着，学校生活的严峻的暗影从他的意识中飘了过去。那将是一种严肃的、有秩序的和毫无热情的生活，一种没有物质上的烦恼的生活在等待着他。他想象不出他将如何度过见习期的第一个夜晚，也想象不出当他第一天早晨在宿舍里醒来的时候自己会感到何等的惊愕。他又一次闻到了克朗戈斯漫长的走廊上的令人心烦的气味，又一次听到了燃烧着的煤气灯发出的审慎的低语。忽然间，一种不安的感觉完全笼罩住他生命的每一个部分。接着他发烧的脉搏也加快了跳动的速度，这时他听到一连串毫无意义的刺耳的话语声把他极有条理的思绪搅成了一片混乱。他的肺向外扩张而下沉，仿佛他吸进了一种潮乎乎的没有浮力的热空气，这时他又一次闻到了在克朗戈斯浴池肮脏、浑浊的水面上浮动着的潮湿、闷热的空气。

随着这些回忆，某种比教育或虔诚的思想还更为强大的本能，在他向那种生活步步靠近的时候，迅速地在他的心中滋长起来，这是一种微妙的反抗的本能，它给予他一种力量，使他不甘再默认下去了。那种生活的冷漠和谨严都使他感到非常厌恶。他已经看到他自己，在一个寒冷的清晨起来排着队和别人一起去参加一次早弥撒，毫无作用地拼命想用祷告声压住他从心眼儿里感到的难堪的恶心。他看到他自己和学校里的会众坐在一起吃饭。使他从不愿意跑到生人家去吃喝的那种根深蒂固的羞怯感现在到哪里去了？那种使他永远把自己看成在各方面都与众不同的精神上的优越感现在哪里去了？

耶稣教会神父斯蒂芬·迪德勒斯。

他将在新的生活中使用的名称以文字的形式跳到他的眼前来，紧跟在它后面的是在他头脑中出现的一张没有明确轮廓的脸或者只是一种脸的颜色。这颜色先慢慢淡去，后来又越变越浓，变成了浓淡不定的红砖一般的土红色。这就是在严冬的早晨，他常常在神父们刚刮过的腮帮上看到的那种红兮兮的光泽吗？这张脸没有眼睛，脸色阴沉而虔诚，明显地露着压抑住的愤怒。曾经有一个耶稣会的神父，有些孩子叫他长下巴颏儿，另一些孩子又叫他狐狸将军，这是否就是他那张脸的鬼魂在他的头脑里出现了呢？

他那时正走过加德纳街耶稣会的会址，心里模糊地想着，他如果接受了那个教职，将来不知哪一个窗户将是他的住房所在。接着他又想到刚才那些想法实在无聊，想到他的灵魂离他一直为她设想的一个修行之所实在相当遥远，想到这么多年来一味循规蹈矩、一味服从的生活对他的约束力竟是如此薄弱，现在仅仅一个明确的、不可挽回的行动已经在威胁着，要在一定时候，永远永远地剥夺掉他的一切自由了。那神父一再劝导他接受随着那教职而来的值得骄傲的教会的权力和神秘的力量的那些话，现在又有气无力地在他的记忆中回响。可是他的灵魂并无心再去倾听那些话，更不用说对它表示欢迎了，他知道他曾听到的那些规劝的话现在已变成一种无聊的故事到处流传了。他永远也不会作为一个神父在圣体盘前面晃动着香炉。他命定对一切社会或宗教上的职务都将采取逃避的态度。那神父所讲的那一套明智的做法完全不能打动他的心。他命定不用任何人的帮助自己去弄清楚到底什么是明智的做法，或者在经历了世界上的各种陷阱之后，自己去学会别人的明智做法。

这世界上的各种陷阱就是它的犯罪的道路。他一定会堕落的。他现在还没有堕落，但是到了某一个时刻他一定会一声不响地堕落下去。要永远不堕落实在太难了，太困难了。他现在已经感到，他的灵魂正不声不响地向下滑去，正像将来某一个时候一定会发生的情况一样，往下滑，往下滑，但是还没有堕落，现在还没有堕落，可是已经快要堕落了。

他走过了托尔卡河上的大桥，又一次转过脸来对那圣母的神龛冷冷看了一眼，那颜色已经退去的蓝色的神龛，像一只鸟一样蹲在那个贫穷的外形像火腿的村舍中间的一根旗杆上。接着，向左一拐弯，他走进了通向他家的一条胡同。从河岸边高地上的菜园子里飘来烂菜叶淡淡的酸臭味。想着他父亲家的这种杂乱无章、无人管理和混乱的情况，这种停滞不前的植物一般的生活却将会赢得他的灵魂，他不禁微笑了。接着由于想到在房子后面菜园子里干活的孤独的长工，这个人他们曾给他取个诨名叫作帽不离头，一阵短促的笑声不禁脱口而出。在第一阵笑声停息之后，由于想到帽不离头干活时的情景，第二阵笑声竟又违反他的意愿从他口中冒了出来，他在干活时，总要先仔细观察好天上四面的方位，然后才带着十分遗憾的心情把锹蹬进园子里的土壤里去。

他推开廊子上没有门闩的门，通过一条什么东西也没有的走道向厨房里走去。他的一群兄弟姊妹正围着一张桌子坐着。他们刚刚吃完午茶，只剩下一些冲过第二遍的茶底还留在他们拿来当茶杯用的一些玻璃罐和果酱罐里。桌上到处是些乱扔的面包皮和一块块带糖的饼干，这些东西由于浸泡在撒在桌上的茶水里已经都变成棕黄色了。桌上一个个小坑里都积满了茶水，一个已经吃掉大半的卷饼上面，插着一把象牙把已经破碎的餐刀。

那即将死去的一天的蓝灰色的宁静而悲伤的余光，透过窗户和开着的门照了进来，掩盖住并不声不响地减缓了斯蒂芬心中忽然出现的难堪的悲痛。他们长期求之而不得的东西，现在他——众弟兄中的长兄，却很容易就能得到了。但是那黄昏的安静的余晖却让他看到，他们脸上并没有任何怨恨的痕迹。

他走近他们，也在桌边坐下，问他们父亲和母亲到哪里去了。他们中一个回答说：

——去那个到那个看那个房子那个去了。

还要搬家！在贝尔维迪尔一个叫法龙的孩子常常带着一脸傻笑问他，他们为什么老是搬家。现在当他再次听到这个问话人的傻笑的时候，一阵轻蔑的乌云很快掩盖住了他的额头。

他问道：

——我们为什么老是在搬家？我想我这样问问总没有什么不可以吧？

——因为那个房那个东那个要那个把那个我们那个赶出那个去了。

坐得离火炉最远的他的最小的一个弟弟开始唱起《每当夜深时分》来了。接着其他人也一个一个跟着唱，直到所有的人组成了一个合唱队。他们常会接连几小时，一个歌接着一个歌，一个曲子接着一个曲子，就这样唱下去，直唱到白天的暗淡的日光已经在地平线上消失，直唱到第一片黑色的夜云在天空飘过，夜幕降临的时候。

他静听着等了一会儿，然后也跟他们一起唱起来。他怀着极大的精神上的痛苦听出，在他们的脆弱而清新的天真的歌声里实际隐藏着一种疲惫不堪的情调。甚至在他们走上生活的道路以前，他们对那条路似乎就已经感到非常厌倦了。

他听到从厨房里传出的这合唱队的歌声，回荡着，越变越强，慢慢和无数世代的孩子们的合唱队融混在一起了，在那无数的回声中，他还听到一个永远重复着的疲惫而痛苦的回声。他们全都似乎在进入生活以前便已对这生活无比厌倦了。他还记得纽曼在维吉尔的残缺不全的诗行中也听出了这种情味：让我们像造化本身的声音一样，尽情表达出孩子们的痛苦、疲惫，然而又总抱着希望的那种心情吧，这正是她的一切男女在任何时候共有的经历。

他不能再等待了。

从拜伦酒馆门口走到克隆塔夫教堂门口，从克隆塔夫教堂门口又走到拜伦酒店门口，然后又走向教堂，然后又走向酒店，他一直就这样来回走着，起先很慢，在那露着一片片修补痕迹的人行道上小心翼翼地迈着步子，让自己的脚步和着诗行中的每一个降音。他父亲和丹·克罗斯比一道去替他打听关于上大学的事，现在已经整整一个小时了。整整一个小时，他就那样来来回回地走着，等待着：可是他现在实在没法再等下去了。

他匆匆向一家酒店那边赶去，他走得很快，生怕他父亲的一声尖叫又会把他叫回来。不一会儿他就转过了警察兵营边的那个拐角的地方，他现在已经不再怕他父亲叫喊了。

是的，他母亲对那一套想法根本不同意，他从她不安的沉默中完全可以看出她的心事。然而她的那种不信任却比他父亲的骄傲神态使他触动更深，他冷漠地想到，他早已看到在他母亲看来日益老练和日益坚强的灵魂所具有的信念实际上已逐渐减弱了。一种模糊的敌对情绪在他心中慢慢滋长起来，它像一片云彩一样模糊了他对她不忠的思想，但等到这情绪又像云彩一样飘过、他的头脑又变得非常清醒而且恢复了对她的孝心的时候，他却模糊地但毫不遗憾地意识到，在他们的共同生活中已出现了第一个不声不响的裂痕。

上大学！那么说，他是偷偷溜过了守护着他的童年处境的那一排岗哨了，他们一直极力要让他和他们待在一起，这样他就会听从他们的管束，按他们的愿望行事。在获得某种满足后产生的骄傲像一排缓慢而宽大的浪头把他高举了起来。他现在尚未能看清的他为之而生的目的引导他从一条看不见的道路上逃了出去，而现在它却又招手让他回来，并在他面前展现了一条新的冒险的道路。他似乎听到一段阵发的音乐的音调，一会儿跳上去变成一段乐曲，一会儿又降下来变成了减四度和弦，一会儿又跳上去变成一种乐调，一会儿又降下来变成第三大调，那神情很像夜半森林中的三条火舌的火焰，一个火焰接着一个火焰忽高忽低地跳动。这仿佛是妖姬的音乐的序曲，无头无尾也没有一定的形式。等到它越变越狂野，节拍越来越快，仿佛那火焰已跳出时间观念之外的时候，他似乎听到树荫下的青草上有许多野兽在赛跑，它们的脚步发出的噼啪声，像雨点打在树叶上一样。它们的脚步发出的混乱的噼啪声在他的头脑中响了过去，其中有家兔和野兔的脚步，有公鹿和母鹿的脚步，还有羚羊的脚步发出的声响，直到后来他再也听不到那脚步声却只记起了纽曼的一句节奏鲜明而强烈的诗：

——他的脚在他的永恒的手臂之下完全像公鹿的脚一样。

这一模糊形象所表现的骄傲情绪又使他想起了他曾经拒绝的那一教职可能带来的威严。在整个孩子时期，他常常想着担任教职是他最后的归宿，可是现在到了要他服从这一召唤的时候，他却服从一个更带有野性的本能，逃避开了。现在时机已经错过：任命教职的神圣膏油将永远不会涂在他的身上了。他已经拒绝了。为什么？

他离开多利蒙特的大路朝海边走去，走过薄木板的桥面时，他感到桥板在他穿得很厚的沉重的脚下摇晃着。一队基督教的弟兄们正从酒馆那边走过来，他们排成双行已经开始过桥了。很快整个桥梁都抖动着，发出隆隆响声。他们的不整洁的脸一对一对地从他面前走过，那脸由于海风的侵袭都染上了发黄或发红或青灰的颜色，而在他试图安详地不动感情地观望他们的时候，在他自己的脸上却出现了一种淡淡的羞怯和同情的神情。这使他对自己十分生气，因而他为了避开他们的眼神转过脸去，侧身观望着桥下起着漩涡的清浅的水流，但尽管这样他从水的倒影中仍然看到他们的高顶的绸帽、朴实的翻着的衣领和宽大的牧师服装。

希基兄弟。
奎德兄弟。
麦卡德尔兄弟。
基奥兄弟。

他们的虔诚一定像他们的名字一样，像他们的脸面一样，也像他们的衣服一样，他没有必要对自己说，他们的那种谦恭和悔恨的心，非常可能，表现了比他从未表现过的更大的虔诚，对他们那种朴实的礼拜，上帝乐意接受的程度恐怕十倍于他那种矫揉造作的虔诚。他用不着敦促自己对他们慷慨一些，也用不着对自己说，如果有一天他抛弃了骄傲的情绪，潦倒不堪，穿着一身乞丐的衣服来到他们门前的时候，他们一定会对他非常慷慨，而且像爱他们自己一样爱他。最后，他还带着既觉得无聊而又痛苦的感情，违反自己一向认定的论点，认为爱的戒条吩咐我们不要使用和爱自己同样数量和同样强烈的爱去爱我们的邻居，但是要用和爱自己同样性质的爱去爱他们。

他从他自己一向珍藏的一些词句中挑出一句，柔和地自己念叨着：

——这一天充满了从海上漂来的斑驳的彩云。

这句成语、眼前的日子和眼前的情景似乎形成了一个和弦。语言。这就是它们的颜色吗？他让那各种各样的颜色：朝日的金黄色、苹果园里的黄褐色和绿色、海浪的蔚蓝色、羊毛般云彩的银灰色等一个接一个亮起来，又暗了下去。不，这不是它们的颜色：这是这个时代本身的姿态和风貌。难道他对于语言的抑扬顿挫的热爱更甚于它们的色彩和它们跟一切传说的关系吗？要不就是由于他视力微弱、思想羞怯，通过五颜六色、内容丰富的语言的三棱镜所表现出来的光辉灿烂的世界的缩影，还不如观赏一段明澈、细腻的散文所完美地反映出来的个人情绪的内心世界，能够给予他更多的乐趣吗？

他从那摇晃的桥面又走上了坚实的土地。就在那时，他似乎觉得空气突然变凉了，侧脸朝水面上望去，他看到一股从远处飞来的暴风雪忽然遮暗并加快了水浪前进的速度。心脏的一次轻微的跳动，他喉咙里的一次轻微的震颤都又一次告诉他，他的肉体对于那冰冷的非人的颜色是何等的恐惧。然而他并没有横穿过他左边的沙丘，却仍然一直向前沿着那条像脊梁一样指向河口的岩石上走去。

被遮蔽的日光微微照亮了河水流入海湾处灰蒙蒙的水面。远处，沿着缓缓流动的里费河，一排排细长的桅杆点缀着远处的天空，更远一些，在一片紫雾中静躺着那轮廓不清的复杂的城市建筑。基督教国家的第七个城市，和人的厌倦情绪一样的古老，和形象模糊的壁毯上的一幅画面一样，通过没有时间观念的空间显现在他的面前。它和它开始存在的那些日子相比起来，并不显得更老，也并不显得更为厌倦，对于自己的臣服的地位也并不比过去感到更容易忍受。

他这样带着沮丧的情绪，抬眼望着由海上飘来的慢慢飞过的斑斑点点的云彩。它们仿佛是沼泽地上的一群游牧民族，在天空的沙漠地带上面飘过，从高处飘过爱尔兰，向西方飘去。它们曾经经过的欧洲现在已被抛在爱尔兰海那边，那是一个使用各种奇怪语言的欧洲，那里布满了山谷、林带和城堡，那里居住着许多深沟高垒、严阵以待的民族。他从自己的内心深处听到一种混乱的音乐，那音乐仿佛唱出了他几乎完全清楚可又全然无法捉摸的一些记忆和一些人的名字。然后那音乐声似乎开始向远处退去，退去，退去，在那模糊的音乐退去的每一个尾声中，总留下一声拉长的喊叫，像流星一样划破那黑暗的沉寂。再来一次！再来一次！再来一次！从世界的那边有一个声音在叫喊着。

——哈喽，斯蒂芬诺斯！

——迪德勒斯大人来了！

——啊哦！……唉，别再弄了，听见没有，我在跟你说哩，要不当心我在你的那张臭嘴上给你来一家伙……啊哦！

——老伙计，陶塞！把他摁在水里！

——来吧，迪德勒斯！布斯·斯蒂芬鲁曼诺斯！布斯·斯蒂芬鲁曼诺斯！

——把他摁在水里！使劲灌他一灌，陶塞！

——救命啦！救命啦！……啊哦！

他还没有认出他们的脸面，但从他们一起发出的嘈杂声他已经知道他们都是谁了。只是看一眼那乱七八糟的湿淋淋的光着的身子就已经使他止不住要浑身发抖了。他们光着的身子，有的像尸体一样煞白，有的显出淡淡的金黄的颜色或因为太阳暴晒显得红彤彤的，现在都因为浇满海水而闪闪发光。用粗糙的木架支撑起来的跳板，每每在他们跳水时都来回摇晃，用粗糙的石头铺成的拦波堤的斜坡，也现出冰凉的湿淋淋的光泽，而他们一直不停地在上面打闹。他们用来在彼此的身上胡乱拍打的毛巾全都浸透了冰冷的海水。他们的头发也被寒冷的海水全给粘在一块儿了。

为回答他们的叫喊他站了下来，不在意地随便讲了几句话，力图避开他们的调笑。他们看来都显得多么没有性格啊：现在在舒利身上已不再看见那敞开的高领，在恩妮斯身上已不再看见那安着蛇头一样的卡子的红色的皮带，在康诺利身上也不再看见他的钉着没有掩口口袋的诺福克式的上衣了！他们那样子使人看着非常不安，特别是看到那些使得他们可怜的赤裸裸的身子不堪入目地初露青春期的迹象，更使人感到刺心一样的痛苦。也许他们是要依靠许多人聚在一起打闹，来逃避他们的灵魂所感到的隐秘的恐怖。可是他，一声不响地远离他们，却完全记得他对他自己的肉体的神秘曾感到何等的恐惧。

——斯蒂芬诺斯·迪达洛斯！布斯·斯蒂芬鲁曼诺斯！布斯·斯蒂芬鲁曼诺斯！

他们的这种玩笑他并非第一次听到，可是，现在它正迎合了他自以为在一切人之上的轻微的优越感。和过去一样，现在他这个奇怪的名字在他听来似乎变成了一种预言。眼前的灰暗、温暖的空气似乎是那样的毫无时间界限，他自己的情绪又似乎是那样的飘忽不定而且已非个人所有，因而他感到自己已和所有的时代融合在一起了。不一会儿以前，丹麦人的古王国的鬼魂曾经通过那被烟霭笼罩的城市在他面前露出头来。现在有人提到这位神话中的发明家(8)的名字，他似乎听到了远处的海浪声，并看到一个什么东西正鼓着双翼在海浪上慢慢向天空爬去。这一切究竟是什么意思？难道是某种奇异的发明，打开了某本充满寓言和象征的中世纪书籍的一页，因而让他看到了一个像鹰一样的人在海上朝着太阳飞去，借以向他预言他为何而生，以及在他朦胧的儿童时代和少年时代便一直努力追求的最终目的，并借以象征那位艺术家在他自己的工作室里用这个地球上毫无生气的物质正在创造的一个新的、向上飞去的、摸不着的、永远不会毁灭的生命的形象吗？

他的心开始发抖了，他的呼吸越来越急促，他感到自己的四肢被一种狂乱的精神所占据，仿佛他自己正朝着太阳的方向飞去了。他的心由于恐惧的狂欢而颤抖，他的灵魂却已经飞去了。他的灵魂现在已超出这个世界在向天空飞翔，而他知道他的肉体已经迅速得到净化，却摆脱了飘忽不定的状态，和宇宙精神混合在一起，放出了光彩。飞翔的狂喜使得他目光炯炯，呼吸狂乱，并使得他的被疾风扫过的四肢颤抖、狂野、光芒四射了。

——一！二！……快注意！

——啊，他妈妈的，我要淹死了！

——一！二！三，快跑！

——下一个！下一个！

——一！……啊！

——斯蒂芬内弗罗斯！

他的喉咙由于渴望大声喊叫都憋得发痛了，他要像高飞的鹰鹞一样喊叫，响彻云霄地喊出他随风飘去的喜悦。这是生命对他的灵魂发出的喊叫，而不是充满各种职责和绝望的世界发出的粗暴而无味的喊声，也不是呼唤他到圣坛前去终日进行那些无聊活动的非人的声音。片刻狂野的飞翔已使他获得彻底的解放，他的嘴唇勉强抑制住的胜利的欢呼几乎撕裂了他的头脑。

——斯蒂芬内弗罗斯！

那日夜追随着他的恐惧、那始终围绕着他的难以捉摸的情况、那从内心到外表都使他感到难堪的羞辱——所有这些现在除了把它们叫作从尸体上剥下的尸衣和死人在坟墓里穿的衣服外，还能叫它什么？

他的灵魂已经从他的儿童时期的坟墓中重新站了起来，抛掉了他身上的尸衣。是的！是的！是的！他将和与他同名的那个伟大的发明家一样，用他的灵魂的自由和力量，骄傲地创造出一个新的、向上的、美丽的、摸不着的、永不毁灭的生命。

他神经质地从那石块上往上爬，因为他已经没有办法熄灭在他的血液中燃烧起来的火焰了。他感到满脸发烧，歌声堵住了他的咽喉。他感到自己的脚有一种要求到处游逛的狂热的欲望，像燃烧着的火焰一样逼迫他出发走向天地的尽头。向前走！向前走！他的心似乎在大声喊叫着。海面上的黄昏很快会越来越浓，平原将被夜幕所掩盖，在他这游荡者的面前将会闪耀着新的黎明，让他看到许多离奇的田野、山冈和人的脸面。可是在哪里呢？

他朝北向着豪思那面观望。在防波堤较浅的那一边海面已经退下去，露出了过去遇难的船只，海浪也从前滩迅速退走了。在一片很小的水浪中间，一条椭圆形的长滩已经暖融融地显露出来。在浅海边的海浪中，这里那里到处都露出了闪闪发光的温暖的沙岛，在那些小岛四周和那长堤的旁边，在海滩边的浅流中到处是半裸着的人，有时涉水前进，有时潜入水中。

过了一会儿，他也脱光了袜子，把它们叠起来装在口袋里，帆布鞋用鞋带拴连着搭在肩头，从一些被海浪漂来停留在乱石中的破烂物件中拾起一根尖头的被盐水浸透的木棍，然后向防波堤的坡下走去。

沙滩上有一条很长的小河，他慢慢蹚着河水前进，河水里漂着无尽无休的水草使他颇为惊诧。宝蓝色、黑色、褐色和橄榄色的海草一直不停地在那河水下面移动着，来回摇晃，不停地打着圈。那小河里的水由于充满各种水草的颜色显得很深，并清晰地照出了在天空飘过的云彩。云彩一声不响地在他头顶上飘过，那墨角藻也一声不响从他的脚下漂走，灰暗而温暖的空气是那样的宁静，一个新的充满野性的生命开始在他的血管里吟唱了。

他的童年时期现在哪里去了？那极力逃避自己的命运的他的灵魂现在又到哪里去了？难道她是独自去忍受她的创伤给她带来的羞辱，或者穿着她的已褪色的尸衣，戴着用手一碰就会凋落的花环在她自己的简陋的与世隔绝的小天地中独自称王去了？再或者他自己到底现在哪里？

他独自一人待着。没有任何人注意他，满心快乐，更接近野性生命的中心。他孤独、年轻、任性和充满了野性，他孤独地待在一片荒凉的充满荒野气息的空气和黑色的水潭之中，孤独地待在无尽的贝壳和墨角藻之中，在他的四周是如笼薄纱的灰色的阳光，是许多穿着灰色衣服的半裸着的孩子和姑娘，空气中充满了孩子和小姑娘们的话语声。

一个小姑娘站立在他前面的河水中，孤独而宁静地观望着远处的海洋。她仿佛曾受到某种魔法的驱使，那形象已完全变得像一只奇怪而美丽的海鸟。她的细长的光着的腿像白鹤的腿一样纤巧而洁净，除了一缕水草在她的腿弯处形成一个深蓝色的图案之外，再看不见任何斑点。她那丰满的、颜色像象牙一样的大腿几乎一直光到她的屁股边，那里一圈外露的裤衩的下口完全像由细软的绒毛组成的白鹤的羽毛。她的浅蓝色的裙子大胆地撩上来围在腰上，从后面掖住。她的胸脯也像一只海鸟的一样柔和而纤巧，纤巧而柔和得像一只长着深色羽毛的鸽子的胸脯。可是她的淡黄色的长发却充满了女儿气：她的脸也带着小姑娘气，但点缀着令人惊异的人间的美。

她孤独而宁静地眺望着远处的海面。当她注意到他的存在，并发现他的眼神正对她表示出无限崇拜的时候，她对他转过脸来，以十分宁静的神态谛视着他的凝望，既无羞怯之感，也无淫欲之念。她听任他长时间，很长时间地对她凝望着，然后一声不响转过脸去，低头看着她面前的河水，用一只脚在水里东一下、西一下，轻轻地搅动。水被搅动时发出的微弱的响声打破了沉寂，那声音低沉、微弱、像耳语一样，微弱得像是在梦中听到的铃铛声，东一下、西一下，东一下、西一下，同时一种淡淡的热情燃起的红晕掠过了她的两颊。

——仁慈的上帝啊！斯蒂芬的灵魂在一阵无法抑制的人间欢乐的激动下止不住大叫着。

他忽然背着她转过身，开始向沙滩那边走去。他满脸发热，感到全身都在发烧，他的四肢也不停地颤抖着。向前，向前，向前，他向前大步走着，踏着沙滩向远处走去，狂野地对着大海歌唱，为那一直在召唤他的生活的来临发出了热情的欢呼。

她的形象已永恒地进入了他的灵魂，没有一句话语打破他的神圣的狂喜的宁静。她的眼睛已经对他发出了召唤，他的灵魂在听到这一召唤时止不住欣喜若狂。生活下去，错误下去，堕落下去，为胜利而欢呼，从生命中重新创造生命！在他面前出现了一位野性的天使，人世的青春和美的天使，她是来自公正的生命的法庭的使者，他要在一阵狂喜中为他打开人世的一切错误和光荣的道路。前进，前进，前进，前进！

他忽然站住，静静地倾听着他自己的心声。他已经走了多远了？现在是什么时候了？

在他四周看不见任何人影，也没有任何声音从远处的空气中传来。但海潮已经快要退去，那一天已经接近尾声了。他背海转过身去，朝着海滩那面奔跑，不顾脚下坚硬的鹅卵石，一直跑上了倾斜的海滩，在那里他看到在一圈长着小草的沙丘中有一个安静的沙窝，于是就在那里躺下，让黄昏的安谧和宁静来慢慢冷却他沸腾的血液。

在他的上空，他可以感觉到那巨大而冷漠的苍穹和无数静静运行着的天体，他也感觉到在他下面的大地，正是这大地给予他生命，并把他放在自己的怀抱中。

他懒懒地闭上眼睛，慢慢睡去。他的眼皮仿佛因为感觉到大地和她的观望者的巨大的环形运转而颤动起来，仿佛感觉到一个新世界的离奇的光亮而颤动起来。他的灵魂在昏厥中进入了另一个新的、离奇的、阴暗的、和下面的大海一样难于捉摸的世界，在那里一些模糊的形象和生命正来回穿行。这是一个世界，是一阵闪光，还是一朵鲜花？闪烁着又颤抖着，颤抖着并慢慢展开，像一线刚刚突破黑暗的光明，像一朵正在开放的花朵，它永无止境地自我重复着伸展开去，一片叶子接着一片叶子，一道闪光接着一道闪光，最后展现出一派通红的颜色，然后又继续展开，慢慢凋谢，变成淡淡的玫瑰色，把它柔和的红晕铺满整个天空，每一个红晕的颜色都比前一个显得更红。

他醒来的时候，黄昏已经来临，他用作床褥的细沙和干草已经不再发光了。他慢慢站起身来，回味着他在睡梦中经历的狂喜，不禁发出了欢乐的叹息。

他爬到一个沙丘顶上，向四面观望。暮色已经笼罩着大地。一弯新月划破了暗淡、荒凉的天空，那新月像镶嵌在灰色沙滩上的一个银环。海潮带着喁喁低语的波浪迅速向沙滩边流过来，使远处浅水边的沙丘又变成了一个个小岛。

————————————————————

(1) 此数语源出于《旧约·雅歌》，第4章第8节。雅歌中的原文是：“我的新妇，求你与我一同离开黎巴嫩，与我一同离开黎巴嫩。从亚玛拿顶、从示尼珥与黑门顶，从有狮子的洞、从有豹子的山，往下观望。”

(2) 拉丁文，意为：“让他在我的两乳间安卧。”此语亦出于《旧约·雅歌》，第1章第13节。但旧译中文《圣经》译作“常在我怀中”。

(3) 按法语意为普通女裤。故有下文有关妇女服装的一番议论。

(4) 英国19世纪的历史学家、政治家和作家。

(5) 19世纪法国的也许是最好争斗的天主教记者和作家。

(6) 拉丁文：走吧，一切都结束了。

(7) 传说是罗马暴君尼禄时代的一位商人。他曾和圣彼得和圣保罗打赌要直接飞向天堂。可在他飞得很高的时候，那两位圣徒向天祷告，又让他摔到地面上来了。

(8) 这里指伊卡罗斯的父亲迪达勒斯。在希腊神话中，他们父子俩曾用自制的蜡翅飞上天空，后因太阳熔化蜡翅而坠入海中。

五

他一滴不剩喝干了他的第三杯淡茶，开始咀嚼撒在他身边桌上的干面包渣儿，同时观望着玻璃罐里的黑色的小水潭。上面的黄色的茶水慢慢倒尽，下面剩下的那个水潭让他记起了克朗戈斯浴池里混浊的泥浆一般的水。他胳膊旁边的那个匣子里装着许多当票，刚刚他已经全部翻过，现在他无精少神地用他满是油腻的手一张张拿起印有蓝色条纹的纸条来看着，满是尘土的皱皱巴巴的纸条上字迹写得很乱，上面是戴利和麦克沃伊等典当人的名字。

一双高靿鞋。

一件四号上衣。

杂物三件和白油漆。

一条男裤。

他把它们放在一边，出神地看着那匣子的盖，盖上点缀着许多虱子屎般的斑点，他心不在焉地问道：

——咱们那个钟现在快多少？

他母亲把那架面朝下躺在炉台上的钟立起来，从钟面上可以看出现在是差一刻十二点，然后她仍然让它躺下了。

——快一小时零二十五分钟，她说。现在正确的时间应该是十点二十分。天知道，你得尽量赶快，要不赶不上听课了。

——把浴缸里放上水让我好洗个澡，斯蒂芬说。

——凯蒂，把浴缸放满水好让斯蒂芬洗澡。

——布蒂，把浴缸放满水好让斯蒂芬洗澡。

——我不成，我要去参加拉拉队。你给放上吧，马基。

当那搪瓷浴盆被安放在下水坑上，一只破旧的洗澡用的手套也扔在浴盆边的时候，他让母亲给他搓洗后脖，搓洗耳根后面，和他的鼻子根的两边。

——唉呀，真叫要命，她说，一个大学的学生竟会脏成这样，还得他妈妈来给他洗。

——但这只是因为你自己喜欢给我洗，斯蒂芬沉静地说。

楼上传来一声刺耳的口哨声，他妈妈把一件潮乎乎的长外衣塞在他手里说：

——看在上天的面上，你自己赶快擦干，上学去吧。

又是一声尖厉的口哨声，这次带着愤怒的情绪拖得更长，几个姑娘中有一个只好赶快跑到楼梯口下面去。

——有什么事，爸爸？

——你那个懒骨头臭丫头哥哥还没走吗？

——走了，爸爸。

——真走了？

——是走了，爸爸。

——哼！

那女孩跑回来对他做了个手势，让他赶快一声不响从后门出去。斯蒂芬大笑说：

——他对性别的看法可真有点怪，他好像把丫头看作是男性的了。

——啊，你真不知道害臊，斯蒂芬，他妈妈说，你怎么会跑到那个地方去了，你将来一辈子都会后悔不迭的！我可知道，你自那以后已完全变了。

——再见，所有的人，斯蒂芬说，微笑着吻了一下自己的指尖向大家告别。

高台子后面的那个胡同里积满了水，他缓步向前走着，在一堆堆潮湿的垃圾中择路而行。这时他却听到从墙那边关女尼的疯人院里传出一个发疯的女尼的喊叫声。

——耶稣基督！啊，基督！基督！

他生气地一摇头，想把那声音从他的耳朵里摇去，他踏着腐烂的垃圾跌跌撞撞匆匆向前走着，一种厌恶和怨艾的情绪竟使他的心感到说不出的疼痛。他父亲的口哨声、他母亲的唠叨、那个看不见的疯人的喊叫，现在变成了许多使他非常难堪的声音，威胁着要消除他那年轻人的骄傲。他发出一声咒骂，把那些声音的回声从他的心中驱赶出去。但是，在他沿着大马路走去，感觉到灰蒙蒙的曙光穿过雨水淅沥的树枝在他的四周散落下来，并闻到水淋淋的树叶和树干发出的带着野性的离奇气味的时候，他的灵魂终于从痛苦中解脱出来。

完全像过去一样，马路上雨水淋漓的树木马上使他想起了格哈特·霍卜特曼(1)剧中的姑娘和妇女，对她们的淡淡的悲愁的记忆和从带水的树枝上散发出的芳香的气息融混在一起，变成一种沉静的欢乐情调。他每天一早横越街市的散步早已开始了，他事先便已知道，在他穿过费尔维尤泥泞的土地时，他将想起纽曼的带有修道院气味的用银线贯穿的散文。在他走过北滩路时，随便朝那里一些食品店的窗口望一望，他就会想起吉多·卡瓦尔坎迪(2)的阴森的幽默而不禁微笑。当他在塔博特街的拐角处走过贝尔德瓷器店的时候，易卜生精神，一种带着倔强的孩子的美的精神，将会像一阵尖厉的清风在他的心上吹过。而当他在里费河那边一个肮脏的旧货店门口走过的时候，他一定会重复唱着本·琼森所写的一首歌，那首歌的开头是：

我待在这里并不感到更为无聊(3)。

每当他的头脑厌倦于从亚里士多德或亚奎纳斯的幽灵般的词句中去寻找美的真髓的时候，他总转向伊丽莎白时代典雅的歌曲从中去寻找乐趣。他的头脑，穿着多疑的僧人的服装，常常站立在那个时代的窗子的暗影之下，倾听着由竖琴奏出的严肃而又虚假的音乐，或倾听着穿坎肩的妇女(4)发出的坦率的大笑声，直到一阵过于低下的大笑，一句被时代所玷污、带着淫浪气息和虚假荣誉的话语，刺痛他那僧侣的骄傲心情，迫使他从他隐藏的地方走了出来。

大家原以为他终日沉湎其中，因而使他远离他的年轻伙伴的那些学问，现在看来也只不过是从亚里士多德的诗学和心理学中搜集来的一些纤巧的句子，只不过来自一本Synopsis Philosaphioe Scholasticoe ad mentem divi Thomoe(5)。他的思想不过是由各种疑虑和对自己的信心不足所组成，仅只偶尔被本能的闪电所照亮的一片朦胧，不过那闪电的光是那样清晰而辉煌，它每一闪亮，整个世界便似被烈火烧熔，立即在他的脚下消失了。而自那以后他便感到自己的舌头已笨拙失灵，而且他所见到的别人的眼神也都显得毫无反响，因为他感到美的精神已经像一件外衣一样把他完全裹住，而且至少在一种朦胧的梦境中他已经和真正的高尚结识了。但是如果这短暂的无声的骄傲不再给他以支撑力量，他也很高兴自己仍然生活在无数普通人的生活之中，在这城市的肮脏、嘈杂和混乱中，怀着轻快的心情无畏地向前走去。

在运河上的挡板附近，他遇上那个长着一张娃娃脸、戴着无边帽的肺病患者，迈着细碎的步子从桥上向他走过来，他穿着一件裹得很紧的栗色外衣，把一把收拢的雨伞，像占卜的神杖似的举在自己的身边。他想现在应该是十一点了，同时转身朝一家牛奶店里望去，想看看时间。牛奶店里的钟告诉他那会儿是五点差五分，可是他刚一转身，却听到近处什么地方有一个看不到的钟急促而清楚地敲了十一下。听到这钟声他不禁笑了，因为这使他想起了麦卡恩，他当时就似乎看到他那穿着一身射击服装的矮胖的身体，留着淡黄色的山羊胡，站在霍普金斯街角的微风中，并听到他对他说：

——迪达勒斯，你可真是个不合群的动物，整天一个人闷着。我可不那样。我是一个民主派，我决心要为未来的欧洲合众国里的一切阶级和性别的社会自由和平等进行工作，并为之奋斗。

十一点！那么说他要赶去听那一堂课也太晚了。今天是星期几来着？他在一家报社的门前停下，看看张贴在门口的报纸的栏头。星期四。十点到十一点，英语；十一点到十二点，法语；十二点到一点，物理。他自己假想着上英语课的情景，而现在即使他远离那教室他也感到非常不安和毫无办法。他看到他的同学们顺从地低下头去，在他们的笔记本上写下老师要他们写下的一切，字面上的定义、实际的含义、各种例证、生死年月、主要作品，以及互相并列的别人的赞扬和批评等。他的头却没有低下去，因为他的思想早不在教室里了，但不管他是四面转头看看那个不大的教室里的同学，或是朝着窗外越过一片荒凉的菜地向远处望去，他都感到有一股令人沮丧的充满地窖里潮湿和腐烂气味的臭味向他袭来。除开他自己的脑袋之外，在他前面的最前几排椅子中也有一个头在所有低着的脑袋中高扬着，它像是一个神父的头，正毫不羞怯地对着圣体盘，在为它周围的恭顺的礼拜者祈求。每当他想起克兰利，他总不能在脑子里形成一个他身体的完整形象，却只能想象他的头和脸，这到底是怎么回事呢？甚至现在衬映着清晨的灰色的帷幕，他眼前所见也只是有如在梦中所见的幻景，只看到一张已和身躯分离的脸，或者是从死人脸上压下的模型，额头上支棱着一头黑色的直竖着的头发，那样子像戴着一顶铁制的王冠。它完全像一张神父的脸，像神父一样脸色苍白，鼻翅很宽，眼睛下面和围绕着下巴底下都露着一片阴暗的颜色，也像神父一样长着很长的毫无血色的嘴唇，老是淡淡地微笑着。斯蒂芬忽然记起他日复一日、夜复一夜地对克兰利讲述着他的灵魂所感受到的苦恼、不安和渴望，而他这位朋友的回答始终只不过是一声不响地听着，他实在早应该看出，那是一张有罪的神父的脸，因为他听了许多人的忏悔却完全不能为他们赎罪，可是这时在他的记忆中他又感觉到那脸上的那双女人气的黑眼珠正向他注视。

通过这一形象，他在一瞥之中看到了一个奇怪的可以使他沉思的漆黑的地洞，可是他又立刻转过身去，感到现在还不是进入那洞中去的时候。但是他的朋友的那种夜色般阴森的心不在焉的神态，却似乎在他四周的空气中散发出一种稀薄的致命的毒气，他并且发现自己正随意读着在他身边或左或右闪现的一个个单词，十分呆痴地纳闷儿，为什么它们忽然不声不响完全失去了任何明白的含义，直到一切毫无意义却在街头巷尾流传的传说像符咒一样紧抓着他的思想，而当他在一堆堆用死亡的语言组成的胡同中走过的时候，他的灵魂却因为衰老，叹息着缩成一团了。他自己对语言文字的意识慢慢都从他的头脑中流出，全部流进那些单词里去，那些单词却自己在那里来回换着样子排列，执拗地定要排出非常别扭的韵脚：

常春藤发出凄厉的叫声爬在墙上，
它哭泣着蔓延着爬在墙上，
黄色的常春藤爬在墙上，
常春藤，常春藤爬在墙上。

谁曾听到过这样充满眼泪的诗行？伟大的上帝啊！谁曾听到过常春藤在墙上哭泣？黄色的常春藤，那倒也还可以。还有黄色的象牙。可是有没有像象牙一样的常春藤呢？

现在那个字在他的头脑中闪着光，比从大象的斑斑点点的长牙上锯下来的任何象牙都更为清晰，更为明亮。Ivory，ivoire，avorio，ebur(6)。他学拉丁文时学的第一个例句便是：India mittitebur，(7)他记起了教他拉丁文的那位校长的狡猾的北方人的脸，他曾经教他用典雅的英文重新改写奥维德的《变形记》，但因为他一再提到小猪肉、陶片和猪肉火腿，总显得非常荒唐可笑。他所知道的那点拉丁文诗歌的规律不过是从一位葡萄牙神父写的一本破烂不堪的书上学来的。

Contrahit orator，variant，in carmine vates．(8)

罗马历史的危机、胜利和动乱就是通过in tanto discrimine(9)这句滥调慢慢传授给他的，他同时还试图通过implere ollam denatiorum几个词来窥探那众城之城的社会生活，这几个字他那位校长曾经用十分响亮的声音翻译成“用银角子装满钱罐。”他那本久经时间磨炼的贺拉斯的作品什么时候摸上去都一点也不冷，尽管他的指头是那么冰凉。那些书页都带有人的味道，五十年前就有约翰·邓肯·英弗拉里蒂用他的手指翻阅过，后来他弟弟威廉·马尔科姆·英弗拉里蒂也翻过它。是的，在那些发黄的扉页上写的都是些高贵的人的名字，而对他这个拉丁文知识少得可怜的人来说，那些含义朦胧的诗行也仿佛这么多年来一直都放在常春花、薰衣草和马鞭草中而显得无比芳香。但是，一想到在世界文化的筵席上他将永远只不过是一位羞怯的客人，他不禁感到非常伤心。另外使他感到伤心的是那僧侣的知识，他原来极力想以它为基础建造起一种美的哲学，现在却看到在他生活的这个时代，一般人把它看得还不如纹章学和驯鹰术所使用的那些微妙而奇怪的术语更为重要。

在他左边的代表三位一体的那块灰色的石头，由于全城人的无知，不过像一块无用的顽石稳坐在一圈栏杆之中。这形象使得他的心绪非常低沉，他正想尽各种办法，企图使自己的脚从获得改造的良心的桎梏中解脱出来，这时他却遇上了那爱尔兰民族诗人的滑稽可笑的塑像(10)。

他并不生气地观望着它，因为，尽管身心的懒散像看不见的蛆虫一样爬满了它的全身，爬满了它那似乎不停移动着的脚和外衣的衣褶，爬满了它那显得很卑贱的脑袋，但它似乎十分谦卑地意识到了自己无足重轻的地位。这是一位古艾尼人穿着借来的古爱尔兰人的外衣。这时他不禁想到了他的朋友达文，那个农民学生。他们彼此开玩笑时他曾对他使用过这个名字，可是那年轻的农民毫不在意地接受了。

——就这么叫吧，斯蒂维，正像你说的，我这人是死脑袋瓜。你愿意叫我什么都行。

这样用家人之间的亲昵称呼来使用他的教名，在他第一次听到这一称呼出自他这位朋友之口的时候，曾感到十分高兴，因为他不论对谁讲话，也和别人对他讲话一样，总是非常严肃的。常常当他坐在格兰瑟姆街达文的屋子里，一面带着惊异的心情观望着他的朋友沿墙根一双双摆着的做工极好的靴子，一面为满足他朋友的容易满足的耳朵，而实际也是为了掩盖他自己的渴望和沮丧心情，念诵着别人的诗行和韵文的时候，他这位倾听者的古艾尼人的粗浅的头脑对他来说，有时颇有吸引力，有时又使他不禁要退避三舍。吸引他的是他那朴实而有礼貌的凝神静睇，或他对古英文用语的奇怪用法，再或者是他对粗野的人的技能所表现的强大的喜悦情绪——因为达文一直是拜倒在迈克尔·丘萨克那个盖尔人的脚下的——而使他的思想不禁迅速而急骤地极力趋避的则是他那莽撞的理智，或愚钝的感情，或他那充满恐惧的呆滞的眼神，那是一个饥饿中的爱尔兰村舍的灵魂所表现的恐惧，在那村舍中戒严令至今仍使所有的人整夜不安。

他叔叔马特·达文，关于那位运动家的能力和事迹他是记得很清楚的，这位年轻农民完全和他那位叔叔一样非常崇拜爱尔兰的各种悲伤的传说。他的那些不惜花费一切代价要使学校的平庸生活变得多少有几分意义的同学们，都喜欢把他看成是一个年轻的芬尼亚分子。他的保姆教他学会了爱尔兰语，并用残缺不全的爱尔兰神话照亮了他的朴质的想象世界。对那些从来无人从中找到一行美丽诗句的神话，对那些在代代相传的过程中已变得十分混乱、复杂、令人难以相信的故事，他的态度却完全像一个缺乏头脑的农奴对待罗马天主教的宗教一样一片忠心。不管任何从英格兰，或者通过英格兰的文化传来的思想或感情，他的头脑都毫无例外地一律加以拒绝。至于英格兰以外的世界，他所知道的唯一的外国是法国，他常常也谈到为法国尽忠。

这种雄心，又配上年轻人的那种幽默，使得斯蒂芬常常把他称作驯顺的白鹅，这个名字甚至还有一点特别令人厌烦的地方，就是它清楚地表明了他这位朋友既不爱讲话也不爱行动的气质，而这种气质似乎常在斯蒂芬的随时都急于进行思考的头脑，和那种爱尔兰的处处躲躲藏藏的生活方式之间形成了一种障碍。

斯蒂芬常常用一阵激烈的或者说过于丰富的语言来回避对方显示精神反抗的冷漠的沉默，而这位年轻农民有一天夜晚由于精神上不堪其扰，讲出一番话来却又在斯蒂芬的头脑里唤起了一种奇异的想象。他们两人那时正穿过贫苦犹太人的狭窄而黑暗的街道，慢慢散着步朝达文家走去。

——去年秋天快入冬的时候，斯蒂维，我自己曾遇到过一件事，这事我从没有对任何一个活人讲过，今天你是第一个听到我讲这件事。我记不清那是十月还是十一月。可能是十一月，因为那是在我到这儿来参加新生班学习之前。

斯蒂芬含着笑对他的朋友转过脸去，很高兴他能这样自信，而且他说话时那种淳朴的腔调也赢得了他的同情。

——那一天，我整天没有回家，一直待在巴特凡特——我不知道你知不知道那地方在哪儿——克罗克健儿和瑟尔斯大无畏球队正在那里进行一场球赛，我的天哪，斯蒂维，那场球赛打得可真叫玩儿命。我一个表哥，方西·达文，由于大部分时间一直跟着前卫到处奔跑，像疯子一样大喊大叫，热得把衣服全都剥光了，可是你知道那一天对一般的利默里克人来说还是很凉爽的。那一天我是永远也不会忘记的。有一次一个克罗克的小伙子狠狠朝他头上一棍打去，那一棍天知道只差一丁点儿就打在他的太阳穴上。啊，上帝可以作证，要是那一棍真打上了，他肯定就算完了。

——我很高兴他逃脱了性命，斯蒂芬大笑着说，但是我肯定你刚才要讲的一件奇事绝不会就是这个吧？

——是啊，我相信你对那个是不感兴趣的，可是不管怎么说，在那次球赛之后，球场上一直热闹非常，弄得我竟误了回家去的最后一趟火车，我也找不到任何便车可以带我回去，因为事不凑巧，那天夜晚正好在城堡镇有一次群众大会，村子里所有的车都赶到那边去了。因此我除了待在那里过夜或用两条腿走回去，就再没有任何其他办法可想了。是啊，我开始步行，我走了一阵天就完全黑了下来。等我走过巴利霍拉山以后，还有很长一段路几乎是什么人也看不见的，而那里离开基尔马洛克可还有十多英里。沿路上你看不见半间基督教徒的住房，也听不到任何声音。天又黑得伸手不见五指。有一两次我在一个树丛下面停下来点着我的烟斗，要不是因为露水太重，我几乎都想两脚一伸就在那儿躺下睡觉了。最后，大路拐过一个弯，我忽然看见远处一个小村子里有一个窗口露出了灯光。我走过去敲门。里面有人问我是谁，我回答说，我在巴特凡特看球赛看得太晚，只好走路回去，如果我能讨一碗水喝，我会非常感谢。过了一会儿，一个年轻妇女打开了门，拿给我一大罐牛奶。她只穿了很少一点衣服，头发也披散着，仿佛在我叫门的时候她正准备上床睡觉了。从她的身材和她的某种奇特的眼神来看，我相信她一定怀孩子了。她站在门口一个劲儿拉着我谈话，谈了很久，我当时就感到很奇怪，因为她的胸脯和肩头几乎全都露着。她问我累不累，愿不愿意就在那里过夜。她说她家里就只她一个人，她的丈夫那天早晨送他妹妹到昆斯敦去了。她就那么一直不停地谈着，斯蒂维，她的眼睛直盯着我的脸，她站得离我非常近，我差不多都能听到她的呼吸声。最后当我把奶罐还给她的时候，她拽着我的手硬要把我往门里面拉，还说：“快进来，就在这儿过夜吧。你完全不用害怕。这屋里除了咱俩什么人也没有……”我没有肯进去，斯蒂维。我向她道了谢，仍开始走我的路，浑身全都像发烧一样。走到大路上第一个拐角的地方我回头望望，她仍然还站在门口。

达文的故事的最后几个字一直在他的记忆中回荡，他故事中的那个女人已变成了他坐在学校的车上开过克莱恩时曾经见到的站在屋门口的农妇的形象，这是她的民族和他自己的民族的一个典型的象征，一个蝙蝠一样的心灵在黑暗中、在隐秘中、在孤独中忽然意识到了自己的存在，于是通过一个毫无忸怩之态的女人的眼神、声音和姿态，邀请一个陌生人到她的床上去。

他忽然感到有一只手抓住他的胳膊，一个年轻的声音叫喊着：

——啊，老爷，是您自己的姑娘，先生！今天的第一束鲜花，老爷。买下这束可爱的鲜花吧。好吗，老爷？

她向他举过来的鲜花和她那年轻的蓝色的眼睛，在那一瞬间仿佛正好表现出毫无忸怩之态的天真形象，他于是不禁停了下来，但不久那形象便消失了，他所看到的只是她的破烂衣衫、潮湿而粗糙的头发和顽皮的脸。

——买下吧，老爷！别忘了您自己的姑娘，先生！

——我没有钱，斯蒂芬说。

——买下这些可爱的花吧，行不行，老爷？只要一个便士。

——你没听见我刚才讲的话吗？斯蒂芬向她低过头去问道。我已经对你说过我没有钱。我再对你说一遍。

——啊，将来您肯定会有钱的，老爷，上帝保佑您，那女孩稍等了一会儿回答说。

——那也许吧，斯蒂芬说，但我看恐怕不一定。

他很快离开了她，担心她那亲昵的表现会进而转为对他喋喋不休，再说他也不愿碍她的事，妨碍她向别的人，一个从英格兰来的旅游家或者三一学校的学生什么的，兜售她的鲜花。他沿着一直走去的那条格拉夫顿大街，进一步延长了那令人沮丧的贫穷景象。在那条街的闹区有一块纪念沃尔弗·托恩(11)的石碑，他还记得当年立这块碑时，他和父亲一起来参加了那个仪式。他一想起当时对托恩表示崇敬的那俗不可耐的仪式，简直感到十分痛心。那时还有坐在一辆漂亮的车子里前来参加仪式的四位法国代表，其中有一个微笑着的胖小伙子，用一根棍挑着一块牌子，那上面写着Vive l'Irlande(12)几个字。

但是斯蒂芬广场上的树木却散发出雨水的芬芳，那被雨水浇透的土地也散发出它的尘世的生命的气息，一种从许多发霉的心灵中升起的淡淡的烟雾。他的前辈曾多次对他讲过的那个英勇、腐朽的城市的灵魂，随着时间的推移，已经萎缩成一股从土地上升起的淡淡的生命的气息。而且他知道待会儿他进入那阴暗的学校大门之后，他就会感受到一种非巴克·伊根(13)和伯恩查佩尔·惠利(14)所知的腐化堕落情景。

现在要到楼上去上法文课已经太晚了。他穿过大厅，朝通向物理实验室的那条过道走去。过道里很黑，很安静，但也并非无人守望之处。他为什么会感到这儿一定有人在守望着？是因为他曾听人说，在巴克·伊根时代，这儿有一个秘密的楼梯口吗？或者还是因为耶稣会的一切房舍都是治外地区，他现在是在一群异族人民之间活动？托恩和帕内尔的爱尔兰似乎已消失在无尽的空间中了。

他打开实验室的门，站在从满是尘土的窗口勉强照进的寒冷、阴森的光线之中。靠近大门前有一个人蹲在那里，从他瘦小的身体和灰色的衣服判断，他知道那是副教导主任正在生火。斯蒂芬轻轻关上门，朝火炉边走去。

——早，先生！我可以帮帮你的忙吗？

那神父马上抬起头来说：

——先等一等，迪达勒斯先生，一会儿你就会看到了。点火也是一种艺术，我们有陶冶性情的艺术，我们也有实用的艺术。这是一种实用的艺术。

——我也来试着学一学，斯蒂芬说。

——煤不要加得太多，副教导主任说，一边两手不停地忙活着，这是生火的秘密之一。

他从袈裟旁边的口袋里掏出四个蜡烛头，灵巧地把它们跟煤块和一些揉皱的纸团一起放进炉子里去。斯蒂芬一声不响地在一旁观望着。他这样跪在一块方砖上点火，忙着把纸团和蜡烛头一件一件往炉子里放，那样子似乎使他比过去任何时候都更像一位恭顺的神父，他仿佛是上帝的祭司，正在一个空荡荡的神庙里准备着向神献祭。他那已退色的破旧的袈裟也像是一件朴素的祭司的布袍，覆盖着这个跪着的形象，而这个人如果让他穿上法衣或穿上挂满铃铛的主教服装，他就会感到极不舒服。由于长时间慢吞吞地为主操劳——点燃圣坛上的炉火、对一切听到的话严格保密、侍候尘世的凡人、不论奉派进行任何工作都积极行动——他的身体已经变得相当衰老，可是他的脸上却看不出任何圣徒或教皇的美。不，他的灵魂本身也由于那种操劳只是变得越来越老，却并没有显得和光明和美更为接近，或者向外散发出表现他的庄严神圣的甜蜜的气息——剩下的只是一个受尽折磨的意志，它在接受命令时的反应也并不比爱情或战斗所引起的反应更为强烈，他的又干又瘦的衰老的身躯，由于覆盖上一层银灰色的绒毛已全部变灰了。

副教导主任蹲下身去，观望木棍被火烧着的情况。完全为了打破沉默，斯蒂芬说：

——我敢肯定我可生不着一炉火。

——你是一位艺术家，是不是，迪达勒斯先生？副教导主任说，抬头望着他眨了眨灰色的眼睛。艺术家的目的是创造美的东西。但到底什么叫美那可是另外一个问题。

他思索着这个难题，慢慢搓了搓自己的干枯的手。

——你现在能回答这个问题吗？他问道。

——亚奎纳斯，斯蒂芬回答说，说是pulcra sunt quoe visa placent(15)。

——在咱们眼前的这一堆火，副教导主任说，看起来也令人感到很愉快。那么它也可以算作美吗？

——从视觉所能体会到的情况来看，这里我想也包含着美的感受的意义，它就应该算是美。可是亚奎纳斯也说过bonum est in quod tendit appetitus(16)。从它能满足动物对温暖的要求来说，火是一种善。可是在地狱里，火却是一种恶。

——完全是这样，副教导主任说，你的话正好说在点子上了。

他敏捷地站起来朝门口走去，让门半开着说：

——据说生火时有点风会有很大的帮助。

在他回到火炉边时，步子很轻快，但微微有点儿瘸，斯蒂芬从他毫无热情的灰眼睛里，看到一个耶稣徒安静的灵魂正观望着他。他和伊格内修斯一样有点瘸，可是他的眼睛却完全没有伊格内修斯热情的火花。甚至传说中他们那一帮人所使用的计谋，一个比记载机密、微妙的机智的神话书中所记载的更为微妙和更为机密的计谋，也没有能够在他的心中燃起耶稣门徒的热情。他仿佛是完全按照吩咐，为了给上帝带来更大的荣誉，在使用着人世的计谋、智能和机智，他在使用它们时没有任何欢乐，对它们在恶人身上的出现也没有任何仇恨，而只是带着坚定的绝对服从的姿态，还它们一个本来面目，而尽管他整天一声不响地操劳着，他似乎对他的主人并不喜爱，对他所干的那些事，如果真有热情的话，那也是微乎其微的。完全像造物者所要求的那样，他是similiter atque senis baculus(17)，像老人手中的一根手杖，在深夜走在路上或遇上恶劣天气的时候，可以做个依靠，在花园的凳子上可以和一位太太送他的花束放在一块儿，有时也可以把它举起来对人进行威胁。

副教导主任回到火炉边，开始抚摸自己的下巴。

——关于这个美学问题，我们什么时候可以听到你的意见呢？他问道。

——我的意见！斯蒂芬惊愕地说，我要是运气好，十天半个月也许能碰上一点关于这个问题的想法。

——这类问题是非常深奥的，迪达勒斯先生，副教导主任说，这仿佛像在莫黑山的峭壁上观望下面的深渊。许多人跳进深渊便再也没有回来。只有那些受过潜水训练的潜水员可以进入深渊里去，进行一番探索，然后再浮到水面上来。

——如果你讲的是思索问题，先生，斯蒂芬说，那我也敢肯定世界上并没有什么独立思考这种东西，因为一切人的思索必须受它自己的规律的限制。

——哈！

——就我的需要来说，我依靠亚里士多德和亚奎纳斯的一两个概念所发出的光就足够我在目前进行工作了。

——我明白。我完全明白你的意思。

——我需要它们只是为了让它们为我所用，作为我的向导，然后我要依靠它们发出的光干一点我所要干的事。如果那个灯光冒出黑烟或者发出臭味，那我就要调整一下它的灯芯。如果它变得不够亮了，那我就要把它卖掉，另外再买一盏。

——耶庇克蒂忒斯(18)也有一盏灯，副教导主任说，那盏灯在他死后卖了个很好的价钱。那就是他靠着它写出哲学论文的那盏灯。你知道耶庇克蒂忒斯是谁吗？

——一位老先生，斯蒂芬哑着嗓子说，他曾经说过，一个人的灵魂完全像装在柳条筐里的一筐水。

——他曾用一种非常朴实的语言对我们说，副教导主任接着说，有一次他在一尊神像前面放上了一盏铁铸的灯，后来一个小偷把灯偷走了。那位哲学家怎么办呢？他想了想偷窃是小偷的本性，因此决定第二天去买一盏瓦灯，不再用铁灯了。

副教导主任放进炉子里的蜡烛头散发出烧焦的蜡油味道，那气味在斯蒂芬的意识中竟和他们的铿锵话语声融混在一起了，柳条筐和灯，灯和柳条筐。那神父的声音也显得响亮而铿锵有调。斯蒂芬的思想本能地停滞住了，那奇怪的声音和形象，那好像一盏没点着的灯或像一个焦距错误的反光镜中的神父的脸，都使他的思想停止活动了。在这张脸后面，或者脸里面有什么东西呢？是一个呆痴、麻木的灵魂，或者还是一团充满智慧，并能表现出上帝的愤怒的包藏着雷电的乌云？

——我说的完全是另外一种灯，先生，斯蒂芬说。

——毫无问题，副教导主任说。

——在美学讨论中，斯蒂芬说，有一个很大的困难，那就是很难知道我们在使用某些词句时，根据的是文学传统还是市井间的传统。我记得纽曼有一句话说到圣母玛利亚，说她由所有的圣徒陪伴着。可是这个字在市井间使用起来意思就完全不一样了。我希望我没有绊住(19)你。

——不不，我也没有什么事，副教导主任客气地说。

——不，不，斯蒂芬微笑着说，我的意思是……

——是的，是的，我明白了，副教导主任连忙回答说，我现在明白你的意思了：你讲的是绊住那个词儿。

他向前伸出下巴，干咳了几声。

——还回到灯的问题上来，他说，往灯里加油也是个很微妙的问题。你必须选择纯净的油，往里加的时候你还必须非常小心，不要让它流在灯外面，也不要让油从漏斗口上漫出来。

——什么漏斗？斯蒂芬问道。

——就是你用它往灯里灌油的那种漏斗。

——那个？斯蒂芬说，那东西叫漏斗，那不是通盘吗？

——什么是通盘？

——就是那个。那个……漏斗。

——这东西在爱尔兰语里叫通盘吗？副教导主任问道，我这一辈子还从没听说过这个词儿。

——在下德拉蒙康德拉一带这东西叫作通盘，斯蒂芬大笑着说，那里的人英语可都是说得呱呱叫的。

——通盘，副教导主任沉思着说，这个词再有趣不过了。我一定得把它记住。说真的，我一定得把它记住。

他这种客气的外貌看来有些虚假，斯蒂芬几乎是用寓言中长兄看待回头浪子的眼神注视着这位英格兰的皈依者。这个待在爱尔兰的可怜的英格兰人，在一阵热闹的精神转变的仪式之后变成了一个虔诚的信徒，他似乎是在那个充满阴谋、痛苦、嫉妒、斗争和卑鄙行为的奇怪的戏快要演完的时候才走进耶稣教会的历史舞台的——他由于姗姗来迟，是一个精神上的后辈。他的宗教思想是从什么地方开始的呢？也许他有生以来就一直生活在一群严肃的离经叛道的人们中间，他只看到耶稣是人类的救星，而对于整个宗教的那一套虚假的仪式非常厌恶。难道在无数派别斗争的混乱中，在什么六大原则会、特殊人、种子和蛇洗礼会、命运先于人世论者等种种混乱派别的胡言乱语之中，他却会感到需要一种出自内心的虔诚吗？难道是在他像缠绕一团棉线一样，把他关于在圣坛前行一次额手礼便会带来一股仙气，或者关于圣灵诞生的细致微妙的思绪，绎到了尽头的时候，忽然发现了真正的宗教吗？再不然难道是他坐在某一个铁皮顶的小教堂门口，打着哈欠细数着教堂收到的便士的时候，耶稣基督碰了他一下，让他跟着走，他也就像坐在税务局前的那个门徒一样跟着他走了吗？

副教导主任又重新念叨着那个词。

——通盘！哎呀，真是太有趣了！

——你刚才问我的那个问题似乎比这个更有趣得多。艺术家们尽一切力量用一团泥表现的美究竟是什么东西，斯蒂芬冷静地说。

这个小词儿似乎让他把他的灵敏感觉的剑尖指向了这个有礼貌的时刻警惕着的敌人。一想到现在跟他说话的那个人是本·琼森的同胞，他不禁有一种很难堪的感觉。他想：

——我们两人刚才谈话所使用的这种语言原来是他的语言，后来才变成了我的语言。像家、基督、麦酒、主人这些词，从他嘴里说出来和从我嘴里说出来是多么不相同啊！我在说这些词和写这些字的时候可能并不感到精神上十分不安。他的语言对我是那样地熟悉，又是那样地生疏，对我它永远只能是一种后天学来的语言。那些字不是我创造的，我也不能接受。我的声音拒绝说出这些字。我的灵魂对他这种语言的阴森含义感到不安。

——要分清什么是美，什么是崇高，副教导主任补充说，分清什么是道德上的美和什么是物质上的美。还要弄清楚对各种不同的艺术来说，什么样的美最适合于什么样的艺术。这是我们应该加以研究的一些有趣的问题。

副教导主任的坚定和枯燥的声音忽然让斯蒂芬感到极不舒服，他于是沉默下来。从远处的楼梯口传来许多皮靴声和混乱的说话声，打破了房间里的沉寂。

——在对这些问题进行探索的时候，副教导主任用一种下结论的口气说，必须注意这里存在着一种因为缺乏营养而陷于枯竭的危险。首先你必须设法取得学位。你应该把这件事当作你的第一个目标。然后一点一点你自然会看清你的道路了。我指的是各个方面的道路，你的生活道路和你进行思维的道路。在一开始这可能有点像骑着自行车爬高山。你比如像穆南先生。他花了很长的时间才爬到山顶上去。可是他终于爬上去了。

——我可能没有他那种才能，斯蒂芬平静地说。

——这个谁也不知道，副教导主任微笑着说，咱们自己谁也说不清自己到底有多大才能。但我们肯定绝不能泄气。Per aspera ad astra．(20)

他匆匆离开火炉，走到楼梯口去，看着正进来的艺术班第一班的同学。

斯蒂芬倚在火炉边，听见他轻快地一视同仁地对班上的每一个同学打招呼，并且几乎可以看到一些比较无礼的学生坦率的微笑。这时一种凄凉和悲悯的感情像露水一样洒在他那容易感伤的心上，他对这个具有武士气派的洛约拉(21)的忠实信徒，这个教会里的后娘的儿子感到十分同情，这个人说话比教会里其他的人更随便，这个人他永远也不会称他教父，但是这个人有一个比他们更为坚定的灵魂。他同时还想到，这个人和他的那些伙伴，由于在他们的一生中一直在上帝的审判台前为一些轻快的、缺乏热情的、安分的灵魂乞求恩惠，所以他们不仅在那些出世者的眼前，而且也在普通世人的眼前赢得了一定的声誉。

坐在那个阴暗的实验室最高处布满蛛网的窗子下面的一些学生，用他们沉重的靴子表现的那一阵热情，说明上课的教授已经进入教室了。教师开始点名，学生回答的声音各式各样，最后点到了彼得·伯恩。

——到！

从高处发出一声低沉的回答，紧接着从别的座位上发出一阵表示抗议的咳嗽声。

那教授稍微停了一停，然后又接着往下点名：

——克兰利！

没有人回答。

——克兰利先生！

斯蒂芬因为想到他这位朋友的学习情况，一阵微笑掠过了他的脸。

——到豹镇去打听打听他吧！他背后一个声音说。

斯蒂芬很快转头去看，可是衬着后面的灰色的光，他所看到的莫伊尼汉的尖着嘴的脸却一点表情也没有。黑板上写出了一个公式。在一片翻动练习簿的沙沙声中斯蒂芬又转过身去说：

——求你看在上帝的面上给我一点纸吧。

——你怎么搞的，连纸也没有一张了？莫伊尼汉咧开嘴笑着说。

他从拍纸簿上扯下一张递给他，对他耳语说：

——在情况必要的时候，任何一个外行人或女人都能干得了的。

一字不落地照抄在那片纸上的公式、老师在演算中的化简和展开的算式、那些像鬼魂一样表示着力量和速度的符号等，既使斯蒂芬感到有趣也使他感到疲劳。他曾听见有人说这位老教授是一个持无神论的自由思想家。啊，这讨厌的阴暗无聊的日子！它简直仿佛是一个盛满毫无痛苦但却颇有耐心的意识的深潭，在这里面数学家的灵魂可以四处游逛，在一层层由越来越稀薄、越来越暗淡的余晖组成的平原上，建造他们的又细又长的各种结构，并向愈来愈大、愈来愈远和愈来愈无法捉摸的宇宙的边沿，不停散发出迅速扩大的光环。

——所以我们一定要区分什么是椭圆形，什么是椭圆球体。也许你们诸位都很熟悉W．S．吉尔伯特(22)先生的作品。他在一支歌中曾经讲到，一个会打弹子的真正行家就必须这样来玩：

在一张铺着虚假的绒布的台子上
用一个弯弯曲曲的弹子棒
打着一个椭圆形的弹子。

——他的意思当然是说，一个形状是椭圆体的球，而那椭圆体是完全合乎我刚才讲的关于它的中轴的规律的。

莫伊尼汉向斯蒂芬的耳边歪过头来，低声说：

——椭圆球什么价钱！快来追我吧，小姐们，我已经参加了骑兵部队(23)。

他的这位同学的这种粗野的幽默，像一阵飓风穿透了斯蒂芬的闭关自守的心灵，软塌塌的教士们的服装都似乎忽然具有了欢乐的生命，它们在一个无人管事的安息日不停地摇晃着，到处蹦蹦跳跳，这一教区的各种人物形象都从这些被风吹动的衣服中显现出来，其中有副教导主任，有戴着用灰色的毛发做成的帽子的身材高大的卖花人，有校长，有写下虔诚诗句的长着一头软发的小教士，有经济学教授的矮墩墩的农民形象，有年轻的讲心灵科学的教授的高瘦的形体，他在楼梯口和他班上的同学们讨论关于良心的问题，那样子真像一只长颈鹿站在一群羚羊之中伸头吃着高处的树叶。还有这里的兄弟会的负责人、长着一双流氓眼睛的圆脑袋的教意大利文的胖教授等。他们跑着、走着、蹦着、跳着，全都把长衣服搂起来准备做跳背游戏，一个接一个趴在别人的背上，拼命摇晃身子发出虚假的大笑，大家胡乱拍打着别人的屁股，又因为这种粗野的下流玩笑大笑不止，他们彼此用大家熟悉的诨名相称呼，忽然又对某人过于粗野的行为装作一本正经表示抗议，三三两两聚在一块儿用手捂着嘴低声耳语。

讲课的那位教授走到墙边的一些玻璃匣子前面，他从一个放玻璃匣子的架子上拿下一套弹簧，仔细吹掉上面各处的灰尘，很小心地把它拿到桌边来，用一个手指头指着它，开始他的讲演。他解释说，现代做弹簧的铁丝是一种叫作赛白金的合金做成的，这种合金是不久前由F．W．马蒂诺发明的。

他非常清晰地念出了那位发明家简写的名字。莫伊尼汉在斯蒂芬的背后低声说：

——就是那位无人不知的清水马丁(24)！

——问问他，斯蒂芬转过头去厌倦地勉强开玩笑说，是否他要找个人去坐电椅。告诉他我可以去。

莫伊尼汉看到教授正低头看着他的弹簧，便从板凳上站起来把右手手指窝得嘣嘣响，学着街上野孩子哭泣的声音喊叫着。

——求求你，老师！这孩子专喜欢讲些脏话，老师。

——赛白金，那教授严肃地说，比德国的银子还要好，因为不管温度怎么变化，它的抗热系数都比较低。这赛白金金丝是绝缘的，用来绝缘的这些丝线是绕在黑色的橡皮管上，就是我手指指的这个地方。如果每根丝单绕就会有一股额外的电流穿透到弹簧里去。这橡皮管是用热石蜡浸透过的……

在斯蒂芬下面的一条板凳上有一个尖利的北爱尔兰的口音说：

——老师可能问我们一些关于应用科学的问题吗？

那位教授开始严肃地翻来覆去解释纯科学和应用科学这两个词儿。一个戴金边眼镜身材高大的学生带着迷惘的神态看着那个提问题的人。莫伊尼汉从后面用他本来的声音低声说：

——凭他那一磅肉来说，麦卡利斯特难道不是一个魔鬼吗？

斯蒂芬冷冷地低头看着他下面的一个椭圆形的脑袋，那脑袋上乱七八糟地长着一头像棕绳一样棕红色的头发。那声音、那腔调、那提问人的头脑都使他非常讨厌，他甚至听任这种厌恶情绪发展成一种有意夸大的愤怒，刻薄地想着，这个学生的父亲要是把他的儿子送到贝尔法斯特去上学那岂不更好得多，这样他还会省下一大笔火车费用哩。

他下面的那个椭圆形的脑袋瓜儿对他这种思想上的暗箭并没有回过头来加以反击，可是很快这支箭却又飞回到弓弦上来，因为不一会儿他就看到了那学生的像白纸一样苍白的脸。

——这段话可不是我自己想出来的，他连忙对自己说。这话后面那条板凳上的那位滑稽的爱尔兰人早就说过。安静一些吧。你能肯定说，你的民族的灵魂是被谁给出卖了？你们的那些上帝的选民是被谁出卖的？——是被问话的人还是被那个取笑他的人呢？安静一些吧。记住耶庇克蒂忒斯的话。他在这个时候，用这种声调提出这样一个问题，而且把科学两个字念得像一个字一样，这也许是他的性格决定的。

那位教授的拉长的声音一直围绕着他所讲的那个弹簧慢慢在教室里漾开，随着弹簧阻抗的成倍增长，他那声音也成倍地，成三倍、四倍地加强了催眠的力量。

莫伊尼汉听到远处的铃声，从背后发出一声喊叫：

——该下课了，先生们！

教室前的门厅里挤满了人，大家都大声谈着话。在门口一张桌上放着两幅带框的照片，这两幅照片中间放着一长条纸，乱七八糟的签名形成了一个很不规则的拖长的尾巴。麦卡恩在成群的学生们中间兴致勃勃地来回奔跑，他滔滔不绝地谈着话，回答别人的指责，把一个又一个学生领到桌边去。在里面的大厅里副教导主任正站在那里和一位年轻教授谈话，他严肃地摸着自己的下巴，有时点点头。

斯蒂芬在门口被人群阻拦住，只好无可奈何地停下来。在一顶宽边的耷拉着的软帽子下面，克兰利的黑眼睛正盯着他。

——你签名了吗？斯蒂芬问道。

克兰利闭上了又宽又薄的嘴唇，稍微想了一想回答说：

——Ego habeo．(25)

这是要干什么？

——Quod？(26)

——这是要干什么？

克兰利向斯蒂芬转过他那苍白的脸，温和地同时又充满怨恨地说：

——Per pax universalis．(27)

斯蒂芬指着沙皇的照片说：

——他长着一张头脑发昏的基督的脸。

他说话的声音里所表现的轻蔑和愤怒，使得本来安静地观望着大厅墙壁上的画轴的克兰利对他转过脸来。

——你生气了吗？他问道。

——没有，斯蒂芬回答说。

——你的情绪很不好吧？

——没有。

——Credo ut vos sanguinarius mendax estis，克兰利说，quia facies vostra monstrat ut vos in damno malo humore estis．(28)

莫伊尼汉在走向桌边的时候对斯蒂芬耳语说：

——麦卡恩现在可真是了不得。他准备洒掉最后的一滴。一个崭新的世界。再没有什么让那些狗杂种更高兴的事，也没有人会选那些狗杂种了。

对他这种十分肯定的态度斯蒂芬不禁笑了笑，在莫伊尼汉走过去以后，他又转过头来望着克兰利。

——也许你能告诉我，他说，他为什么这样毫无顾忌地把他的心里话告诉我。你能说得清吗？

克兰利的前额上出现了某种生气的神态。他转身望着那张桌子，那里莫伊尼汉正低下头去在那张纸上写下自己的名字，然后他又冷冷地说：

——一个马屁精！

——Quis est in malo humors，斯蒂芬说，ego aut vus？(29)

克兰利对他的奚落没有在意。他正不高兴地仔细琢磨他自己的这个判断，接着他仍然用那种冷冷的、强有力的声音说：

——一个他妈的该死的马屁精，他就是那么个玩意儿！

这是他对任何一个已死去的友情的一句评语，斯蒂芬心里想，将来有一天他对他是否也会这样说。那迟钝的话语像一团烂泥上的石块一样慢慢沉下去，让人听不见了。斯蒂芬简直是看到它在往下沉，这样的情景他已经见过许多次了。他感到它沉重地压在自己的心上。克兰利的话不像达文所讲的话，因为它既缺乏伊丽莎白时代英语的那种精巧的成语，也没有那种巧妙地加以改装的爱尔兰俏皮话。它那种拖长的声音不过是由荒凉、腐烂的海港反射回来的、都柏林码头嘈杂声的回音，它的力量也不过是由威克洛的一个讲台平淡地反射回来的都柏林神圣高论的反响。

克兰利脸上的怒容慢慢消失了，这时麦卡恩正从大厅的那一头朝他们快步走过来。

——你们在这儿！麦卡恩兴致勃勃地说。

——我在这儿！斯蒂芬说。

——和平常一样又迟到了。你就不能把你的进步倾向跟遵守时刻结合在一块儿吗？

——你这个问题完全不相干，斯蒂芬说，下一步干什么。

他含笑的眼睛直盯着从这位宣传家胸前口袋里伸出来的一根用银纸包着的牛奶巧克力糖。一小群听众围过来，要听他们两人斗智。一个皮肤发蓝的瘦小的长着一头黑发的学生把脸伸在他们两人中间，在他们每说一句话的时候看看这个又看看那个，仿佛要用他张开的湿润的嘴捕捉住在他眼前飞过的每一句话。克兰利从口袋里掏出一只很小的灰色皮球，转来转去仔细研究着。

——下一步？麦卡恩说，嗬！

他大笑着咳嗽了几声，满脸含笑，两次捋了捋挂在他那宽大的下巴底下的稻草一样的山羊胡。

——下一步该做的事，就是在这个证书上签名。

——我要是签名了，你给我多少，斯蒂芬问道。

——我以为你是一位理想主义者，麦卡恩说。

这个长得像吉卜赛人的学生四周看看，然后用一种含糊的悲伤的声调对他身边的人说。

——真见鬼，这可是个奇怪的想法，我认为这种想法，叫作只认得钱。

他说完后，大家全沉默下来。谁也没有对他的话在意。于是他转过他那长得像马一样的橄榄色的脸，望着斯蒂芬，意思要让他讲几句。

麦卡恩开始热情而滔滔不绝地讲起沙皇的诏书，讲起斯特德(30)、普遍裁军、对国际纠纷的仲裁、时代的迹象、新的人类，和一种将使所有的社会全都负起责任来，以最小的代价求得最大多数人的最大幸福的新福音。

他的话刚一说完，那个吉卜赛学生立即报以欢呼声：

——让我们为整个人类的兄弟般的团结三呼万岁！

——说下去，坦普尔，他旁边的一个矮胖的、脸色红润的学生说，回头我请你喝一瓶。

——我的信念是建立全人类的兄弟般的团结，坦普尔说，用他的椭圆形的黑眼睛向四周望望。马克思只不过是一个大傻瓜。

克兰利使劲抓住他的一只胳膊让他别再说下去了，他很不安地微笑着重复说：

——别上火，别上火，别上火！

坦普尔挣脱了胳膊，嘴角上挂着唾沫星子，仍然继续说：

——社会主义是一个爱尔兰人开创的，第一个在欧洲宣传思想自由的是柯林斯(31)。那是两百年以前的事了。那位米德尔塞克斯的哲学家不相信神父们搞的那套玩意儿。让我们为约翰·安东尼·柯林斯三呼万岁吧！

站在那一圈人最外边的一个人尖着嗓子回答说：

——万岁！万岁！

莫伊尼汉在斯蒂芬的耳边低声说：

——关于约翰·安东尼的可怜的小妹妹可怎么办(32)：

洛蒂·柯林斯丢掉了她的裤衩；
好心人，你能不能把你的借给她？

斯蒂芬大笑起来，莫伊尼汉看到他笑，感到很高兴，于是又接着低声说：

——关于约翰·安东尼·柯林斯，我们可以多拿出五个先令来打赌。

——我在等待你的回答哩，麦卡恩直截了当地说。

——你说的那些事我丝毫不感兴趣，斯蒂芬厌倦地说，这一点你知道得很清楚。你干吗还要这样吵吵嚷嚷呢？

——那好吧！麦卡恩说，吧嗒了一下嘴唇。那么说，你是一个反动派？

——你以为你挥舞你那根木头剑，斯蒂芬问道，我就会对你另眼看待了吗？

——这不过是打比喻！麦卡恩仍板着脸说，让咱们来谈谈事实。

斯蒂芬脸一红转过身去。麦卡恩仍然寸步不让，他怀着敌意说：

——那些较小的诗人，我想，对这些什么普遍和平的小问题是不会感兴趣的。

克兰利扬起头来，把他的皮球举在那两个学生中间，表示要让他们议和，他说：

——Pax super totum sanguinarium globum．(33)

斯蒂芬从那些旁观者的身边走开，向着沙皇的头像愤怒地一耸肩膀说：

——留着你们的那个偶像吧。如果我们必须有一个耶稣，那就让我们有一个完全合法的耶稣。

——天理良心，这句话可是说在点子上了！那个吉卜赛学生对周围的人说，这句话说得真漂亮。这种说法让我感到说不出的高兴。

他仿佛要吞下这句话，咽下了哽在他喉咙里的口水，然后他摸摸自己的花呢帽的顶盖，转向斯蒂芬说：

——请原谅，先生，你刚才说的那句话究竟是什么意思呢？

他感到身边的同学们正向他挤过来，因而对他们说：

——我现在真想知道，他说的那句话是什么意思。

他又一次转向斯蒂芬，在他耳边低声说：

——你相不相信耶稣基督？我的信仰是人。当然，我不知道你对人相信不相信。我崇拜你，先生。我崇拜不受一切宗教影响的人的头脑。你刚才那句话就是你对耶稣的心灵的见解吗？

——说下去，坦普尔，那个红脸盘的矮胖学生说，一如他往常的习惯，现在又回到他最早的想法上去，那瓶酒还等着你哩。

他认为我是一个白痴，坦普尔对斯蒂芬解释说，因为我相信人的智力的巨大威力。

克兰利和斯蒂芬以及他的崇拜者一起挽起手来说：

——Nos ad manum ballum jocabimus．(34)

斯蒂芬在被拉走的时候，看到了麦卡恩那张小鼻子小眼儿的通红的脸。

——我的签字没有任何作用，他客气地说，你按照你自己的路走下去是完全对的。让我也按我的路往下走吧。

——迪达勒斯，麦卡恩干脆地说，我相信你是一个很正派的人，可是你也应该理解到利他主义的可贵和个人对人类的责任。

又一个声音说：

——让有才气的怪僻之论停留在这个运动外边，看来比让它混到运动里边来要更好一些。

斯蒂芬听出那是麦卡利斯特的粗哑的声音，因而并没有向那边转过头去。克兰利一本正经地在一大堆学生中间向前挤着，让斯蒂芬和坦普尔护在他的两边，那样子仿佛是一位大祭司在他的助手陪伴下正向祭坛走去。

坦普尔急切地向克兰利的胸前俯过身子去说：

——你刚才有没有听见麦卡利斯特在讲些什么？那小子对你非常嫉妒。你看出来了没有？我敢打赌克兰利完全没有看出来。我敢他妈的发誓，我可是一眼就瞧出来了。

在他们走过里面的大厅的时候，副教导主任正极力想从那个和他谈话的学生身边脱身。他站在楼梯口，一只脚踏在楼梯最下一层阶梯上，撩起他的破旧的袈裟像女人似的小心翼翼的往上爬去，不时还点头重复说：

——这完全无可怀疑，哈克特先生！太好了！完全无可怀疑！

在大厅中间学校教会的负责人正严肃地、用一种温和而毫不饶人的口气在和一个寄宿生讲话。他一边说一边皱起他那满是斑点的眉头，而其在说话中还不时咬着一个很小的铅笔头。

——我希望新生今天都会来了。艺术班第一班是肯定会来的。艺术二班也会来。可是我们一定要把新生的情况全都弄清楚。

当他们走过门口的时候，坦普尔又向克兰利俯过身来急促地低声说：

——你可知道他是结过婚的？他在他们让他皈依上帝以前就已经结过婚了。他的老婆孩子都没有住在这里。他妈的，这可是我从没听说过的一件最稀奇的事！嗯？

他的耳语慢慢变成了狡猾的咯咯的大笑声。他们一走过那个门洞，克兰利马上粗暴地抓住他的脖子使劲摇晃着说：

——你这个该死的他妈的笨蛋！我敢拿我的脑袋打赌，在整个这个他妈的浑蛋的世界上，你知道吗，再也找不出第二个像你这么浑蛋的大傻瓜了！

坦普尔使劲在他的手中挣扎着，仍暗暗感到满意，大笑不止，克兰利却一直粗暴地摇晃着他，一个劲儿重复说：

——一个他妈的该死的浑蛋白痴！

他们走过了长满荒草的花园。穿着一身笨重、宽大衣服的校长，沿着一条小道朝他们走过来，嘴里还不停地念着他的祷文。走到小道尽头的时候，他停下来朝他们这边望着。那几个学生向他敬礼，坦普尔和刚才一样用手摸了摸他的帽子的顶盖。他们一声不响仍然向前走去。在他们走近那条胡同的时候，斯蒂芬听到玩球的人用手打在一个湿水的球上的声音，并且听到每打一下达文都发出一阵激动的叫喊。

达文坐在一只木箱上看他们打球，这三个学生也在那里停了下来。过了一会儿坦普尔横着身子向斯蒂芬靠过来说：

——对不起，我想问问你，你相信让·雅克·卢梭是一个规矩人吗？

斯蒂芬马上大笑起来。克兰利从脚边的草地上拾起一块破木桶板，立即转过身来严厉地说：

——坦普尔，我向活着的上帝发誓，你要是敢，你知道吗，再吱声和任何人谈任何问题，我就会立刻把你宰了。

——我想，斯蒂芬说，他完全和你一样是一个容易感情冲动的人。

——去他妈的吧，让他见鬼去！克兰利爽朗地说，可别再跟他谈话了。说真的，你要是跟坦普尔谈话，你知道吗，还不如跟一个他妈的破夜壶去谈哩。回家吧，坦普尔。看在上帝的面上，回家去吧。

——我根本不拿你他妈的当回事，克兰利，坦普尔回答说，他一边躲开那举起的木桶板，一边用手指着斯蒂芬。他是我在这个学院里见到的唯一一个有独立思考能力的人。

——学院！独立思考！克兰利大叫着说，回家去吧，见你的鬼去，因为你是一个毫无希望的浑蛋。

——我是一个爱动感情的人，坦普尔说，他那句话说得完全对。我为我自己多愁善感感到骄傲。

他斜着身子走出胡同，脸上仍挂着狡猾的微笑。克兰利脸上毫无表情地一直看着他。

——你瞧他！他说，你过去见过这样一个慌慌张张的家伙吗？

他这句话招来了一个学生的一阵奇怪的大笑，他那时正靠墙根站着，高顶的帽子盖在眼睛上。那笑声调门很高，发笑的又是一个身材魁梧的男人，因而那声音简直像大象的一声长鸣。这学生止不住浑身抖动着，为了让自己止住这欢乐的笑声，他显得十分高兴地用双手揉着自己的腰。

——林奇已经醒了，克兰利说。

林奇伸了伸懒腰，挺了挺胸脯，作为回答。

——林奇挺出他的胸脯，斯蒂芬说，作为对生活的一种批评。

林奇嘣嘣地敲着自己的胸脯说：

——谁还对我这一身力气不服气吗？

克兰利表示不信那一套，于是两人开始摔跤。摔了一会儿两人都累得满脸通红，然后喘着气分开了手。斯蒂芬向达文弯过腰去，可是达文正一心一意看球赛，对别人的讲话完全没有在意。

——我的那个驯服的小鹅怎么样？他问道，他也签名了吗？

达文点点头说：

——你呢，斯蒂维？

斯蒂芬摇了摇头。

——你这人真可怕，斯蒂维，达文说，从嘴边拿下短杆烟斗，你总是自己干自己的。

——那么你是在要求普遍和平的请愿书上签过名了，斯蒂芬说，那我想你一定会把我那天在你房间里看到的那个小练习本烧掉吧。

达文没有回答，斯蒂芬于是开始念着小本儿里的话：

——大踏步前进，芬尼亚主义者！朝着正确的方向前进，芬尼亚主义者！芬尼亚主义者，报数！我向你们致敬，一，二！

——那完全是另外一个问题，达文说，首先和最主要的，我是一个爱尔兰民族主义者。可你也应该完全是那样。而你生来对什么都一味冷嘲热讽，斯蒂维。

——你们下一次再用棒球棍来造反的时候，斯蒂芬说，如果想找到一个必不可少的告密的人，你们只要告诉我一声好了。在这个学校里我可以替你们找到几个的。

——我简直没法儿理解你，达文说，一会儿我听到你大声疾呼反对英国文学。现在你又在反对爱尔兰的告密者。想想你的名字和你的那些思想……你到底是不是一个爱尔兰人？

——你现在跟我一起到纹章档案馆去，我马上就可以让你看到我们家的家谱，斯蒂芬说。

——那你就跟我们站在一起吧，达文说，你为什么不学爱尔兰文？你为什么在青年联合班刚上了一课就退出来了？

——其中一个理由你是知道的，斯蒂芬说。

达文一扬头大笑起来。

——哦，行啦，他说，就是因为某一位年轻小姐和莫兰神父吗？可那全是你自己在那儿瞎想，斯蒂维。他们只不过在一块儿说说笑笑罢了。

斯蒂芬沉默着把一只手友善地放在达文肩上。

——你还记得，他说，我们第一次相识的情况吗？我们相遇的第一天早晨，你问我到新生班去怎么走，你说这句话时音调非常特别。你还记得吗？后来我听到你管那些耶稣会会员都称神父，你还记得吗？我那时就常常问我自己：他真是像他说话那样天真无邪吗？

——我是一个头脑很简单的人，达文说，这你知道得很清楚。那天夜晚在哈考特街你对我讲了许多关于你自己的私生活以后，上帝作证，斯蒂维，我几天都吃不下饭去。我感到非常不舒服。那天晚上我一直躺着，很长时间都没有睡着。你为什么要对我讲那些事情呢？

——非常感谢，斯蒂芬说，你的意思是说我简直像个妖怪。

——不，达文说，但我真希望你没有对我讲那些事情。

在斯蒂芬的友情的宁静的水面之下开始出现了一股浪潮。

——这个民族和这个国家和这种生活产生了我这样一个人，他说，我心里怎么想就一定要怎么说。

——请你尽量和我们站在一起吧，达文重复说，在你的内心深处你是一个爱尔兰人，可是你让你的骄傲把你给制服住了。

——我的祖先抛掉了他们自己的语言，接受了另一种语言，斯蒂芬说，他们容许一小撮外国人把他们征服了。你难道认为我会拿我的身家性命来偿付他们欠下的债吗？再说那又是为了什么呢？

——为了我们的自由，达文说。

——从托恩的时代到帕内尔的时代，斯蒂芬说，没有一个正派、诚实的，为爱尔兰牺牲自己的生命、青春和爱情的人，不是被你们出卖给敌人或者在他最需要你们的时候被你们抛弃掉或者受到了你们的咒诅，你们扔下他又去追随另外一个人。可现在你却要我站在你们一边。我倒宁愿先看到你们全都见鬼去吧。

——他们是为他们的理想贡献了自己的生命，达文说，你相信我的话吧，有一天我们会胜利的。

斯蒂芬想着自己的心思，很久没有说话。

——就在我刚说到的那个时代，他含含糊糊地说，灵魂首先诞生了。它的诞生缓慢而阴森，比肉体的诞生更为神秘。当一个人的灵魂在这个国家诞生的时候，马上就有许多网在他的周围张开，防止他飞掉。你和我谈什么民族、语言、宗教。我准备要冲破那些罗网高飞远扬。

达文搕掉了烟斗里的烟灰。

——你的话太深奥，我没法理解，斯蒂维，他说，可是一个人首先应该考虑的是自己的国家。首先是爱尔兰，斯蒂维。然后你才能说你是一个诗人或者是一个神秘主义者。

——你知道爱尔兰是个什么吗？斯蒂芬带着冷酷的愤怒的感情问道。爱尔兰是一个吃掉自己的猪崽子的老母猪。

达文从他的木箱子上站起来悲伤地摇着头，朝着那些打球的人走去。但不一会儿那悲伤的情绪已经过去，他又跟克兰利和那两个刚打完球的同学热烈地争论起来。他们准备来一场有四个人参加的双打，但克兰利坚持要用他的那个球。他让它在地上跳了两三下，然后迅速地使劲一下把球朝本垒打去，随着球的撞击声，他也大叫一声：

——你的灵魂！

斯蒂芬和林奇站在一旁观望着，不久，双方都获得了很大比分。然后他扯一扯他的袖子准备走开。林奇一边跟他走一边说：

——让我们亦走吧，像克兰利说的。

斯蒂芬对他这侧面的一击不禁笑了笑。

他们又向回走，穿过花园走到大厅外面去，那里一个老态龙钟的工友正在一个布告牌上粘贴一个通知。走到台阶下面，他们停了下来，斯蒂芬从口袋里拿出一包香烟，递给他的伙伴。

——我知道你很穷，他说。

——让你那下流的傲慢情绪见鬼去吧，林奇回答说。

这表明林奇很有教养的第二个证明使得斯蒂芬又笑了。

——你现在决心用下流这样的字眼来骂街，他说，这表明欧洲人的教养已经达到最高水平了。

他们各自点燃了一支香烟，然后转身朝右边走去。过了一会儿斯蒂芬又说：

——亚里士多德并没有对怜悯和恐惧下过定义。我下过。我说……

林奇停住脚步毫不客气地说：

——你别说！我不要听！我有些不舒服。昨天晚上我跟霍兰和戈金斯都下流地喝醉了。

斯蒂芬仍然继续说：

——怜悯是使人的头脑停留于任何一种人所遭受的严肃而经常的痛苦之中，并使它和受苦的人相联系的一种感情。恐惧是使人的头脑停留于任何一种人所遭受的严肃而经常的痛苦之中，而使它和某种难于理解的原因相联系的感情。

——你再说一遍，林奇说。

斯蒂芬又慢慢地重述了他的这两个定义。

——几天前，一个小姑娘，他接着说，在伦敦街上坐上了一辆小马车。她准备去会见她多年未见的母亲。在一条街的拐角处，一辆马车的辕杆捅碎了马车的玻璃，在玻璃上留下了一个像五星一样的窟窿。一块又细又长像针一样的碎玻璃直刺透了她的心脏。她当场就死去了。记者们都说她死得很惨。这话不对。根据我对怜悯和恐惧所下的定义，她这种死和那两种情绪都完全不相干。

——事实上，悲伤的情绪是一张向两面观望着的脸，一面朝着恐惧，一面朝着怜悯，而这两者都不过是它的两个不同的阶段。你瞧我用的是停留这个词。我的意思是说悲哀的情绪是静态的。或者应该说任何戏剧性的情绪都是静态的。不正当的艺术所挑起的感情却是动态的，比如像欲望或者厌恶。欲望使人产生占有的念头，让人要去追求什么东西；厌恶则使人产生抛弃的念头，让人想要避开什么东西。因此凡是挑起这种情绪的艺术都是不正当的艺术，不管是淫秽的也好，还是专门说教的也好。审美的感情（我说的是这个词的一般含义）因此也是静态的。它使人的头脑停留在某一状态之中，超出于欲望和厌恶的情绪之上。

——你是说艺术绝不能挑起人的情欲，林奇说，我跟你说过，有一天在博物馆里，我用铅笔在普拉克西提勒斯(35)雕塑的维纳斯的屁股上写下了我的名字。你能说那不是情欲吗？

——我说的是人的正常天性，斯蒂芬说，你还跟我说过，当你还是一个在可爱的加尔默罗教会学校念书的孩子的时候，你曾经吃过好多块干牛粪。

林奇又一次发出像大象鸣叫一样的笑声，又一次用他的两手在他的两边腰胯上揉着，可是这一次他并没有把手从口袋里抽出来。

——哦，我吃过！我吃过！他大声叫着说。

斯蒂芬向他的这位伙伴转过脸去，直盯着他的眼睛看了一会儿。林奇在慢慢停住笑以后，也用他羞怯的眼光回看着他。那很高的尖顶帽下面的那个又细又长的扁平的脑袋让斯蒂芬想起了眼镜蛇的形象。他那眼睛也像蛇一样目光炯炯地闪着光。然而就在那一瞬间，那一对看来既谦和又警觉的眼睛却被一种细微的人的气质照亮，它们仿佛变成了一个缩成一团、机智而又自怨自艾的灵魂的窗户。

——说到这一点，斯蒂芬客气地补充说，我们都不过是些普通动物。我也不过是一个普通动物。

——你当然是，林奇说。

——不过我们现在正好生活在一个心灵的世界中，斯蒂芬接着说，用不正当的美的手段挑起的情欲和厌恶都绝不能说是美的感情，这不仅仅因为在性质上它们是动态的，而且还因为它们并没超出肉体的范围。我们的肉体，纯粹依靠神经系统的反射活动，对我们害怕的东西本能地退缩，而对能够刺激我们的情欲的东西表示欢迎。我们的眼皮，在我们还没有发现一个苍蝇要飞进我们的眼睛的时候，就会自动地闭上了。

——也并不总是这样，林奇表示不完全同意地说。

——同样的，斯蒂芬说，你的肉体对一个裸体的雕像的刺激发生反应，可是我说，那只不过是简单的神经反射活动罢了。艺术家所表现的美不可能在我们身上引起动态的感情或者纯属于肉体的激情。它唤醒，或者应该唤醒，诱发，或者应该诱发一种美的静态平衡，一种意念上的怜悯或意念上的恐惧，这种静态平衡将招致、延长以及最后消除我所说的美的节奏。

——你的话到底怎么讲呢？林奇问道。

——节奏，斯蒂芬说，是任何一个美的整体的一部分同另一部分之间，或任何一个美的整体同它的一部分或各部分之间，或者作为一个美的整体的一部分的任何部分和这个美的整体之间的首要的形式上的美学关系。

——如果你把那个叫作节奏，林奇说，那让咱们听听什么是美呢？我还要请你记住，尽管从前我曾吃过牛粪，我最赞赏的却只有美。

斯蒂芬仿佛要对他敬礼似的摸摸自己的帽子。然后脸上微微一红，把他的一只手放在林奇的厚花呢的袖子上。

——我们是对的，他说，其他的人全都错了。谈论这些东西，试图理解它们的性质，既理解之后，就设法通过这粗糙的泥块，或者它所要求的任何东西，通过作为我们的灵魂的牢门的声音、形态和色彩，来表现出，或者说来再现我们现在正试图理解的美的形象——那就是艺术。

他们这时已经走到运河的桥上，他们离开正道，沿着一排树林走过去。照在一摊死水上的刺眼的灰暗的光线、从他们头上湿漉漉的树枝上散发出的气息仿佛都极力要打断斯蒂芬的思绪。

——可是你还没有回答我的问题，林奇说，什么是艺术？什么是艺术所表现的美？

——我刚才自己思索这个问题的时候，斯蒂芬说，你这个昏头昏脑的家伙，念给你听的那第一个定义就是这个。你还记得那天晚上的事情吗？克兰利忽然发起脾气来，他开始谈论什么威克罗火腿问题。

——我记得，林奇说，他还跟我们谈到那些该死的魔鬼一般的肥猪。

——艺术，斯蒂芬说，是人类为了美学的目的对于可感知的或者可理解的东西所做的安排。你还记得那些猪，却忘记了这个。你和克兰利，你们这一对儿真叫人毫无办法。

林奇向着多云的灰暗的天空做了一个鬼脸，接着说：

——如果要我听你这一套美学上的大道理，你至少还得给我一根香烟。对那玩意儿我可没有什么兴趣。我甚至对女人也没有兴趣。让你和你那一套都见鬼去吧。我要找到一个每年能拿到五百镑的工作。你也没有办法给我找到这么一个工作。

斯蒂芬把一包香烟递给他。林奇从里面拿出了仅有的最后一支烟，然后毫不在意地说：

——讲下去！

——亚奎纳斯，斯蒂芬说，曾说凡是使人高兴的感受就是美。

林奇点点头。

——我记得他的原话是，他说：“Pulera sunt quoe visa placent．”

——他在这里用了visa(36)这个词，斯蒂芬说，意思是要包括各种各样的感受，不管是通过视觉或者听觉或者通过任何其他的道路感知到的东西都包括在内。这个字，虽然意义有些含糊，却也清楚地表明，引起人的欲望或者厌恶的善与恶的观念是并不包括在内的。它的意思只包括某种静态平衡，而不是动态的东西。关于真又怎么样呢？真也能够在人的头脑中产生一种静态平衡。你就绝不会用铅笔在一个直角三角形的屁股上写上你的名字。

——那当然，林奇说，我只要普拉克西提勒斯雕刻的维纳斯的屁股。

——因此是静态的，斯蒂芬说，据我记得，柏拉图曾说过美是真散发的光辉。这话在我看来并无任何意义，但是真和美显然是互相关联的。可以使我们用以观赏真的智力获得安抚的是可理解的事物中的最完美的关系，而可以使我们用以观赏美的想象得到安抚的却是可以感知的事物中的最完美的关系。通向真的第一步是理解智力本身的结构和规模，对智力活动本身获得了解。亚里士多德的整个一套哲学系统的基础就是他的讲心理学的那部书，而他那部书在我看来又是以这样一个论点作为基础的，那就是，同样一个属性不可能在同一个时候和在同一种关系中属于又不属于同样一个事物。通向美的第一步却是要理解想象的结构和规模，要对美的感受的活动本身有所了解。我的话说清楚了吗？

——可到底什么是美呢？林奇不耐烦地问道。再念一个定义让我听听。就只是任何我们看到并喜欢的东西！闹了半天你和亚奎纳斯所能说的也只不过是这些吗？

——让咱们拿女人来做个例子，斯蒂芬说。

——让咱们来谈谈女人！林奇热情地说。

——希腊人、土耳其人、中国人、科普特人(37)和霍屯督人(38)，斯蒂芬说，各自崇拜完全不同类型的女人的美。这似乎就让我们陷在一个无法逃出的迷宫里面了。但我看却有两条出路。一条是这样的一个假定：男人对女人的肉体所崇拜的任何一点都和女人为了传宗接代而具有的多方面的功能直接有关。可能就是这样。这个世界似乎甚至比你，林奇所想象的还要更无聊得多。就我来说，我不喜欢这样一条出路。这条出路只能通向优生学，而不是美学。它把你领出那迷宫后，却把你领进一个新的装饰得很花哨的教室里去，在那个教室里麦卡恩一手放在《物种起源》上，另一只手放在《新约》上对你说，你所以崇拜维纳斯的粗大的腰身，是因为你感到她将可以为你生下又肥又壮的子孙，你所以崇拜她那一对肥大的乳房，是因为你感到她将可以有足够的肥美的奶水来喂养她的也就是你的孩子。

——照你说，麦卡恩是个无比下流的骗子，林奇热情地说。

——可是另外还有一条出路，斯蒂芬大笑着说。

——那就是？林奇说。

——这样一个假定，斯蒂芬说。

这时一辆很长的平板车上面装满了破铜烂铁，从帕特里克·邓恩的医院拐角处开了过来，发出一阵刺耳的丁零哐啷的金属声，完全掩盖了斯蒂芬下面所讲的话。林奇两手捂着耳朵一句接一句不停地咒骂着，直到那平板车过去了才算完。然后他粗暴地一转身子。斯蒂芬也转过身来，停了一会儿，他这位伙伴的怒气慢慢平息下去。

——这个假设是，斯蒂芬重复说，另外一条出路，那就是，尽管同样一件事物不一定所有的人看来都觉得美，但是凡欣赏一件美的事物的所有的人都一定能够在其中找到某种能够满足美的感受的各个阶段本身的要求，并和它们相适应的关系。这种可以通过这种形式让你看到，又通过另一种形式让我看到的可感知事物的关系，就必然是美的必不可少的特性。现在我们还可以从我们的老朋友圣托马斯那里再找一找，看能不能再借来几分钱的智慧。

林奇大笑了。

——听到你时不时像一个地道的行脚僧一样引用他的话，他说，真让我感到有趣极了。你自己是否偷偷在暗笑呢？

——麦卡利斯特，斯蒂芬回答说，可能把我的美学理论叫作实用的亚奎纳斯学说。沿着美的哲学这条线来讲，我是一直追随亚奎纳斯的。但当我们接触到艺术感受现象，艺术的孕育和艺术的再生等问题的时候，我却有我自己的一套新的用语和新的个人经验。

——那当然，林奇说。不管怎么说，亚奎纳斯尽管智力过人，仍不过是一个地地道道的行脚僧。可是关于那新的个人经验和新的用语等，你将来有机会再对我讲吧。现在快快讲完你的第一部分。

——谁知道呢？斯蒂芬微笑着说，也许亚奎纳斯比你更能理解我的话。他自己是一个诗人。他曾为濯足节写过一首赞美诗。那首诗开头几个词是“Pange lingua gloriosi”(39)。他们说这首诗为赞美诗获得了最高的荣誉。那是一首含义复杂、给人很大安慰的赞美诗。我很喜欢它，但是没有任何一首赞美诗可以和费南提厄斯·佛吐纳忒斯的Vexilla Regis(40)，那首悲哀而庄严的入场歌同日而语。

林奇开始用一种低沉的声音庄严而轻柔地唱起来：

Impleta sunt quoe concinit
David fideli carmine
Dicendo nationlbus
Regnavit a ligno Dens．(41)

——实在太伟大了！他很高兴地说，这真是伟大的音乐！

他们转身向下蒙特街走去。在离拐角不远的地方，一个胖胖的年轻人围着一条丝巾，停下来向他们敬礼。

——你们听说考试的结果了吗？他问道，格里芬是完了。哈尔平和奥弗林通过了政府法令考试。穆南的印度语得了个第五。奥肖内西考了个第十四名。昨天晚上克拉克的那些爱尔兰老乡请他们大吃了一顿。他们都吃了许多咖喱。

他苍白肥胖的脸上表现出一种善意的怨恨，当他一边讲述这些胜利的消息一边往前走时，他肿眼皮的小眼睛从他们眼前消失，他微弱的尖细的声音也慢慢听不见了。

为了回答斯蒂芬的一个问题，他的眼睛和他的声音又从它们隐藏的地方显露了出来。

——是的，还有麦卡拉和我，他说，他准备学纯数学，我准备学宪法史。一共有二十种学科。我还准备学植物学。你们知道，我是野游俱乐部的成员。

他做出很庄严的样子从那两人的身边退开，同时把一双戴着羊毛手套的肥大的手放在自己的胸脯上，很快从那里发出一阵被压抑着的尖细的大笑声。

——下次你们出去的时候，斯蒂芬一本正经地说，给我们带点萝卜和蒜头来，好让我们做一次烧肉。

那个胖学生纵声大笑说：

——我们野游俱乐部的成员可都是非常规矩的体面人物。上星期六我们到格伦马卢尔去了，一共有七个人。

——还有女人吧，多诺万？林奇说。

多诺万又一次把他的一只手放在胸脯上说：

——我们的目的是追求知识。

然后他急促地说：

——我听说你正在写一篇关于美学的论文。

斯蒂芬做了一个模糊的手势，表示并无其事。

——歌德和莱辛，多诺万说，对这个问题都写过不少文章，什么古典派，又是什么浪漫派的，简直说不清。我读过《拉奥孔》，那本书让我很感兴趣。当然那都是些唯心主义的东西，那些德国人的作品可是深奥极了。

另外那两个人谁也没有说话。多诺万有礼貌地向他们告别。

——我一定得走了，他轻柔而和善地说，我非常相信，几乎已经变成了一个肯定的信念，我妹妹今天要给多诺万全家做煎饼当晚餐。

——再见，斯蒂芬在他的身后说，别忘了给我和我的伙伴们带萝卜。

林奇望着他的背影，嘴唇慢慢卷曲着显露出轻蔑的表情，直到最后，他的整个脸更露出一副恶狠狠的神态：

——想想这个好吃煎饼的屎巴巴橛儿定能找个好工作，他最后说，而我却不能不抽这种蹩脚的烟卷儿！

他们向梅里昂广场那边转过身去，一声不响向前走了一段。

——让我把我刚才讲的关于美的问题说完吧，斯蒂芬说，可感知的事物的最完美的关系，因此就必须能够和艺术感受的各个必要的阶段相适应。抓住了这一点，你就抓住了一切美的基本特点。亚奎纳斯说：Ad pulcritudinem tria requiruntur integritas，consonantia，claritas．我把这句话翻译成这样：任何一种美必须具备三样东西，完整、和谐和光彩。这些东西是否和感受的各个阶段相适应呢？你明不明白我讲的话？

——当然，我明白，林奇说，如果你认为我也只有屎巴巴橛儿那点智慧，那你快去赶上多诺万，让他来听你讲吧。

斯蒂芬指着一个屠户的儿子扣在脑袋上的一个竹篮子。

——你看那个篮子，他说。

——我看见了，林奇说。

——为了看清那个篮子，斯蒂芬说，你的头脑首先必须把篮子和宇宙间其他一切可见的非篮子的东西区分开来。感受的第一阶段是，在你要感受的东西的周围画下一个轮廓来。一个美的形象是或者通过空间，或者通过时间呈现在我们眼前的。可以用耳朵听见的东西通过时间呈现出来，可以用眼睛看见的东西便通过空间呈现出来。但不管空间也罢时间也罢，那美的形象，在与它无关的不可限量的空间或时间的背景上，首先必须作为一件有自己的轮廓和有自己的内容的东西被人所清楚地感知。你首先感觉到它是一件东西。你看到一件完整的东西。你感受到了它的完整性。这就是integritas （完整）。

——一箭中的！林奇大笑着说，再讲下去。

——然后，斯蒂芬说，你沿着构成它的形式的线条，一点一点地看下去，你感受到在它的限度之内的各部分之间的平衡，你感觉到了它的结构的节奏。换句话说，紧跟在直接感知的综合活动之后的是对感受的分析。你先已经感觉到它是一件东西，现在你却感觉到它是一个东西。你感知到它复杂、多层、可分、可离，是由许多部分组成的，而这许多部分和它们的总和又是和谐的。这就是consonantia（和谐）。

——又一次一箭中的！林奇俏皮地说，那么现在再告诉我什么是claritas，那你就赢得这支雪茄了。

——这个字的含义，斯蒂芬说，是相当模糊的。亚奎纳斯用了一个看来很不精确的词儿。很长一段时间来，它都使我困惑不解。你很容易想到并且相信，当时他的脑子已被一种象征主义或者唯心主义的东西所占据，以为美的最高特性是从另外一个星球上照来的光，是那物质不过是它的阴影的理念，是只不过作为它的表象的物质后面的真实。我曾经想，他要说的也许是，claritas是人对任何东西或者一种概括力中的神的意志的艺术发现和再现，它使得美的形象成为一种具有普遍意义的形象，使得它散发出远远超过它的一切具体条件的光彩。但这是一种咬文嚼字的说法。我的理解是这样的。当你把那个篮子作为一件东西加以感知，然后又根据它的形式对它加以分析，并把它作为一个东西加以感知之后，你就会作出从逻辑上或从美学上讲唯一可以容许的一种综合。你看到它就是它被视作的那个东西，而不是任何别的东西。这就是他在他那学术性的quidditas，也就是一物之所以然中所说的光彩。这种最高的特性，一个艺术家最初在想象中孕育这个美的形象时便已经感觉到了。雪莱把处于这神秘的一瞬间的心灵，美妙地比作即将熄灭的煤火。美的最高特性，美的形象的清晰的光彩，能被为美的完整所吸引和为美的和谐所陶醉的心灵透彻明晰地加以感受的那一瞬，便是美的喜悦所达到的明晰而安谧的静态平衡，这种精神状态非常像意大利的生理学家路易吉·加尔法尼，用一句和雪莱所用一样美丽的词句，称之为心灵的陶醉的那种心境。

斯蒂芬停住了，虽然他的伙伴并没有说话，他却感到他的话在他们周围唤起了一种思想的陶醉所引起的沉默。

——我刚才说的这些，他又接着说，讲的是广义的美，是美这个词在文学传统中的含义。在市井间，它的意义可就完全不同了。如果从美这个词的第二种意义来谈美，我们的判断首先会受到艺术本身的影响，受到那种艺术的形式的影响。很明显，美的形象必须建立在艺术家自己的头脑或感觉和别人的头脑或感觉之间。如果你记得这一点，你就会看到艺术必须把自己划分为三种形式，一种形式接着一种形式往前推进。这三种形式是：抒情的形式，艺术家利用这种形式表现和他本人直接相关的形象；史诗的形式，艺术家利用这种形式表现和他自己以及其他的人间接相关的形象；戏剧的形式，艺术家利用这种形式表现和别人直接相关的形象。

——关于这一点，前几天晚上你已经对我说过，林奇说，我们还因此发生了一次很激烈的争论。

——在我家里有一本书，斯蒂芬说，我在上面写下了许多显然比你提出的更为有趣的问题。为了回答那些问题，我想到了我现在要向你解释的这些美学上的理论。我向自己提出了这样一些问题：一把做得非常漂亮的椅子，是悲剧性的还是喜剧性的？如果我喜欢看蒙娜·丽莎(42)的画像，那是否就一定说明那是一张画得很好的画？菲利普·克兰普顿的半身雕像是抒情的、史诗式的，还是戏剧性的？如果不是，为什么不是？

——真的，为什么不是？林奇大笑着说。

——如果一个人在愤怒的时候，用刀乱砍一块木头，斯蒂芬接着说，砍出了一头母牛的形象，那这形象算不算一件艺术品？如果不算，为什么不算？

——这个问题提得太好了，林奇说，又笑起来，这问题真带有几分学术的臭味。

——莱辛，斯蒂芬说，本来不应该拿许多雕像来加以论述。这种较为低下的艺术并不能表现出我所讲的彼此严格区分的各种形式。甚至拿文字，这最高和最偏于精神方面的艺术来说，它的各种形式也常常混淆在一起了。抒情形式，事实上是用最简单的语言外衣装扮起来的一瞬间的感情，比如像在几百年前一个人在看到别人使劲摇桨或者把大石块运上山时发出的一阵有节奏的欢呼声。发出这欢呼声的人当时所意识到的只是他那一瞬间的感情，而不是感觉到这种感情的自身。当这一艺术家延续他的这种感情，并把他自己当作一个史诗事件的中心加以反复思索的时候，我们便看到从这种抒情的文学中出现了最简单的史诗的形式。这种形式再慢慢发展下去，到后来那种感情重心的中心点和艺术家本人之间的距离便和它和其他的人之间的距离完全相等了。这时这种叙述就不再是纯个人的东西。艺术家的人格也就慢慢渗透到那叙述本身中去，它像一片澎湃的海洋绕着那里的人物和行动不停地流动。这种进展你在《特平(43)英雄》那古老的英国民歌里可以很容易看得出来，那民歌以第一人称开始，却以第三人称结束。当那海洋以它巨大的力量在每一个人物的周围澎湃起伏，使得每一个人物也都具有这种巨大的力量，而且使他或她形成一种正常的可以感知的美学上的生命的时候，那这叙述便具有了戏剧的形式。艺术家的人格，最初不过表现为一声喊叫或一种节奏感或一种短暂的情绪，接着它却变成了流动的闪烁着光辉的叙述，最后它更使自己升华而失去了存在，或者也可以说，使自己非人格化了。具有戏剧形式的美的形象是在人的想象中加以净化后再次投射出来的一种生命。美学的神秘，和物质的创造的神秘性一样，是逐渐形成的。一个艺术家，和创造万物的上帝一样，永远停留在他的艺术作品之内或之后或之外，人们看不见他，他已使自己升华而失去了存在，毫不在意，在一旁修剪着自己的指甲。

——设法也让它们全部升华，失去存在吧，林奇说。

霏霏细雨开始从蒙着面纱的高天降落下来，他们转进公爵的草坪，要在大雨来临之前赶到国家图书馆去。

——你到底为什么，林奇皱着眉头问道，在这个可怜的被上帝抛弃的岛国上，大谈什么美和什么想象？也难怪艺术家们在把这个国家搞得乱七八糟之后，都躲到他们的艺术作品里面或者后面去了。

雨下得更大了。他们一走过基尔德尔校园前的过道，就看到图书馆前面的拱门里已有许多学生在那里避雨。克兰利靠在一根柱子上，正用一根修尖的火柴棒剔着牙，静听着他的几个伙伴们的谈话。大门口附近还站着几个姑娘。林奇低声对斯蒂芬说：

——你爱的那个人儿也在那儿。

斯蒂芬一声不响，在那些学生下边的一个台阶上找到一个地方站下来，完全不理会越下越大的雨，却不时转眼去看看那个姑娘。她也不声不响地和她的几个伙伴站在一块。这会儿她身边没有一个神父好让她跟他调情了，他带着明显的怨恨的情绪心里想着，记起了他上一次和她见面时的情景。林奇刚才说得很对。他的头脑中的那些理论和所有的勇气刚刚已倒空了，现在已慢慢回到一种没情没绪的宁静中来。

他听到那些学生正随意谈论着。他们谈到已通过期中考试的两个医科学生，谈到在远洋客轮上找工作的机会，和行医能捞钱不能捞钱的问题。

——那全都是些空话，到爱尔兰乡村去行医肯定会好得多。

——海因斯在利物浦已待了两年了，他也这么说。他说那个破地方简直令人可怕。整天没别的尽是给人接生。

——那你是说在农村找一个工作，比在这个富足的城市里还要好吗？我知道有一个家伙……

——海因斯根本没有头脑。他完全是靠死用功才念毕业的，纯粹靠死用功。

——不用去管他吧。在一个大商业城市里你可以赚到很多钱。

——那要看你的生意怎么样了。

——Ego credo ut vita pauperum est simpliciter atrox，simpliciter sanguinarius atrox，in Liverpoolio．(44)

他们的说话声仿佛从很远的地方时起时落地传进他的耳朵里来。她准备和她的同伴们一起走了。

那阵急促的小阵雨已慢慢过去，只是在那正方形广场中的丛林上留下一串串珍珠般的水滴，同时那正方形广场上的黑色的泥土发出一种奇怪的气息。她们都站在柱廊前的台阶上，她们干净的靴子不时发出一阵啪啪声，她们安静而高兴地谈讲着，时而看看天上的云彩，举起雨伞，寻找适当的角度挡住最后的几点雨滴。时而又把伞收起来，一本正经地搂起自己的裙子。

他对她的评价是否太过分了？她的生活是否真会像一串念珠一样的简单，她的生活是否真会像一只小鸟的生活一样简单而又离奇。清早非常轻快，一天烦躁不安，到太阳落下时又感到非常疲倦？她的心是否和一只小鸟的心一样简单而又自信？

在快天亮的时候，他醒来了。啊，多么甜蜜的音乐！他的灵魂全都被露水浸湿了。在睡梦中一阵阵惨白、清凉的光的波浪从他的肢体上漂了过去。他安静地躺着，仿佛他的灵魂正躺在一潭清水中，耳边却一直响着微弱的甜蜜的音乐。他的头脑慢慢清醒过来，品尝到闪耀着黎明的清光的知识和清晨的灵感。一种像最纯的水一样纯净，像露水一样甜蜜，像音乐一样动人的精神充满了他的身心。但那精神进入他的身体时是那样的轻巧，那样的毫无激情，仿佛是那些天使长自己在对着他嘘气！他的灵魂正慢慢地醒来，害怕自己会完全清醒了。这时正是黎明前的无风的时刻，在这时疯狂的情绪都会清醒过来，奇怪的植物都会向光明展开它的叶子，飞蛾也会静静地开始飞出了。

一种心灵的陶醉！夜也已经陶醉了。在一个梦境或幻境中，他已经体会到了天使般的生活的狂喜。这仅只是一瞬间的陶醉，或者还会延续许多小时、许多年甚至许多世纪呢？

那一瞬间的灵感现在似乎忽然从各个方面，从已经发生或者可能发生的无数暧昧的情况中反射出来。那一瞬间像一点亮光一样忽然闪现，而现在从那模糊情景的团团云雾中飞出的混乱的形式却缓缓地盖住了它的余光。啊！在想象的处女的子宫里，语言文字已变得更加清新了。天使长加布里埃尔(45)已经进入了这个处女的闺房。当白色的光焰过去以后，在他的精神中那红色的余光越变越深，最后变成了玫瑰色的充满热情的光亮，那玫瑰色的充满热情的光亮便是她的离奇的、自有其主见的心，它离奇得从不为人所知，将来也不会为人所知，它的主见先于天地之始便已经存在了。在那种充满热情的玫瑰般的火光的引诱下，众天使的歌声正从天上飘落到人间。

你对你那永恒的热情岂不感到厌倦？
你简直可以迷住堕落的天使长。
啊，不要再提那令人陶醉的华年。

这诗行从他的心中来到他的唇边，低声把它重念一遍，他感到一首维兰内尔(46)的有力的节奏流过了他的嘴唇。那玫瑰般的火光散发出一道道它的韵律的光线；厌倦，华年，火焰，香烟，歌篇。它的光线使整个世界燃烧起来，消融了人的心和天使的心：从这玫瑰中射出的光线便是她的自有主见的心灵。

你在男人的心中燃起了热情的火焰，
你让他为你失去了自己的主张。
你对你那永恒的热情岂不感到厌倦？

后来呢？那节奏慢慢消失，停止了一会儿，接着又开始一拍一拍地活动起来。后来呢？后来是烟雾，那从人世的祭坛上向上飞去的香烟。

在那火焰上飘动着赞美的香烟，
它从海面上一圈圈飞向天上。
啊，不要再提那令人陶醉的华年。

香烟从整个大地的地面上，从整个沸腾的海洋上向上飘去，那是为赞美她而升起的香烟。整个地球像一个被来回摇晃着的香炉，它本身便是一个用香料做成的大球，一个椭圆形的球。那节奏忽然终止了，从他心中发出的呼喊声已变得断断续续。他的嘴开始一次再次默默念诵着那第一节诗；接着他勉强念完了全诗的上半部分，结结巴巴，念不下去了；然后他停住了。他的心的呼号声已变得断断续续了。

那罩着面纱的无风的时刻已经过去了，在赤裸裸的玻璃窗的后面，晨间的清光正在慢慢聚集。从极远的地方传来了微弱的钟声。一只鸟在啾啾鸣叫，两只鸟，三只。那钟声和鸟叫都停止了，一股冷漠的白色的光向东方和西方铺展开去，盖住了整个世界，盖住了他心中的玫瑰色的光亮。

担心一切会全部消失掉，他匆匆用胳膊撑起身子寻找纸片和铅笔。但这两样东西桌上全都没有，而只有他昨天吃晚饭时用过的一个汤盘和满是蜡泪的一个烛台，烛台的纸做的承盘还留有昨天的火焰燃烧后的痕迹。他疲倦地把手向脚那边伸去，在那里挂着的一件上衣口袋里乱摸索。他的手碰到了一支铅笔，接着还碰到一个香烟盒。他回身倒在床上，撕开香烟盒，把里面的最后一支香烟放在窗台上，开始用清晰细小的笔画在那粗糙的纸盒面上写下他那首维兰内尔诗体的几节诗。

全部写完以后，他躺在那已被压扁的枕头上，低声念了一遍。他头下枕头里结成团的毛绒使他想起了她的客厅沙发里结成团的马毛。他曾多次微笑着或者严肃地坐在那沙发上，由于对她和对他自己感到生气，止不住一再问自己为什么到那里去了，而那贴在光秃秃的炉台上面的《神圣的心》的图片更使他感到心烦意乱。他看她在一阵催人欲睡的谈话中向他走了过来，请他唱一支他平常唱过的那些奇怪的歌。然后，他就看到自己在那张古老的钢琴边坐了下来，用手轻轻敲打着那已满是斑纹的琴键，然后，在屋子里又一次响起的谈话声中，看着她倚立在炉台边，为他唱一支伊丽莎白时代的精巧的歌曲，唱一支悲伤而又甜蜜的难分难舍的送别歌，唱一支歌颂阿金库尔的胜利(47)的歌曲，或一支轻快的有关绿袖姑娘(48)的曲调。在他唱着，她听着，或者假装听着的时候，他的心便完全平静下来，可是当那些古色古香的歌曲唱完以后，他又听到了那屋子里的说话声，并记起了自己的一句充满讽刺的话：在这屋子里年轻人被人过早地用教名来称呼他们了。

有那么一会儿，她的眼睛似乎准备对他表示出全部的信任，可结果他只是徒劳地等待了一阵。她现在是轻轻移动着舞步正从他的记忆中走过，她完全像那天夜晚狂欢节舞会上的情景，一手轻轻提着白色的衣裙，一束白色的小花在她的头上轻轻颤动。她随大家一起脚步轻盈地跳着舞。她向他这边跳了过来，在走近他的时候，她微微向一边转过眼睛，脸上露出淡淡的红晕。在手拉着手连成的人环断开的地方，她曾把她的手在他的手里放了一会儿，一件柔软的商品。

——你这会儿可是一位非常少见的稀客了。

——是的，我天生是当和尚的。

——我恐怕你是一个异教徒。

——你很害怕吗？

她沿着手拉着手的那一排人群迅速从他身边跳开去，算作对他的回答，她轻巧而小心地舞着，不和任何人接触。她头上的白花随着她的舞步颤动着，在她躲进一片阴暗中去的时候，她脸上的红晕显得更浓了。

和尚！他自己的形象忽然变成了一个修道院的破坏者、一个相信异端邪说的方济各会会员，既愿意又不愿意皈依上帝，却像格拉尔蒂诺·达波尔戈·山·达尼洛(49)一样编织出了一面轻薄的诡辩的蛛网，并在她的耳边低语。

不，这不是他的形象，这倒像是上次他见到她时和她在一起的那年轻神父的形象，那天他看到她从她的小鸽子般的眼睛里偷看着他，手里胡乱翻着她学习爱尔兰语的练习簿。

——是的，是的，那些姑娘们已经都转向我们了。这情况我每天都能看到。姑娘们已经和我们在一起。她们是我们学习语言的最好的帮手。

——还有教堂呢，莫兰神父？

——教堂也一样。和我们站在一边。那里的工作进展得很顺利。不要为教堂发愁了。

算了吧！他厌恶地离开那里是做得完全对的。在图书馆的台阶上他没有和她打招呼，也做得完全对！他就应该让她去和她的神父调情，让她去玩弄教堂吧，因为教堂不过是基督教的下贱的厨娘。

一阵粗暴的愤怒彻底驱散了他灵魂中最后一刹那的欢乐。它残暴地彻底打碎了她的美好形象，并把那形象的碎片四散抛撒。于是她的形象的被歪曲的缩影便从四方八面飞来，在他的记忆中显现：他看到了那个穿着破旧衣服、顶着一头板结的粗糙的头发、长着淘气的孩子脸、把自己叫作他自己的姑娘、还向他要他的一束花的卖花姑娘，想到了他隔壁人家一边哐啷哐啷地洗着碗盘一边用农村歌手的拖长的音调老唱着《在基拉尔尼的湖山边》的头几节的厨娘，想到了在科克山附近的人行道上，因看到阴沟上的铁板挂住了他破烂的鞋跟，使他几乎摔倒而大笑不止的那个姑娘，还想到了他曾经看了一眼，并被她小巧的红透的嘴唇所吸引的那个姑娘，她在从雅各布饼干厂走出来的时候，回过头来对他叫着说：

——你已看到了我直直的头发和弯弯的眉毛，你喜欢吗？

然而不管他怎么对她的形象百般诋毁和嘲笑，他始终感到，他的愤怒也仍然只是对她表示爱慕的一种形式。那天他带着轻蔑的神气走出教室，其实也有些故意撒赖，他感到也许在她那长睫毛投下一片阴影的黑眼睛后面隐藏着她的整个民族的秘密。在他从街上走过的时候，他曾经怀着怨恨的心情对自己说，她是她本国妇女的一个典型形象，她是一个在黑暗、机密和孤独中忽然清醒过来，意识到自己的存在的一个像蝙蝠一样的灵魂，她没有爱情也没有罪孽地和她温和的爱人一块儿待上一会儿，然后却让他去对躲在格子后面的一位神父的耳朵低声坦白自己天真的过失。他只有粗野地对她的情人加以咒骂还可以稍稍缓解他对她的愤怒，她情人的名字、声音和长相都使他受到打击的骄傲情绪感到难以忍耐：他是一个当了神父的农民，有一个哥哥在都柏林当警察，还有一个弟弟在莫伊卡伦当招待。对他，对他那样一个就知道如何进行各种形式主义的宗教仪式的人，她可以让他看到她不加掩盖的灵魂，而对他这个宣扬永恒的想象力的教士，一个能够把每天普通生活上的经历变作具有永生生命的光辉形体的教士，她却不肯那样。

那次圣餐会上的鲜明形象又和他那一瞬间出现的充满怨恨和绝望的思想联系起来，从他那思想中发出的连续不断的喊叫声形成了一支感恩的圣歌。

我们的断续的喊叫和悲伤的歌篇
随着圣餐会上的圣歌向天上飞扬。
你对你那永恒的热情岂不感到厌倦？
现在贡献牺牲的手正高高举向苍天，
圣餐会上的酒杯都已满满斟上。
啊，不要再提那令人陶醉的华年。

他从第一行开始大声朗诵这些诗，直到它的音乐和节奏占据了他的整个头脑，使它变得无比开朗而宁静，然后他一笔不苟地把那首诗全部写下来，这样用眼睛看着它，就能使他对它的感受更深了一层。写完，他又在枕头上躺下了。

清晨已经来临。四周什么声音也听不见，可是他知道在他的周围生命马上就会清醒过来，带来它的一般的嘈杂声、嘶哑的说话声和充满睡意的祷告声。为了躲避那种生活，他向墙那边转过脸去，用毯子蒙着头，两眼呆呆地看着破碎的糊墙纸上画着的那些开过头的大朵的红花。他极力想用它们的那红色的光辉重新温暖他即将消失的欢乐，想象着从他躺着的地方有一条铺着红色花朵的玫瑰之路可以直通天堂。厌倦！厌倦！他对他自己永恒的热情也感到厌倦了。

一阵徐徐袭来的温暖，一种令人惆怅的厌倦从他紧包着的头上，沿着脊梁一直往下流动。他感觉到它从上往下流去，并看到他自己躺在那里，微微含笑。很快他就将入睡了。

在十年之后，他又为她写下了这首诗。十年前，她曾把她的披肩做成像帽子一样戴在头上，向静夜的空气散发出她温暖的气息，并在长满青草的路上轻轻拍打着她的双脚。那是最后一趟街车，高瘦的枣红马也了解这一点，因而在那明澈的夜晚摇动着它们的铃铛以引人注意。售票员和赶车的人谈着话，他们两人在蓝色的灯光下常不停地点点头。他们站在马车的阶梯上，他在上面一层，她在下面一层。他们谈话的时候，她好几次都爬上来站在他那一层上，然后又走下去，有一两次她一直站在他的身边忘记下去了，但后来又走了下去。就让她这样吧！就让她这样吧！

从那儿童时期的智慧到他现在的愚蠢，相隔已经是十年了。他要是把他这首诗送给她，怎么样？那在吃早饭的时候，在敲开蛋壳的剥剥声中，准有人会把它拿来大声朗读。真是再愚蠢不过了！她的弟兄们一定会大笑着，伸出他们强壮有力的粗手彼此争夺着这篇诗稿。她的叔父，那个温和的神父坐在安乐椅上，将会老远举着这诗篇含笑念诵着，并对它的文学形式表示赞赏。

不，不，那简直是愚蠢。即使他把这诗给她送去，她也不会让别人看见的。不，不，她不能那样做。

他开始感到他完全冤枉了她。一种觉得她天真无邪的感觉使得他几乎对她产生了怜悯之情，这种天真无邪，直到他通过犯罪对它有所认识以前，他一直全然不理解。这种天真无邪，在她还是天真无邪的时候，或者在她的天性第一次奇怪地受到屈辱以前，她也是绝不理解的。然后，她的灵魂，像他自己的灵魂第一次犯罪时候一样，开始了自己的生活，现在他回忆起她苍白的脸色，和因为女性受到阴森的羞辱而在她的眼神里表露出来的羞怯和悲伤，他心中不禁充满了万种柔肠的怜悯之情。

在他的灵魂正从狂喜进入惆怅心情的时候，她在哪里呢？精神生活本来是非常神秘的，可不可能那时候她的灵魂便已经完全感受到了他对她的崇敬？这是完全可能的。

一阵情欲的闪光又一次点燃了他的灵魂，燃烧着并充满了他的肉体。是她诱使他写下了那首维兰内尔诗，她在意识到他的情欲的时候，忽然从她充满芳香气息的睡眠中惊醒过来了。她阴沉的、带着惆怅情绪的眼睛睁开来，对着他的眼睛。她向他献出了她的不加掩盖的灵魂，鲜艳、温暖、芬芳、丰腴，像一片闪着光的云彩把他包裹起来，像一潭具有流动生命的清水一样把他包裹起来：于是，也像雾腾腾的云彩，或者像在空中周游流动的清水，这一段行云流水般的语言，这神秘气质的象征，也在他的头脑中流过。

你对你那永恒的热情岂不感到厌倦？
你简直可以迷住堕落的天使长。
啊，不要再提那令人陶醉的华年。
你在男人的心中燃起了热情的火焰，
你让他为你失去了自己的主张。
你对你那永恒的热情岂不感到厌倦？

在那火焰上飘动着赞美的香烟，
它从海面上一圈圈飞向天上。
啊，不要再提那令人陶醉的华年。

我们的断续的喊叫和悲伤的歌篇，
随着圣餐会上的圣歌向天上飞扬。
你对你那永恒的热情岂不感到厌倦？
现在贡献牺牲的手正高高举向苍天，
圣餐会上的酒杯都已满满斟上。
啊，不要再提那令人陶醉的华年。

但你却仍守着我们相互凝睇的眉眼，
你肢体丰腴，神态是那样惆怅！
你对你那永恒的热情岂不感到厌倦？
啊，不要再提那令人陶醉的华年。

它们是些什么鸟？他站在图书馆前面的台阶上，倚在一根白蜡树棍上，观望着那些鸟。它们绕着墨尔斯沃思街一所房子向外伸出的屋脊来回飞着。三月末梢黄昏时候的天空使得它们的飞翔显得异常清晰，它们向前直冲的微微颤抖的黑色的身体，衬着天空，仿佛衬着一块软软的悬挂着的轻烟般的蓝布一样，让人看得非常清楚。

他观望着它们飞翔，一只鸟接着一只鸟：一点黑色的闪光、一扭身躯、一拍翅膀。他想在所有那些向前直冲微微颤抖着的身体飞过以前，数一数它们共有多少：六只，十只，十一只，他弄不清它们到底是双数还是单数。十二只，十三只：因为又有一对鸟儿从高空盘旋着飞下来了。它们有时飞得很高，有时飞得低一些，可永远是直线或曲线地绕着圈飞，总是从左向右飞，围着一座空中庙宇盘旋。

他倾听着它们的叫声：那声音像护墙板后面的老鼠发出的尖叫：是一种由双音符组成的尖叫声。但那声腔不像其他一些有害人类的动物的鸣叫，显得又尖又长，还带着嗡嗡声，在它们用尖嘴划破长空的时候，常常会发出震颤的音调，而且还下降三度或四度。它们的叫声，尖厉、清晰而又轻巧，简直像是从一个发出嗡嗡声的线轴上抽出的细丝一样的光线。

在他耳朵里还一直不停地响着他妈妈的哭泣声和生气的唠叨，这非人的鸣叫声对他的耳朵却是一种安慰，那绕着耸立在清澈的天空、由空气组成的庙宇盘旋着的黑色的单薄的颤抖着的身躯，有时拍打几下翅膀，有时一摆尾巴来一个急转弯，这些对于他的仍能看见他母亲的面容的眼睛也是一种极大的安抚。

他为什么站在廊子前的台阶上，举头观望，听着它们的双重音调的鸣叫，观望着它们飞翔？他是要靠鸟占(50)来一卜吉凶吗？科尼利厄斯·阿格里帕(51)的一句话在他的思想中掠过，接着更有各种无形的思想在他的头脑里翻腾，从斯韦登伯格(52)关于鸟语的理论，一直到智力问题；他并且想到，在空中生活的生物所以能获得知识，所以能知道时间的变迁和季节的转换，是因为它们一直生活在它们固定的生活秩序中，而不像人用他们的理智完全扰乱了自己的生活秩序。

许多世纪以来，都有人像他这样抬头端详着鸟的飞翔。他上面的那柱廊使他模糊地想起了古代的某座神庙，他把疲惫的身子倚在上面的那根白蜡树棍则使他想起了鸟占术士使用的弯曲的手杖。一种对不可知的事物的恐惧扰乱着他疲惫的心灵，那是对各种符号和预兆的恐惧，对那个名字和他相同靠柳条编成的翅膀像鹰一样飞出牢笼的人(53)的恐惧，对多思(54)这个写作之神的恐惧，他用一只芦管在木板上写字，在他狭窄的鸟头上挂着一个两头尖尖的弯月。

他一想到那个神的形象不禁微笑了，因为这使他想到了那个戴着假发、鼻子像酒瓶一样的法官，他把一份文件举得老远阅读着，不时加上几个逗点。他并且知道，要不是因为这神的名字跟爱尔兰语的一句骂人话非常相近，他是不会记得那个名字的。这可真是愚蠢。但是，就因为这种愚蠢他就打算永远离开他已经降生其中的那所供祈祷和修行的房屋，和他自己从中而来的生活秩序吗？

鸟儿尖声鸣叫着又飞回到那间房子向外伸出的屋脊边来了。衬着光线越来越暗的天空，它们飞动的身影显得更黑了。它们究竟是一些什么鸟？他想它们一定是刚从南方飞回的燕子。不久它们还会飞走，因为它们是一些经常来来去去的候鸟，它们在人的屋檐下永远修筑着使用不久的住处，永远转眼又离开它们修建好的住处再去四处游荡。

低下你们的头来，欧纳和阿里尔(55)。
我凝神静息向你们观望，恰像
那已准备向海洋那边飞翔的燕子，
观望着它修建在别人檐下的窝巢。

一种冉冉流动的欢乐，像许多流水发出的声响，在他的记忆中流过，他感到心中有一种软绵绵的寂静，这寂静乃是由那水域上面颜色暗淡的天空的寂静空间，由大海上的寂静，由那些在流水上空穿过海面的黑暗飞翔的燕子所组成。

一种冉冉流动的欢乐，流过那无声地来回抛掷着柔和、拖长的韵母使之归一寂灭的话语，流去又流回，永不停息地摇动着它的浪头上的白色的铃铛，使之发出无声的曲调、无声的狂喊和柔和而低沉的令人昏厥的痛哭。他感到，他依靠盘旋疾飞的鸟儿和头顶上苍白的天空所作的鸟占，全不过来自他的心中，他的心也正像一只安静而迅速地从一个高塔上飞下的小鸟儿。

这是离别的象征还是孤单的象征呢？在他的记忆的耳边低吟着的诗行，慢慢在他的记忆的眼前，构成了那天晚上国立剧院开门时大厅里的景象。他正一个人站在一个阳台边，用他疲惫的眼睛在那些书摊上和那些俗不可耐的图片上观看着都柏林的文化，并在镶着一圈装饰灯光的舞台上看到了用人做成的玩偶。在他身后一个身材高大的警察满脸冒着汗，仿佛随时都准备采取行动。在那大厅中，他的三五成群到处散立的同学们像一阵暴风似的发出各种猫叫声、嘘嘘声和各种嘲笑声。

——这是对爱尔兰的诽谤！

——是从德国传来的！

——这是亵渎上帝！

——我们从来没有出卖过我们的信念！

——从来没有一个爱尔兰妇女干过这种事！

——我们不要业余的无神论者。

——我们不要刚露土的佛教徒。

从他头上的各个窗口忽然传来一阵急促的嘘叫声，他知道上面阅览室的电灯已经打开了。他转身走进那满是柱子的大厅，现在那光亮的大厅已很安静，然后走上楼梯，走过了那个嘎嘎响着的转门。

克兰利坐在放字典的书架前面。一本很厚的书从最前面的一页翻开，摆在他面前的木架上。他靠在椅子上，像一位听忏悔的神父把耳朵对着一个医科学生的脸伸过去，那医科学生正从一本杂志上给他念关于一盘棋的介绍。斯蒂芬在他的右边坐下，在桌子的另一边的一位神父，生气地合上他正阅读的《图片集成》，站了起来。

克兰利带着温和的表情莫名其妙地看着他的背影。那个医科学生接着用更低的声音说。

——卒子进入王的第四线。

——咱们最好走吧。狄克逊，斯蒂芬警告说，他一定是告状去了。

狄克逊合上那本杂志，装出一副很庄严的样子站起身来说：

——我们的人秩序井然地撤出战场。

——带着大炮和牲畜，斯蒂芬补充说，指着克兰利看着的那本书的封面，那封面上印着《牛病大全》几个字。

当他们走过桌子间的过道的时候，斯蒂芬说：

——克兰利，我要跟你谈谈。

克兰利没有回答他的话，也没有回头。他把他的书放在柜台上走了出去，他的穿得很厚的脚走在地板上发出一种呆重的声音。到了楼梯上，他停住脚心不在焉地看着狄克逊又重复说：

——把卒走到王的他妈的第四线上去。

——你要那么走就那么走吧，狄克逊说。

他说话的声音安静而平淡，他的神态倒显得十分温文尔雅，一双白胖的手，一个指头上戴着一只刻着名字的戒指。

他们走过大厅的时候，一个身材十分矮小的人朝他们走过来。在一顶很小的帽子下面，他那张没有刮过的脸开始高兴地对他们微笑，他们还听到他低声在说话。他那双忧郁的眼睛很像猴子的眼睛。

——晚上好，先生们，那张扁平的猴子般的脸说。

——这三月的天气，也算够暖和了，克兰利说，他们在楼上已经把窗户都打开了。

狄克逊微笑着，转了转他手上的戒指。那像猴子一样尖着嘴的黑黑的脸高兴地撅起那上面的嘴，并用一种呜隆呜隆的声音说：

——要论这三月的天气，可真令人爽快。简直是令人爽快极了。

——楼上有两位漂亮的年轻小姐，队长，她们都等急了，狄克逊说。

克兰利微笑着，客气地说：

——我们的队长只爱一个人，那就是瓦尔特·司各特爵士。是不是这样的，队长？

——你现在正读哪一本书呢，队长？狄克逊问道，是在读《拉默尔穆尔的新娘》吗？

——我很喜欢老司各特，那两片柔和的嘴唇说，我认为他写的东西实在太美了。没有任何一个作家能够和瓦尔特·司各特爵士相比。

他仿佛要给他这些赞美的言辞打拍子，轻轻在空中晃动着他的一只干瘦的棕色的手，一双神色忧伤的眼睛，薄薄的眼皮老是急速地眨巴着。

但是让斯蒂芬听来更觉得悲惨的是他说话的方式：一口绅士腔调，低沉而润滑，不时被错误的用语打断，听着他谈话，他拿不准那传说是不是真的，不知在他那干瘦的身躯里流着的稀薄的血是否真是来自乱伦的爱情的贵族的血液？

公园里的树木上积满了雨水，雨一直还在下，而且总是下在湖面上，灰色的湖面静静地躺着，像一面盾牌。一群家养的天鹅飞到湖里来，那水和水下的浅滩都被它们灰白色的粪便脏污了。在那雨中的灰暗的光线、安静的湿水的树木、可以作证的盾牌一样的湖面和那群天鹅的诱引下，他们轻轻地拥抱了。他们既无欢乐也无热情地拥抱着，他的一只胳膊搂着她妹妹的脖子。一件灰色的羊毛衣从她的一边肩头到对面腰边，斜着包裹着她，她的长着淡黄头发的脑袋半推半就羞怯地向他歪了过去。他有一头蓬松的红棕色的头发，和一双细嫩、匀称、长着许多雀斑的坚强的手。脸呢？脸根本看不见。那个哥儿们的脸贴在她冒着雨水香味的淡黄的头发上。那只长满雀斑、坚强、匀称的正在抚摸着的手，却是达文的手。

他对他的这种思想和引起这种思想的那个干瘦的长得像猴儿一样的人都感到非常生气。他父亲嘲笑班特里那帮家伙的那些话，现在忽然从他的记忆中冒了出来。他尽可能避开那些话，仍不安地想着他自己的那些思想。那为什么不是克兰利的手？难道达文的淳朴和天真更为机密地刺痛了他？

他和狄克逊一起走过大厅，让克兰利一个人煞有介事地去和那个矮子告别。

在外面的廊柱下，坦普尔正和一群同学站在一起。他们中有一个人叫着说：

——狄克逊，你也过来听听。坦普尔可了不得。

坦普尔向他转过他那深黑的吉卜赛人似的眼睛。

——你是一个伪君子，奥基夫，他说，狄克逊是一个笑面人。我的天，我想这可是个带有文学意味的呱呱叫的新词儿。

他羞怯地大笑着，看着斯蒂芬的脸重复说：

——天哪，我真非常喜欢这个名字。一个笑面人。

站在他下面台阶上的一个身材魁梧的学生说：

——还回来谈那个情妇吧，坦普尔。我们愿意听你谈谈那个。

——他是有，说真的，坦普尔说，而且他是早已结过婚的。所有的神父都常常到那里去吃晚饭。天知道，我想他们谁都沾到了点儿油水。

——我们得把这叫作，心疼自己的马租匹马去打猎，狄克逊说。

——你告诉我们，坦普尔，奥基夫说，你肚子里现在装有多少瓶葡萄酒？

——你心灵中的全部智慧一股脑儿都放在这句话里了，奥基夫，坦普尔公开表示轻蔑地说。

他迈着歪歪斜斜的步子绕着那群人走了一圈，然后对斯蒂芬说。

——你知不知道那个福斯特家族是比利时的王室？他问道。

克兰利从门厅的门口走了出来，一顶帽子戴在他的后脖儿上，他非常小心地剔着牙。

——这位古今无双的聪明人来了，坦普尔说，你知道福斯特家族的情况吗？

他停下来准备回答。克兰利从牙缝里剔出一个无花果籽，用他那粗大的牙签举着，来回仔细研究。

——福斯特家族，坦普尔说，是从佛兰德斯的皇帝鲍德温一世传下来的。他当时的姓是福雷斯特。福雷斯特和福斯特完全是一样的。鲍德温一世的后裔，弗朗西斯·福斯特队长在爱尔兰定居下来，和克兰布拉西尔最后的一个酋长的女儿结了婚。另外还有布莱克·福斯特一家。那完全是另外一支。

——那是从佛兰德斯皇帝鲍尔德海德传下来的，克兰利重复说，再次聚精会神地剔着他闪闪发光的外露的牙齿。

——你是从什么地方知道所有这些历史事件的？奥基夫问道。

——我还知道你们家的全部历史，坦普尔转身对斯蒂芬说，你知道吉拉尔德斯·坎布兰西斯对你们家是怎么说的吗？

——他们也是鲍德温的后裔吗？一个长着一双黑眼睛、害着肺病的高个子学生问道。

——鲍尔德海德，克兰利重复说，使劲嘬着他的牙缝。

——Pernobilis et pervetusta familia，(56)坦普尔对斯蒂芬说。

站在下面台阶上的那个身材魁伟的学生轻轻放了个屁。狄克逊向他转过身去用一种很柔和的声音说：

——刚才是有位天使讲话了吗？

克兰利也转过身来，有些激动但并没有生气，说：

——戈金斯，你真是我从没见过的一个最下流、肮脏的魔鬼，你知不知道？

——我脑子里倒是想到一句话，如鲠在喉，戈金斯坚定地回答说，这也没有跟任何人过不去的地方，不是吗？

——我们希望，狄克逊温和地说，你这并不是科学上所谓的paulo post futurum(57)。

——我有没有对你们说过他是一个笑面人？坦普尔转头左右看看说，我不是给他取了那么个名字吗？

——一点不错。我们并不是聋子，那个身材高大的害肺病的学生说。

克兰利仍然对他下面的那个体格魁伟的学生皱着眉头。然后，他厌恶地哼了一声，使劲把他推下台阶去。

——你离开这儿吧，他粗暴地说，滚开，你这个臭东西。你就是一只臭马桶。

戈金斯在那条碎石路上跑了几步，立刻又带着笑脸回到他原来的地方。坦普尔转身看着斯蒂芬问道：

——你相信遗传规律吗？

——你是喝醉了还是怎么着？你到底想说什么？克兰利带着一种莫名其妙的表情转过脸来问他。

——世界上写在纸上的最有深义的一句话，坦普尔十分热情地说，是写在动物学最后的一句话。生殖是死亡的开始。

他胆怯地碰了碰斯蒂芬的胳膊，急切地说：

——你能感觉到，因为你是一个诗人，那句话有多深奥吗？

克兰利伸出一个很长的中指头指点着。

——你看看他！他对其他人轻蔑地说，你看看这个爱尔兰的希望！

他们听到他的话，看到他那样子都不禁大笑起来。坦普尔勇敢地向他转过身去说：

——克兰利，你老是在讥笑我。这我看得出来。可是不管任何时候我也并不比你差什么。你知道要是拿你和我相比，我现在对你怎么想吗？

——我亲爱的老伙计，克兰利毫无礼貌地说，你根本没有能力，你知道吗，完全没有能力思考。

——可是你知道，坦普尔接着说，我现在把我们两人拿来比较，我对你怎么想，对我自己又怎么想吗？

——那你说出来，坦普尔！站在台阶上的那个魁伟的学生叫喊着，一点一点地说出来！

坦普尔向右边看看又向左边看看，忽然做出一个非常无力的姿态说。

——我是一个卵蛋，他说，绝望地摇摇头。我是一个卵蛋，我知道我是。我承认我是。

狄克逊轻轻拍拍他的肩膀，温和地说：

——这称呼对你可是再合适不过了，坦普尔。

——可是他，坦普尔说，指着克兰利，他也是一个卵蛋，跟我一样。只不过他自己不知道。我能看到的他和我的差别，不过如此而已。

一阵大笑淹没了他的话。可是他又忽然转身对着斯蒂芬急促地说：

——这个词儿可是非常有趣。这是唯一的一个既做单数又做双数用的词儿(58)。你知道吗？

——是这样吗？斯蒂芬不在意地说。

他这会儿正观望着克兰利轮廓分明的痛苦的脸，看到那上面露出了一种虚假的满不在乎的微笑。那个粗野的名字，仿佛泼在一尊古老石像上的脏水，从他那勉强忍受着凌辱的脸上掠过：而在他正望着他的时候，他看到他脱下帽子来向大家敬礼，露出一头从额角直竖上去好似一顶铁制王冠的黑色的头发。

她从图书馆的廊子里走出来，越过斯蒂芬微微点头，回答克兰利的问候。还有他？克兰利的脸不是微微有点红了吗？或者，他脸红是因为坦普尔的话引起的？这时那里的光线已经很暗。他看不太清楚。

但这是否就说明，为什么他这位朋友老是心神不安，一言不发，有时尽讲些刺人的话，有时又用些粗暴的言辞故意打断斯蒂芬，不让他有机会讲出他急于想表示的忏悔？斯蒂芬对谁都很容易原谅，因为他发现他自己有时候态度也很粗暴。他还记得有一天晚上，他从一辆借来的浑身嘎吱响的自行车上下来，在马拉海德附近一个树林里向上帝祷告的情景。他已经举起双臂带着狂喜的心情向阴森的树林深处开始祷告了，他知道那应该是一个非常神圣的时刻，而自己是正站在神圣的土地上。然而就在这时有两个警察从阴暗的道路拐角处走了过来，他却立即停止祷告，用口哨大声吹奏着最新的一个滑稽剧里的插曲。

他开始用他那白蜡树棍带杈儿的一端打着一个柱子的底部。克兰利没有听见他的话吗？他还可以等待。他身边的谈话声停止了一会儿，从上面的窗口又传下来比较温和的嘘叫声。但是空中再没有任何其他的声音了，他刚才睁着一双悠闲的眼睛观望的那些飞翔的燕子，现在已经都睡着了。

她朝着黑暗中走去。空气中除了从上面传下来的温和的嘘叫声之外，完全是一片寂静。在他身边的所有的嘴现在都停止叨叨了。黑暗正从上面降临。

黑暗正从天空下降。(59)

一种像闪烁着的微光一样抖动着的欢乐像一群神话中的人物在他的四周跳动。可这是为什么？是由于她走进了越来越浓的黑暗，还是由于那满是黑色韵母的诗和它开头处那圆润的、有如悠扬笛声的曲调？

他慢慢朝着柱廊更阴暗的一头走去，用他的棍子轻轻敲打着地上的石块，借以扰乱他要离开的那些同学的注意，不让他们觉察到他自己梦幻中的景象：他听任自己的思绪沉浸到多兰德、伯德和纳什(60)的时代中去。

眼睛，从情欲的黑暗中睁开的眼睛，使刚刚发白的东方变成一片昏暗的眼睛。除了那床笫间的娇柔，又哪里来的什么令人惆怅的美？它们所发出的闪光，也不过是一位流着鼻涕的斯图亚特王(61)宫庭里的粪坑上的浮渣所放出的光彩罢了。他在他记忆的语言中，尝到了琥珀色的酒、在死亡中纷纷下落的甜蜜的曲调和骄傲的宫廷舞的味道，他通过他记忆的眼睛，看到温柔的高贵的妇女们在科文特歌剧院的阳台上撅起嘴来对别人调情，并看到酒馆里出着水痘的姑娘和一些年轻媳妇，带着喜悦的心情屈服于想要玩弄她们的男人，一次再次跟他们拥抱。

他所召唤出来的这些形象并没有带给他任何欢乐。它们都神秘而热情，但她的形象并没有被它们所搅乱。这样来想她，是不对的。他自己甚至从来也没有这样想过她。难道他的思想现在已经对自己失去信心了吗？旧的一些话语，像克兰利从他闪闪发光的牙缝里剔出的无花果籽儿一样，只是依靠被发掘出的芬芳它们才有一些芳香的气息。

虽然他模糊地知道，她的身影正穿过那城市向她自己的家里走去，但这既不能说是思想，也不能说是幻境。一开始很模糊，接着他明确地感到，他嗅到了她身体的气味。一种明确意识到的不安在他的血液里翻腾。是的，他嗅到的是她身体的气味，一种野性的令人沉醉的气味，这气味来自他充满情欲的音乐曾来回飘过的温柔的肢体，来自她的肌肤曾散发出的纯净的气息和一阵清露般隐蔽而柔软的内衣。

一个虱子在他的后脖儿上爬行，他伸出大拇指和食指灵巧地从他宽松的领子下面抓住了它。他用手捻着它的身体，感到它像一颗稻米一样既软又有些扎手，他这么两个指头搓了一会儿就把它扔下，心里想不知它是活着还是死了。他脑子里忽然想起了科尼利厄斯(62)说过的一句很奇怪的话，那意思说由人体的汗产生的虱子不是由上帝跟别的动物一起在第六天创造出来的。可是，他脖子上的皮肤痒得使他的思想变得通红和发毛了。他的身体所经历过的穿得很坏、吃得很苦、挨尽虱子咬的生活，使得他在忽然产生的一阵绝望情绪中合上了眼皮，而在那一片黑暗中他却看到许多闪光、发脆的虱子从空中降落下来，一边下落还常常一边翻滚。是的，从空中降落的不是黑暗，而是光明。

光明正从天空下降。(63)

他甚至并不能准确地记得纳什的那行诗了。它所唤起的形象全都是虚假的。他的头脑本身就孕育着种种祸害。他的思想便是由懒惰的汗水产生出来的虱子。

他很快又跑回来，沿着柱廊向那群学生跑去。算了吧，让她去，让她见鬼去吧！她可以去爱某一个胸部长着黑毛，每天早晨齐腰以上得洗一遍的干净的运动员。让她去。

克兰利从口袋里又掏出一个干无花果，正慢慢地、叽叽喳喳地吃着。坦普尔坐在一根柱子的台基上，背靠着它，帽子往前拉下来盖住了他惺忪的睡眼。一个矮墩墩的年轻人从门廊里走出来，胳肢窝里夹着一个大皮包。他朝那群人走去，用靴后跟和一把沉重的雨伞的铜帽儿嘣嘣敲打着地上的石板。然后他举起雨伞来做个敬礼的姿势，对所有的人说：

——晚上好，诸位先生。

他又在石板上敲了几下，咯咯笑着，神经质地摇晃了一下脑袋。那个身材高大的害肺病的学生和狄克逊和奥基夫正用爱尔兰语交谈着，谁也没有理他。然后他便转向克兰利说：

——晚上好，我是特别对你说的。

他举起雨伞来指点着，又咯咯笑了几声。克兰利这时还正嚼着他的无花果，他使劲动了几下下巴作为回答。

——好？是的。这倒是一个很好的晚上。

那个矮墩墩的学生严肃地看着他，温和地并表示不赞成地又摇晃了几下他的雨伞。

——我可以看得出，他说，你现在正要讲一些用不着说的大实话。

——嗯，克兰利回答说，同时把他已嚼烂的那个无花果从嘴里拿出来，朝那个矮胖的学生嘴边送去，意思要让他吃掉。

那矮胖学生并没有吃，可是为了表示容忍他这种特殊的幽默，他一边仍然咯咯笑着，一边用他的雨伞指指点点地严肃地说：

——你的意思是打算……

他咽下了自己的话，用伞直指着那个已被嚼成烂泥的无花果，大声说：

——我指的是那个。

——嗯，克兰利仍和刚才一样说道。

——你刚才那样做，那个矮墩墩的学生说，意思是ipso facto(64)，还是比如说，不过随便说说呢(65)？

狄克逊对那群学生背过身去说：

——戈金斯正等着你，格林，他跑到阿德尔菲去找过你和莫伊尼汉。你这里面装的什么？他问道，拍拍格林夹在胳肢窝下面的公文包。

——都是些考卷，格林回答说。我每个月让他们进行一次考试，看看经过我的教学后他们所获得的成绩。

他也拍拍那公文包，微笑着轻轻咳嗽了几声。

——教学！克兰利粗暴地说。我想你指的是，那些让你这老猢狲教着的那群光着脚的孩子吧。求上帝保佑保佑他们吧！

他咬下剩下的半个无花果，把果蒂扔掉。

——我让小孩子们都爬到我的身上来，格林友好地说。

——一只该死的老猴头，克兰利咬牙切齿地重复说，还是一只公然亵渎上帝的老猴头！

坦普尔站起来，把克兰利推开，对格林说：

——你刚才说的这句话，他说，是从《新约》上“让孩子们都来到我的身边”这句话变来的。

——还去睡你的觉吧，坦普尔，奥基夫说。

——那么好，坦普尔仍冲着格林继续说，既然耶稣让孩子们都到他身边去，那教堂为什么要把没有受洗死去的孩子全送到地狱里去？那是为什么？

——你自己受过洗没有，坦普尔？那个害肺病的学生问道。

——可他们为什么要给送到地狱里去，如果耶稣说过他们都可以到他那里去？坦普尔说，两眼直盯着格林的眼睛。

格林咳嗽了几声，使劲忍着神经质的咯咯的笑声，每说一句话晃一下雨伞，温和地说：

——至于你的话，如果真是这样，我要非常严肃地问你，这“这样”又是从哪里来的？

——因为教堂和一切老罪犯一样残酷，坦普尔说。

——你这说的完全是合乎正统的说法吗，坦普尔？狄克逊温和地说。

——圣奥古斯丁就说过没有受过洗的孩子将进地狱的话，坦普尔回答说，因为他也是一个残酷的老罪犯。

——我向你致敬，狄克逊说，但我有一个印象，确有一个名为林堡(66)的地方是专为这类孩子预备的。

——不要和他争论了，狄克逊，克兰利恶狠狠地说。不要和他讲话，也不要看他一眼。拿一根草绳拴着他，像牵着一头咩咩叫的山羊一样把他牵回家去吧。

——林堡！坦普尔叫喊道，那真是一个呱呱叫的发明。和地狱是完全一样的。

——但是并不像在地狱里那样令人难受，狄克逊说。

他微笑着转身对别的人说：

——我想我讲的这些话，可以代表这儿我们大家的意见。

——一点不错，格林用一种很坚定的声调说。在这一点上整个爱尔兰是团结的。

他用伞头上的铜帽儿敲打着柱廊上的石头地板。

——见鬼，坦普尔说。对于那位魔鬼的亲眷的那个发明我可以表示尊敬。地狱就是罗马，像罗马人住房的墙壁一样结实而非常难看。可林堡到底是个什么东西？

——还把他送回婴儿车去吧，克兰利，奥基夫叫着说。

克兰利迅速朝坦普尔迈过一步去，他停住，跺了一下脚，仿佛对一只鸟儿似的叫喊着：

——唬嘘！

坦普尔灵巧地退到一边去。

——你知道什么是林堡吗？他大声说，你知道在我们罗斯科门我们把这玩意儿叫作什么吗？

——唬嘘！去你的吧！克兰利拍手叫着说。

——它既不是我的屁股，也不是我的胳膊肘儿(67)，坦普尔轻蔑地大声叫着。那就是我所知道的林堡。

——把那根棍子给我，克兰利说。

他粗野地从斯蒂芬手里夺过那根白蜡棍，几步跳下台阶去：可是坦普尔，因为听到后面有人追赶，于是像一只灵巧的长着飞毛腿的野兽一样直向黑暗中跑去。大家听到克兰利沉重的靴子跑过广场时发出的巨大的声响，接着又听到他迈着沉重的脚步跑了回来，每跑一步都把路上的小石子踢得乱飞。

他的脚步已显出了他的愤怒，接着他更用一种愤怒的鲁莽的姿态把那棍子又塞回到斯蒂芬手里。斯蒂芬感觉到他的愤怒另有原因，可是为了装出很有耐性的样子，他轻轻碰碰他的胳膊，安详地说：

——克兰利，我刚才已经对你说过，我要跟你谈几句。跟我来吧。

克兰利对他看了一会儿，问道：

——就现在？

——是的，就现在，斯蒂芬说，在这儿我们没法谈话。跟我来吧。

他们俩一同默默地走过了那个方形广场。一种从《西格弗里德》(68)中学来的用口哨轻轻吹出的鸟叫声随着他们从门前的台阶上下来。克兰利回过头去，跟在他们后面学鸟叫的狄克逊叫着问道：

——你们两个家伙要到哪儿去？咱们那场球还打不打，克兰利？

他们越过一片宁静的空气，大声叫喊着商量要到阿德尔菲旅馆去一同打一场台球。斯蒂芬一个人向前走着，直走到安静的基尔德尔大街对面的枫树旅馆那边，他站在那里等待着，心情又变得很平静了。那旅馆的名字，一种没有颜色的光滑的木头，和它那毫无色彩的门脸儿，仿佛对他摆出一副彬彬有礼的轻蔑的神态使他感到十分难堪。因而他也愤怒地回望着旅馆里灯光柔和的会客室，他想象着爱尔兰的显贵们一定都安静地住在这旅馆里，过着舒适的生活。他们整天想的是军部的委令，是土地买卖：在乡村的大路上农民见到他们都要行礼，他们还知道某些法国菜的名字，还会用一种土腔土调向当地的行政长官发布命令，他们那又尖又高的声音简直把他们原来包裹得很紧的土腔调都给刺破了。

他有什么办法可以打动他们的良心，或者在他们的女儿的想象中散布下他那些阴暗思想，让她们在生下那样一些农村绅士之前，能够繁殖出一支不像他们自己那样下流的人种来呢？在愈来愈浓的暮色中，他感觉到自己所属的那个民族的思想和欲望，像一群群蝙蝠，飞过那黑暗的农村小道，飞到一片满是水潭的沼泽地附近河边的树丛中去。达文那天夜晚走过那里的时候，有一个女人曾经在门口等待着，她请他喝了一杯牛奶，差一点把他勾引到她的床上去，因为达文长着一双能够严守秘密的人的温和的眼睛。可就没有一个女人的眼睛勾引过他。

一只强有力的手抓住了他的一只胳膊，他听到克兰利的声音说：

——咱们亦走吧。

他们默默地向南走去。过了一会儿克兰利说：

——那个该死的傻瓜，坦普尔！你知道吗，我向摩西发誓，早晚我得要了那个浑蛋的命。

但是他的声音里再没有任何愤怒的意思，斯蒂芬拿不准他是不是想到了在门廊上她跟他打招呼的情景。

他们向左转弯，仍和刚才一样向前走去。过了一阵之后斯蒂芬说：

——克兰利，今天晚上我赶上了一场非常不愉快的争吵。

——跟你自己家的人？克兰利问道。

——跟我妈妈。

——因为宗教问题？

——是的，斯蒂芬回答说。

过了一会儿，克兰利问道：

——你妈妈多大年岁了？

——不算老，斯蒂芬说，她要我复活节去向上帝履行我的职责。

——你去吗？

——我不去，斯蒂芬说。

——为什么不去？克兰利说。

——我不愿意担任教职，斯蒂芬回答说。

——这话你过去早说过，克兰利安静地说。

——我现在是事后再说一遍，斯蒂芬生气地说。

克兰利抓住斯蒂芬的胳膊说：

——你先不用急，我亲爱的朋友。你知道，你这人有点他妈的太爱激动了。

他说话的时候，神经质地大笑起来，接着他用友好的充满热情的神色看着斯蒂芬的脸说：

——你知不知道你是一个非常爱激动的人？

——我敢说是这样，斯蒂芬说，也笑起来。

他们两人近来思想上很有些不和的意思，现在似乎忽然间彼此又变得非常亲近了。

——你相信关于圣餐的那一套吗？克兰利问道。

——我不相信，斯蒂芬说。

——那么你就是不相信咯？

——对这个问题，我既说不上相信，也说不上不相信，斯蒂芬回答说。

——许多人对这件事都有怀疑，甚至那些教会里面的人，可是他们克服了那种怀疑，或者把它抛到一边去，克兰利说，你对这个问题的怀疑竟是那么难以破除吗？

——我并不想克服我的怀疑，斯蒂芬回答说。

克兰利仿佛感到有点难堪，他从口袋里又掏出一个无花果来准备放到嘴里去，这时斯蒂芬却说：

——求你别吃了。你嘴里装满嚼着的无花果，那咱们就没有办法讨论这个问题。

克兰利举着那个无花果，在他站立处头顶上的灯光下，反复端详着。然后他用两个鼻孔分别闻闻它，咬下一小块，把它吐掉，随即又使劲把那个无花果扔到阴沟里去。它现在躺在那里，你对它去讲吧，他说：

——你走开吧，该死的东西，愿你滚到永不熄灭的地狱烈火中去！

他抓住斯蒂芬的两只胳膊，又向前走着说：

——你不害怕在最后审判的那一天，有人会对你讲这种话吗？

——可是在另一方面我又能得到什么呢？斯蒂芬问道，整天陪着那个教导主任就能得到永恒的幸福吗？

——你记住，克兰利说，他可会因此感到无比高兴。

——啊，斯蒂芬多少有些怨恨地说，他是那样地明快、活跃、无情，而最主要的是机灵。

——你知道，克兰利不带任何感情地说，奇怪的是，你脑子里完全塞满了你说你根本不相信的宗教。当年你在学校的时候相信宗教吗？我敢打赌你那会儿是相信的。

——我那会儿是相信的，斯蒂芬回答说。

——那你那会儿是不是比现在幸福一些呢？克兰利温和地问道，是不是比现在更幸福些，比方说？

——常常感到很幸福，斯蒂芬说，常常又感到很不幸福。我当时完全是另外一个人。

——怎么叫另外一个人？你这话是什么意思？

——我是说，斯蒂芬说，那时的我不是现在的我，我不能不变。

——不像现在的你，不像不能不改变的你，克兰利重复说。让我现在问你一个问题。你爱你的妈妈吗？

斯蒂芬慢慢摇了摇头。

一我不知道你这话是什么意思，他简单地说。

——你从来没有爱过任何人吗？克兰利问道。

——你是说女人？

——我不是说那个，克兰利用一种更冷淡的腔调说。我是问你从来没有对任何人或任何东西发生过爱情？

斯蒂芬在他朋友身边走着，脸色阴沉地看着脚下的小道儿。

——我曾试着去爱上帝，他最后说，现在我感到我似乎失败了。这件事竟非常困难。我试着要把我的意志一点一点和上帝的意志联系在一起。在这方面我也并不是绝对办不到的。也许现在我还可以那样做……

克兰利打断他的话，问道：

——你妈妈曾有过幸福的生活吗？

——我怎么知道？斯蒂芬说。

——她有几个孩子？

——九个或者十个，斯蒂芬回答说，有几个死掉了。

——你父亲是……克兰利停了一会儿接着又说：我并不想探听你们家里的事。可你父亲的境遇说得上一般人所说的富裕家庭吗？我是说，在你长大成人以后？

——可以那么说，斯蒂芬说。

——他是干什么的？克兰利停了一会儿问道。

斯蒂芬开始滔滔不绝地述说他父亲过去的为人。

——学过医，驾过船，唱过男中音，当过业余演员，做过大喊大叫的政治家，当过小地主、小发明家，当过酒鬼，还是有名的好人，写过小故事，给别人当过秘书，还自己酿过酒、收过税、破过产，目前是整天吹嘘自己的过去。

克兰利大笑起来，更加使劲捏着斯蒂芬的一只胳膊说：

——做酿酒的买卖可是他妈的太棒了。

——还有什么别的你想知道的情况吗？斯蒂芬问道。

——你们现在境况还很好吗？

——你瞧我这样子像吗？斯蒂芬毫不掩饰地说。

——那么说，克兰利感到很有趣地说，你是生在一个豪华的怀抱中的。

他在使用这句话的时候，完全像他一向使用什么技术术语似的，不着边际地大声嚷嚷着，仿佛他希望听他讲话的人明白，他虽这么说，但自己也并不相信。

——你母亲一定经历过许多苦难，接着他又说，你难道不想救救她，别让她再受更多的苦难吗？甚至在……或者说，你愿意这样做吗？

——如果我办得到，斯蒂芬说，那并不需要我付出什么重大代价的。

——那你就那么办吧，克兰利说，她希望你怎么做，你就怎么做好了。对你来说这有什么关系呢？你不相信那些东西。这只是一种形式：再没有别的什么。这样你就能让她的心情安静下来。

他停住了，因为斯蒂芬没有回答，他也就没有再说下去。接着，仿佛他要说出自己的思想过程似的，又接着说：

——在这个臭狗屎堆的世界上，你可以说任何东西都是靠不住的，但是母亲的爱可是个例外。你母亲把你生到这个世界上来，先在她自己的身子里孕育着你。至于她怎么感觉，我们能知道什么？但不管她怎么感觉，她的感觉至少是真实的。也只能是真实的。我们的理想或者说野心都是些什么？玩儿。理想！咳，那个该死的像一只山羊整天咩咩叫的坦普尔有理想。麦卡恩也有不少理想。每一个准备上路的豺狼都想着，它有许多理想哩。

斯蒂芬一直细听着这些话后面他没有说出的意思，最后装着满不在乎地说：

——帕斯卡(69)，如果我记得不错的话，因为害怕和任何女性接触，就从不肯让他妈妈吻他。

——帕斯卡是一个浑蛋，克兰利说。

——阿洛伊修斯·冈萨戈我想也是这样一个人，斯蒂芬说。

——那他也是一个浑蛋，克兰利说。

——可是教堂称他是圣徒，斯蒂芬不同意地说。

——别人叫他什么我他妈全管不着，克兰利粗暴、直率地说，我叫他浑蛋。

斯蒂芬先在脑子里把他要说的话整理了一下，继续说：

——耶稣在公众场合，对他母亲似乎也不很礼貌，可是苏阿莱兹那个耶稣教的神学家和西班牙绅士却为他进行了一些辩解。

——你脑子里有没有想到过，克兰利问道，耶稣实际完全不是他假装的那么个人？

——脑子里出现这种想法的第一个人，斯蒂芬回答说，是耶稣自己。

——我是说，克兰利声音越来越生硬地说，你有没有想到过，他自己也感觉到他是个伪君子，或者说，像他咒骂当时的犹太人时所说的那样，是一个假善人？或者，说得更直爽一些，他不过是一个恶棍？

——我倒从来没有这么想过，斯蒂芬回答说，可我真不明白，你现在的目的是要让我相信上帝呢，还是要让你自己也不再相信上帝了？

他转身看看他朋友的脸，他在他脸上看到一丝尴尬的微笑，但那里却同时流露出要使那微笑具有某种细微含义的强大的意志力量。

克兰利忽然用一种平淡的、心平气和的声调问道：

——告诉我实话，你刚才听到我的话，感到很吃惊吗？

——是有些吃惊，斯蒂芬说。

——既然你肯定地认为，克兰利仍用原来的声调进一步追问，我们的宗教是假的，耶稣并不是什么上帝的儿子，那你为什么会吃惊呢？

——那些事我也并不能完全肯定，斯蒂芬说，他倒更像是上帝的儿子，而不像是玛利亚的儿子。

——你所以不愿意参加圣餐会，克兰利问道，就因为你对那些事也不敢肯定，因为你感到圣餐会上的面包也许真是上帝的儿子的血和肉，而不只是一块面包？因为你担心可能是那样？

——是的，斯蒂芬安静地说，我确有那种感觉，对那个我也害怕。

——我明白，克兰利说。

斯蒂芬听他那声调，仿佛是要结束这次谈话了，因而为使讨论继续下去，接着说：

——我害怕许多东西：狗、马、枪炮、大海、雷电、各种机器，还有深夜里乡村的道路。

——可是对一小片面包你有什么好怕的呢？

——我想象，斯蒂芬说，在我说我害怕的那些东西后面存在着某种真实的邪恶。

——那么你害怕，克兰利问道，如果你在圣餐会上干了什么亵渎神灵的事，罗马教堂的上帝会马上置你于死地，并把你打入地狱吗？

——那罗马天主教堂的上帝现在就可以那么做了，斯蒂芬说，比那个更使我害怕的是，如果我对某一种象征给予虚假的崇拜就可能在我的灵魂中发生的那种化学作用，因为在那个象征后面已经聚集着二十个世纪的权威和崇敬了。

——到了十分危急的时候，克兰利问道，你也会愿意犯下刚才说的那种亵渎神灵的罪过吗？比方说，如果那会儿让你整天去悔罪？

——对过去的事我现在没法回答，斯蒂芬回答说，也许不会。

——那么，克兰利说，你是不打算变成一个新教徒了？

——我说过我已经失掉了信念，斯蒂芬回答说，但我并不是说，我失掉了对自己的尊敬。如果一个人放弃掉一种合乎逻辑的、合情合理的荒唐信念，却去抓住一个不合逻辑的和不合情理的荒唐信念，那算得上是一种什么思想上的解放呢？

他们原来一直朝着彭布罗克的市镇走去，现在他们仍缓慢地走在大马路上，那里的树林和从一些别墅照出的一星一点的灯光使他们的心境更为平静了。在他们周围出现的这种富裕和安宁的气氛似乎对他们的贫困也是一种安慰。在一排桂花树组成的树篱后面，一点灯光从一间厨房的窗口照射出来，同时他们还听到一个女佣一边磨刀一边歌唱的声音。她断断续续地唱着：

“罗西·奥格雷迪。”

克兰利止住步仔细听着，然后说：

——Mulier cantat．(70)

这拉丁话语的温柔的美，用一种令人陶醉的触摸，一种比音乐或一个女人的手更为轻柔、更为触动人心的触摸，抚摸着黄昏时的夜色。他们头脑里的纷乱的思想现在已平静下来。一个从教堂圣餐室走出来的女人的身影一声不响穿过那片黑暗：那是一个穿着白衣服的身影，矮小细瘦得像一个男孩，她的腰带几乎都要掉下来了。他们听到她像男孩子一样的又高又尖的声音领起了远处一个合唱队里由女声开头的歌唱，那声音穿透了那第一段充满热情的歌词所引起的忧闷和嘈杂：

——Et tu cum Jesu Galiloeo eras．(71)

所有的心都受到了触动，那声音像一颗年轻的星星闪闪发着光，它在和着先重后轻的节奏唱着的时候照得更亮，而在那节奏消逝的时候就显得更为暗淡了。

歌声停止了，他们又往前走去，克兰利用着意加强的节奏唱着那首歌的最后一节：

等到咱俩结婚以后，
　　啊，我们该是何等的快活，
因为我热爱温柔的罗西·奥格雷迪，
　　罗西·奥格雷迪也热爱我。

——你听听，这才真叫是诗，他说，这才是真正的爱情。

他斜着眼，带着奇怪的微笑看着斯蒂芬说：

——你认为那是诗吗？再说，你懂不懂得那些话是什么意思？

——我得先找到一个罗西再说，斯蒂芬说。

——要找她也不难，克兰利说。

他的帽子往额头上搭了下来。他把它往后推推，在那树林的阴影下，斯蒂芬看到了衬在一片黑暗中他苍白的脸和一双乌黑的大眼睛。是的。他的脸很漂亮，他的身体也很强壮。他曾讲到母爱。他体会到妇女的苦难，体会到她们的身体和灵魂的虚弱，他准备用他强有力的坚定的胳膊去保护她们，他在思想上向她们致敬。

那么离开这里吧，是该走的时候了。在斯蒂芬孤独的心中有一个声音柔和地说，它要他离开，并告诉他，他的友情到此也该结束了。是的，他要走。他不能和别人进行斗争。他知道他的地位。

——也许我要离开这里，他说。

——上哪儿？克兰利问道。

——上我能去的地方，斯蒂芬说。

——那也好，克兰利说。现在你要是还住在这里，可能有些困难。可是就因为那个就要走吗？

——我不能不走，斯蒂芬回答说。

——因为，克兰利继续说，如果你并不想走，你没有必要把自己看作是被人驱逐了，或者觉得自己是一个异教徒，或者是什么不法分子。有许多很好的宗教信徒，想法也和你差不多。你听了觉得奇怪吗？组成教堂的并不只是那几间石头房子，甚至也不是那些教士和他们的教条，而是生来就和它结下不解缘的一大群人。我不知道你在一生中想干些什么。你想干的，就是那天夜晚我们站在哈考特街外面车站上的时候，你对我说的那些吗？

——是的，斯蒂芬说，想到克兰利每一回想起过去的事，总喜欢跟事情发生的地点联系在一起，止不住违反自己的意愿笑了笑。那天晚上，你差不多费了半个小时和多尔蒂争论着，从萨利加普到拉拉斯到底走哪一条路最近。

——那个木头脑袋！克兰利轻蔑地说，他知道什么从萨利加普到拉拉斯去的路？不管对任何事他能知道些什么？他真算得上是天下最大的愚蠢的木头疙瘩脑袋！

他止不住放声大笑起来。

——啊，斯蒂芬说，后来的事你还记得吗？

——后来你讲的那些话，是吗？克兰利问道，是的，我记得的。你说你要去发现另一种生活方式或另一种艺术，依靠它你的心灵可以不受任何约束，自由地表现它自己。

斯蒂芬举举帽子表示他说得很对。

——自由！克兰利重复说，可是你并没有那么多可以亵渎神明的自由。告诉我，你会去抢劫吗？

——我先会想到乞讨，斯蒂芬说。

——如果你什么也讨不到，你会抢劫吗？

——你的意思是要我说，斯蒂芬回答说，所谓财产所有权也不过是暂时的，在某种情况下抢劫将会变成并非什么违法的事。每一个人都可以按照自己的信念行动。我现在可不想那样回答你的问题。这个你可以去问问那位耶稣会的神学家胡安·玛丽亚娜·德塔拉贝拉(72)，他会向你解释，在什么情况下你完全可以合法地杀死你的君王，还会告诉你，最好是用酒杯给他一杯毒药，还是把毒药抹在他的袍子上或者马鞍的扶手上。至于我，你倒不如问问，我会不会容忍别人来抢劫我，或者，如果有人抢劫了我，我会不会呼喊，要对他加以我相信是属于世俗的权力所行使的惩罚？

——你会吗？

——我想，斯蒂芬说，这让我感到的痛苦将和我遭到抢劫时的完全一样。

——我明白，克兰利说。

他掏出火柴来，开始又剔着他的两颗牙齿之间的一个牙缝。然后他极不在意地说：

——告诉我，比方说，你愿意和一个处女睡觉吗？

——对不起，斯蒂芬客气地说，这难道不是大多数年轻的先生们求之不得的事吗？

——你的看法怎么样呢？克兰利问道。

他最后这句像煤烟一样发着酸臭味并令人沮丧的话，刺激着斯蒂芬的头脑，那烟雾似乎把他的头脑给掩盖住了。

——你听我说，克兰利，他说，你刚才已经问我，我愿意干些什么和不愿意干些什么。我不愿意去为我已经不再相信的东西卖力，不管它把自己叫作我的家、我的祖国或我的教堂都一样：我将试图在某种生活方式中，或者某种艺术形式中尽可能自由地、尽可能完整地表现我自己，并仅只使用我能容许自己使用的那些武器来保卫自己——那就是沉默、流亡和机智。

克兰利抓住他的一只胳膊，拉他转过身来，领着他向利森公园走去。他几乎显得有些狡猾地大笑着，并带着一位长辈对年轻人的关怀拍拍斯蒂芬的肩膀。

——还说什么机智哩！他说，你说的是你吗？你这个可怜的诗人，你呀！

——你已经使我，斯蒂芬说，他的安抚使他十分感动，和过去一样向你坦白了许多事情，你说不是吗？

——是的，我的孩子，克兰利仍然很高兴地说。

——你让我向你坦白了我都害怕些什么。可是我还得要告诉你，我不害怕的又是些什么。我不怕孤独，不怕为别人的事受到难堪，也不怕丢开我必须丢开的一切。我也不怕犯错误，甚至犯极大的错误，终身无法弥补，或者也许永远无法弥补的错误。

克兰利现在又变得严肃起来，他放慢脚步说：

——孤独，十分孤独。你不害怕那个。可是你知不知道这话是什么意思？这不仅只是和所有的人分开，而且是甚至连一个朋友也没有。

——我愿意冒这个危险，斯蒂芬说。

——甚至也不要任何一个人，克兰利说，一个比朋友更亲近，比任何人所曾有过的最高贵、最可靠的朋友还要亲近的人和你在一起。

他的话似乎拨动了埋在他自己的天性最深处的一根琴弦。他是不是在说他自己，说他自己就是那样一个人，或者希望是那样一个人？斯蒂芬一声不响注视着他的脸。在他的脸上他看到一种冷漠的悲伤。他是在谈他自己，谈着使他害怕的他自己的孤独。

——你刚才说的是谁？斯蒂芬最后问道。

克兰利没有回答。

三月二十日。和克兰利就我的反抗问题谈了很久。

他又拿出了他那副神圣不可侵犯的样子。我还是那么温和，事事顺从。在一个人应该热爱自己母亲的问题上他对我进行攻击。曾极力想象他母亲是个什么样子：想不出。有一次因为没有细想，顺口告诉我，他父亲生他的时候已经是六十一岁。常可以见到他。强壮的农民的体格。穿着芝麻点花色的衣服。方头脚。灰色的胡须从来不加修整。也许还爱参加田径赛。对拉拉斯的德怀尔神父从不亏礼，但也并非十分尊重。有时候在夜里找一些姑娘闲聊。可他的母亲怎么样？很年轻还是很老了？恐怕不会年轻了。要不，克兰利就不会那样讲了。那么一定很老。也许，又没人关心她。因此克兰利才从心眼里感到绝望：这个干瘪老头儿生下的孩子。

三月二十一日，清晨。昨晚睡在床上想到这些事，可是因为太懒，思想太自由没有加以补充。思想太自由，是的。以利沙伯和撒迦利亚(73)就都是那么干瘪了。那么说他是一位先驱。还有，他主要吃猪肚肠、咸肉和干无花果。读一些关于蝗虫和野蜂蜂蜜的书。还有，每一想到他，总是看到一张严厉的没有身子的头，或者仿佛后面衬着一面灰色的幕布或红布的死人的脸。在某些宗教圈子里他们把这叫作亡头。拉丁门边的圣约翰简直有点把我弄糊涂了。我看见什么了？一个亡头的先驱正在设法掏开一把锁。

三月二十一日，夜晚。自由自在。灵魂自由自在，想象也自由自在。让死人去把死人埋掉吧。就是。让死人去和死人结婚吧。

三月二十二日。和林奇一块儿盯梢一个身材高大的医院看护。林奇的主意。根本不感兴趣。两只干瘦的饥饿的猎狗走在一头小母牛后面。

三月二十三日。从那天晚上以后，一直还没有见到过她。她不舒服了？也许正坐在火边上，把妈妈的头巾披在肩上。可是已经不再那么闹脾气了。来一碗煮得很好的稀粥？你现在要吃吗？

三月二十四日。跟我妈妈开始讨论一个问题。题目是：贞女圣玛利亚。由于我的性别和年纪太轻，我难以进行讨论。尽量避免拿耶稣跟爸爸的关系去和玛利亚跟她的儿子的关系相对比。说宗教不是一个产科医院。妈妈对我很宽容。说我的思想真怪，书读得太多。这话不对。读书少，了解的东西更少。接着她说我还会再回头相信上帝的，因为我的思想总也不得安宁的。那意思是说，我从罪孽的后门离开教堂，却又要从悔罪的天窗再进入教堂了。不可能悔罪。我这样明确地对她说，又问她要六个便士。只弄到三个便士。

然后上学校去。又和那个小圆脑袋的流氓眼睛格齐争吵了一番。这回争论的是关于诺拉的布鲁诺(74)的问题。开始用的是意大利语，最后说的全是支离破碎的英语。他说布鲁诺是一个可怕的异教徒。我说他倒是可怕地让人给烧死了。他带着某种悲伤的情绪同意了这一点。接着他开给我一个说明，告诉我怎么做他所说的risotto alla bergamasca(75)。他在念一个软音O的时候，把他的丰满的血红的嘴唇伸得老远，好像他要和那个母音亲吻似的。他是这样吗？他会不会忏悔？是的，他会的：他会哭出两颗圆圆的流氓的泪珠来，一个眼睛一颗。

走过斯蒂芬的，也就是我的菜园子，想起了那天夜晚克兰利所说“我们的宗教”的发明人原是他的同胞，而不是我的同胞的那番话。他们一共是四个人，都是九十七步兵旅的士兵，一起坐在那个十字架的脚下，用掷骰子来决定看谁应该得到那个钉在十字架上的人的外衣。

到图书馆去。尽力读了三篇评论文章。没有用。她还是没有出来。我因此感到很不安？干吗不安？怕她永远不再出来了。

布莱克曾写道：

我不知道威廉·邦德是否能保住性命，

因为，千真万确，他实在病得不轻。

天哪，可怜的威廉！

有一次在圆形大厅我看到一张透明画。大厅的尽头，尽都是些显要人物的画像。他们中还有威廉·尤尔特·格拉德斯通，他那会儿才刚刚死去。乐队演奏着《啊，威廉，我们全都想念你》。

全是一帮土包子！

三月二十五日，清晨。一夜尽做些令人讨厌的梦。希望尽可能把它们都从我心中清除掉。

一条很长的弯曲的走廊。从地面升起一条条黑色的烟柱。那里尽是些镶嵌在石头上的奇奇怪怪的帝王的形象。他们看来很疲倦，都把手放在自己的膝盖上，他们的眼神非常阴暗，因为人的错误总是变成黑色的烟雾飘到他们的眼前来。

离奇的人影从一个山洞中走了出来。他们没有一般人那么高。每一个人似乎都和身边的人挨得很近。他们的脸上闪着磷光，还有一条条颜色很深的条纹。他们全望着我，看他们的眼神仿佛要问我什么问题。他们都不说话。

三月三十日。今天晚上在图书馆的门廊上，克兰利对狄克逊和她的哥哥提出一个问题。一个妈妈让她的孩子掉在尼罗河里了。还在谈他的关于妈妈的问题。一条鳄鱼咬住了那孩子。妈妈要把孩子要回来。鳄鱼说，只要她告诉他，他应该怎么对待那个孩子，吃掉他还是不吃掉他，他就可以把孩子还她。

这种思想方法，莱皮德斯会说，真是靠着你自己的太阳的作用，在你自己的烂泥里孕育出来的。

我的呢？不是也一样吗？那就把它扔到尼罗河的烂泥里去吧！

四月一日。对最后那句话不很赞同。

四月二日。看到她在约翰斯顿、穆尼和奥布赖恩的店里喝茶、吃饼干。林奇的眼睛真是尖，在我们走过的时候，看见了她。他告诉我，克兰利是被他弟弟邀请到那里去的。他是否把他的鳄鱼也带去了？他现在是一只闪光的明灯吗？啊，是我发现他的。我肯定是我发现的。原来只是在威克罗谷仓一个大斗后面静静地发着光(76)。

四月三日。在芬勒特教堂对面的雪茄烟店里见到了达文。他穿着一件黑毛衣，拿着一根棒球棍。问我是不是真要出门去，并问我为什么。我告诉他到塔拉去最近的路是从霍利赫德那边走。就在那时我父亲来了。给他们介绍介绍。我父亲很客气，也很细心。问达文他可不可以请他吃点什么。达文不能吃，要去参加一个集会。我们走开的时候，我父亲告诉我说他有一双善良而诚实的眼睛。问我为什么没有参加一个划船俱乐部。我假装说准备考虑考虑。后来还告诉我说他怎么伤了彭尼费瑟的心。要我去学法律。说我天生是学法律的料。又是些烂泥，又是些鳄鱼。

四月五日。寒冷的春天。奔驰的云彩。啊，生活！在浑浊的烂泥塘中黑色的水流边，苹果树抛下了它们的娇嫩的花朵。在那些树叶间可以看到许多女孩子的眼睛。一些显得很端庄的蹦蹦跳跳的女孩子。都是白皮肤的或者是琥珀色的，没有一个黑皮肤的。她们脸一红便显得更美。真叫妙！

四月六日。她肯定记得过去的事。林奇说所有的女人都记得过去的事。那么她一定记得她儿时的情景——还有我童年时候的情况，如果我也曾经有过童年的话。过去被现在吞噬了，现在所以活着是因为它会带来将来。如果林奇说得不错，所有女人的雕像都应该永远浑身都遮盖起来，女人的一只手总遗憾地摸着自己的后部。

四月六日更晚一些。迈克尔·罗巴茨记起了被他遗忘的美，当他用胳膊拥抱她的时候，他使劲搂着的是在这个世界上早已凋谢的爱。不要这个。完全不要。我希望，我能在我的怀抱里搂抱着一种还未曾来到这世上的爱。

四月十日。这个城市，像一个十分疲惫、任何抚摸都不能使他动心的情人一样，由各种梦境进入了无梦的睡眠，就在这个阴森的夜晚，通过城市里的寂静，大路上隐隐传来了马蹄声。马蹄来到桥边，那声音显得更清晰了。不一会儿，它们从黑暗的窗口外边走过，于是那里的寂静像被一支箭穿过一样，被一阵惊愕划破了。马蹄现在又越走越远了，在阴森的黑夜中马蹄像珠宝一样闪着光，它们匆匆穿过睡眠的田野要前往何处——要进入什么人的心？——携带着什么消息？

四月十一日。重读了读昨天晚上写下的那些话。表达一种模糊感情的模糊的语言。她会喜欢它吗？我想会的。那么我也应该喜欢它。

四月十三日。“通盘”那个词儿长时期来还一直扰乱着我的思想。我查了一查，发现它原是英语，而且是规规矩矩的古老的英语。让那个副教导主任和他的漏斗见鬼去吧！他到这儿干什么来了，是教我们他自己的语言，还是跟我们学习我们的语言。不管是哪一样，都让他见鬼去吧！

四月十四日。约翰·阿方萨斯·马尔雷南刚刚从西爱尔兰回来了。欧洲和亚洲的报纸请刊登这个消息吧。他告诉我们，他在那里的一间山上的木房子里遇见了一位老人。那位老人眼睛发红，抽着一根很短的烟斗。老人讲爱尔兰语。马尔雷南也讲爱尔兰语。后来那老人和马尔雷南又一起讲英语。马尔雷南和他谈了一些关于宇宙和星体的事。老人坐着，听着，抽着烟，吐着痰。然后说：

——啊，到世界快结束的时候，准会出现许多可怕的奇怪的人。

我怕他。我怕他那眼圈发红又发硬的眼睛。整个一夜直到天亮，我必须和他进行斗争，直到他或者我死去，我要紧抓住他的满是青筋的脖子直到……直到什么？直到他向我屈服？不。我没有意思要伤害他。

四月十五日。今天在格拉夫顿大街，我和她面对面地相遇了。是拥挤的行人把我们挤到一块儿去的。我们俩都站住了。她问我，为什么我从没有去看她，说她听到别人讲了许多关于我的传闻。这样说不过只是为了拖延时间。问我现在有没有写诗？写什么人？我也问她。这不免使她更感到有些难堪，我感到很抱歉，很不应该。马上关掉那个活门，打开了精神英雄主义的冷气设备，这东西是丹特·阿利吉雅里发明，并在全世界各国取得专利权的。连珠炮似的谈着我自己和我的各种计划。不幸在我说话中间，我忽然做了一个革命的手势。我当时的神态一定像一个抓着一把豌豆往空中乱撒的家伙。街上的人全转过头来看着我们。过了一会儿，她和我拉了拉手，在离开的时候，她说她希望我照我说的去做。

现在我把这叫作一种友好态度，你说呢？

是的，今天我很喜欢她。有一点喜欢还是非常喜欢？说不清。我喜欢她，而这对我仿佛是一种很新的感情。那么，这么说来，其他的一切，我过去想我曾想到的一切，和我过去感到我曾感觉到的一切，从今以后其他的一切，事实上……啊，全部抛开吧，老伙计！去睡一觉，把它们全忘掉。

四月十六日。走吧！走吧！

拥抱的胳膊和那声音的迷人的符咒：大路的白色的胳膊，它们已许诺要紧紧地拥抱，映衬着月影的高大船只的黑色的胳膊，它们带来了许多远方国家的信息。它们都高高举起，仿佛在说：我们很孤单——快来吧。而那些声音也和它们一起叫喊着：我们是你的亲人。在它们向我，它们的亲人召唤的时候，空气里充满了它们的友情，我准备走了，它们正扇动着它们得意的和可怕的青春的翅膀。

四月二十六日。妈妈为我整理我新买来的一些旧衣服。她说，她现在天天祷告，希望我能在远离家庭和朋友的时候，通过自己的生活慢慢弄清楚什么是人的心肠，它都有些什么感觉。阿门。但愿如此。欢迎，啊，生活！我准备第一百万次去接触经验的现实，并在我心灵的作坊中铸造出我的民族的还没有被创造出来的良心。

四月二十七日。老父亲，古老的巧匠(77)，现在请尽量给我一切帮助吧。

都柏林，一九〇四年

————————————————————

(1) 近代德国剧作家。

(2) 13世纪意大利诗人。

(3) 见其所作：《欢乐的幻景》（1641）。

(4) 指下等妓女。

(5) 拉丁文书名：《圣托马斯哲学思想纲要》。

(6) 分别为英、法、意、拉丁文，均为象牙之意。

(7) 拉丁文：印度出产象牙。

(8) 拉丁文：演说家力求简约，诗人却需铺张。

(9) 拉丁文：十分危殆。

(10) 指该学校西侧托马斯·穆尔塑像。

(11) 西奥博尔德·沃尔弗·托恩是18世纪末爱尔兰革命家，曾要求法国派兵到爱尔兰帮助本地的革命运动，被英政府判处叛国罪，后自杀。

(12) 法语：意为爱尔兰万岁！

(13) 即约翰·伊根，英国下院议员，对当时英国政治十分不满。

(14) 即托马斯·惠利，英国下院议员，在联合问题上进行投票时，受贿变节。

(15) 拉丁文，意为：意之所悦者谓之美。

(16) 拉丁文，意为：心之所向者谓之善。

(17) 拉丁文，即下句“像老人手中的一根手杖”。

(18) 公元2世纪初希腊斯多葛派哲学家。

(19) 这里的“陪伴”和“绊住”原文是同一个词（detain）。斯蒂芬讲这句话只是在说明这个词在“市井间”的用法，而副教导主任却以为是斯蒂芬在对他表示歉意，因而有下文的误会。

(20) 拉丁文，意为：只有通过艰险才能到达高峰。

(21) 指伊格内修斯·洛约拉，见本书注(22)。

(22) 20世纪初英国喜剧作家。

(23) 这里后一句是重述吉尔伯特的流行喜剧中的一句台词。

(24) 上文F．W．马蒂诺这个名字和“清水马丁”的英语读音颇有相似之处，因而“清水马丁”中的“清水”二字，可能只是由F．W．两字母意测为Fresh Water的玩笑话。

(25) 拉丁文：我签了。

(26) 拉丁文：什么？

(27) 拉丁文：为普遍的和平呼吁。

(28) 拉丁文：“我想你他妈的全是撒谎”，“因为你的脸色表明你正是满肚子怨气”。

(29) 拉丁文：“谁满肚子怨气”，“是我还是你”。

(30) 全名为威廉·托马斯·斯特德，《帕尔·莫尔报》著名记者，当时曾大力宣传国际和平。

(31) 18世纪初的一位自然神论者。

(32) 当然是信口开玩笑：下文爱尔兰歌谣中的洛蒂·柯林斯的名字不过是偶然巧合而已。

(33) 拉丁文：让这血腥的世界全面和平吧。

(34) 拉丁文：我们得不怕玩硬球。

(35) 公元前4世纪雅典著名的雕刻家。

(36) 此词按前见译文“意之所悦者谓之美”（见本书注(15)），则应作“意”字解释。但此词原文义确较含糊，斯蒂芬这里是将它译作“感受”了。

(37) 一种埃及土人，据信是古埃及人的后裔。

(38) 西南非的一个少数民族。

(39) 拉丁文：舌啊，盛赞光荣的。

(40) 拉丁文：皇帝的旗帜。

(41) 拉丁文：大卫高唱虔诚的赞歌，他向各族人民发出宣言：“十字架上的上帝仍统治一切！”他的话已全部应验。

(42) 欧洲文艺复兴时期著名的美术家达芬奇的著名的肖像画。

(43) 特平是传说中18世纪英国的著名大盗，据说他曾骑着一匹快马一口气从伦敦直跑到纽约。

(44) 拉丁文：我相信在利物浦穷苦人的日子简直就是可怕，简直就是他妈的没法过。

(45) 据《圣经》，他是向人间宣布让贞女玛利亚作为耶稣的母亲的天使长。

(46) 一种十九行二韵的法国诗体。

(47) 指15世纪初亨利五世于此大败法军的一战。

(48) 绿袖姑娘即思恋中的姑娘的代称，此说在英国民歌中曾一度流行。

(49) 13世纪意大利一僧侣和神学家。

(50) 从古罗马时期便已开始的一种迷信的占卜办法。其主要的方式是通过观察鸟的飞翔情况以判断神的意旨。

(51) 19世纪初法国宣扬炼金术和魔术的术士。

(52) 18世纪瑞典科学家和神秘主义思想家。

(53) 当指希腊神话中靠蜡做的翅膀飞翔的迪达勒斯（参看本书注(8)）。此处谓“柳条编成的翅膀”不知何所据。

(54) 埃及神话中司智慧和魔法的神，他一般被画作人身鸟头的形象。

(55) 叶芝诗剧《卡斯琳公爵夫人》中两人物名（分别为卡斯琳的养母和情人）。此一短歌原为卡斯琳临终所唱。

(56) 拉丁文：一个非常著名的古老的家族。

(57) 拉丁文：有待证实。

(58) 此词原文以s结尾，故复数不变。类似情况英语中并不少。

(59) 见注(63)。

(60) 这里所提三人均为英国17世纪音乐家或作家。

(61) 苏格兰的斯图亚特王室自14世纪后曾长期统治苏格兰和英格兰。

(62) 17世纪福佛兰德耶稣会教士和神学家。

(63) 引自托马斯·纳什的《死的召唤》。上文“黑暗正从天空下降”，是有意反用其意。

(64) 拉丁文，原意为“以事实而论”，这里或可解释为：“有所实指”。

(65) 英文口语to give one fig（给人无花果）义为对某人作出表示轻蔑的姿态。此处因联想及这一成语。故有此问。

(66) 原文limbo，按西方迷信说法，在天国和地狱之间还有此一地方（弥尔顿《失乐园》中即有此说），收容本人无罪而因其他种种原因不能进入天堂的灵魂，其中包括未受洗的孩子。

(67) 因原文limbo和limb（义为人的肢体）词体、词音均相近，因有此戏语。

(68) 西格弗里德是日尔曼民族传说中的民族英雄。此处指19世纪德国作曲家理查德·瓦格纳的作品。

(69) 法国17世纪著名科学家、数学家、哲学家和作家。

(70) 拉丁文：一个妇女在唱歌。

(71) 拉丁文：你和加利利的上帝同在。

(72) 17世纪西班牙历史学家和政治哲学家，他曾大力倡导不顾人民死活的暴君人人得而诛之的理论。

(73) 见《新约·路加福音》第1章第6节：大意说上帝使这一对年岁已很老的夫妇生下了儿子。

(74) 16世纪意大利著名哲学家。

(75) 意大利语：柏加莫风味的米饭。

(76) 英文有一句成语：大意是“以斗掩光”，主要用以形容一个人不露锋芒，有点近似中文的成语韬光养晦。这里显然是借用其意。

(77) 自然仍指传说中的那个迪达勒斯，参看注(8)。

译本序

一

内维尔·舒特出生于1899年，毕业于牛津大学，获得工程学学位，1923年进入伦敦的德哈维兰飞机有限公司，边工作边学习驾驶飞机，并且利用业余时间写作。为了避免航空工程师和作家两个角色的混淆，他在从事航空工作时使用原名内维尔·舒特·诺威，写作时使用内维尔·舒特一名。其后他成为R100飞艇设计和制造团队的成员。由于R101飞艇在1930年坠毁，英国决定停止飞艇研制工作，内维尔所在的团队也被解散。二战爆发后，内维尔参加了海军，战时主要在伦敦从事秘密的海军工作，最终升任至英国皇家海军志愿后备队的少校。离开海军后，他远访远东和澳大利亚，并在途中听到了八十位欧洲女士二战期间在印尼被日军俘虏，被迫徒步长途跋涉的悲惨故事。他被这个故事深深触动，怀着对幸存者的尊敬，构思了《像爱丽丝的小镇》前半部的情节，这部小说也成为了他的代表作。

内维尔·舒特的第一部长篇小说《玛拉赞》于1926年出版，讲述一个商务飞行员坠机后流落荒岛，被一个罪犯所救的故事。该罪犯实际上是因为惨遭其贩毒的哥哥陷害而蒙冤的。后来，在两人的共同努力下，该贩毒集团终于被捣毁。内维尔最著名的小说还有《彩衣风笛手》（1942）、《公路已尽》（1948）、《海滩之上》（1957）和《来自工具室的受托人》（1960）。他喜欢把航空知识和他的战时经历写进小说中。内维尔1950年移居澳大利亚，1960年猝然离世，终其一生共留下了二十三部小说，其中多部被搬上荧幕。在美国现代图书馆（Modern Library）网站由读者评选的二十世纪一百部最佳英文小说中，他有三部小说入选，《像爱丽丝的小镇》位列最高，排名十七。澳大利亚中部的爱丽丝斯普林斯（爱丽丝泉）因该书而闻名。英国汉普郡朴茨茅斯机场的诺威路和内维尔·舒特路以他的名字命名，澳大利亚东南部维多利亚州的贝里克也有以他的名字命名的舒特大街。

二

拿到这本书的时候，仲夏正炎，展眼却已秋情萧瑟，寒意渐生，正如这部小说一路写来热烈激荡，却在斯特拉坎先生那冷雾围绕的寒舍中落幕。

《像爱丽丝的小镇》于1950年出版，大获好评，再版多次，并于1956年被拍摄成电影。翻译这本名作的这六个多月，每天焦灼不安。本来翻译就像给别人带孩子，比带自己的孩子还要紧张一万倍，深恐磕着碰着，不能完整交回朋友手中，译者也最怕把书翻走了样，交到读者手里的，竟是自己的重新创作，糟蹋了作者的心血。

小说以二战结束为界，分为两部分。前半部分，从英国远赴马来亚工作的年轻姑娘，琴·佩吉特，在二战期间日本侵略马来亚的战争中被俘，被迫和其他妇女儿童一起在马来亚北部各地之间徒步跋涉。其间他们遇到了年轻的澳大利亚战俘乔·哈曼，他为了帮助战俘们渡过难关铤而走险。下半部分写琴在战争结束后回到英国，继承了一笔丰厚的遗产。为了报答战时马来亚村民对他们这群战俘的保护和照顾，她返回马来亚报恩，并偶然得到乔仍然在世的消息……

若将《像爱丽丝的小镇》比喻成一幅油画，必定属于不厌其烦的古典派。细细读来，不禁感到舒特先生简直就像在写回忆录，努力将情节安排得真实自然，把人物写得栩栩如生，让读者觉得仿佛确有其人其事，而作者只是一个忠实的记录者。通部小说出现了多个“of course”（直译则是“当然”，“自然”），并处处做了铺垫，使故事的推进顺理成章，鲜有突兀之处，不露堆砌痕迹。因此，书中叙述虽然细致繁复，似有赘言，回头看时，却发现伏笔布满，一不小心就容易走漏瞬息繁华。例如，写到诺尔送别琴的时候，作者说诺尔莫名其妙地感到琴不会回来，看似老人家的痴语，实则却为后文伏笔。当然，“无巧不成书”，主角琴和乔之间的爱情故事还是稍微落入了俗套，读者读至彼处自能体会。

作者在写这本小说的时候，已经年逾五十，历经一战和二战，也经受了职业生涯的跌宕起伏，因此笔下每一句话都功力深厚，不能等闲视之。他在书中深刻地探讨了人生和人性，正如书中结尾所说的，他写了“陌生的场景”和“勇敢的人”。这些不是一根青春烂漫的笔能写出来的。他写琴去到马来亚，和同胞们一样不知战争之险恶，也不知祸之将至，在硝烟即将弥漫之时仍然载歌载舞地忙得不可开交，却又马上写她成了战俘，陷入绝境；他写绝境中之人性，一人一个样，绝无重复，幸存下来的人，却又都一致地乐观坚强；他写战俘眼里的战争，真实地描画了在战争里隐忍求存的平民百姓，写出了军官的残暴，也写出了某些日本士兵的善良。后来，他又写琴和乔的爱情故事，写琴如何融入海湾地区的生活，如何勇于改变威尔斯镇的面貌，虽淡淡写来，却都是经验智慧之言。他写到被抛弃的黄金镇，那透骨的荒凉，却又通过写琴改变威尔斯镇的努力种下了复苏的种子，仿佛预示温暖的东风即将吹开一季繁花。这一切，时而通过琴来叙述，时而由诺尔以第一人称叙述，娓娓讲来，历历在目，不矫揉造作，不哗众取宠，真实的情感委婉动人，让读者不知不觉中跟着书中的人物一起悲伤，一起快乐，一起惆怅，一起沉迷于这个具有魔力的故事中，读着读着仿佛都变成了诺尔，忘不了米德赫斯特的牧场住宅，忘不了威尔斯镇鲜艳夺目的红色屋顶，忘不了那里朴实却令人感动的平凡居民，与他们的欢笑悲辛。

本书对于人物的描写，也委实难有其他小说出于其右。琴和乔都不是什么大人物，没有出格的个性，也不是什么悲天悯人的大救世主，这样的人物，最是难写。两个普通人，没有惊人的美貌，没有惊天动地的壮举，却凭着认真坚韧的心，度过逆境，守来幸福，遂了心愿。琴是一个活泼聪明的姑娘，文化水准中等，没有上过大学，却善解人意，真诚善良，敢作敢为，讲诚信，有义气。在马来亚的时候，敌人马上杀到眼前，她却担心霍兰太太无法带着两个孩子一起逃难，自告奋勇地去帮助她，结果跟着霍兰一家一起被俘。被迫徒步东奔西走时，她勇于转换生活方式，适应当地恶劣条件，并主动与日本看守和当地村民交流，积极化解困难，最后带领幸存的战俘们成功安顿下来，挽救了自己和他人的生命。她头脑清楚，同伴们都认为乔是神的使者，她却知道乔也是一个普通人，但她依然深爱着他。她因失去爱人而伤心欲绝，却依旧生活得认真踏实。拿到遗产后，她首先想到的不是个人享受与实现个人梦想，而是赶紧回马来亚去报答战时恩人。知道乔仍然在世，她不顾一切地赶赴澳大利亚，只为了再见他一面，自是一个有情有义的人。后来，为了乔的事业，她又决定留在偏远的海湾地区，并且积极进取地实施自己的计划，最终将乔的家园建设得温馨时尚，将勃勃生机和无限希望带到这片土地上。

而乔则是一个满腔热血的男子，有正义感，也很善良，虽然话多了些，却朴素踏实，像一座沉稳秀美的山。他看见琴和她的同伴忍饥挨饿，心有不忍，舍命偷鸡给他们吃，结果事发受刑。后来他听见琴未婚，马上从澳大利亚远赴英国，为的也只是再见琴一面，也是一个性情中人。他热爱自己的工作，对未来充满乐观，积极进取，在所有人都要离开海湾地区的时候，他却看到了繁荣的远景，对牛场的发展作了详细周密的计划。他去英国旅行，让他兴奋不已的不是华丽的著名宫殿，而是先进的育种技术。终于与琴相见后，他想为了琴而放弃自己的家园，为了心爱的人情愿委屈自己。别人偷他的牛而受伤，他也马上去救人，可见他心胸之宽广。他没有什么文化，说起话来土气扑面，但是却可亲可爱，真挚诚恳，活力四射，仿佛浑身上下都散发着温暖的阳光。

本书另一个重要人物诺尔，是一位收入丰厚的律师，年事已高，生活孤单冷清，却仿佛作者自己的化身，是一位可亲而深邃的老人家。他历经人世沧桑，晚年遇到一位年轻漂亮的姑娘，成为了她的托管人，并尽他所能帮助她实现愿望。他对她有一种无从述说的感情，正如书末所说，她是一个“迟到了四十年的姑娘”，也正是以他的口气，才能将这样一个故事讲得字字深情，千回百转。若换一个人来讲，或者换一个角度叙述，这个故事只是平淡如水。这正是作者独特的匠心与苦心，其对待写作的态度是如此认真，本身也足以令人感动。其他人物，如给唐纳德开死亡证明的医生、弗里思太太、马特·阿明、安妮等，全部个性鲜明，跃然纸上，读者阅读之时，自能玩味。

最爱结尾的那一点不甘心和遗恨，使人读到诺尔的梦境时，禁不住地悲伤，方知道这一本书，也有一点“妖”，是能使人着魔的，诺尔梦里的那些场景，倒像是自己也真实看到过的。

这样一部小说，翻译起来真是费尽思量。力求真实的故事、平凡的人物、细致的描写，以及作者每一句话里的机锋，让我这个非常欠缺生活经验的人挠破了头。这部小说时而写东半球，时而写西半球，时而是发达的伦敦，时而是落后的马来亚，时而是蓬勃发展的澳大利亚，所涉及的人物更是多如牛毛，各有各的性格，各有各的语言特点。作者在英国出生长大，后来去过马来亚旅游，五十岁时定居澳大利亚，一切细如毫发的描写可说与现实丝毫不差，翻译时绝不敢怠慢或轻松带过，几乎所有的场景和物品都要查一次，看到图片或相关介绍才能放心地翻译出来。书中说到海湾地区有许多牛场，后来我查了沈永兴老师等编著的《澳大利亚》，方知道确有其事，而且昆士兰出口的牛肉占澳大利亚一半以上，而澳大利亚又是仅次于阿根廷的世界牛肉出口大国，可知书中背景并非凭空捏造。而最难翻译的，当属人物语言。英国人说英式英语，日本人英语大多很差，马来亚人自然说的是另一种英语，而澳大利亚人则满嘴澳洲土话。有许多俚语和土话，连我们学院的外教都闻所未闻，例如“fair cow”，连澳洲外教都不知道是什么意思，后来托外教住在澳大利亚的亲戚才辗转查到了。第九和第十章的广播用语也令我左右为难。此外，作者是一个职业工程师，游历广泛，知识丰富，在书中讲述了很多有趣的知识，例如稻田种植、沙袋鼠、飞机、飞行、卡车等，这些离我的生活都很远，翻译的时候，只好硬着头皮重新看书学习。需要指出的是，书中的威尔斯镇却是作者以伯克镇和诺曼顿为原型虚构的一个小镇。通篇小说语言严密，却又以老人讲故事的口吻，平淡而絮叨地讲来，往往话里有话，翻译时必须步步留神，一不小心就会错失字里行间的隐含意义。

有鉴于此，加上这本书在国内是第一次被翻成中文，没有前人的成稿可以参考，我的译稿必然有许多错漏之处，恳请读者谅解，也恳请前辈们不吝指正。

翻译这本书，前后只有六个多月的时间，加上开学后行政工作和教学工作繁重，总怕自己力有不逮，不能将这本书翻得合乎理想。很多前辈、同事和学生都看见过我每天下班后翻译的狼狈相，给予了我许多许多帮助，我的内心，自然对他们充满了感谢。此外，书中《圣经》和《古兰经》的句子，分别使用基督教协会和马坚老师的经典译文，在此一并致谢。

经典之所以成为经典，自有其过人之处，非寻常浮光掠影般的快餐文学可比。如果各位能抽空好好品读一下这个故事，将是我极大的幸福。也许这个故事有一点长，但读罢掩卷，其袅袅余韵，一定会比其本身更加悠长。

第一章

1905年3月，四十七岁的詹士·麦法登在德里菲尔德的一次定点越野赛马中不幸丧生。

他大部分财产由儿子道格拉斯继承。那时麦法登家和达尔豪西家都住在珀斯，达尔豪西家的佐克是道格拉斯的同学。佐克当时还很年轻，却已经是伦敦赞善里一家律师事务所——欧文、达尔豪西和彼得斯——的初级合伙人。这个律师事务所历史悠久，三位创始人都早已辞世，但我作为现任高级合伙人，从未想过要给它起一个新名字。

佐克·达尔豪西顺理成章地成为了道格拉斯·麦法登的代理律师，并一直亲自处理好友的财产事务，直到1928年去世。在分摊达尔豪西的工作时，麦法登先生成为了我的客户，但我却忙于应付其他事务，渐渐把他的事情抛在了脑后。

一直到1935年，麦法登先生从埃尔寄来一封信，我才重新想起这位客户来。信上告知，他的妹夫亚瑟·佩吉特在马来亚惨遭车祸，不幸罹难，因此他意欲修改遗嘱，以遗产托管的方式，将遗产转移到妹妹琴和她两个孩子的名下。作为他的代理律师，竟然对委托人孑然一身、无儿无女的情况一无所知，我不禁感到惭愧不安。信的结尾说，由于健康状况太糟糕，无法亲自到伦敦来，所以如果我们能够委派一名小职员去见他以安排相关事宜，他将不胜感激。

这与我的行程不谋而合。收到这封信的时候，我正要动身去希尔湖度假，享受为期两周的钓鱼之旅。所以我写信告诉他，将在假期结束，南下返回的时候顺道去拜访他。写好信后，我把他的档案材料塞进旅行箱底，打算在度假时找一个晚上好好做做功课。

到达埃尔后，我在车站酒店住了下来——既然信中只字未提我的食宿，我想麦法登先生也不会操这份心。我脱下灯笼裤，换上深色正装，去拜访这位素未谋面的客户。

他的生活状况完全出乎我的意料。我不知道他的遗产具体有多少，但肯定超过两万英镑，所以我想这位先生应该会住在一幢体面的房子里，由一两名仆人伺候生活起居。但是，情况全然不是这样。他住在海边一个很小的私人旅馆里，在同一层里租了一个卧室和一个起居室。他才五十出头，比我还年轻十岁，但显然已过着病榻生活，起居不便。他跟一个八十岁的老太太一样弱如风烛，脸色死灰，似乎一半身子已经躺在了坟墓里。我刚刚从空气清新的湖边湿地回来，蓦地走进这个窗户紧闭、阴暗局促的房间，觉得浑身不自在。窗户上挂着一排鸟笼，养着许多虎皮鹦鹉，散发出来的味道使得这个房间越发令人窒息。从家具布置来看，这位先生已经在这个房间里生活了许多个年头。

我们讨论遗嘱时，他谈到了他的生活。他亲切友善，对于我的亲自来访感到喜出望外。尽管他有浓重的苏格兰口音，但应该是一位知书识礼的先生。“我的生活波澜不惊，斯特拉坎先生，”他说，“健康状况不允许我出远门。天气好的时候，我会起个大早，在门前晒晒太阳。然后，玛姬——老板娘道尔太太的女儿——就会过来帮我坐上轮椅，推我出去散散心。她们对我真是照顾有加。”

谈到遗嘱，他告诉我说他只剩下妹妹琴·佩吉特一位近亲了。“如果不算上我父亲在澳大利亚可能还有的一到两个所谓的私生子，”他说，“我不能确定有，尽管我一个都没见过，也没有收到过他们的来信。不过有一次琴向我提起过母亲曾为此事悲痛万分。这种事情最能刺激女士的神经，而且我父亲又是个精力旺盛的风流人物，去到哪里都闲不住。”

他妹妹琴在一战期间参加了英国妇女后勤军团，并在1917年春天与一位佩吉特上校成婚。“有点出乎我们意料，”他和蔼地说，“要知道我妹妹在参军前没离开过苏格兰半步，后来又去了帕斯，而亚瑟·佩吉特却是从汉普郡南安普敦来的一位英格兰人。我对亚瑟倒是没什么意见，但我们一直都很自然地以为琴会嫁给一位苏格兰人。不过，话说回来，他们的婚姻还算美满——起码不比大部分夫妻差吧。”

战后亚瑟·佩吉特在马来亚太平镇附近一个橡胶庄园找到了工作，琴当然也跟着他去了，从此便几乎从道格拉斯·麦法登的生命中消失。她只在1926年和1932年趁休假回家探过亲。她生了两个小孩儿，儿子唐纳德出生于1918年，女儿小琴出生于1921年。1932年的时候，琴把兄妹俩送到南安普敦的爷爷奶奶家，把他们留在那里上学，自己则回到了马来亚。我的客户与他们唯一一次见面就在那一年。

现在的情况是，亚瑟·佩吉特在怡保附近出车祸去世了——他从吉隆坡开车回家时车速太快，滑出马路，撞到了树上。可能他当时睡着了。他的遗孀琴·佩吉特事发时在英格兰。亚瑟去世前大约一年，她回家给两个小孩找了一套房子，就在南安普敦边上的巴西特，以方便他们上学。这个安排还算合理，但是麦法登先生对此多少感到有些遗憾，因为兄妹俩没能够住得离彼此更近一些。我能看出来麦法登先生对此耿耿于怀，因为他不止一次地提到这件事。

他想修改遗嘱。现在这份遗嘱只是很简单地把所有遗产都留给琴。“我还是会把遗产给她，”他说，“但是我写这份遗嘱的时候亚瑟·佩吉特还活着，而且我当时并没想到他会比我先走一步。我这身子骨一向很差，想是也活不长的，而他和琴风华正茂。我原以为他可以帮助我妹妹好好规划一下如何使用这笔钱。”

他似乎顽固地认为所有女人都不谙世事，不善理财。她们没有责任心，而且投机商能轻而易举地把她们玩弄于股掌之中。所以，尽管决定了把全部财产都留给妹妹，他还是打算要找一位托管人，以保证唐纳德能够在她去世后分文不少地得到这笔遗产。要实现这个要求当然并不困难。作为例行公事，我向他列举了这个做法的种种利弊，同时指出，他在道尔太太的房子里住了这么多年，而且很可能会一直住到离世，如果不能留出一笔小小的遗赠给她，多少有点不妥。他认同我的说法。此外，由于已经没有其他近亲在世，他想委托我作为全权托管人和遗嘱执行人。那倒是家庭律师的分内事，但是我告诉他，鉴于我年事已高，最好找一位共同托管人。他同意由我们所的初级合伙人列斯特·罗宾逊来担任此职，对我们在这些事务上的收费条款，他也没有异议。

这份遗嘱毕竟很简单，再敲定余下几个小问题就完成了。我问他，如果他和妹妹都在唐纳德未满二十一岁之前去世，我们该如何处理这笔遗产。我的建议是，在唐纳德成年时托管结束，所有遗产归他自由支配。麦法登先生同意了，我在便笺上记下来。

“假设发生另外一种情况，”我说，“唐纳德先于他母亲去世，又或者母子俩都由于某种原因先于您去世，那财产就转由小姑娘小琴继承。我是否也可以认为，托管期同样地在她成年时结束？”

“您是说，”他问，“在她满二十一岁的时候？”

我点点头。“是的，和她哥哥一样。”

他摇摇头。“我认为那太不周全了，斯特拉坎先生，请原谅我这样说。但是，没有一个二十一岁的姑娘能够管理好自己的财产。那个年纪的姑娘都很容易上男人的当，斯特拉坎先生。她们会上男人的当的。她的托管期必须要长很多，至少要到她满四十岁时才能结束。”

过去种种经历让我不禁同意他这个观点。一个二十一岁的女孩子确实还太年轻，无法驾驭这样一笔巨款，但是我又觉得四十岁太老了。我对他说，二十五岁是一个比较合适的年纪，他很勉强地让步到三十五岁。那已经是他的底线了。他开始表现出明显的疲态，并且变得有点不耐烦，所以我只好接受那作为托管的最长期限。这意味着托管期可能长达二十一年，尽管这种情况不太可能发生，因为小琴生于1921年，而当时才1935年。我们的会面就到此为止了。我与他分别，回到伦敦起草遗嘱，并寄给他签字。从此，我就再没跟他见过面。

与他失去联系是我的错。多年来，我养成了春天度假的习惯，跟妻子一道去苏格兰——通常是希尔湖——玩两周，享受钓鱼的乐趣。人常常会不自觉地以为，生活总是会一成不变地过下去。所以我想，明年此时，当我再度从北方南返时，还可以顺道拜访一下麦法登先生，看看有没有别的事情可以为他效劳。但世事无常，在1935年冬天，露茜去世了。我不愿沉溺其间，但我们是二十七年的老夫妻了——是的，那使我十分悲痛。当时两个儿子都在国外，哈利在驻中国英军基地的潜水艇上服役，马丁在巴士拉(1)的石油公司工作。我无心再赴希尔湖，并从此再未踏进苏格兰半步。我拍卖了大部分家具，并卖掉了我和妻子在温布尔登公地共同居住过的房子。人在此情此境更须振作，不应埋首于往日幸福的灰堆。

我在白金汉门(2)租了一套公寓，在皇家马厩对面，与我在蓓尔美尔街的俱乐部只隔一个公园。我用从温布尔登带来的几件家具简单布置了一下新家，请了一位保姆每天早上来做早饭和打扫卫生。在这里，我渐渐过上了和俱乐部其他会员一样的生活：在公寓吃早饭，步行穿过公园，沿河岸街走到位于赞善里的办公室，工作一整天，在办公桌上吃一顿简单的午餐，六点到俱乐部去看看杂志，闲聊一会儿，吃晚饭，打一局桥牌。从1936年起，我就养成了这样的生活方式，直到现在，依然如此。

上述一连串变故让我的心思离开了道格拉斯·麦法登。我将大部分精力放在处理私事上，工作上只能应付那些有急事的客户。不久，另一件事又更加吸引了我的注意。战争的硝烟开始弥漫，而俱乐部的一些会员——包括我在内——因年纪太大无法服兵役，便都积极投身空袭预防工作。长话短说，这项被称作民防的工作在接下来的八年里占据了我所有的闲暇时间。我成了一个民间防空员，负责在伦敦大轰炸期间以及其后漫长的战争岁月中在威斯敏斯特地区执勤。实际上我的下属都去服兵役了，我只能勉强独力支撑整个律师事务所的运营。那些年里，我从未休假，甚至连每晚五小时的睡眠时间也难以保证。待到战争终于在1945年结束，我已经白发苍苍，颤颤巍巍了。虽然接下来几年身体状况有所好转，我还是不可挽回地加入了老年人的行列。

1948年1月的一个下午，我收到一封从埃尔发来的电报。上面写道：

道格拉斯·麦法登先生昨夜去世深切哀悼请回复指导葬礼事宜

道尔

埃尔，巴勒莫尔旅馆

恐怕我必须努力回忆起战前发生的事情，才能想起道格拉斯·麦法登先生是谁。我不得不翻查档案和遗嘱，让它们帮助我回忆起十三年前发生的点点滴滴。我觉得很奇怪，在埃尔居然没有一个人能够帮助麦法登先生料理后事。我马上打了一个长途电话到埃尔，很快我便和道尔太太通上了话。线路很差，但我勉强听懂了她说麦法登先生的亲戚她一个都不认识。很明显，已经很久没有人去看望他了。看来我必须亲自去一趟埃尔，或者派一个人去。接下来两天我手头没有紧急事务，而这件事情又有点棘手，于是我去找列斯特·罗宾逊商量此事，他是从战场上回来的陆军准将，我现在的合伙人。很快，我就清理好办公桌，吃过晚饭便坐卧铺车到格拉斯哥。第二天早晨，我已经坐上了开往埃尔的慢车。

我到达巴勒莫尔旅馆时，看见房东夫妇穿着丧服，一脸悲伤。他们一直很喜欢这位古怪的房客，也许正是亏得他们的细心照料，麦法登先生才能这么长寿。死因并无可疑，我从医生那里了解到他身上的种种毛病。弥留之际医生就在他身边，他们的住所只隔了两扇门。死亡证明也已签妥。我简单确认了遗体并办理了各种与死亡有关的手续。一切都进行得很顺利——除了没有任何亲戚露面。

“我想他一个亲戚也没有了，”道尔先生说，“有一次他妹妹还给他写信来着，还来看了他一回。好像是在1938年吧。她住在南安普敦。但这两年他好像再也没有收过信了，除了几张账单之外。”

他妻子说：“他妹妹肯定已经不在了。你忘了他告诉过我们，说她妹妹在战争结束之前不久就去世了吗？”

“哦，我不记得了，”他说，“那阵子发生了太多事情。也许她确实去世了。”

不管麦法登先生还有没有亲戚，葬礼都要尽快举行。下午，安排好葬礼事宜后，我仔细地把麦法登先生桌子里的文件看了一遍。账簿上和支票簿里几个写在票根背后的数字引起了我的注意。很明显，明天早上我要做的第一件事情，就是和银行经理见面。我发现了他妹妹1941年写的一封信，是关于房屋租赁的。当然，这封信并未透露她死于何事——如果她确实已离世，但它提供了两个小孩的关键信息。他们那时候都在马来亚。儿子唐纳德那时应该已经二十三岁了，在瓜拉雪兰莪(3)附近一个橡胶农场工作。他的妹妹琴1939年冬天去投奔他，那时任职于该农场在吉隆坡的办事处。

五点左右，我站在旅馆狭窄的电话间里，给在伦敦的合伙人打了一个长途电话。“听我说，列斯特，”我说，“我告诉过你死者亲戚的问题有点棘手。很遗憾，我现在一筹莫展。我已经临时将葬礼安排好了，后天两点在圣伊诺克公墓举行。我目前所知道的唯一一个亲戚，就是在——或者曾经在南安普敦生活的妹妹亚瑟·佩吉特太太。1941年的时候，这位太太住在巴西特的圣罗南路十七号，就在南安普敦附近。那个地区还有佩吉特家的其他亲戚，比如说亚瑟·佩吉特的父母。亚瑟·佩吉特太太——她的教名是琴——是的，她就是死者的妹妹。她有两个孩子，唐纳德和琴·佩吉特，但他们1941年的时候都在马来亚。天晓得他们遇到了什么事情。我现在不会浪费太多时间在他们身上，但是能不能请你告诉哈里斯，让他尽量找到在南安普敦生活的佩吉特家人，告诉他们葬礼的事？他最好对着电话号簿逐个打给南安普敦姓佩吉特的人。应该没几个。”

第二天早上，我刚从银行回来，列斯特就给我打电话了。“诺尔，很抱歉，关于你想找的人，我没有找到任何确切消息，”他说，“但我发现了一件事：佩吉特太太已经于1942年去世，所以不用再花力气找她了。她在防空洞中死于肺炎——哈里斯从医院查到的。其他姓佩吉特的人在电话号簿上有七个，我都打过电话了，可是他们跟你所提到的家庭一点关系都没有。但其中一个，尤丝缇丝·佩吉特太太，觉得你要找的应该是爱德华·佩吉特一家。他们在第一次南安普敦大轰炸后就举家搬到北威尔士去了。”

“大概在北威尔士的什么地方？”我问。

“毫无线索，”他说，“我想现在你能做的也就只有继续办葬礼了。”

“你说得对，”我回答，“但还是请你让哈里斯继续调查吧，因为除了要办葬礼，我们还必须找到继承人。我刚刚去了银行，发现那可是一笔很可观的遗产呢。要知道我们可是托管人啊。”

我利用那天余下的时间打包麦法登先生的个人物品和书信文件，以便带回事务所。那时候家具供应紧缺，我找了一个地方存放那两个房间的家具，因为继承人可能会用得上。我把衣物交给道尔太太，请她拿去施舍给埃尔的贫困居民。最后只剩下两只虎皮鹦鹉，我把它们留给了道尔太太，她似乎已经离不开它们了。第二天早上，我又跟银行经理见了一面，并打电话预订好卧铺票——我将乘坐夜班邮车回伦敦。下午，我们安葬了道格拉斯·麦法登先生。

那是一月的下午，公墓里一片愁云惨雾，寒气刺骨。送葬的只有道尔一家——父亲、母亲和女儿，和我。记得我当时在想，这个葬礼真是奇怪，我们对眼前即将被自己掩埋的人，竟几近一无所知。经过与道尔一家的短暂相处，我已经对他们产生了深深的尊敬之情。之前我告诉他们，麦法登先生给他们留了一笔小小的遗赠，把他们惊呆了，第一反应就是不愿接受。他们说，这些年麦法登先生吃住在这里，从不曾亏待他们，他们为他所做的其他一切，纯粹出于真诚友爱。在那个灰冷的一月下午，有朋友送他最后一程，墓边的风景便少了几分凄寂。

葬礼就这样结束了。我和道尔一家开车返回旅馆，和他们在厨房旁边的起居室喝茶。喝完茶后，我就起程去格拉斯哥，并于当晚坐火车回伦敦，带着两个手提箱的文件和个人物品。如果一时无法找到继承人，闲来无事之时还要细细查看，寻找线索。它们也是遗产的一部分，将来要交给继承人的。

实际上，寻找继承人的过程并没有大费周章。杨·哈里斯不到一周就找到了继承人的消息，不久我们就收到阿加莎·佩吉特小姐的一封信，她是科尔温贝(4)女子学校的校长，在马来亚车祸中丧生的亚瑟·佩吉特的姐姐。

她证实了他的妻子于1942年在南安普敦去世，同时告诉了我们一个新消息：唐纳德也已经过世了。他在马来亚战争中成为了俘虏，在被俘期间死去。然而，她的侄女琴却仍然在世，现在就住在伦敦地区。这位校长不知道琴的确切地址，因为她住在租来的房间里，搬过一两次家，住所不固定，所以写给她的信通常都寄到公司去。琴现在在帕克和利维公司里做事，地址是：伦敦西北海德区佩里维尔。

这封信夹在早班邮件里送来。我从一堆信件中翻出它，重新读了一遍，又让秘书把麦法登先生的档案拿给我，再看了一遍遗嘱、其他文件和关于遗产的笔记。最后我翻开电话号簿，找到帕克和利维公司，看看这个公司经营什么业务。

不久，我从桌子旁边站起来，在窗前站了一会儿。窗外是伦敦一月份灰蒙蒙的寒冷街道。我喜欢三思而后行，从不鲁莽行事。然后，我回身出去，走进罗宾逊的办公室。他正在口述文件，所以我先站到壁炉前暖和一下身子。他完事后，做记录的女孩离开了办公室。

“我找到麦法登的继承人了，”我开口说，“我一会儿会告诉哈里斯。”

“太好了，”他说，“你找到那个儿子了？”

“不，”我说，“我找到女儿了。儿子已经去世了。”

他笑道：“真倒霉。这就是说，在她三十五岁之前，我们要一直当这笔遗产的托管人了，是不是？”

我点点头。

“她现在多大了？”

我算了一下，说：“二十六七岁吧。”

“这个年纪，足够给我们添麻烦的了。”

“可不是。”

“她现在在哪里？在干什么？”

“她现在是一个文员或者打字员，在佩里维尔一个手提包厂工作，”我说，“我打算给她写一封信。”

他微笑道：“你可真是她的天降贵人啊。”

“一点不假。”我答道。

我回到办公室坐下来，考虑如何写那封信。第一次给这位年轻的女士写信，似乎应该显得正式一些。最后我写道：

亲爱的太太：

我们非常悲痛地通知您，令舅道格拉斯·麦法登先生于1月21日在埃尔去世。作为其遗嘱执行人，我们一直在寻找其遗产继承人，此间遇到了一些困难。如果您是曾住在南安普敦和马来亚的琴（·妮·麦法登）和亚瑟·佩吉特的女儿，将很有可能对遗产享有继承权。

请您在方便之时与我们电话预约见面，进一步商讨相关事宜。为了前期阶段工作的顺利进行，请您届时提供身份证明，例如出生证明，身份证，或者其他有效之证件。

顺颂　近佳！

欧文、达尔豪西和彼得斯律师事务所

N.H.斯特拉坎

第二天早上她就给我打电话了。她的声音很悦耳，听起来像一位训练有素的秘书。她说：“斯特拉坎先生，我是琴·佩吉特。我收到您29日给我写的信了。请问您周六上午是否上班？我平时走不开，所以周六对我而言再合适不过了。”

我回答道：“噢，是的，我们周六上午上班。你方便几点过来？”

“十点半可以吗？”

我在记事本上写下来。“没问题。你有出生证明吗？”

“有的。我还有母亲的结婚证明，那有用吗？”

我说：“有的，请一并带来。好了，佩吉特小姐，那我们周六见。报我的名字就能找到我，诺尔·斯特拉坎先生。我是高级合伙人。”

周六早上十点半，她准时出现在我的办公室。她身材中等，头发乌黑，看不出来是否已经结了婚。她恬静漂亮，有一种淡定的风度。这种风度很难确切形容，是苏格兰后裔女性身上常见的那种从容优雅。她穿着深蓝色的外套和裙子。我站起身，与她握手，请她坐在我桌子前的椅子上，再回身在我自己的椅子上坐下。我已经把文件都准备好了。

“我们开始吧，佩吉特小姐，”我说，“我通过你的姑姑找到了你——我想她是你的姑姑吧，在科尔温贝的那位？”

她点点头。“雅姬姑姑给我写信了，告诉我她收到了您的信。没错，她是我的姑姑。”

“我想，你就是曾经在南安普敦和马来亚生活过的亚瑟和琴·佩吉特的女儿？”

她点点头。“是的。我带了我和我母亲的出生证明，还有她的结婚证明。”她从包里掏出这几份文件，连同身份证一起，放在我的桌上。

我打开这些文件，仔细检查了一遍。毫无疑问，她就是我要找的人。我重新把身子靠到椅背上，摘掉眼镜。“请告诉我，佩吉特小姐，”我说，“你曾经见过你刚过世的舅舅道格拉斯·麦法登先生吗？”

她犹豫了一下。“我一直在想这件事情，”她坦率地说，“我不能发誓说我肯定见过他，但是有一次，我母亲带我去苏格兰拜访过一个人，那个人肯定就是他。那个时候我好像只有十岁吧，母亲带着我和我哥哥一起去的。我记得好像是一个老人家，住在一个闷热的房间里，用笼子养了很多鸟。我想那就是道格拉斯舅舅吧，不过我不是很确定。”

这与麦法登先生的说法相符。母子三人确实于1932年去拜访过他。这个女孩当时应该是十一岁。“能跟我说一下你的哥哥唐纳德吗，佩吉特小姐？”我问，“他是否还在世？”

她摇摇头。“他1943年去世了，在被俘期间。我们投降的时候(5)，他在新加坡被日本兵抓走，送到了铁路上。”

“铁路？”我有点疑惑不解。

她冷冷地看着我，目光中仿佛包含了一丝宽容——对战时留在英国的人所表现出来的无知。“日本兵迫使亚洲人和战俘建造的泰缅铁路。每安放一条枕木，就有一个人死去，而铁路大约有两百英里长。唐纳德就是其中一个。”

接下来我们都没有说话。“我很抱歉，”我终于打破沉默，“但恐怕我还是要问你一件事——你有没有他的死亡证明？”

她盯着我说：“我不可能会有吧。”

“噢……”我重新把身子靠到椅背上，拿起遗嘱。“这是道格拉斯·麦法登先生的遗嘱，”我说，“我给你准备了一份复印件，佩吉特小姐，但是我想最好先用普通的语言来告诉你里面写了什么。除了两份小小的遗赠之外，你舅舅把所有剩余财产都以托管方式归到你哥哥唐纳德名下。托管的条件是，托管财产的收益归你母亲所有，直到她去世。如果她在你兄长满二十一岁前去世，托管将在他成年时结束，财产就归他任意支配。而如果你的兄长在继承财产前去世，你将在你母亲去世后，继承剩余的财产。但这样的话，托管期将一直延续到1956年，你满三十五岁的时候。我想你会希望我们取得你兄长的合法死亡证明的。”

她犹豫了一下，然后说道：“斯特拉坎先生，恐怕我真是愚蠢透顶。我能够理解为什么您需要唐纳德的死亡证明。但如果您真的拿到了这份证明，是不是就意味着我可以继承道格拉斯舅舅留下来的一切？”

“基本上——是这样的，”我回答，“但在1956年之前，你只能获得这笔遗产的收益。之后，财产就是你的了，你想拿来做什么都可以。”

“他留下了多少钱？”

我从面前的文件里拿起一张纸条，从上到下把数字扫了一眼，最后再检查一遍。“扣除税款和遗赠后，”我小心地说，“剩余的财产大约价值五万三千英镑——以目前的价格计算。我必须提醒你，这是按照目前的价格计算的，佩吉特小姐。不能保证到1956年的时候你就一定会继承这个数目。股市的低迷甚至会影响到信托证券。”

她直直地盯着我，说：“五万三千英镑？”

我点点头。“大概是这个数目。”

“这样一笔资本每年可以产生多少收益，斯特拉坎先生？”

我扫了一眼我面前纸条上的数字。“投资于受托公债的话，目前每年大约能有一千五百五十英镑的总收入。扣除所得税后，每年大概还能剩下九百英镑，佩吉特小姐。”

“噢……”接下来是一阵长长的沉默。她坐在那里，目光落在前方的桌子上。忽然她抬起头来看着我，莞尔一笑。“我还没回过神来，”她说，“我是说，一直以来我都是自己挣钱养活自己，斯特拉坎先生。我从未想过我还能干点什么别的，除非嫁人——但那似乎只是换一种方式工作罢了。但是从今往后我再也不用工作了——除非我乐意。”

最后一句话真是一针见血。“一点不假，”我回答，“除非你乐意。”

“如果再也不用去办公室上班了，我不知道要做什么，”她说，“我几乎没有业余活动……”

“那就应该继续去办公室上班。”我指出。

她笑道：“我想我也没有其他事情可以做了。”

我重新把身子靠到椅背上。“我已经是个老头子了，佩吉特小姐。我这一辈子犯了很多错误，并从中学会了一个道理，那就是：欲速则不达。我想你的生活会因为这份财产而变得很不一样。如果你问我的话，我会请你千万不要马上辞掉手头这份工作。现在，我先不跟你在办公室里谈遗产的事情。首先，就算是财产的收益，你也还要等几个月才能拿到。我们还没拿到你哥哥的合法死亡证明，苏格兰的遗嘱执行人也还没批准我们变卖部分证券来偿付财产税和其他税款。告诉我，你在帕克和利维公司做什么工作？”

“我是速记员，”她说，“现在是帕克先生的秘书。”

“你现在住在哪里呢，佩吉特小姐？”

她说：“我租了一个不含厨房的开间，在坎贝恩路四十三号，对面就是伊令公地。地方很方便，但自然要经常在外面吃饭了。附近就有一家里昂斯餐厅。”

我想了想，说：“你在伊令有很多朋友吗？在那儿住了多久了？”

“我认识的人不多，”她回答说，“一两家人吧，都是同事。我回国后就住在那里，有两年多了。之前我在马来亚，斯特拉坎先生。有三年半的时间，我基本上是一个战俘。回国后，我就在这家公司找到了工作。”

我在记事本上记下了这个地址。“现在，佩吉特小姐，”我说，“请让我继续把接下来要做的事情告诉你。我周一早上会咨询陆军部，希望尽快获得你哥哥的死亡证明。请告诉我他的姓名、身份证号和分队编号。”我把她提供的信息一一记下来。“我一拿到证明，就会上交遗嘱，等待认证。遗嘱被批准执行后，托管就开始，直到1956年你能任意支配财产为止。”

她抬起头来看着我。“请向我解释一下托管是怎么回事，”她问，“恐怕我对法律事务不怎么在行。”

我点点头。“这很正常。我给你的遗嘱复印件都是以法律语言写成的。关于托管一事，其实是这样的，佩吉特小姐。当你舅舅立下这份遗嘱的时候，他对女性管理自己财产的能力抱有一种非常不合理的偏见。很抱歉说了这样的话，但是我想最好是能让你知道整件事情的来龙去脉。”

她笑道：“请不必替他道歉，斯特拉坎先生。请继续。”

“开始的时候，他觉得至少要等你满四十岁，才能让你自由支配遗产，”我说，“我提出了反对意见，所以现在遗嘱上写的是三十五岁，我无法让他缩短这个期限了。现在，托管的目标是这样：立遗嘱人指定托管人——在这里是指我和我的合伙人——尽其所能保护好这份财产，在托管结束时，把它完好无损地交到继承人——也就是你——的手里。”

“我知道了。道格拉斯舅舅害怕我会一下子把这五万三千英镑花个精光。”

我点点头。“他就是这样想的。他不了解你，当然，佩吉特小姐。所以他并不是针对你个人的。他只是有一个很笼统的概念，认为年轻女性控制巨款的能力不如男性。”

她平静地说：“他可能是对的。”思考片刻后，又说，“所以，在我三十五岁之前，您将会一直帮我保管这笔钱，把它的利息给我，每年九百英镑，对吗？”

“如果你希望我们帮助你处理所得税事宜的话，就是这个数目，”我说，“你能选择一种支付方式，比如季度或者月度支票。你将每半年收到一份账目明细表。”

她好奇地问道：“你们为我做这么多事情，怎么收费呢，斯特拉坎先生？”

我微笑道：“这是一个很精明的问题，佩吉特小姐。你会在遗嘱里找到一条相关的条款，好像是第八条吧。它赋予我们因提供专业的托管服务而收费的权利。当然了，如果你遇到任何法律上的麻烦，我们会很高兴成为你的代理人，并且尽一切努力帮助你。不过那样的话，我们会按照正常标准收费。”

她出乎意料地说：“托付给您再好不过了。”她瞥了我一眼，调皮地说，“我昨天就查询过您这家公司。”

“噢……希望结果让你满意？”

“非常满意，”她说，“把事情交到您手中，我绝对放心，斯特拉坎先生。”不过她事后才告诉我，泄密者把我们描述成“牢如英格兰银行(6)，黏如糖蜜(7)”。

我点点头。“希望如此。恐怕有时候你会觉得这个托管很烦人，佩吉特小姐，不过我会保证尽量避免发生这种情形。你会看到，立遗嘱人会在遗嘱里给予托管人一些权力，在对继承人确实有利的情况下，托管人是可以解冻一部分财产的。”

“您的意思是，如果我真的需要很多钱——做手术或者什么的——只要您同意，我就可以预支这笔钱？”

真是思维敏捷，这姑娘。“我想那是一个很好的例子。如果你生病时没有钱做手术，为了你的利益，我当然会解冻一部分遗产。”

她向我微微一笑，说：“现在我是不是还挺像受大法官监护的未成年人？”

这个比喻不知怎的触动了我。我说：“如果你愿意把我当成监护人，我将感到不胜荣幸，佩吉特小姐。这份遗嘱将无可避免地打乱你的生活，我愿意尽我所能帮助你尽快适应新情况。”我递给她遗嘱的复印件。“这就是遗嘱。我建议你带走它，找个时间安静地认真读读。我会暂时保留这些证件。等你过几天想清楚到底发生了什么事之后，肯定会生出很多问题，并且想要知道答案。到时你是否愿意再过来与我见一面？”

她说：“我当然愿意。我一定会有无数的问题，但是我现在一个都想不出来。这一切太突然了。”

我看看预约日志，道：“那——我们下周二或者周三再见一面如何？”我一边看着我的预约安排一边说，“当然了，你白天要上班。你几点下班，佩吉特小姐？”

她说：“五点。”

“周三晚上六点你方便吗？希望到时候有关你哥哥的事情会有些进展。”

她说：“嗯，可以的，斯特拉坎先生。但是对您来讲不会太晚了吗？不耽误您回家吗？”

我心不在焉地说：“我只去俱乐部。不耽误，周三六点对我来讲正合适。”我记下新的预约事项，犹豫了一下。“如果事后没有安排，你是否愿意跟我一起去俱乐部，在淑女馆餐厅吃晚饭呢？”我说，“恐怕那个地方算不上很时髦漂亮，但是菜不错。”

她微微一笑，热情地说：“太好了，斯特拉坎先生。谢谢您的邀请。”

我站起来。“很好，那么，佩吉特小姐，周三晚上六点。同时，请记住：三思而后行，欲速则不达。”

她走了。我收拾好桌子，打车去俱乐部吃午饭。饭后，我喝了杯咖啡，在壁炉前的椅子里睡了十分钟。醒来时，我想活动活动，于是戴好帽子，穿上大衣出去遛弯。我漫无目的地沿圣詹姆斯大街往北走，再顺着皮卡迪利大街走到公园。一边走，我一边想那位突发横财的女士正在干什么。她是正在向好友炫耀这份好运气呢，还是正坐在一个温暖而安静的地方，酝酿着一个计划，好让我给她预支一笔财产？又或者已经在挥金如土、肆意狂欢了？她也可能正在和一位年轻有为的男士约会——她现在已经有足够的资本，可以从众多追求者中从容选择一位如意郎君，我讽刺地想着。然后，我突然意识到，她可能已经有很多男朋友了——她正值妙龄，待字闺中。实际上，她是那么漂亮迷人、温柔可亲，要是还没结婚才奇怪呢。

那晚我在俱乐部跟一位内政部的朋友聊天，向他了解如何确认一位战俘的死亡事实。周一我打了好几个电话到陆军部和内政部咨询这个案子。不出所料，有一个例外程序可以证明战俘的死亡事实——如果战俘营里的俘虏去世时有医生在旁照料，这位医生就有权开具有效的死亡证明。在这个案子中，有一位名叫费里斯的全科医师，曾经在泰缅铁路沿线塔库南地区的第二〇六号营地当过随军医生，目下在贝肯汉姆开诊所。陆军部的官员说这位医生有权开具一份正规的死亡证明。

第二天早上，我给这位医生打电话，但不巧他出诊了。我试着让他的妻子明白我需要什么，但是那对她而言似乎太过复杂了。她建议我等夜间应诊时间结束，晚上六点半再去找他。我犹豫要不要去，因为贝肯汉姆离我的公寓非常远。但我想尽快替这位姑娘拿到这份文件，所以当天晚上就去拜访这位医生了。

他不到三十五岁，性格开朗，面色红润。他颇具幽默感，但是喜欢时不时拿死亡来开玩笑。这位乡村医生看上去健康结实，就像从未离开过英格兰一样。见到他时，他刚送走最后一位病人，正好有空与我说话。

“佩吉特中尉，”他边想边说，“噢，是的，我知道他。唐纳德·佩吉特——他是叫唐纳德吗？”我说是，他接着说：“噢，当然了，我记得很清楚。没问题，我可以给他开一份死亡证明。我很乐意为他效劳，虽然我觉得他要这份证明也没有用。”

“是给他妹妹的，”我说，“关乎她的继承权。正式手续办理得越快，对她越有利。”

他伸手去取表格。“我真想知道她是不是和她哥哥一样胆色过人。”

“他是个了不起的小伙子吗？”

他点点头。“是的。他看起来有点弱不禁风，忧郁苍白，但他是个棒小伙。我想他原来是个农场主吧——总之，他后来参加了马来亚的志愿军。他的马来语说得很好，暹罗语也说得不错。当然了，他会这两种语言，真是帮了我们大忙。我们那时常常要跟村民们做黑市买卖，跟战俘营外面的暹罗人。而且他是那种特别讨人喜欢的军官。他的去世真是让我们损失惨重。”

“他的死因是什么？”我问道。

他停下笔。“这个——你可以从十几个原因里挑一个。我当时不可能有时间做尸检。实话告诉你，我并不能确定死因，反正他就是去世了。但是他已经熬过了足以杀死十几个普通人的病痛，所以我不知道在死亡证明上写什么是否那么要紧。死因并不会影响它的法律效力，是不是？”

“啊，不会的，”我说，“有一个死亡证明就足够了。”

他沉浸在回忆中，仍然没有动笔。“我们当时正在治疗他左腿上一块面积巨大的热带溃疡，那产生的毒素毫无疑问正在向全身扩散。如果溃疡继续恶化下去，就不得不截肢了。之所以被耽误到那么严重，就因为他是那种只要还能走得动，就不会告诉别人他生了病的小伙子。唉，当他因为溃疡住院的时候，又得了脑型疟疾。当时我们没有办法治疗那种该死的病，直到后来我们终于能腾出手来，自制奎宁溶液，给病人进行静脉注射。那是很冒险的一招，我们都很害怕，但别无选择。我们就这样帮助很多人渡过了难关，佩吉特就是其中之一。他战胜了疟疾。紧接着就爆发了霍乱。霍乱横扫了医院，势不可当。我们没有办法隔离病人，或者采取任何类似的措施。我再也不想看到那样的场面了。我们手头什么都没有，什么都没有！甚至连碱盐泻药都没有，更别提药物和设备了。我们只好用旧煤油罐来做便盆。佩吉特也得了霍乱。你能相信吗？他连霍乱也挺过来了。我们给他注射了一些预防药物，从日本人那里拿来的，可能起了点作用。至少，我们给他注射了那种药——不过我记不清了。当他从霍乱中康复过来之后，已经非常虚弱了。当然了，原来的溃疡并没有什么好转。大概一周后的一个晚上，他死去了。我想是心脏的原因吧。我会告诉你我将会怎么做。我会把死因写成——霍乱。好了，请收好。抱歉让你为它走了那么远的路。”

我收下证明，好奇地问：“你有没有也得那些病？”

他笑道：“我是幸运儿。我只得了普通的痢疾和疟疾，普通的那种疟疾，不是脑型疟疾。我的问题是超负荷的工作，不过其他人也一样。当时真是一团糟，没完没了的。我们把几百个病人放在地板上，或者放在棕榈树小屋的竹子吊床上——那会儿一直在下雨。没有床，没有床单，也没有设备，药物少得可怜。我们连喘口气的机会都没有，一直工作到倒头昏睡过去，醒来后又要马上继续工作，不知什么时候是个头。连松懈半个小时去抽根烟的机会都没有，去散个步也不可能，除非你把几个急需你医治的可怜蛋甩下不管。”

他稍稍停顿了一下。我默默地坐着。相形之下，我所遇到的所谓战争是多么微不足道。“就那样熬了差不多有两年，”他说，“有时候会很抑郁，因为甚至连去听个讲座的时间都没有。”

“你们还有讲座？”我问。

“啊，有的，我们营里有很多小伙子，常常给我们做各种讲座。考克斯橙皮苹果(8)的栽种方法啦，TT摩托车公路赛啦，好莱坞的生活之类的。这些讲座多少能开解一下大家。但我们这些医生经常没有时间去听。我的意思是，如果有病人发生抽搐，我们却在营地的另一头听别人讲考克斯橙皮苹果，似乎有点说不过去。”

我说：“那肯定是很可怕的一段经历。”

他顿了顿，回忆起当时的生活。“那里的景色太美了，”他说，“三塔边界(9)肯定是世界上最可爱的地方。河流顺着广阔的峡谷流下来，还有茂密的热带森林和大山……有时候，我们坐在河边看日落，感叹这将是一个多么神奇的度假胜地。不管一个战俘营有多可怕，如果周围有美景，总会有点不一样的。”

当琴·佩吉特周三晚上来看我的时候，我已经准备好向她报告我取得的进展。首先我大概介绍了几件在我们清理财产时发生的事情，给她看了看埃尔的家具清单。她对那些家具没有什么兴趣。“我想我应该把它们都卖掉，是不是？”她说，“我们可以拿它们去拍卖吗？”

“也许还是先等等再说吧，”我建议道，“也许将来你要买新房子或者新公寓呢？”

她蹙起鼻头，说：“即使是那样，我也不会用道格拉斯舅舅的家具来布置我的新家。”

然而，她同意先不去处理它们，等确定好将来的计划再说。然后我们就去谈别的事情。“我拿到你哥哥的死亡证明了。”我说。但是，当我正准备进一步告诉她我是如何得到它的时候，她打断了我。

“他因什么而死，斯特拉坎先生？”她问。

我迟疑了一会儿。从费里斯医生那里听来的故事是如此令人不安，我不想把它讲给一个这么年轻的女士听。“死因是霍乱。”我最后说。

她点点头。好像她等的就是这个答案。“可怜的人，”她轻声说，“不是一种很舒服的死法。”

我感到一定要说点什么来减轻她的忧伤。“我跟照顾过他的医生聊了很久，”我告诉她，“他去世的时候很平静，在睡梦中。”

她盯着我看。“哦，如果是那样的话，就不是霍乱，”她说，“霍乱引起的死亡不是那样的。”

我本来是想帮她免除不必要的痛苦，但她一语戳穿了我的谎言，使我阵脚大乱。“他先是得了霍乱，但是好了。实际的死因可能是心脏衰竭吧，由霍乱引起的。”

她仔细想了一会儿，道：“他还有没有得其他病？”

好吧，在那种情况下，我只好老老实实将我所知道的和盘托出。我感到非常惊讶，因为她在听到这些令人不愉快的细节时，能保持一种就事论事的淡定态度，也因为她知道如何医治热带溃疡之类的疾病，直到我想起来，这位姑娘自己也曾经在马来亚当过日本人的俘虏。“真是该死，运气糟透了，溃疡扩散得快一些就好了，”她冷冷地说，“如果截了肢，他们就会让他从铁路上撤下来，那就不会得脑型疟疾或者霍乱了。”

“他肯定有一副很强健的体格，才能熬了那么久。”

“他没有，”她很肯定地说，“唐纳德总是咳嗽啊、感冒啊什么的。他有的是极强的幽默感。就因为这一点，我总以为他能够挺过来。不管遇到什么事情，他都能拿来开玩笑。”

我年轻的时候，姑娘们都不懂霍乱或者大面积溃疡，所以我不知道应该怎样回答她。我把话题转回到法律事务上——我这方面的知识更巩固——告诉她遗嘱认证的进展情况。不久，我带她下楼，一起坐出租车去俱乐部吃晚饭。

那是我们第一次晚上出去吃饭，我有充足的理由要好好款待一下她。很明显，接下来几年我将会经常和她打交道，加深对她的了解很有必要。实际上，当时我对她受教育的情况和人生背景一无所知，比如说，她对于热带疾病的丰富知识就让我感到很困惑。我想请她吃一顿不错的晚饭，请她喝一点酒，让她多说一些话。如果我了解她的兴趣爱好和思维方式，托管工作会变得容易很多。所以我带她到俱乐部的淑女馆餐厅，一个相当不错的地方。在那里我们可以不受音乐打扰，饭后在安静的环境中慢慢聊。普通餐厅混乱嘈杂，会使我无精打采，疲惫不堪。

我告诉她洗手间的位置。在她梳洗的时候，我给她点了一杯雪利酒。看见她向我走来，我从客厅的桌子旁边站起身，递给她一根香烟，并替她点着。“周末干什么了？”她坐下来的时候我问她，“出去庆祝了吗？”

她摇摇头。“我没做什么特别的事情。我之前约了办公室的一个女孩儿周六一起吃午饭，去可胜街看贝蒂·戴维斯的新电影。一切按计划进行。”

“有没有告诉她你的当头红运？”

她摇摇头。“谁我都没告诉。”她顿了顿，抿了一口雪利酒。她抽烟和喝酒的动作都相当娴熟。“听起来太不可思议了，”她笑着说，“我都不知道该不该相信那是真的。”

我向她微微一笑。“任何事情在发生前都不会成为现实，”我说，“你会相信这是真的，当我给你寄去第一张支票的时候。不过，在那之前，如果太把它当回事，就大错特错了。”

“我没有，”她笑道，“不过我能确定一件事。我相信你不会把时间浪费在一件毫无意义的事情上。”

“一点不假。”我顿了顿，“再过几个月，你就能拿到托管财产的收益了，每个月的税后收入是七十五英镑。你有没有想过到时要做什么？应该不会还想继续做手头这份工作了吧？”

“不了……”她盯着袅袅升起的香烟烟雾，“其实我不想停止工作。我一点也不介意在帕克和利维公司继续工作下去，就像什么都没发生过一样，如果那是一份很有意义的工作的话，”她说，“不过——唉，它不是。我们生产女装鞋子和手提包，斯特拉坎先生，还有专门用于高端贸易的精装小提箱——就是那种在邦德街的商店里卖三十基尼(10)一个的箱子，只有那些钱多得没处花的蠢女人才会买。我们还定做用珍稀皮革制成的小化妆包，反正净是那一类玩意儿。如果是为了谋生，在那种地方也还干得下去，了解一下那方面的贸易也很有意思。”

“当你还处在学习阶段的时候，大部分的工作都很有趣。”我说。

她转向我。“是这样的。我在那里过得挺快乐的。但是我现在有钱了，情况就不一样了。人应该做更有意义的事情，但我现在还没想到该做什么。”她又喝了一点雪利酒，“您瞧，我没有一技之长，只会速记、打字和一点簿记。我从没正儿八经上过学——我是指职业技术学校，拿一个学位什么的那种。”

我想了想。“我可以问你一个比较私人的问题吗，佩吉特小姐？”

“当然了。”

“你觉得你短期内会结婚吗？”

她微微一笑。“不，斯特拉坎先生。我觉得我甚至都不会结婚。当然了，话不能说得太绝对，但是——我觉得不会。”

我没有对此作出评论，只是点点头。“好吧，那你有没有想过要攻读一个大学学位？”

她睁大双眼。“不会的——我从没想过。我做不来，斯特拉坎先生。我不够聪明，考不上大学。”她顿了顿，“我一直成绩中等，而且连中学六年级(11)都没上过。”

“这只是我的一个想法而已，”我说，“我想知道它会不会引起你的兴趣。”

她摇摇头。“我现在没法再回去上学了。我太老了。”

我向她微微一笑。“也不至于老成那样了。”我说。

不知怎的，这个小小的奉承好像并没能令她愉快。“每次我拿自己和办公室里的姑娘们作比较，”她轻声说，不带任何开玩笑的口吻，“我就知道我已经差不多七十岁了。”

我似乎开始了解她了。不过为了使气氛变得轻松一些，我提议先吃晚饭。点好菜后，我说：“请告诉我你在战争中的遭遇。你当时在马来亚，是吗？”

她点点头。“我当时有一份办公室的工作，在霹雳一家种植园公司上班。我父亲原来就在那里工作，唐纳德也是那里的员工。”

“你遇到什么事情了？”我问道，“成为了战俘？”

“算是吧。”她说。

“在战俘营里？”

“没有，”她回答，“他们让我们过得挺自由的。”然后她果断地转移了话题，说道，“您呢，斯特拉坎先生？一直在伦敦吗？”

如果她不愿意提及战争经历的话，我不能够强迫她。于是我告诉她我的经历——原原本本地。不久，我发现我在跟她谈我的两个儿子，在中国军事驻地的哈利和在巴士拉的马丁，他们的战争记录、家庭和孩子。“我已经当了三次爷爷了，”我幽幽地说，“相信不久就会再当一次。”

她笑道：“那种感觉怎么样？”

“还跟以前一样，”我告诉她，“不管年纪多大，感觉都是一样的。只是，能做的事情越来越少了。”

不久我又把话题引回她身上。我向她描述了与九百英镑的年收入相符合的生活状态。我举了个例子，她可以在德文郡买一套乡村别墅和一辆小车，雇一个女仆，用剩下的钱作海外旅行。“在找到一个新的人生目标之前，我不知道应该干什么，”她说，“我一直在为某个目标努力着，一辈子都这样。”

我知道有几个慈善组织正等待着上帝的恩赐——从天而降一个不收工资的速记员，就问她要不要考虑一下，但她似乎觉得这种幻想是需要批评的。“如果一件事物有价值，自然就是有价钱的，”她说，显示出强烈的商业本能，“这个世界不需要一个白干活的秘书。”

“慈善组织喜欢把日常开支维持在低水平。”我说。

“如果一个组织连秘书都请不起的话，我不认为它能为社会做什么贡献，”她说，“我希望能够为一个真正有价值的目标而奋斗。”

我向她介绍一份医院的社工工作，她非常感兴趣。“这比较像了，斯特拉坎先生，”她说，“是那种值得为之付出时间精力的工作。但我不想和病人打交道。不知道您是否觉得自己对病人有一份天生的责任，我是不觉得的。不过这份工作值得考虑。”

“嗯，慢慢来吧，”我说，“不必着急去做任何事情。”

她向我笑道：“我相信您的座右铭就是——三思而后行。”

我微笑道：“比它糟糕的座右铭有的是。”

喝完饭后咖啡，我带她去艺术馆试探她的艺术造诣。她对音乐一窍不通，除了喜欢一边听收音机一边做女红；也不懂文学，除了爱看有着欢喜结局的小说；她喜欢看名画的复制品，她叫得出名字的那些，但从未去过皇家艺术学院；她还完全是个雕刻盲。作为一个生活在伦敦，年收入九百英镑的女士，竟然毫无艺术和社交修养，这在我看来多少有点遗憾。

“你是否愿意找个晚上去看场歌剧？”我问。

她微笑道：“我能看得懂吗？”

“噢，你会看得懂的。我去查一下最近有什么可以看的，尽量挑简单易懂的英文剧。”

她说：“您愿意邀请我真是太好了，但是我觉得，您还不如去打桥牌，那样您会快乐得多。”

“完全不是这样，”我说，“我很多年没去看过歌剧什么的了。”

她微微一笑。“好吧。我当然很乐意去，”她说，“我长这么大，还没去看过歌剧呢。我甚至都不知道歌剧是怎么演的。”

我们坐在艺术馆里闲谈这些事情，不觉一个多小时过去了，转眼已经九点半，她起身要走。回到她在郊区的房间要走三刻钟，先要去圣詹姆斯公园车站坐车。我送她去车站，因为——怎么能让这么年轻漂亮的姑娘独自一人穿过深夜的公园呢？在车站，我们站在阴暗潮湿的人行道上，车站顶棚灯火通明。她向我伸出手。

“真是太感谢您了，斯特拉坎先生。谢谢您的晚饭，还有您正在为我做的一切。”她说。

“我很荣幸，佩吉特小姐。”我回答，并不是客套话。

她迟疑了一下，然后微笑着说：“斯特拉坎先生，我们以后还要经常打交道。我的名字是琴。您要一直叫我佩吉特小姐的话，我会受不了的。”

“你无法教会老狗新把戏。”我尴尬地说。

她笑道：“您刚才还说，不管年纪多大，感觉都是一样的。请您尝试一下。”

“谨遵教诲。”我说，“你确定现在一个人回去就可以了吗？”

“当然了。晚安，斯特拉坎先生。”

“晚安，”我说，把我的帽子举起来，逃避离别的场面，“我会约你去看话剧。”

在接下来等待遗嘱公证审核的几周里，我带她去了许多地方。我们一起去阿尔伯特音乐厅看了几场周日下午上演的歌剧，还去美术馆看了几次画展。作为回报，她带我去看了几场电影。我不敢说她因此就养成了高雅的艺术欣赏水平。她喜欢绘画多于音乐会。如果一定要去欣赏音乐的话，她更愿意选择歌剧，而且越简单轻松越好。当耳朵被音乐灌满的时候，她不喜欢让眼睛也闲着。我们去了两次皇家植物园，因为春天的脚步越发近了。在此期间，她到我在白金汉门的公寓做过几次客。我告诉她厨房的位置，有几次一同外出归来后，她在那里沏茶。我从未在那所公寓里招待过任何姑娘，除了我的儿媳妇——她来伦敦办事的时候，会在空房间里住一两晚。

她的事情终于在三月份都办妥了。我给她寄去了第一张支票。她并没有马上辞去工作，而是像往常一样继续去上班。她很聪明，打算在靠这笔额外收入生活之前，先用它攒起一笔小小的资本。况且那会儿她也还没有找到新的人生目标。

四月的一个星期天，我为她安排了一次短途旅游。她将在中午的时候过来公寓吃饭，然后和我一起去南面的汉普顿宫。她从未去过汉普顿宫，但我想她一定会喜欢那里的古雅宫殿和明丽春花，我为此兴奋了好几天，对这次旅行充满期待。然后，当然——那天下雨了。

她午饭前来到了公寓，拿着一把湿淋淋的雨伞，雨水顺着深蓝色的雨衣流淌下来。我帮她脱去外套，挂在厨房里。她进空房间收拾了一下，再到起居室里来，和我一起站在窗前，看着雨打在对面的皇家马厩上，考虑当天下午可以做什么别的事情。

饭后，我们在壁炉前坐下来喝咖啡，还没做好决定下午要做什么。我提议了一两件事情，但她好像有点心不在焉。喝完咖啡后，她终于说道：

“我已经决定第一步要做什么了，斯特拉坎先生。”

“噢，”我问，“是什么？”

她犹豫了一下。“我知道您会觉得这很奇怪。您可能会觉得我很愚蠢，把钱花在这上面。但是——嗯，这就是我想做的事情。我想最好在出门之前告诉您。”

坐在壁炉前既温暖又舒适。外面天色阴沉，雨倾盆而下，拍打着湿答答的人行道。

“别这样说，琴，”我回答，“我不会觉得你愚蠢的。你想做什么呢？”

她说：“我想回马来亚，斯特拉坎先生，去挖一口井。”

————————————————————

(1) 伊拉克最大的港口城市。

(2) 伦敦街道名，在白金汉宫附近。

(3) 马来亚海滨市镇。

(4) 也称科尔温湾，英国海滨小镇。

(5) 根据历史记载，日军1942年1月攻陷吉隆坡，新加坡的英军于1942年2月向日军投降，日军从此控制马来亚全境，直至1945年9月投降。

(6) 英国的中央银行。

(7) 制糖工业的副产品，非常黏稠。

(8) 英国培育的一种品质优良的苹果，皮色橙黄至橙红。

(9) 在泰缅边界上。

(10) 英国旧时金币，1基尼等于21先令。

(11) 相当于我国高三年级。

第二章

如果我没有记错的话，在她说完那句话之后，我们陷入了长久的沉默。我惊呆了。当不知道可以说什么的时候，我习惯性地躲进沉默中去。我想她从我的沉默中读出了责备之意，所以她向我倾过身子，说：“我知道这件事情听起来确实有点滑稽。可不可以先让我告诉您，我为什么要这么做？”

我说：“当然了。是否跟你的战时经历有关？”

她点点头。“我从未跟您提起过。不是不想提，是想不起来。那么久远，就像是多年前发生在另一个人身上的事情一样——仿佛我并没有亲身经历过，只是书上的故事。”

“这样难道不是更好吗？”

她摇摇头。“现在不是了，因为这笔钱。”她顿了顿，“您对我太好了，”她说，“我真的很想试着让您理解我的决定。”

她说，她的人生可以分成三个部分。前两部分与余者有天壤之别，现在已经很难在她身上找到它们的影子。最开始的时候，她是一名学生，和母亲一同住在南安普敦近郊一所有三间卧室的小房子里。此前他们曾全家住在马来亚，但后来，当她长到十一岁，哥哥唐纳德十四岁时，母亲带着兄妹俩回到了英格兰。马来亚的生活对她而言，只是一些残存的模糊片段。显然，亚瑟·佩吉特去世的时候，妻小都在英格兰，他是孤身一人在马来亚。

他们的生活和普通郊区英国小孩并无二致。他们上学、放假，生活简单，节奏柔和。每年八月迎来一个激动人心的三周假期，去怀特岛(1)

上的海景村或者弗雷什沃特。但有一件事情使他们跟其他家庭不太一样，就是他们都会说马来语。当然，是保姆教会孩子们说马来语的，母亲则鼓励他们在英国也一直说下去。一开始，他们只是说着好玩，当作家庭秘密语言，但后来马来语成了一件严肃的事情。亚瑟·佩吉特在怡保附近驾车一头撞到树上时，正在因公出差途中。他的遗孀根据公司计划获得了一份年金。他能力出众，是一个宝贵的人才。马来亚霹雳种植有限公司的董事们痛失英才，一面又求贤心切，便写信给这位遗孀说，等唐纳德一满十九岁就为他安排一个职位。这是一份美差，琴一家上下都很欢喜。这就意味着唐纳德长大后要去马来亚投身橡胶种植事业。马来语是帮助他顺利打开局面的重要技能，因为在去东方寻找人生第一份工作的十九岁男孩中，会说当地语言的实在是凤毛麟角。那位精明的苏格兰女士，他们的母亲，时刻谨记不能让孩子们忘了马来语。

她非常喜欢南安普敦，在那里度过了一个愉快的童年，宁静的生活在连接着家、学校、帝王影院和溜冰场的轨道上悠然往复。她记得最清楚的是溜冰场，而每当想起溜冰场，就总是仿佛能听见瓦尔特费尔的溜冰圆舞曲。“那真是一个美妙的地方，”她望着火炉，似乎那里跳动着一团温暖朦胧的回忆，“我想，它算不上气派，真的——我想它是一栋木楼，在一战时建造的，后来改作了溜冰场。记忆中，我们每周在那里大约溜两次冰，每次都非常愉快。那里的音乐，干净迅速的动作，所有的男孩和女孩。荧光灯，人群，还有滑冰道。我溜得还不赖。妈妈给我买了一套衣服——黑色的紧身衣和紧身马甲，还有一条小短裙。在冰上跳舞感觉真的很棒……”

她转向我。“您知道吗，在马来亚，在我们被疟疾和痢疾折磨得死去活来，在雨里发着烧打着冷战，没有衣服，没有食物，无处可去，因为没人想要我们的时候，我就会想起南安普敦的溜冰场。那是过去生活的象征，提醒我生活曾经如此美好——告诉我不要放弃。”她顿了顿，“一回到英国，我马上就回到了南安普敦，迫不及待地——我要去那里处理点事情，但是实际上是因为在那些年里，我曾对自己发誓，总有一天，我一定要回去，再在那里滑冰。但是它遭到了空袭，只剩下一个焦黑的、千疮百孔的外壳。现在南安普敦已经没有溜冰场了。我站在人行道上，让出租车在后面等着，拿着靴子和溜冰鞋，情不自禁地因为失望而失声大哭。不知道出租车司机怎么看我。”

她的哥哥1937年去了马来亚，那年琴十六岁。她十七岁时离开了学校，去了南安普敦的一个商学院，集中学习六个月后，拿到了速记员的文凭。然后她在镇上一个律师事务所工作了大约一年。这一年，她去马来亚工作的事情渐渐有了眉目。她的母亲一直和霹雳种植园公司的董事长保持联系，这位董事长对经理关于唐纳德的汇报非常满意。马来亚的未婚姑娘为数不多，所以当佩吉特太太跟董事长联系，请求他为琴在吉隆坡总部找一份工作的时候，公司认真地考虑了这个请求。公司上下都不想看到他们的经理跟当地女人通婚或者订婚，要想避免这个结局，一个显而易见的方法就是鼓励未婚女孩从英格兰过来工作。现在，这个女孩不仅来自他们熟悉的家庭，还会说马来语，这在从英国来的速记员中是一种罕见的本领。于是琴获得了这份工作。

这一切都准备妥当后，战争爆发了。一开始，在英国人们都认为这只是一次假战争，不会真的打起来。似乎并没有理由为了一件这么微不足道的事情阻碍了琴的大好前程。而且在佩吉特太太看来，如果战争突然在英国打起来的话，琴待在马来亚要比留在国内好得多。所以琴在1939年的冬天出发去了马来亚。

在刚到马来亚的十八个月里，她的生活妙不可言。办公室就在秘书处附近。秘书处是一栋巨楼，建得非常宽敞气派，有意宣示英国统治者的力量。它占据了所在广场的一整面，这个广场隔着板球场与俱乐部相望，另一面有一个堪称完美典范的英国乡村教堂。这里的热带气候温和舒适，每个人都过着典型的英国式生活：充足的闲暇，玩不完的游戏，开不完的派对，跳不完的舞会，有大量仆人供他们使唤，帮助他们操办这一切。刚到马来亚那几周，琴和公司的一个经理一起住，后来在都铎玫瑰旅馆找到了一个房间。那是一个英国女人开的小型私人旅馆，很多在办公室和秘书处工作的未婚姑娘都住在那里，就跟单身宿舍差不多。

“好得让人难以置信，”她说，“每个晚上都有舞会或者派对。如果你不拒绝邀请，就连写封信回家的时间都没有。”

日本南下进攻东南亚的消息传来时，她并未感到情势危急，周围一切也平静如常。1941年12月7日，美国被迫参战，似乎也是一个好消息。在吉隆坡举行的派对并没有什么异样，除了年轻小伙儿们开始请假不上班，穿上了军装，而这本身就让人感到一种愉悦的兴奋。甚至当日本人在马来亚北部登陆时，吉隆坡的英国人也还安之若素。延绵三百英里的大山和森林本身就是一道天然屏障，能抵抗从北部而来的侵略。威尔士亲王号战列舰和反击号战列巡洋舰的沉没虽然表明事态严重，但对一个刚拒绝了生平第一次求婚的十九岁女孩来说，是不值一提的。

很快，至少在理论上，所有已婚妇女和她们的孩子都已被撤离到新加坡。当日本军队采取迅速迂回绕行的战术，穿越了那片从未被任何军队征服过的森林，向半岛南下推进的时候，人们开始意识到情况的严重性。一天，琴的主任梅里曼先生把她叫到办公室，开门见山地告诉她办事处要关门了。她必须马上收拾好行李，去火车站坐第一趟火车南下新加坡。他给了她一个公司代理人的地址，在莱佛士广场附近，让她去那里报到，要求放她通行回国。另外五个姑娘也收到了相同的命令。

那时，有报告说日本人已经逼近怡保，仅在北方大约一百英里处。

城里一片风声鹤唳。琴到银行取出她所有的积蓄，大约六百马来亚元。她没有去火车站，但即使去了也不一定能坐上南下新加坡的火车，因为那时铁路上已经挤满了开赴前线的军队和物资。她本可以从公路逃走，却错失良机，去了巴图塔斯克找霍兰太太。

巴图塔斯克距吉隆坡约二十英里。霍兰先生今年四十岁，是一个露天锡矿的经理，一家人住在锡矿边上一间舒适的平房里。他的妻子叫艾琳，三个孩子分别是七岁的弗雷迪、四岁的简和只有十个月大的罗宾。艾琳·霍兰是一个平易近人的慈母，三十到三十五岁。霍兰一家从不参加派对和舞会，他们不喜欢那种场面。他们总是安静地待在家里，任凭世事变迁。琴刚到马来亚的时候，他们邀请她到家里做客。琴觉得和这家人待在一起非常轻松自在，后来又去了好几次。有一次，她刚得完轻微的登革热，在他们家住了一个星期，静心休养。前一天在吉隆坡的时候，她听说霍兰先生带家人去了车站，但是没能坐上火车，又回家了。琴觉得她不能抛下霍兰一家，她必须带着那几个孩子一起走。艾琳·霍兰是一个好母亲，也是一流的家庭主妇，但现在兵荒马乱，要她独自带着三个孩子逃难，她应付不来。

没费多大力气，琴就搭上了当地一辆开往巴图塔斯克的公共汽车。她大约在午饭时间到达，发现霍兰太太单独和孩子们在一起。矿上所有卡车和轿车都被军队带走了，霍兰一家只剩下那辆破旧的奥斯丁十二，其中一只轮胎磨损严重，帆布层都露了出来，另外一只的内壁很可疑地鼓起一个大包。这是他们唯一的交通工具，要靠它撤离，但它看起来根本就无法把全家人送到新加坡去。霍兰先生黎明前出发到吉隆坡去找两个外胎，到现在还没回来，霍兰太太焦急万分、坐卧不宁。

屋子里一片混乱。保姆回家了，或者正在外出办事。满屋子都是半收拾好的手提箱，或者是收拾好又打开了的。弗雷迪一直在池塘里玩耍，浑身是泥；简坐在便壶上，在许多手提箱中间哭个不停。霍兰太太正在一边给婴儿罗宾喂奶，一边指挥仆人做午饭，同时又要顾着简，心里还惦记着丈夫。琴先帮弗雷迪擦干净身子，再去照顾简。不久他们就坐在一起吃午饭了。

比尔·霍兰差不多日落时分才回来，两手空空。吉隆坡所有的轮胎储备都被强行征募了。不过，他发现有一辆当地的公共汽车第二天早上八点会去新加坡，就给家人订了座。回程的最后五英里，他只能步行，因为实在找不到交通工具了。在热带正午的酷热中，在柏油碎石路上徒步五英里，可不是一件开玩笑的事情。他浑身上下都湿透了，渴得要命，整个人都虚脱了。

他们本应当晚就出发去吉隆坡，但是晚上军队封锁了道路，而且，开着这辆奥斯丁在黑暗中四处乱撞，神经过敏的哨兵很可能会向他们开枪。他们决定黎明动身，留出充足的时间，确保在八点前到达吉隆坡。琴当晚跟他们一起待在平房里，一夜辗转无眠。半夜时她听见比尔·霍兰起身出去走廊上。透过蚊帐，她能看见他一动不动地站着，望着星星。她从蚊帐底下爬出去，穿上晨衣——在马来亚，人们睡觉时几乎不穿衣服。她沿着门廊走到他身旁。“怎么了？”她轻声说。

“没什么，”他说，“只是好像听见了什么声音。就这样。”

“有人在院子里？”

“不，不是那样。”

“那是什么？”

“我觉得我听到了枪声，在很远的地方，”他说，“可能是幻觉吧。”他们紧张地站着，在一片蛐蛐和青蛙的叫声中，努力寻找另一种声音。“上帝，”过了一会儿他说，“让黎明快点降临吧。”

他们回去睡觉。那晚，日军先头侦察部队潜入了在美罗驻扎的英军后方，并且渗透至仕林河，离他们仅有不到五十英里远。

他们黎明前就全都起来了，趁着第一缕灰色的光线往奥斯丁上装行李。三个成年人，三个小孩，还有他们所有的行李，把奥斯丁装得满满的。霍兰先生给男仆们结清工资，就出发南下吉隆坡。但是才开出不到两英里，那个露出帆布的车胎就爆了。他们被迫停下来，紧张万分，大家七手八脚把备胎——那个内壁上鼓起来一块儿的轮胎——换上。但这个轮胎只支撑了半英里。霍兰先生绝望地继续往前开，光秃秃的钢丝轮只跑了两英里就坏了。这样奥斯丁就完全走不动了。他们那时离吉隆坡还有十五英里远，而时间已经是七点半了。

霍兰先生把他们留在车里，自己匆忙跑下马路。大约一英里开外，有一间种植园平房。但他没有在那里找到交通工具，经理前一天就离开了。他绝望而焦急地返回来，发现孩子们烦躁不安，妻子则只想回到自己的平房去。在这种情况下，似乎没有其他更好的选择了。于是，每个大人带一个小孩，背着、抱着或牵着，走了五英里回家。他们把行李锁在车里。

他们在热气刚刚开始袭来的时候到家，筋疲力尽。他们从冰箱里拿出几瓶冰镇饮料，喝完便躺下休息。一个小时后，一辆卡车停在平房前，把他们惊醒了。一个年轻军官匆忙走进来。

“你们一定要离开这里，”他说，“上车，我搭你们。你们有几个人？”

琴说：“六个，算上孩子。您可以把我们带去吉隆坡吗？我们的车子坏了。”

军官冷笑道：“不行。日本兵已经到吉宁了，或者说，在我最后一次听到他们消息的时候，他们已经在那里了。他们现在可能已经进一步南下了。”吉宁离这里只有二十英里。“我带你们去帕农吧，那里有去新加坡的船。”他拒绝开车去取他们的行李，也许他是对的。那辆卡车上已经装了好多个没能及时撤离的家庭，而奥斯丁在五英里外，敌人方向。

瓜拉是河口的意思，瓜拉帕农则是位于帕农河口的一个小镇。那里有一个常驻地区委员。到达他的办公室时，卡车上有被迫撤离的四十个男人、女人和孩子，都是在经过沿路庄园时捎上的。大部分是出身相对卑微的英国女性，锡矿工程师长或者铁路领班的妻子，没几个能意识到日军推进的迅速和危险。种植园经理、秘书处职员和其他政府职员消息更灵通，也更富有，都及时把家人转移到了新加坡。这些自己没走成，最后一刻才搭上卡车的人，都是最无能的。

卡车在地区委员的办公室前停下来，陆军中尉走了进去。地区委员不久走了出来，这位男士一脸担忧地看着这群拥挤的妇女和儿童，以及当中寥寥几个男士。“天啊。”他轻声说，知道这个新担子有多重。“这样，把他们载到那边会计办公室去，命令他们坐在门廊上等一两个小时，我去想想办法。告诉他们别到处乱跑。”他转身返回办公室。“我想我可以把他们送到渔船上，”他说，“正好有几条闲置着。这就算仁至义尽了，我没有大汽艇。”

这群人被扔在会计办公室的门廊里。他们可以在那里做做伸展运动，活动活动筋骨。办公室里有自来水，门廊阴凉清爽。琴和比尔·霍兰把艾琳留在门廊上，让她带着孩子背靠墙坐下，两人结伴进村，把能买的东西都买下来，代替丢失的行李。他们找到一个给婴儿用的奶瓶，一点奎宁，一些治疗痢疾的盐，两罐饼干和三听肉罐头。他们想买蚊帐，但蚊帐已经卖光了。琴买了一些新针线，看见一个大帆布背袋，也买了下来。随后三年里，她一直背着那个袋子。

大约在下午茶时间，他们回到门廊，向霍兰太太展示购买成果，并吃了一点肉，喝了一些柠檬水。

日落时分，河口的灯塔守卫打电话到地区委员办公室，报告说巨鹗号正在进河。巨鹗号是海关的大汽艇，负责在海岸巡逻，搜寻从苏门答腊岛出发，偷越马六甲海峡作案的走私客。她是一艘柴油内燃船，大约有一百三十英尺长，平时驻扎在槟榔屿，强而有力，可用于远洋航行。地区委员的脸放光了——这就能解决他的问题。不管巨鹗号的任务是什么，她都必须捎上这些撤离者，带着他们沿海岸线南下，脱离险境。不久他离开办公室，走到码头上，打算在她进港时上船跟船长会面。

她出现在河的转弯处。他看见她装满了军队——矮胖的小个子男人，穿着灰绿色的军装，装备着来复枪，拿着比他们还要高的刺刀。怀着沉痛的心情，他看着她沿河驶过来，知道这就是他所有努力的终点。

日本人冲上岸，马上逮捕了他，用枪指着他的后背，押着他走上防波堤，随时准备给他一枪——哪怕只是遇到最轻微的抵抗。但那里根本就没有能够抵抗的部队，就连开卡车的军官也已经把车开走了，去找他自己的分队。日本士兵们迅速散开，没费一颗子弹就占据了整个驻地。他们来到撤离者们面前，这些人乖乖地坐在门廊上，呆若木鸡。日本兵立刻举起来复枪和刺刀对准他们，命令他们交出所有自来水笔、腕表和戒指。在男同伴们的劝说下，女士们默默地照做了，避免了遭受进一步的折磨。琴失去了她的腕表。士兵们搜查她的背包，想看看有没有自来水笔，但是她把自来水笔装在了行李里。

不久，夜幕降临，一个军官走过来，用一盏防风灯检查门廊上这群人。他沿门廊走着，把灯猛地塞到他们面前，两名士兵紧随其后，拿着上好膛的来复枪和寒光闪闪的刺刀。大部分孩子都哭了。检查结束后，他用蹩脚的英语发表了一个小小的演讲。“你们现在是俘虏，”他说，“你们今晚留在这里。你们明天去战俘营，也许。你们做好事情，对命令遵守，你们会从日本军人收到食物。你们做坏事情，你们就被马上射死。所以，总是做好事情。军官来的时候，你们站起来，鞠躬，每次都要。那就是好事情。你们现在去睡觉。”

其中一个男士问道：“请问有床和蚊帐吗？”

“日本军人没有床，没有蚊帐。你们可能明天有床和蚊帐。”

另外一个说：“我们可以吃点晚饭吗？”这个需要解释一下。“食物。”

“明天你们有食物。”军官离开了，留下两个哨兵把守门廊两头。

瓜拉帕农位于一个长满红树林的沼泽地区内，在一条浑浊河流的入口，所以蚊子极多。孩子们整个晚上都在不停地呻吟，焦躁地哭泣，闹得大人们也没法睡觉。他们躺在硬邦邦的门廊地板上，长夜漫漫，令人厌烦。被囚禁、吃败仗、受蚊子折磨，重重痛苦压在身上，没有几个人能睡着。刚开始的时候，琴眯瞪了一会儿，不久便醒来，浑身僵硬疼痛，脸和手臂都被蚊子咬肿了。她听到孩子们又突然大闹起来，知道在黎明前蚊子的攻击将变得更密集、更凶猛。当天边终于绽放出第一道曙光的时候，俘虏们的状态都非常糟糕。

会计办公室后面有一个公共厕所，但是人太多不够用。他们尽量相互协调，勉强解决了如厕问题。接下来，他们无事可做，只好干坐着，听天由命。霍兰和艾琳用罐头肉和甜饼干给孩子们做了一些三明治。吃了这顿简单的早饭后，大家感觉好了一些。很多人随身带着少量食物，并分给没带食物的人。那天早上日本人什么都没给他们吃。

上午九十点钟的时候，审讯开始了。士兵把每个家庭轮流带进地区委员办公室。办公室里有一个日本陆军大尉——琴过后知道他叫阳丹，大尉身旁坐着一个陆军中尉。中尉把笔记写在一本儿童临摹练习本上。琴和霍兰一家一起进去，当大尉问她是谁的时候，她解释说她是这个家庭的朋友，和他们结伴旅行，并说她在吉隆坡工作。审讯很快就结束了。最后大尉说：“男人今天去战俘营，女人和孩子留在这里。男人下午就走，所以你们现在跟他们道别，直到下午。谢谢。”

他们一直害怕日本兵把他们分开，也在门廊上讨论过此事，但没想到会这么快。霍兰先生问：“我可以知道你们会把女人和孩子们送到哪里去吗？他们的战俘营在哪里？”

军官说：“日本皇军不会在妇女们和孩子们身上打仗。也许不去战俘营，如果他们做好事。也许他们回家。日本军人总是对女人们和孩子们好。”

他们回到门廊上，和其他家庭一起讨论目前的情况。将男人和妇女儿童分别拘留是战时通常做法，他们不可能改变这个决定，但这仍然让他们难以承受。琴觉得，霍兰一家此时此刻并不需要她，便走开去，独自坐在门廊边上。她感到饿了。年轻的活力稍稍冲淡了眼下的抑郁忧愁。她在想，前路茫茫，有什么艰难困苦在等待着她？有一件摆在眼前的事：如果他们还要在门廊上过夜，必须找到一些驱蚊膏。北边的村子里有一家药剂店，他们前一天下午曾去过那儿，在这个地区应该有驱蚊膏卖。

她尝试引起哨兵的注意。她指指身上的蚊口，又指指那个村子，然后从门廊下来到地上。他马上举起刺刀指向她，她匆忙回到门廊上。这种做法明显行不通。他怀疑地向她大吼大叫，回到岗位上。

还有一个办法。公共厕所在大楼背后，靠着一面墙。那里没有哨兵，因为有墙挡住，不能从那里走出会计办公室，要出去就必须绕过大楼走到前面。过了一会儿，她起身走出后门，在大楼的掩护下，她东张西望。有一些孩子在不远处玩耍。

她轻声用马来语叫道：“姑娘！对，就是你，姑娘，过来一下。”

那个孩子向她走来。她大概十二岁，琴问：“你叫什么名字？”

她害羞得咯咯直笑：“哈里娅。”

琴说：“你知道那个药店吗，中国人开的？”

她点点头。“陈可欢记。”

琴说：“去找陈可欢。如果你把我的消息带给他，他过来找我，我就给你十分钱。告诉他有蚊子咬夫人们，”她给小姑娘看她的蚊口，“请他带一些药膏到门廊来，夫人们会买很多。快去，如果他带着药膏回来，我就给你十分钱。”

那个孩子点点头，跑走了。琴回到门廊等待，不久中国商人就出现了，拿着一个托盘，上面摆满了管装和罐装的药膏。他走向哨兵，向哨兵表示他想卖商品，哨兵犹豫了一下，最后还是同意了。琴买了六管防蚊膏，其他女士马上就把剩下的买走了。哈里娅拿到了十分钱。

不久一个当值的日本兵拿来两桶很稀的鱼汤和半桶米饭，脏兮兮的，让人直倒胃口。没有餐具，但他们除了尽量吃，也没有别的选择。战俘的生活方式要求严格平分所有食物，但那时他们还没习惯这种生活，所以有的人吃得比别人多很多，有的人吃得很少，还有的人根本就没吃上。不过，自带食物还没吃完，所以他们还可以靠饼干和其他私人储备来补充营养。

那天下午，男人们被迫与家人分离，被看守押走了。比尔·霍兰告别了他肥胖慈祥的妻子，眼睛湿润了。“再见，琴，”他沉重地说，“祝你好运。”又道，“请尽量不要扔下他们不管，好吗？”

琴点点头。“请放心。我们会进同一个战俘营。”

男人们站好队，一共七人，在看守的监押下离开了。

剩下的人里有十一位已婚女士，两位未婚姑娘——琴和一位死气沉沉的女孩埃伦·福布斯。埃伦一直跟其中一个家庭住在一起，她是来马来亚找结婚对象的，但不幸尚未成功。除了这些人外，还有十九个小孩，有大有小，从十四岁的女孩到仍在襁褓中的婴儿。加起来一共三十二人。大部分女人只会说英语，其中几个，包括艾琳·霍兰，可以用马来语来指挥她们的仆人，但再多的就不会了。

他们在会计办公室住了四十一天。

第二晚和第一晚很相似，但日本人把办公室的门都给打开了，把房间给他们使用。晚上，日本人送来第二顿鱼汤餐，但没有提供其他东西——没有床，没有毯子，也没有蚊帐。有些女人带着行李，所以有毯子，但数量实在是太少了，根本不够分。一个一脸严肃的女士，霍斯福尔太太，要求见军官。阳丹大尉来了，她抗议说条件太差，要求给他们提供床和蚊帐。

“没有床，没有蚊帐，”他说，“很抱歉。日本女人们睡在地板、草席上。所有日本人都睡草席。你丢掉骄傲的思想，很坏的东西。你睡在草席上，跟日本女人一样。”

“但我们是英国人，”她愤怒地说，“我们无法像动物一样睡在地面上！”

他的眼睛睁圆了。他向哨兵做了个手势，哨兵们冲进来，一人抓住霍斯福尔太太一条手臂，大尉狠狠地扇了她四巴掌。“很坏的思想。”他说，转身离开了他们。从此再没人提床的事情了。

第二天早上，阳丹来检查他们。霍斯福尔太太并没有因为昨天的事而畏首畏尾，她提出他们需要水。她指出，不仅是婴儿，他们每一个人都渴望洗澡。当天下午，有人把一个桶放进那间最小的办公室，请来一个苦力负责装水。他们把这个房间改装成浴室和洗衣间。刚开始的时候，大部分妇女还有钱，村子里的小贩效仿陈可欢把东西拿来卖给这些战俘，所以她们积攒起一些足以维持生存的生活必需品。

他们慢慢开始习惯这种艰苦的生活。孩子们很快就学会了毫无怨言地睡地板，年轻的女士们为此花的时间要多许多，三十岁以上的女士们则难得睡上半个小时而不被痛醒——但她们确实睡着了。阳丹大尉向他们解释说，要等到战役结束，获胜的日本人才有时间给女人们建一个战俘营。日本成功占领马来亚全境后，他们会搬进一个宽敞漂亮的战俘营，专门为他们在山区疗养胜地金马伦高原上修建的。那里有床和蚊帐，以及他们过惯了的舒适生活，但为了获得这一切乐趣，他们必须“做好事情”。“做好事情”意味着，每当看见他走近就要站起身鞠躬。在阳丹大尉扇了好几张脸，用军靴踢了好几次小腿后，他们都学会了“做好事情”。

日本兵提供的食物仅够勉强果腹，而且每顿都是一成不变的鱼汤和米饭，每天两顿。抱怨毫无用处，而且常常是危险的，在阳丹大尉看来，这些都是过于骄傲的思想，需要接受道德审查。然而，村子里有一间小中国餐馆可以提供饭菜。钱还没花光的时候，大部分家庭每天从那间餐馆预订一顿煮好的饭。

他们没有医生，也没有任何药物。一周后，痢疾袭击了他们。晚上一片混乱，孩子们尖叫着和母亲一起踉踉跄跄地跑进公共厕所。疟疾一直在流行，但是被他们从陈可欢记买到的奎宁控制住，尽管价钱一涨再涨。为了对付痢疾，阳丹大尉减少了汤量，增加了米饭的补给，在米饭里多放一些腐烂的干鱼——那些干鱼可能原来是用来熬汤的。另外，他往食谱里添加了一桶茶，每天下午送去，作为对英国生活习惯的一种让步。

在这段时间里，琴一直和霍兰太太分担照顾三个孩子的工作。她很虚弱，明显因饮食改变而引起的困乏也使她痛苦不堪，但她每晚都睡得很好，尽管频频醒来。艾琳·霍兰受的苦更多。她的年纪比琴大，在地板上很难入睡。她失去了大部分青春活力，迅速地消瘦了下去。

第三十五天，艾思梅·哈里森去世了。

艾思梅是一个八岁的小孩。她患了痢疾有一段时间了，变得骨瘦如柴，非常虚弱，基本不能入眠，常常哭泣。不久她发烧了，又得了疟疾，有两天烧到一百零四度(2)。霍斯福尔太太告诉阳丹大尉，必须给她找一个大夫，并送她去医院。他说很抱歉，但没有医院。他会试着去找一个医生，但医生们都在为皇军的胜利而努力战斗。当天晚上，艾思梅陷入了持续的抽搐状态，黎明前不久就去世了。

当天上午，她被埋葬在村子后面的穆斯林墓地里。她的母亲和另外一个女士被允许参加葬礼。在语言不通的日本兵和马来亚人面前，她们从祈祷书上给她读了一段祷文，葬礼就结束了。生活还像从前一样，在会计办公室继续下去。但是，死亡的阴影开始悄悄侵入孩子们的梦境了。

第六周末尾，阳丹大尉做完上午的检查后，和他们面对面站着。女人们全身湿透，精疲力竭地站在门廊的阴影中，面对着他，用手抓住自己的孩子。很多大人和大部分孩子到那时都已瘦骨嶙峋，病病歪歪。

他说：“女士们，日本皇军已经进入新加坡，整个马来亚都自由了。现在战俘营正在被建造给男人，还有女人们和孩子们。战俘营在新加坡，你们去那里。我很伤心你们的生活不舒服，但是现在好一些了。你们明天出发去吉隆坡，不会比你们每天能走的更多。你们从吉隆坡坐火车去新加坡，我想。在新加坡，你们会很开心。多谢。”

从帕农到吉隆坡有四十七英里远。理解他的话需要一点时间，然后霍斯福尔太太说：“我们怎样去吉隆坡？有卡车吗？”

他说：“很抱歉，没有卡车。你们走，轻松的旅程。不会多过你们每天能走的。日本军人帮助你们。”

她说：“带着这些孩子，我们没法步行。我们必须要有一辆卡车。”

这些是坏的思想。他的目光变得僵硬无情。“你们走。”他重复道。

“但是我们的行李怎么办？”

他说：“带上你们能够带的东西。不久行李就会给你们送过去。”话毕便转身离开。

那一天余下的时间里，她们陷在一种震惊的绝望中。那些有行李的人绝望地收拾着行李，她们想将生活必需品都打包带走，但又不想让包裹变得太沉。曾任女校长的霍斯福尔太太主动承担起领导的角色，在她们之间来回走动，向她们提供帮助，出各种各样的主意。她只带着一个十岁的男孩约翰，所以她的情况比大部分人要好，因为对于一个女人来说，携带一个十岁男孩儿的必需品上路并不会很费力。有些年轻母亲带着好几个孩子，她们面临的处境要艰难得多。

琴和霍兰太太面临的问题小一些，她们丢过一次行李，所以现有的东西不多，也不必花许多心思东挑西拣。她们几乎没有可以换的衣服，仅有的几件可以轻易地放进琴的背包。她们买到了两张毯子和三个饭碗，还有三个汤匙。于是她们决定用毯子把这些小东西捆起来，然后用一条绳子捆住毯子，并利用这条绳子做背带，这样一个人就可以同时背一个背袋和一个毯子包裹。她们最大的问题是鞋，这些鞋都很时髦，但很不适合走远路。

傍晚时分，孩子们都不在身边，她们俩抱着婴儿独自坐在角落里。霍兰太太轻声说：“亲爱的，我不该说泄气话，但是我想我走不了那么远。我最近身体状况很糟糕。”

琴说：“会好的。”虽然在内心深处，她也知道事实并非如此。“你比我们其中一些人健壮得多，”这倒可能是真的，“我们会慢慢地走，因为孩子们。我们会走好几天。”

“我知道，亲爱的。但我们在哪里过夜？他们会给我们安排住宿吗？”

没人能回答。

黎明后不久米饭就送来了。八点钟的时候，阳丹大尉和四个士兵一起出现，这四个士兵将担任这次旅途的看守。“今天你们走去亚逸彭吉斯，”他说，“天气好，旅途很轻松。到达亚逸彭吉斯你们就有好晚饭。你们会很高兴。”

琴问霍斯福尔太太：“亚逸彭吉斯离这里有多远？”

“我觉得有十二到十五英里吧。我们当中有些人还没有走过那么远的路呢。”

琴说：“最好和士兵们一样，每小时休息一下，是不是？”

“如果他们允许。”

一个小时后，最后一个孩子终于上完厕所，女人们也终于做好了远行的准备。看守们蹲在那里，出发后他们就轻松多了。最后，阳丹大尉又出现了，他的眼光冷酷无情，充满愤怒。“你们现在就走，”他说，“还留下的女人们被打，打得厉害。你们做好事情才会高兴。现在就走。”

没有办法，他们只好启程了。他们三三两两一组，在烈日下沿着柏油路南行，每遇到树荫就躲进去。琴跟霍兰太太一起走，把最热也是最重的负担——毯子包裹挂在肩上，手牵着四岁的简。七岁的弗雷迪跟在母亲旁边走，霍兰太太抱着婴儿罗宾，背着背包。一个日军中士缓步走在最前面，三个士兵殿后。

妇女们走得很慢。每当一个母亲带着孩子撤进灌木丛，整个队伍就要停下来，这种情况频繁发生。根本不需要向看守提一个小时休息一次的问题，因为痢疾让它变得毫无意义。对于没有受到痢疾困扰的人来讲，旅途变得没完没了，基本上成了一个在烈日下站在路边等待的过程，因为中士不允许队伍抛下落伍的人继续前进。在他们的职责范围内，日本士兵还是很人道和很能帮忙的，他们每个人都帮忙抱着一个孩子走了很远的路。

这一天过得很慢。中士一开始就说得很清楚，在他们到达亚逸彭吉斯之前，一路上没有食物，也没有遮阴处，而且他似乎并不关心要走多久。这一天他们的时速不超过一英里半。走着走着，女士们都开始觉得脚疼，尤其是年纪大一些的女士。她们的鞋子都不适合走远路，柏油路的热气让她们的脚都肿起来了，所以不久很多人就因为脚疼而变得一瘸一拐的。有一些孩子赤着脚走，倒也走得很顺畅。琴观察了一段时间，弯下身把鞋脱掉，小心地用光脚感受陌生的路面。她开始光着脚走，把鞋子拿在手里，仔细地看着路。虽然柏油沙子还时不时刺痛她柔软的脚底，但脚已经不疼了。她觉得光着脚走更舒服，但是艾琳·霍兰拒绝尝试。

那天晚上六点钟，天马上要黑的时候，他们跌跌撞撞地来到亚逸彭吉斯。这是一个马来亚村庄，给附近橡胶庄园的工人居住的。附近就有一个乳胶加工厂，工厂旁边有一个用棕榈树做房顶的仓库，里面有很多平行的木板条，平时用来烟熏挂在上面的生橡胶片，现在是空的，女士们成群走进去。他们筋疲力尽，东倒西歪，精神恍惚。过了一会儿士兵们送进来一桶茶、一桶米饭和干鱼。他们很多人都一杯接一杯地喝茶，但是几乎没有人有胃口吃东西。

趁着最后一缕光线，琴信步走到外面，四周看看。看守们正忙着在一堆小火上做饭，她走到中士的跟前，问他今天晚上她可不可以进村子里走走。他理解了琴的意思，点头同意。离开了阳丹大尉，纪律变得很宽松。

在村子里，她找到几间卖衣服、糖果、香烟和水果的小商店。她看到有卖芒果的，就买了一打。她跟卖水果的马来女人讨价还价，因为她的现金少得可怜，要省着点花。买来后她马上吃了一个，感觉舒坦了一些。在瓜拉帕农，他们基本没吃水果。她回到仓库，发现士兵们用椰子油给他们点起了一盏小小的灯，灯芯是露在外面的。

她把芒果分给艾琳和三个孩子，又分给其他人，发现这桩买卖真是一个巨大的成功。有了从其他妇女那里拿来的钱作武装，她又去了一趟村子，买回来五十多个芒果，不久所有的妇女和儿童都在埋头吃芒果了。士兵们又送进来一桶茶，每人拿了一个芒果，作为他们辛苦付出的回报。妇女们吃了芒果后，感觉精神多了，差不多能把所有米饭都吃下去。不久，他们就在疲劳、虚弱和病痛中，昏昏睡去。

仓库里满是老鼠，整个晚上在他们身上和周围跑来跑去。早上起来他们发现有几个孩子被咬了。

他们醒来时，昨天长途跋涉所造成的新疼痛、僵硬和疲劳开始发作，使得他们无法再上路了。中士却强迫他们继续走，这次要走去一个叫作亚沙汉的地方，比昨天的行程短一些，大约十英里。至少有十英里，因为他们花了差不多相同的时间才走到那里。这次主要是被科勒德太太耽误了行程。她是一个肥胖的女人，大约四十五岁，有两个孩子，哈里和本，大约十岁和七岁。她在帕农患了疟疾兼痢疾，现在非常虚弱。每隔十分钟，她就必须停下来，其他人也不得不跟着停下来，因为中士不准他们分散。她无须背任何东西，年轻一些的女人轮流扶着她走，帮她拿行李。

到下午，大家看到她好像变了一种颜色。她本来还算红润的脸变成斑驳的蓝色。她不断抱怨胸口疼。当他们终于到达亚沙汉的时候，她实际上已经无法单独行走了。住宿的地方跟昨天一样也是一个橡胶固化仓库，她们搀科勒德太太进去，扶她靠墙坐下，因为她说躺下来会疼到无法呼吸。有位女士出去拿了点水给她洗脸，她说：“谢谢，亲爱的。请给哈里和本也洗洗，亲爱的。”那个女士便带孩子出去给他们洗澡。等她回来的时候，科勒德太太已经歪在一边，失去了意识。半个小时后，她去世了。

当天晚上琴又给他们买了一些水果，芒果和香蕉，还给孩子们买了一些糖果。卖糖果的马来女人拒绝收她钱。“不，太太，”她说，“日本人这样对你们太过分了。这是我们的礼物。”琴回去之后告诉大家发生了什么事，大家听了都很感激那个女人。

在仓库外面炊火的光亮中，霍斯福尔太太和琴一起，跟中士进行了一次谈判。这个中士只会说几个英文单词，为了让他听明白，她们一边说一边打手语。“明天不能再走，”她们说，“不，不能再走。休息——睡觉——明天。明天再走，更多女人死去。明天休息。走一天，休息一天。”

她们无法知道他是否听懂了。“明天，”他说，“女人在土里。”

明天早上必须将科勒德太太下葬。这样一来就不用一大早出发了，而且也走不完十英里。她们抓住这一点作为借口。“明天埋葬女人在土里，”她们说，“明天留在这里。”

她们已经尽了力，他不理解也没有办法。他跟三个士兵一起在炊火前蹲下来。过了一会儿，他走向琴，脸上闪烁着智慧的光芒。“走一天，睡一天，”他说，“女人们就不死了。”他使劲儿点着头，又把霍斯福尔太太叫过来，三人一起，友好地微笑着，使劲儿地点头。他们都对彼此感到满意。为了庆祝这一外交胜利，她们给他一根香蕉以示尊敬。

那一整天，琴都赤着脚走来走去，虽然不慎几次踢到脚指头，踢破了脚趾甲，但在晚上她感到了久违的舒爽清新。晚上，远行的效果开始以不同形式显现在不同年龄段的人身上。大部分三十岁以下的妇女和孩子们，状态实际上都比离开帕农时要好。宽松的纪律使他们振奋，走路活动身体，有水果和糖果吃，也使他们变得更精神。老一些的女人状况却糟糕得多。对她们而言，极端的疲劳压倒了这些改善带来的好处。她们在黑暗中或躺或坐，无精打采，被淘气的孩子们折磨着，连吃东西的力气都没有。很多人都累到失眠。

第二天早上，他们埋葬了科勒德太太。附近找不到可以做墓地的地方，但当地的马来首领告诉他们，可以在院子的一角挖一个洞，在一堆橡胶的旁边。中士找来两个苦力给挖了一个浅浅的墓坑，把包裹在毯子里的科勒德太太放进去。霍斯福尔太太从祈祷书上读了一段祷文。然后她们又把毯子拿回来，因为实在是没有多余的毯子了。随后就盖上了土。琴找来一个木匠替他们钉了一个小小的十字架，但是这个木匠拒绝收费。他是一个穆斯林，或者仅仅是一个万物有灵论(3)者，但他知道老爷们是怎样办一个基督教葬礼的。他们用一根永久铅笔把“茱莉亚·科勒德”和死亡日期写在上面，希望雨水不会把字迹冲刷掉。然后她们就开始了冗长的讨论，以决定在上面写什么铭文。所有女士都兴致勃勃，热烈的讨论持续了一个半小时。出人意料地，霍兰太太建议使用《新约·罗马书》第十四章中的句子：“你是谁，竟论断别人的仆人呢。他或站住，或跌倒，自有他的主人在。”暗指那个迫使他们上路的中士。但其他的女士并不喜欢这句话，最后她们妥协成“安宁，真正的安宁，心爱的人远在他方”。那使所有人都很满意。

葬礼结束后，她们散坐在各处洗衣服。肥皂现在变得很稀有，跟钱一样。吃完米饭后，霍斯福尔太太把大家召集起来，开了一个简单的会议，核实经济状况。有一半女人已经身无分文，其他人的钱加起来总共也只有十五美元左右。她提议把钱集中起来使用，但兜里还有钱的女人们宁愿把钱留着，花在自己的孩子身上。不过，由于钱实在是太少了，没有什么讨论价值。然而，她们都同意平分日本兵每日提供的食物，此后他们吃饭的时候就更加井然有序了。

大约在中午的时候，阳丹大尉开着地区委员的轿车出现了。他停车下来，发现他们没有在路上，不禁怒火中烧。他用日语数落了中士一顿。中士僵硬地站在那里，专注地听着，完全没有为自己解释或辩护。之后大尉转向女人们。“你们为什么不走？”他愤怒地质问道，“非常坏的事情。你们不走，没有食物。”

霍斯福尔太太冲着他说：“科勒德太太昨天晚上去世了。我们今天早上才把她葬在那里。如果你强迫我们每天都这样走，我们会统统死掉。这些女人一点也不适合走远路。你知道的。”

“女人为什么死？”他询问道，“什么病？”

“她得了痢疾和疟疾，就像我们大部分人一样。昨天，我们走了那么多路，她累死了。你最好进来看看弗里思太太和茱迪·汤姆逊。她们今天都不可能上路。”

他走进仓库，站着看了看两三个无精打采地坐在昏暗中的女人。他和中士说了点什么，便回去开车。在门口，他转向霍斯福尔太太。“很伤心女人死了，”他说，“也许我找一辆卡车在吉隆坡。我会问的。”他上了车，开走了。

他的话很快就在女人们中间传开了。他要去给她们找一辆卡车！她们可以坐卡车去吉隆坡了！不用再走远路了！事情到底还不至于那么糟糕。她们将会从吉隆坡坐火车去新加坡，跟其他英国女士一样住进一个像样的战俘营。在战俘营里，她们可以安顿下来，重新组织生活，好好照顾孩子。战俘营里还有医生，也总会有地方医治病重的人。她们变得欢欣鼓舞，连最无精打采的人也恢复了，纷纷出来洗漱，把自己收拾得干净漂亮一些。那个下午她们都非常关心自己的外表，因为她们以前常常去吉隆坡购物，那里的人都认识她们。她们必须在卡车到达之前把自己打扮好。

日落前大概一个小时，阳丹大尉又来了。中士向他敬了一个礼，他又和中士说话。然后他转向女人们：“你们不去吉隆坡，”他说，“你们去瑞天咸港(4)。英国人毁坏了桥，所以通向新加坡的铁路不好。你们现在去瑞天咸港，然后坐船去新加坡。”

妇女们陷入了震惊的沉默。霍斯福尔太太问道：“会不会有卡车送我们去瑞天咸港？”

他说：“很抱歉没有卡车。你们慢慢走，轻松的行程。两天，三天，你们走去瑞天咸港。然后船带你们去新加坡。”

从亚沙汉到瑞天咸港有大概三十英里远。她说：“阳丹大尉，请你讲讲道理。我们中的很多人都不适合继续走路了。无论如何，你就不能给我们的孩子找一些交通工具吗？”

他说：“英国女人们有骄傲的思想，总是。太骄傲了，不像日本女人们那么好。你们明天走去巴克里。”他上车走了。那是她们最后一次见到他。

巴克里大概有十一英里远，大约和瑞天咸港在同一个方向上。突如其来的变故让她们失望透顶，任人摆布的命运更是如此。霍兰太太绝望地说：“我真不懂，难道在帕农的时候，他就不知道桥都断了？他就不应该让我们去吉隆坡！我真怀疑瑞天咸港到底有没有船……”

第二天早晨他们只好又出发上路了。两个士兵被带走了，只剩下一个士兵和中士一起留下来看守他们。看守减少并不会增加他们的危险性，因为没有人想过要逃走。但现在只剩下两个看守给她们带年幼的孩子，所以母亲们的负担增加了。

那天，琴第一次抱着婴儿罗宾走路。霍兰太太走得太痛苦了，必须减轻她的负担。她仍然背着背包，照顾着弗雷迪，但是琴不仅要背毯子包裹和零碎物件，还要抱着婴儿，另一只手牵着简。她像以前一样赤脚行走。经过几番试验，她发现，像马来女人那样把婴儿背在臀上是最轻松的方式。

奇怪的是，这个婴儿在三个小孩中最省事。她们喂他米饭、鱼汤或鱼汁，效果很好。六周里面，他好像只得了一次痢疾，吃了一两次芒硝就好了。蚊子好像从来不去骚扰他，他也没发过烧。另外两个孩子就没那么幸运了。他们时不时受到痢疾的折磨，现在虽然已经好了，人却变得相当的瘦。

当天晚上他们睡在一间平房里。这间平房原来属于巴克里锡矿的经理，一个英国人。他七八周前就抛下它离开了，在此期间它被双方部队占领过，也遭受了马来人的洗劫，现在只剩下光秃秃的墙。然而，奇迹般地，肮脏不堪的洗澡间还能用。洗澡间里堆着一些切好的木头，用于生炉子烧热水。中士信守承诺，允许他们休息一天，他们便充分利用热水来洗衣服和洗澡。他们的状态稍稍好了一些，精神也恢复了。

“我想船上会有热水，”霍兰太太说，“通常都会有的，是不是？”

第二天，他们继续上路，出发去一个叫作迪里特的地方。这一天他们基本上都沿着橡胶种植园的小路行走，树荫覆盖了大部分道路，让他们感到很舒服。即使是年老一些的妇女，也发现今天的行程可以忍受。他们在探路的时候遇到了一些困难。中士基本上不会说马来语，他时不时去问路，但是听不懂那些负责收割橡胶的马来女人们在说什么。琴发现她能听懂那些女人所说的答案，也可以跟她们沟通，但她自己知道方向后，又很难让中士听得懂。时近黄昏，他们俩达成了一项协议，由她负责跟马来女人们交谈——无论如何，这些马来女人跟她聊天时没那么害羞；然后她发明了一种中士能看明白的手势语。从那时起，琴便负责为大家打探最近的路。

下午三四点钟，本·科勒德——已逝科勒德太太的儿子——光着脚在草丛中走的时候，踩到一样东西，那东西用毒牙咬了他一口，逃走了。他过后说那看起来像一只大甲虫，很可能是蝎子。霍斯福尔太太负起责来，让他平躺在地面上，从伤口中吮吸出毒液。但是他的脚迅速地肿了起来，一直肿到膝盖，看起来就很疼，使他哭个不停。她们别无他法，只好把他背起来。对于本身已经虚弱不堪的女士们来讲，要背着一个五英石(5)重的七岁男孩走路并不是一件容易的事情。霍斯福尔太太背着他走了一个小时，然后中士背着他走完剩余的路程。到达迪里特后，他的脚踝已经肿成一个大包，膝盖也僵硬了。

在迪里特没有地方住，也没有食物。那个地方是一个典型的马来村庄，房子用木制成，棕榈屋顶离地板有四英尺高，地板用柱子支撑。地板下面是空的，狗在那里睡觉，家禽在那里做巢。他们疲惫地或坐或站，等待中士与马来首领进行交涉。很快他就把琴叫过去，让她加入了三语谈判。村子里有米，可以给他们做一顿饭，但是首领提出要收钱。最后中士答应日后一定会付账，首领才勉强同意提供晚饭。关于住宿，他冷漠地说，没有，但他们可以跟狗和家禽一样睡在屋子底下。后来他同意腾出一间屋子，这样这三十个战俘就可以睡在屋顶下，大约十五英尺见方的地板上。

琴占了一个角落，艾琳·霍兰带着孩子和婴儿坐进去。在几英尺开外，霍斯福尔太太正在照料本·科勒德。她们有一些高锰酸盐结晶和旧剃须刀片。尽管孩子痛得尖叫，她们还是用刀片稍稍切开了伤口，放进去一些结晶，再重新包扎好伤口。随后她们用热敷。琴帮不上忙，信步走出去了。

在一个类似村子公用厨房的地方，日本士兵正在指挥村子里的女人做米饭。首领的住所就在附近。他坐在通向屋子的楼梯上，坐在脚后跟上，抽着一根长管烟。他是一名头发灰白的老人，穿着纱笼和一件褪了色的卡其斜纹粗棉布夹克。琴走到他跟前，含羞用马来语说：“很抱歉，我们被迫来到这里，给你们添了这么多麻烦。”

他站起来，向夫人鞠了一躬。“不麻烦，”他说，“看到夫人们境况如此凄惨，我们感到很难过。你们是否从很远的地方来？”

她说：“今天从巴克里来。”

他请她进房子里去。那里没有椅子，她和他一起坐在地板上，靠着门洞。他问他们的遭遇，琴告诉了他，他发出一声哼哼。不久他的妻子从里面出来，拿着两杯没有糖和牛奶的咖啡。琴用马来语谢谢她，她含羞一笑，又退回房子里面去。

过了一会儿，首领说：“那个矮子，”他指日本中士，“他说你们明天必须待在这里。”

琴说：“我们太虚弱了，无法每天走远路。日本人准许我们每走一天就休息一天。如果明天可以留在这里，对我们恢复体力将很有帮助。中士说他可以找到钱买食物。”

“矮子们从来都是白吃白喝，”首领说，“不过你们要留下来。”

她说：“我不知道能说什么——除了谢谢你。”

他抬起灰白的头。“《古兰经》第四章(6)写道：‘人性是贪吝所支配的。如果你们行善而且敬畏，那末，真主确是彻知你们的行为的。’”

她和这位年老的男人一起坐着，直到米饭飘香，她才离开他去吃晚饭。其他女人奇怪地看着她。“我看见你和首领坐在一起闲聊，”其中一个说，“就像老朋友一样。”

琴笑道：“他请我喝了一杯咖啡。”

“真好！能用他们的语言和他们交谈，总能得到点好处，不是吗？他都说了些什么？”

琴想了想。“东拉西扯——关于我们的旅途。他聊了一下上帝。”

女人们盯着她看。“你是指他自己的上帝？不是真正的上帝？”

“他没有把两者区分开来，”琴说，“就是上帝。”

第二天，他们休息了一整天，然后步行去离瑞天咸港三到四英里远的巴生。小本·科勒德的情况虽无恶化，但也并无好转，大腿肿得厉害。他现在主要的问题是身体上的虚弱：受伤后他就再没有吃过东西，因为一吃就要吐出来。那个时候，孩子们都累得一点劲儿没有了。首领指挥村民们给他做了一个担架，把两条带枝丫的长竹竿并排扎起来，再在中间放一个用棕榈树叶织成的垫子，这样他们可以把小本放在上面，轮流抬着他。

他们当天下午就走到了巴生。那里有一个空校舍，中士把他们安置进去之后，自己就到附近的日军营地报到，汇报工作并安排日常食物供给事宜。

不久，一个带着六个护卫士兵的军官来了，对他们进行了检查。他是合欢少佐，英语说得非常好。他说：“你们是谁？来这里干什么？”

他们盯着他。霍斯福尔太太说：“我们是战俘，从帕农来。我们在去新加坡战俘营的路上。帕农的阳丹大尉派看守把我们押来这里，让我们从这里上船去新加坡。”

“这里没有船，”他说，“你们应该留在帕农。”

没有争论，她们也没有力气了。“我们被送来这里。”她机械地重复道。

“他们没有权利把你们送来这里，”他生气地说，“这里没有战俘营。”

接下来是漫长而尴尬的沉默：女人们盯着他，茫然，绝望。霍斯福尔太太再次把残存的能量集中起来。“我们可以看医生吗？”她问，“我们当中有人病得很厉害——尤其是一个孩子。另一位女士在路上去世了。”

“她死于什么？”他很快地问道，“瘟疫？”

“不是感染。她累死了。”

“我会派一个医生去给你们所有人做检查。你们今晚可以留在这里，但是必须尽快离开。我们自己的食物都不够，更别说养活战俘。”他转过身去，走回营地。

他给校舍安排了一个新看守。他们再也没有见过那个友好的中士和那个士兵了。也许他们被派回帕农了。不到一个小时，一个年轻的日本医生来了。他让他们都站起来，检查看他们有没有被感染，然后就要走，但是他们请他留下来看看小本·科勒德的大腿。他命令他们继续做热敷。当他们问是否可以请他把小本送进医院的时候，他耸耸肩，说：“我问一下。”

他们在看守的监视下一直留在校舍里，日复一日。第三天，他们又去叫医生，因为本·科勒德的情况陡然恶化。尽管很不乐意，医生还是用卡车把他送到医院去。六天后，他们听说小本去世了。

琴·佩吉特弯腰蹲在起居室壁炉边的地板上。窗外，风转了方向，把伦敦的雨吹到了窗户上。

“在战俘营度过战争岁月的人们写过很多书，写他们过得有多糟糕。”她轻声说，望着余烬，“没有在战俘营里待过的人，是不会知道那是怎么样的。”

————————————————————

(1) 英格兰郡名，在英吉利海峡中，为著名旅游胜地。

(2) 书中的温度单位均为华氏度。

(3) 该理论认为天下万事万物皆有灵魂，享受同等的权利。

(4) 马来亚第一大港。

(5) 英国重量单位，1英石相当于14磅。

(6) 这一章内容主要针对妇女，故首领在此时引用。

第三章

他们在巴生待了十一天，但觉前路茫茫。食物又差又短缺，附近也没有商店——即使有也没有区别，因为实际上他们已经没钱了。第十二天，合欢少佐让他们在收到通知半小时内起程，走路去波德申(1)，并派一个下士作为看守。他说，可能那里会有一条船带他们南下新加坡，如果没有的话，他们就朝战俘营的大致方向走。

那时候大概是1942年3月中旬。巴生离波德申有大约五十英里远，但他们现在走得不如从前快了。他们一直走到月底才到达波德申。途中他们在一个村子滞留了几天，因为霍斯福尔太太患疟疾倒下了，一度烧到一百零五度。不到一周她就恢复了，可以走路了——或者说，蹒跚而行。但她再也没能恢复活力。从那时候起，领导的责任渐渐落到了琴的肩上。

他们到达波德申的时候，衣衫褴褛，惨不忍睹。妇女们没有衣服可换，因为她们已经把负担降到最低限度。琴和霍兰太太被抓时，穿的就是现在身上的薄棉连衣裙，它们都穿破、洗旧了。刚从帕农出发不久，琴就开始赤脚行走，并打算就这样一直走下去。她现在的穿衣风格又向马来女人靠近了一步。在沙拉克，她把小胸针卖给了一个印度珠宝商，换来十三美元，她用宝贵的两美元买了一件纱笼。

纱笼是一种管状的衣服，直径大概三英尺，人套进去，像毛巾一样围在腰上，让其余部分自然垂下来成褶皱状，人就可以自由移动了。睡觉的时候，可以把围着腰的部分解开，让它松软地铺在身上，不必担心滑走。它是最轻薄、最凉快的热带服饰，也最实用，穿洗都很方便。她剪掉连衣裙破烂不堪的裙摆，把余下的部分当成一件束腰外衣穿在上面。从那个时候起，她穿得比其他妇女都要轻松凉快。一开始其他女士都对这种下等的当地穿法表示强烈不满，但随着衣服越穿越破，她们中的大部分也都开始效法她。

在波德申，他们并没有碰上什么好运气，也没有船。日本人允许他们留在波德申，待在一个干椰子肉仓库中，并未进行严格监管。就这样过了大约十天。日本指挥官认定他们是令人讨厌的累赘，于是又要把他们赶往塞伦班。他解释说，显而易见地，他们又不是他的俘虏，不是他的责任，应该由那些抓住他们的人把他们送去战俘营。他的目的很明显，就是要摆脱他们。因为如果他们继续赖着不走，他就不得不向日本皇军提出申请，请求军队、食物和医疗支援了。

在波德申和塞伦班之间的西里奥，悲剧降临到霍兰一家头上——简去世了。他们走了一整天，在一个熏橡胶的小屋里休息。简在路上发起烧来。那个时候他们有两个日本看守，其中一个当天大部分时间背着她。体温计在几天前意外损坏了，所以没有办法测量疟疾病人的体温，但是她很烫。她们有一点奎宁，想给她吃，但喂不下去。后来，直到她虚弱得无法抵抗，才喂了下去，可惜为时已晚。她们说服日本中士让大家留在西里奥，不去冒险继续移动这个孩子。琴和艾琳·霍兰一直陪着她，不眠不休，在那个阴暗发臭的地方，与死神战斗，听任老鼠晚上在周围发疯似的跑来跑去，母鸡白天不断进进出出。第二天晚上，她去世了。

面对这个打击，霍兰太太表现得很坚强，远远超出了琴的想象。“这是上帝的意志，我亲爱的，”她轻轻地说，“当她爸爸听到这个消息的时候，上帝也会给他力量，使他坚强。就像上帝给我们力量，来忍受现在的审判一样。”她站在小坟墓旁边，没有流泪，帮忙制作小木头十字架，并选好写在上面的铭文：“让小孩子到我这里来。(2)”她轻轻地说：“我想她爸爸会喜欢这一句。”依然没有掉一滴眼泪。

琴那天晚上在黑暗中醒来，听到她在哭泣。

经历了这一切，婴儿罗宾却越发地健壮了。他很幸运，只吃新鲜煮熟的食物，靠米饭和汤果腹。没有人故意安排这一切，但这可能解释了他为什么没有像其他人那样闹肚子。琴每天背着他，她自己的健康也绝对比他们离开帕农时要好。她在巴生烧了五天，但有一段时间，痢疾没有找她麻烦，她胃口很好。由于一直暴露在太阳下面，她被晒得黝黑，臀上的孩子也随着晒黑了。

塞伦班在铁路沿线上，她们希望可以从那里坐火车南下新加坡。他们大约在四月中旬到达塞伦班，但那里没有他们可坐的火车。铁路被限制使用，可能不通新加坡。不久他们又被迫上路去淡边，但出发之前，他们又失去了一个成员。

失踪的人叫埃伦·福布斯，就是那个从英国出来找对象却没找着的未婚姑娘。在跟她密切接触的这几个月里，琴深刻地理解到她为什么找不着对象。埃伦空虚无聊，自由散漫，爱开玩笑，跟日本兵随意打闹，令其他女士嗤之以鼻。在塞伦班，他们住在小镇外面一个满是日本兵的校舍里。白天的时候，埃伦无缘无故消失了，他们再也没见到她。

琴和霍斯福尔太太要求见军官，并向军官汇报了这个案子，说她们有一个同伴失踪了，可能是被士兵们绑架了。军官承诺进行调查，但毫无下文。两天后，他们收到南下淡边的命令，在看守的监视下出发了。

他们在淡边停留了几天。食物太少了，实际上他们都在挨饿。在他们的迫切恳求下，当地的指挥官派人监视他们南下去了马六甲，说那里可能有船。但马六甲也没有船，那里的负责军官又把他们打发回淡边。他们拖着沉重的步子，绝望地往回走。在亚罗牙加，茱迪·汤姆逊去世了。留在淡边不可避免地意味着更多的死亡。所以他们建议，应该让他们继续南下步行去新加坡，于是指挥官派了一个下士押送他们去金马士。

五月中旬，途经亚逸古宁时，霍斯福尔太太去世了。她得过疟疾，两个月前又原因不明地发烧，实际上一直没有康复。她总是不定期地重复发低烧，琴不禁怀疑她到底是不是患了疟疾。不论得的是什么病，总之她变得十分虚弱。在亚逸古宁，她又得了痢疾，两天后就去世了。也许是心脏衰竭或者劳累过度。弗里思太太接管了庄妮·霍斯福尔所操心的事情。她是一个病得变了色的小个子女士，已经五十多岁了，一直都病恹恹的，好像总是徘徊在死亡的边缘。新的责任给她注入了活力，从那天起她越变越精神，晚上也听不到她呻吟了。

三天后，他们到达金马士。就跟以往在镇上的时候一样，他们被安置在校舍里。镇上的日本指挥官二须井大尉当天晚上去检查他们。他对他们之前的事一无所知。这些日本军官总是这样，琴已经习以为常。她解释说他们是被迫远行去新加坡战俘营的俘虏。

他说：“战俘不去新加坡。严格的命令。你们从哪里来？”

“我们都走了两个多月了，”她说，在经历了无数次的失望后，她变得非常淡定，“我们必须住进战俘营，不然我们都要死掉。路上已经死了七个人。原来被俘的时候，我们有三十二个人，现在只有二十五个。我们不能一直这样走下去。我们必须住进新加坡的战俘营。您必须理解。”

他说：“不能再有战俘去新加坡。很抱歉，但这是严格的命令。太多战俘在新加坡。”

她说：“但是，二须井大尉，那不可能指女囚犯，那肯定说的是男战俘。”

“不能再有战俘去新加坡，”他说，“严格命令。”

“那好吧，那我们可以在这里留下来，给自己建一个战俘营，并请你们给我们派一个医生吗？”

他眯起眼：“没有战俘留在这里。”

“但是我们要怎么做？我们可以去哪里？”

“很可怜，”他说，“明天我告诉你们去哪里。”

他走后，她回去找她的同伴。“你们都听见了，”她平静地说，“他说无论如何不会让我们去新加坡。”

这个消息对于他们而言几乎没有意义。他们已经习惯了这种单调的生活，永远与新加坡隔着千山万水。“看起来哪儿都不想要我们。”普莱斯太太沉重地说，“波比，如果再让我看到你挑逗艾米，我就像你老爸那样揍你一顿。马上，我说到做到。”

弗里思太太说：“如果他们不管我们，我们就可以去找一个小村庄，在那里生活，等这一切结束。”

琴盯着她。“他们不可能养活我们，”她慢慢地说，“我们跟着日本兵才有食物。”但这个想法萌芽后，一直留在她的脑海里。

“多么珍贵稀有的食物！”弗里思太太说，“有生之年我都不会忘记淡边这个可怕的地方。”

第二天，二须井大尉来了。“你们现在去关丹，”他说，“关丹的女士战俘营。很好。你们会高兴的。”

琴不知道关丹在哪里。她问：“关丹在哪里？远吗？”

“关丹在海边，”他说，“你们现在去那里。”

后面有人说：“有好几百英里远。在东海岸。”

“好吧，”二须井大尉说，“在东海岸。”

“我们可以坐火车去那里吗？”琴询问道。

“抱歉，没有火车。你们走，十，十五英里每天。你们很快到那里。你们会很高兴。”

她轻轻地说：“已经有七个人在这次长途跋涉中去世了，大尉。如果您强迫我们从这里走去关丹，会有更多人死去。我们可以坐卡车去那里吗？”

“对不起，没有卡车，”他说，“你们很快去到那里。”

他想让他们马上动身，但已是早上十一点了，他们誓死不从。通过耐心的谈判，琴迫使他同意第二天黎明再起程，这是她能做的最大限度的争取了。但是，她确实说服了他当天晚上给他们提供一顿丰盛的晚饭——肉炖米饭，外加每人一根香蕉。

从金马士到关丹有大约一百七十英里，没有直达的路。五月最后一周，他们离开了金马士。按照之前的速度计算，琴想，他们去到那里需要六周。此前他们从未连续走过那么远的路。之前每走五十英里就有希望可以坐上交通工具，而现在他们要连续走六周，而且还不知道到达目的地后有没有喘息的机会。没有人真的相信关丹有战俘营。

“你犯了一个错误，亲爱的，”弗里思太太说，“居然求他让我们留在这里，并给我们建个战俘营。看得出来他不喜欢这个主意。”

“他只是想甩掉我们，”琴疲倦地说，“他们不想我们在这里碍手碍脚——只是想把我们打发走。”

第二天早上，一个中士和另一个士兵看守押送他们上路。金马士是一个铁路枢纽，东海岸的铁路经过这里，连接向北走的铁路。铁路那时闲置着。有传言说日本军队将拆除这条铁路，把铁路材料运送到北方一个秘密战略目的地。女人们并不关心这种事，她们满心在想的是，她们要在一天大部分时间里走在烈日之下，没有火车捎她们一程。

他们每隔一天走上十英里。一个星期后，许多孩子都发烧了。她们永远都不知道那到底是什么病。是从小艾米·普莱斯开始的。她出了疹子，体温飙升，还流鼻涕。可能是麻疹。当时的条件不可能允许她们把孩子们隔离开来。接下来几周孩子们全部被传染了。艾米·普莱斯慢慢康复了，但等她好到能走路的时候，另外七个孩子又倒下了。她们一筹莫展，只能不断擦洗这些汗流如注的小脸庞，给疲倦的孩子们降温，并不断把衣服洗净晒干，将他们身上湿透的衣服换掉。疾病在一个叫作马口的地方达到高潮。他们住在车站里，在售票处、候车厅和月台。很不巧地，在他们到达的三天前，马口有一个日本军医，但他坐卡车朝瓜拉基亚旺的方向去了。她们请首领派人跑去追他，但没追上。没有人能帮助她们。

在马口，四个小孩去世了：哈里·科勒德，苏珊·弗莱彻，只有三岁的多丽丝·西蒙斯，还有弗雷迪·霍兰。琴自然最关心弗雷迪，但她也无能为力。在他发烧的第一天，她就猜到他会去世，那时她已经积累起许多悲伤的经验。在有些人——甚至包括幼小的孩子——对待自身所患疾病的态度里，似乎隐藏着某种信息，预示死亡即将降临。大约是一种萎靡不振的状态，仿佛在说他们已经太累，没有气力为生存作斗争。那个时候，她们已经变得很坚强，能够面对死亡的现实。她们不再深陷于悲伤和哀悼之中，明白到死亡是一个事实，必须避开它，或者和它作斗争，但是当它降临的时候——好吧，它不过是那些不得不去面对的事实之一。一个人死了以后，有一些事情要做：伸直四肢，挖坟墓，做十字架，在日记里记载死者姓名和坟墓的确切位置。也就是这样了，她们没有力量再回头细想。

琴现在更关心霍兰太太的情况。埋葬了弗雷迪之后，她尝试把婴儿交给艾琳照顾，最近几周琴一直负责给罗宾喂食，照顾他，把他背在臀上，她觉得自己离不开这个小宝贝儿了。在两个更年长的孩子去世后，琴将他交还给艾琳照料。这么做不是因为她想甩掉他，而是因为她觉得艾琳·霍兰需要一个精神寄托，她想这个孩子应该可以让她提起精神来。但这个试验并不成功。艾琳那个时候已经虚弱到无法抱着小孩走路，也无法召集起足够的力气和他玩耍了。更重要的是，比起自己母亲，这个婴儿明显更喜欢这位年轻的女士，因为他在她背上度过了如此多的光阴。

“他仿佛已经不再属于我了，”霍兰太太有一次说，“你带着他吧，亲爱的，他喜欢跟你待在一起。”从那时起，她们一起照顾他，艾琳给他喂食，琴陪他玩耍。

他们继续上路，把四个小坟墓留在马口的铁路信号房后面。她们抬着两个竹竿担架走在铁路上，把最虚弱的孩子轮流放在上面。跟从前一样，她们发现这两个日本看守也很人道，很讲道理。他们习惯粗野，完全不能理解西方人的思维方式，但他们对虚弱的女人很宽容，也为孩子们付出了很多。一连几个小时，中士步履沉重地走着，肩上扛一个孩子，手里抓住担架的一头，把来复枪放在担架上，孩子的旁边。和往常一样，他们遇到了语言不通的问题。她们那时学会了一些日本单字，但只有琴能够说流利的马来语。正是她负责向村子里的人问路，并不时为日本人做翻译。

弗里思太太使琴非常惊讶。她年过五十，是一个衰老的小个子女人，总是一副半死不活的样子。远行初期，她非常虚弱，并没完没了地作邪恶的预言，使她们非常厌烦。她们平常已经麻烦缠身，前路的艰辛，她们不愿去想。但自从弗里思太太接替了庄妮·霍斯福尔太太的角色之后，仿佛重获新生。她的健康改善了，现在她的步履和其他人一样有力。她在马来亚住了十五年左右，只能说几个马来单字，但她对于这个国度及其疾病的知识非常丰富。她很开心大家能走去关丹。“那里很不错，”她说，“比在西部健康多了，那里的人也好一些。我们一到那儿就会没事的。相信我。”

随着时间的流逝，琴越来越频繁地求助于弗里思太太，请她提出一些建议，好让他们在困境里过得舒服一些。

在亚逸克宁，霍兰太太的力气用尽了。她在路上倒下了两次，她们轮流搀扶着她走。把她放到竹轿上去是不可能的，因为即使她现在已经大大消瘦了下去，依然重八英石。那时大家都疲惫不堪，没有人可以抬着那么大的负重走远路。而且，把她放在竹轿上就意味着要把一个孩子挤下来，这个想法本身就让她无法接受。她咬着牙踉踉跄跄地走到村子里，整个人都变了颜色，就像之前的科勒德太太一样。那是一个不祥的征兆。

亚逸克宁是火车站附近的一个小村庄，没有车站大楼。经过交涉，首领把一个屋子腾出来给他们住，就像之前好几回那样。她们把霍兰太太安置在一个阴凉的角落里，给她做了一个枕头，并帮她洗脸。她们没有白兰地或者其他酒可以给她喝了。她无法躺下来休息，只好强坐着，所以她们把她留在角落里，让她靠着墙。她当天晚上喝了一点汤，但吃不下任何食物。她知道自己的生命已经到了尽头。

“我很抱歉，亲爱的，”夜深人静的时候，她轻声说，“抱歉给你添了这么多麻烦。我替比尔感到伤心。如果你再看见他，请告诉他不要苦恼。告诉他，如果他能找到一个好人，不要介意再婚。他还年轻。”

过了一两个小时，她又说：“我真的觉得，你这样背着宝宝很可爱。他真幸运，不是吗？”

早上的时候，她仍然活着，但已经失去了意识。她们用尽了一切办法——当然她们也没有多少办法可以用了，但她的呼吸越来越微弱，差不多到中午的时候，她去世了。她们当晚把她葬在村子的穆斯林墓地里。

在亚逸克宁，他们进入了一路走来最不健康的地区。马来亚中部的大山目前在他们左边，也就是西边，因为他们正在往北走。他们来到彭亨河上游地区，这是一条向东流入东海岸的河流。在这里，它分成数不清的支流，如孟旷河，巴塘河，白浪鼓河，等等。这些支流流经地势平坦的农村地区，形成一个长满灌木和红树林的沼泽区，沿着他们的步行路线绵延四十英里。这是一个蛇和鳄鱼丛生的区域，蚊子多得无法想象。白天的时候，这里潮湿翳闷，热得让人窒息；晚上却笼罩在湿冷无情的浓雾中，冷得让人发抖。

进入这个地区的第二天，有几个人发起了烧。跟以往由疟疾引起的那种烧不一样，体温不会升到很高，可能是登革热。那个时候她们几乎没有办法对付它，并不是因为她们没有钱，而是因为在那种热带丛林的村子里，根本就没有药。琴咨询了中士，他建议他们加快步伐，尽快走出这个鬼地方。琴自己也发起了烧，所有东西都在她面前模糊地摇晃着。她头痛欲裂，无法集中精神看东西。她咨询了出奇健康的弗里思太太。

“他说得对，宝贝儿，”弗里思太太宣称，“不走出这个沼泽地带，你们就不会好起来。我想我们应该每天都往前走，如果你问我的话。”

琴强迫自己集中精神：“西蒙斯太太怎么办？”

“如果她的情况恶化，也许可以请士兵们背着她。——不知道，我也拿不准。这确实艰难，但我们必须走。我们最好走，走出去。这就是我的看法。我们在这个糟糕的地方逗留绝对没有什么好处。”

那之后他们不再隔天休息，而是每天上路，踉踉跄跄地，生着病，发着烧，虚弱不堪。琴背着的那个婴儿，罗宾·霍兰也发了烧，这是他第一次得病。她让门里村的首领看看他，首领的妻子用一种树皮制作了一剂热腾腾的溶液，盛在一个肮脏的椰子壳里拿给她。琴尝了尝，觉得很苦，所以她觉得那里面含有奎宁。她给婴儿喝了一点儿，自己也喝了一些，当天晚上就起效了。第二天上路之前，另外几个女士也喝了一些，这对她们的病情很有帮助。

他们花了十一天才走出沼泽地，过了淡马鲁，来到一个更高的地带。他们把西蒙斯太太和弗莱彻太太留在后面，还有小吉莲·汤姆逊。当他们进入了这个更健康的地区，终于敢停留一天稍事休息的时候，琴已经虚弱不堪，但烧总算是退了。婴儿还活着，不过明显生了病，醒着时哭个不停。

现在是弗里思太太在鼓舞着他们，就像早些时候她使大家沮丧一样。“从现在起一切都会好起来，”她告诉他们，“我们越靠近海岸，就会变得越精神。东海岸很舒服，有漂亮的沙滩，总是海风习习，而且很健康。”

他们不久来到山顶上一个隐藏在丛林深处的村庄。他们从来都不晓得它叫什么名字。它在增卡河上方。此时他们已经离开了铁路，在一条丛林小路上往东走，这条小路很可能会接上通向关丹的大路。这个村子很凉快，空气清新，村民善良好客。他们给女士们一间屋子歇息，还提供食物和新鲜水果。相同的树皮溶液也能治疗发烧。他们在那里待了六天，陶醉于新鲜清冽的微风和清爽宜人的夜晚。他们终于再次踏上行程的时候，状态比之前好多了。他们留了一个小胸针给首领，作为对村民们提供食物和照顾的报酬。它原来属于弗莱彻太太，他们想这位逝者应该不会提出反对意见。

四天后的晚上，他们来到了马兰。一条横穿马来半岛的柏油路穿过马兰，连接关丹和吉宁。这个村子可能有五十间屋子，一所学校，和几间当地商店。他们在马路上走了大概一英里半，去到村子的北边。在铁轨和丛林小路上走了五周之后，这条马路上的现代文明迹象使他们欣喜若狂。他们迈着轻快的步子走向村子。突然，他们看见前面停着两辆卡车。有两个白人男人在修理它们，日本看守在旁监视。

他们快步向卡车走去，发现那上面装满铁轨和枕木。卡车面朝关丹方向停着。其中一辆被从车上搬下来的枕木顶了起来，两个白人男人躺在车底下修理后轴。他们穿着短裤和军靴，没穿袜子，皮肤被太阳晒得黝黑，身上被后轴上的泥巴弄得脏兮兮的。但他们都是肌肉发达的健壮男士，尽管精瘦精瘦，但身体状况良好。他们都是白人，这是女人们五个月来第一次见到白人男性。

他们把卡车团团围住。他们的看守开始用断断续续的日语和卡车看守说话。其中一个白人男人面朝上躺在车轴底下，手里摆弄着螺丝扳手，瞥眼看着视野范围内的赤脚和纱笼，一边慢悠悠地说：“告诉那些脏兮兮的日本人让那些脏兮兮的女人挪开一点，给我们透点光。”

一些女人笑了，弗里思太太说：“不许那样跟我说话，年轻人。”

男人们从卡车底下翻出来，坐到地上，盯着女人们和孩子们看，看棕色的皮肤，纱笼和赤脚。“刚才是谁在说话？”拿着螺丝扳手的人问，“你们谁会说英语？”他慢悠悠地拉长调子说话，每两个单词之间都好像有停顿。

琴笑道：“我们都是英国人。”

他盯着她看，注意到编成马尾的黑发，棕色的手臂和双脚，纱笼，以及背在臀上的棕色婴儿。她穿着脏兮兮的衬衫，开领处有一道白色的皮肤。“海峡土生白人(3)？”他冒昧地问道。

“不是，真正的英国人——我们全是，”她说，“我们是俘虏。”

他站起来。他是一个金发青年，很健壮，二十七八岁。“真的？”他说。

她听不懂他说的话(4)。“你也是战俘吗？”她问。

他慢慢地微笑了。“我们是战俘吗？”他重复了一遍，“哦，老天！”

这个男人身上有一种什么东西是她从来没有碰到过的。“你是英国人吗？”她问。

“当然不是，”他拖着那种慢条斯理的调子说，“我们是澳洲人。”

她说：“你们住在这里的战俘营吗？”

他摇头。“我们从关丹来，”他说，“但我们整天都在开车，把这些东西运到海边去。”

她说：“我们要去关丹，去那里的女子战俘营。”

他盯着她看。“那一开始就是一个骗局，”他慢悠悠地说，“关丹那里没有什么女子战俘营。只有一个给我们建造的临时战俘营，因为我们是卡车司机。谁告诉你关丹有一个女子战俘营的？”

“日本人告诉我们的。他们负责把我们送去那里，”她叹了一口气，“那只是又一个谎言。”

“那些可恶的日本人信口开河，”他慢慢地微笑了，“我还以为你们是一大群土著(5)呢，”他说，“你说你们是英国人，真的？一路从英国来？”

她点点头。“是的。我们有些人已经在马来亚待了十到十五年，但我们都是英国人。”

“还有这些孩子们——他们也都是英国人？”

“全部都是。”她说。

他慢悠悠地笑了：“我从来没有想过会与一个长成你这样的英国女士说话。”

“你长得也不怎么样。”琴说。

另一个男人正在和另一群女人聊天。弗里思太太、普莱斯太太和琴在一起。他转向琴她们。“你们从哪里来？”他问道。

弗里思太太说：“我们在西海岸那头的帕农被抓住了，在等船接我们离开的时候。”

“但是，你们现在从什么地方来？”

琴说：“日本兵要送我们去关丹。”

“不是一路从帕农来？”

她立刻笑道：“我们到处去——瑞天咸港，波德申——到处走来走去。没有人想要我们。我想我们走了差不多有五百英里了。”

“哦，老天，”他说，“那听起来像一个骗局。要是你们没待在战俘营里，上哪儿找‘塔克’？”

她没听懂。“塔克？”

“你们吃什么？”

“每天晚上我们都在村子里过夜，”她说，“我们必须找个歇脚的地方。可能就在这样一个地方，也可能是在学校里。我们从村子里找到什么就吃什么。”

“看在上帝的分上，”他说，“等我一下，我去告诉我哥们儿。”他猛地转向他的同伴。“你听到他们遇到的那个骗局了吗？”他说，“被抓后就一直被迫走来走去。从来没有进过战俘营。”

“她们跟我讲的就是这个，”另一个说，“这些可恶的日本人就是这么做事。让人作呕。”

第一个男人回身问琴：“你们生了病的话怎么办？”

她嘲讽地说：“如果生病了，要不就好起来，要不就死掉。我们过去三个月里没有见到过一个医生，我们实际上也没有药了。所以我们差不多全死了。我们被抓的时候有三十二个人，现在只剩下十七个了。”

澳洲人轻轻地说：“哦，老天！”

琴说：“你们今天晚上会在这里过夜吗？”

他说：“你们呢？”

“我们会留在这里，”她说，“我们明天也还会留在这里，除非他们让我们坐你们的卡车。我们不能让孩子们每天都走，得走一天歇一天。”

他说：“如果你们留下来，土著太太，那我们也留下来。我们可以修理修理这根可恶的轴，让它再也转不起来，如果有需要的话。”他停下来，缓慢地思索着。“你们没有药吗？”他说，“你们想要什么？”

她很快地说：“你们有芒硝吗？”

他摇摇头，说：“那就是你们想要的？”

“我们一点芒硝都没有了，”她说，“我们想要奎宁，还有可以治疗这些孩子身上所有皮肤病的药物。这里有吗？”

他慢慢地说：“我去试着找一下。你们有钱吗？”

弗里思太太哼了一声：“在跟着日本人走了六个月之后？他们拿走了我们身上所有的东西。连我们的结婚戒指也不放过。”

琴说：“我们还剩下一点珠宝，如果有人买的话，就有钱了。”

他说：“我先试试，看能做点什么。你们去找地方睡觉吧，回头见。”

“好的。”

她回去找中士，向他鞠了一躬，因为那能使他高兴，这样一来事情就会变得对他们更加有利。她说：“军曹，今晚哪里歇息？孩子们必须歇息。我们去见首领，关于歇息和食物？”

他和她一起去找到首领，交涉借用校舍来安置俘虏的事情，并且请求首领提供大米作为食物。他们没有像过去那样遭到断然拒绝，因为那时候他们有三十人，现在人数变少了，提供住宿和食物就变得容易多了。他们在校舍里安顿下来，开始处理例行琐事，洗洗刷刷，这占据了他们大部分的空余时间。在关丹没有女子战俘营的消息，虽然是他们都早就暗中预料到的，还是不免有点令人失望。但两位澳大利亚男士带来的新鲜感对此作出了补偿，因为他们一直在严格的看管下，过着一成不变的无聊生活。

澳洲小伙们又回去修理卡车。他们在后轴底下交头接耳，刚才和琴说话的金发青年说：“这么下作的骗局真是闻所未闻。我们可以怎样修理这个混账家伙，好让我们今天晚上能够留下来？我跟她们说，我要试着给她们弄点药。”

他们已经修理好刹车卡滞的问题，正是这个问题使得内侧轮毂过热，导致卡车无法前进。另外一个说：“把整个混账的轮毂卸下来瞧一眼，把传动轴从差速器里拉出来。那会弄得脏兮兮的一团糟，并意味着我们要睡在卡车里。”

“我说我要试着搞点药来。”他们又干了一会儿。

“你打算怎么办？”

“汽油，我想。那是最容易的。”

天快黑的时候，他们从后轴里把带着键槽的金属传动轴抽了出来，这个东西有四英尺长，非常沉。他们把滴着黑油的传动轴拿给负责看守他们的日本下士看，作为他们辛勤工作的证据。“今晚在这里休息。”他们说。下士心下怀疑，但还是同意了。实际上他也只能同意。他走开去给他们安排晚饭，让跟着他的士兵留下来看守他们。

金发青年借口上厕所离开了卡车，趁着夜色后撤到一座房子的后面，迅速在一排房子后溜了下去，来到大街上。他在大街上跑了几千码，去到村子另一头。这里有一个中国人，开一辆破旧的公共汽车。澳洲人定期地在这条路上开车来回跑，在多次穿过马兰的旅途中注意到了这个地方。

澳洲人用慢悠悠的语气轻声地说：“哥们儿，买不买汽油？你出多少钱？”语言不通所造成的障碍，在一个有心买的人和一个有心卖的人之间，竟然是如此的小。在谈判中，他们一度通过写字来交流，澳洲人用大写字母在一张包装纸的碎片上写道：“芒硝和奎宁和皮肤病药膏”。

他带着三个两加仑的罐子和一条橡胶管溜回房子背后，把这些东西藏在公共厕所后面。不久他就回到卡车去，招摇地扣上短裤上的纽扣。

大约十点钟，趁尚未夜深人静，他摸黑找到校舍。本应有一个日本士兵整晚值勤看管他们，但在过去五周里面，妇女们并没有在两名看守面前表现出最轻微的逃跑倾向，所以这两位看守早就放弃了晚上的监视。澳洲人弄清楚他们的确切位置，待看见那两个日本兵和卡车看守蹲到一起，他马上悄无声息地来到了学校。

门开着，他站在门口，轻声问道：“下午是哪位女士和我聊天来着？背着婴儿的那个。”

琴睡着了。她们把她摇醒，她套进纱笼，套上上衣，出来到门前。他给她带了几个小包裹。“那是奎宁，”他说，“如果你还有需要的话，我可以再去弄一些。我找不到芒硝，但中国人用这种东西治疗痢疾。上面都是中文，按他的意思，每隔四小时用三片这种叶子泡温水喝。那是一个成年人的量。如果有效，把标签留好，在其他中国药店也可以买到。还有这个青草膏是用来涂的。如果你还想要的话，还有很多。”

她感激地把药收下。“真是太棒了，”她温柔地说，“花了多少钱？”

“没关系，”他慢条斯理地说，“日本人付的账，但他们不知道。”

她又谢谢他。“你在这里干什么？”她问，“你们要开车去哪里？”

“关丹，”他说，“本来我们今晚就应该到达那里，但是本·莱格特——我哥们儿——他把卡车拆碎了，只好作罢。明天下午再去。不过，如果方便的话，我们还可以多留一天，虽然我觉得需要冒点险。”他告诉她，他们有六个人，为日本人开着六辆卡车。他们定期从关丹开去内地，跑上大约一百三十英里，到铁路沿线一个叫而连突的地方。花一天时间到达而连突后，他们拆下铁路的枕木和铁轨，装满卡车，第二天再开回关丹。在关丹，他们把铁路材料卸在码头周围，有船来把东西运到一个未知的目的地。“我想他们是要在另一个地方建一条新铁路吧。”他说。一百三十英里很远，在这种热带条件下开着满载的卡车，一天勉强能走完。如果无法在天黑之前赶到关丹，就找一个村庄过夜。关丹的日本兵不会注意到他们缺席。

他在柔佛被俘后，一直在做这项工作，大概已经有两个月了。“比待在战俘营好。”他说。通往学校的台阶有三级，她坐在最上面一级，他在她面前的地上坐下来。她觉得他的坐姿很有意思，因为他像本地人一样一条腿坐在脚后跟上，但却伸出左腿。“你是澳大利亚的卡车司机吗？”她问道。

“才不是呢，”他说，“我是个套环(6)。”

她说：“‘套环’是什么？”

“我是个牧工，”他说，“我在昆士兰出生，就在克朗克里后面，我全家都是昆士兰人。我爸从伦敦来，来自一个叫作哈默斯密斯的地方。他过去是开出租的，但他很懂马，所以就出来到昆士兰，为科布马车公司(7)工作，并遇到了我妈。但我很久没回克朗克里了。我在它西边的北领地(8)工作，在一个叫作沃拉华的农场。那里大概离斯普林斯西南一百一十英里。”

她笑道：“那斯普林斯在哪里？”

“爱丽丝，”他说，“爱丽丝斯普林斯。在澳大利亚正中央，达尔文和阿德莱德中间。”

她说：“我还以为澳大利亚中部都是沙漠呢。”

她的无知引起了他的关心。“哦，老天，”他慢悠悠地说，“爱丽丝是个很棒的地方。那里水源充足，人们整晚开着水龙头，给草地浇水。就是那样，他们整晚开着水龙头。不过当然了，北领地大部分地区都很干旱，但小河边的牧草通常很茂盛。只要你找一找，就会发现河边到处都有水。虽然只有在雨季的时候河里才有水，但即使是在干涸的时候，只要你往下挖不到一英尺，就一定能找到水源。就是那样，即使是在干旱地带的中央也一样。”不知道为什么，他说话的调子又慢又平，听起来非常舒服。“你去到一个类似的地方，就能看见沙地上满是小洞，那是袋鼠和岩大袋鼠挖来找水喝的。它们知道上哪儿找水喝。内地到处都有水，但你要知道去哪里找。”

“你在这个叫作沃拉华的地方做什么？”她问道，“看羊吗？”

他摇摇头。“在爱丽丝地区，你是找不着绵羊的，”他说，“那里对它们来讲太热了。沃拉华是一个牛场。”

“你们有几头牛？”

“我离开的时候，大概有一万八千头吧，”他说，“数量上上下下的，根据湿度情况。”

“一万八千头？有多大啊？”

“沃拉华？大概两千七百吧。”

“两千七百英亩啊，”她说，“真够大的。”

他盯着她看。“不是英亩，”他说，“是平方英里。沃拉华有两千七百平方英里大。”

她惊呆了。“但那全是一个地方吗——我是说，一个牧场？”

“是一个牛场，”他回答，“归一个人单独所有。”

“但那要多少人才能经营得了它啊？”

他满怀感情地任思绪在记忆犹新的场景中驰骋。“有杜维恩先生，汤米·杜维恩——他是经理，然后是我——我是牧工头，或者以前是。汤米说，他会留一个位置给我，等我回去的。我希望能再回到沃拉华，在未来某一天……”他沉思了一会儿。“我们还有另外三个牧工——都是白人，”他说，“然后有快乐、月光、金块儿、雪白和柏油路……”他想了想。“我们有九个土著，”他说，“就那么多了。”

“九个什么？”

“长得很黑的家伙——土著牧工。土著。”

“但那也只有十三个人。”她说。

“是的，如果你算上杜维恩先生的话就有十四个。”

“但是十四个人能看得住那么多牛吗？”她问。

“哦，当然了，”他边想边说，“从某个意义上讲，沃拉华是一个很好管理的牧场，因为它没有篱笆。天然的屏障把它围了起来。北面有帕默河和利维山；西边是沙地，牛不去那里边；南边有科诺特山和奥默罗德山，东边有孖岗山。十四个人足够管理那样一个牧场了。如果多几个白人就更容易了，但是雇不到。那些可恶的土著，他们总是动不动就要去丛林流浪(9)。”

“那是什么？”她问。

“丛林流浪？哦，土著牧工总是冷不丁地走到你面前说：‘老板，我现在去丛林流浪。’然后就离开牧场，只穿着短裤，戴着旧帽子，带着枪——要是他们有的话，要不然就拿着矛和飞标，你留不住他们。他们到处乱走，消失两到三个月。”

“但他们要去哪里？”她问道。

“就是瞎逛。他们每次都要走很远——哦，老天，”他说，“四百到五百英里。走够了就回到牧场继续工作。土著的麻烦就在于，你永远都不知道他们下周会不会来上班。”

接下来是一段短暂的沉默。在热带的夜色中，这两位背井离乡的年轻人一起安静地坐在校舍台阶上。狐蝠在他们头上的月光里飞来飞去，像皮革一样的翅膀扇出清脆的沙沙声。“一万八千头牛……”她思考着说。

“差不多吧，”他说，“水源充足的时候，会升至两万一千或者两万两千头。然后就会迎来干旱的一年，数量直线下降到一万两千或者一万三千。我想我们每年都会因为干旱而损失三千头牛。”

“但你们不能把它们带到有水的地方去吗？”

他慢慢地笑道：“只靠十四个人是不够的。每年在北领地和北昆士兰死于干渴的牛足以养活整个英格兰。当然了，在沃拉华还有马，所以情况更糟糕。”

“马？”

“哦，老天，”他说，“我们有大约三千匹野马，但它们一点用都没有——它们是害虫。沃拉华几年前有一个马场，把马卖给印度军队，但现在你不能卖马了。我们会使用一些马，当然——大约一百匹，和驮马一起。你没法消灭它们，除非把它们射死，但你永远都找不到一个会去射杀马匹的牧工。它们吃掉给牛吃的牧草，并把草地给毁了。牛不喜欢在被马吃过的地方吃草。”

她问：“沃拉华有多大？——多长？多宽？”

他说：“哦，让我说的话，最宽的地方大概东西九十英里，南北四十五到五十英里。但它是一个很容易管理的牧场，因为牧场住宅设在中央附近，往哪个方向走都不会很远。去科诺特山是最远的，大概要走六十英里。”

“从牧场住宅去要六十英里？你就住在牧场住宅里？”

“是的。”

“其他地方还有住宅吗？”

他盯着她。“每个牧场只有一处牧场住宅。有的会有分牧场，在上面建个棚屋什么的，牧工们可以在那里放一些毯子和食物，但这种情况不多。”

“那需要多长时间才能去到最远的地方——科诺特山呢？”

“到科诺特山去？哦，好吧，来回需要花一个星期。那是骑马去，如果开越野车去的话，一天半就够了。但骑马最好，虽然有点慢。骑驮马不会比走路快，如果你爱惜它。跟电影里人们策马狂奔到处去的情景完全不一样——哦，老天。要是在北领地这样做的话，不消一会儿就会把马给骑坏了。”

他们在一起坐了超过一个小时，在校舍入口轻声交谈。最后，牧工从他奇怪的姿势中站起身来，说：“我不能再留在这儿了，不然那些日本人回来后就该气得跳来跳去了。我哥们儿也是——他会以为我出了什么事。我跟他说我去烧水来着。”

琴站起来。“你人真是太好了，给我们找来这些东西。你不知道它们对我们有多重要。请告诉我，你叫什么名字？”

“乔·哈曼，”他说，“哈曼中士——牧工哈曼，他们有人这么叫我。”他迟疑了一下，说，“对不起，我今天叫你土著太太，”他尴尬地说，“那是个很蠢的笑话。”

她说：“我叫琴·佩吉特。”

“那听起来像一个苏格兰名字。”

“是的，”她说，“我不是苏格兰人，但我母亲来自帕斯。”

“我母亲生于一个苏格兰家庭，”他说，“来自因弗内斯。”

她伸出手。“晚安，中士，”她说，“跟另外一个白人聊天真是太令人愉快了。”

他抓住她的手。他的握手强而有力，给她带来了极大的安慰。“喂，佩吉特太太，”他说，“我会尝试说服日本人让你们坐我们的卡车往南走。如果这些小浑蛋们不同意，我们也没有办法。这样的话，在你们到达关丹之前，我们还会在路上相遇，到时我他妈的一定会给卡车做手脚。你们还想要别的什么东西？”

“肥皂，”她说，“你有可能给我们弄点肥皂吗？”

“应该可以。”他说。

“我们一点肥皂都没有了，”她说，“我们有一个小金盒，是一位过世的女士的，里面有一些头发。我看看能不能把它卖掉换点肥皂。”

“别卖，”他说，“我会帮你找到肥皂。”

“既然你已经帮我们找到了这些药，肥皂就是我们最急需的东西。”她说。

“请放心。”他迟疑了一下，然后说，“抱歉，我太唠叨了，跟你讲了那么多内地的事情，你一定觉得很无聊。只是，有时候不免情绪低落——不能让自己相信，还能再回到那个地方。”

“一点也不无聊，”她温柔地说，“晚安，中士。”

“晚安。”

早上，琴向同伴们展示她拿到的东西。“我听见你跟他谈了很久，”普莱斯太太说，“要我说，他真是个不错的小伙儿。”

“他是个有思乡病的小伙儿，”琴说，“他喜欢谈论他的牛场。”

“思乡病！”普莱斯太太说，“我们所有人都患着思乡病，不是吗？”

澳洲人当天早上和他们的看守进行了一场很聪明的辩论，但日本人断然拒绝了让女人们坐卡车南下的提议。在他们看来，这是有一定道理的，因为两辆卡车已经严重超载，再搭上十七个女人和孩子，增加的重量很可能就会最终把卡车压垮。要是卡车报废，就连看守自己都逃不过上级军官的鞭打。九十点钟的时候，哈曼和莱格特已经把后轴安装好，做好出发的准备。

乔·哈曼说：“让那个小浑蛋忙活一阵，我要把油管接头弄松。”他指那个日本看守。过了一会儿，在哈曼的带领下，他们松开油管接头，让一些汽油漏出来。看守并未注意到这一切。这样一来，卡车没油时，别人不会怀疑到他们身上来，也不会有人知道他们偷走六加仑汽油卖给了那个中国人。

从马兰到关丹有五十五英里。女人们在马兰休息了一天，第二天又开始沿着柏油路前进。当天晚上他们来到了一个叫作布湾的地方。琴一整天都在留心寻找乔·哈曼的卡车，希望能在它往回走的时候看见它。她不知道它因为汽油耗尽而在薄海滞留了一个晚上，耽误了回程。第二天，他们在布湾逗留了一天，住在一间以聂帕榈做屋顶的棚屋中。女人们轮流和琴一起到路边守候那辆卡车。他们的健康稍微有所改善。在经历了铁轨和森林小径之后，走在柏油路上感觉非常轻松，药物也已经开始起效。他们朝地势更高的地方走，环境越来越健康，想象力丰富的人已经在说他们能闻到海的味道了。和两位澳洲人的接触也明显提升了他们的士气。

乔·哈曼开卡车驶过布湾时没有遇到他们。然而，晚上有一个马来女孩给他们送去一个棕色纸的包裹，里面装着六块救生圈牌肥皂，包裹上写着佩吉特太太收，还有留言：

亲爱的女士：

现送上一些肥皂。目前我们只能找到这么多，但稍后我还会再找来一些。很抱歉没能与你见上面，但日本兵不让我们停车，所以我把这个包裹交给了马兰的中国人，他说他会转交给你。注意看我们，我会尝试在回程的时候停下来。

乔·哈曼

女人们都很高兴。“救生圈牌，”沃纳太太说，欣喜若狂地嗅着它们，“你都能闻到石炭的味道！我的乖乖，你想他们是上哪儿找来的？”

“我猜有两种可能性，”琴回答，“要不就是偷来的，要不就是用偷来的东西换来的。”实际上是后者。在薄海，澳洲人的日本看守在村子水井边洗脚时把靴子脱了下来。洗了三十秒后，他转过身来，发现靴子不见了。不可能是澳洲人干的，因为他们俩都马上出现在另外一个方向。这成了一个永久的谜。然而本·莱格特帮了大忙，当天晚上他从一个呼呼大睡的日本兵那里偷了一双靴子交给他们的看守，看守大大松了一口气，给了本一美元。

第二天，女人们走到了薄卡坡。他们进入了一个比从前好得多的地区，环境更宜人，也相对健康。那里的道路蜿蜒曲折，环绕山腰，几乎全部覆盖在树荫里。那天，他们第一次吃上了椰子。普莱斯太太有一双破旧的拖鞋，原来是霍斯福尔太太的，这几周她一直带在身上，从来没有穿过。一到薄卡坡，他们就用它换椰子，每人一个，想着椰汁里的维生素对她们有好处。在薄卡坡他们住在路边一个很大的聂帕榈顶椰子棚里。时近黄昏，两辆熟悉的卡车停在村子前，驾驶员是本·莱格特和乔·哈曼。就跟往常一样，车上装满了枕木和铁轨，目的地是海边。

琴带上几个同伴，和日本中士一起步行穿过马路去迎接他们。日本看守聚在一起说话，乔·哈曼转向琴。“我们不能在而连突及时装车，赶在今晚到达关丹了，”他说，“本找到了一头猪。”

“一头猪？”她们围住本的卡车，看见那头死猪躺在铁路材料上面。它是一头黑色的长鼻东方猪，好像受了点伤，身上盖满了苍蝇。在特卡姆河附近，本的车开在最前面，在路上发现了这头猪，就开车追着它跑了四分之一英里。坐在他身旁的日本看守用来复枪向它开了六枪，都没有打中，第七枪才终于打伤了它，本于是能够用一个前轮轧倒它。他们把车停下来，哈曼也在他们后面停车，两位澳洲人和日本看守七手八脚地把猪抬到铁路材料上面。他们在一位暴怒的中国店主面前发动卡车继续上路——那位中国店主声称那头猪是他的财产。哈曼轻声对琴说：“我们不得不让那些浑蛋日本人先吃个饱，并带走一些。交给我，我去看看能不能弄一些来给你们吃。”

当天晚上，那些女人拿到大约三十五磅煮熟的猪肉，它们被分成好几次偷偷摸摸送给他们。他们在椰子商店后面用椰子壳生火，把猪肉放进日本兵送来的米饭里炖着吃。他们吃得很省，再次出发前还可以吃三顿。吃完饭后，他们在屋里或路边闲坐。他们终于能够饱餐一顿，数月来第一次吃上了真正有营养的晚饭。不久，澳洲人过来找他们聊天。

乔·哈曼走到琴面前。“抱歉我不能再给你们送来更多的猪肉了，”他拖着慢悠悠懒洋洋的昆士兰腔调说，“都让那些混账日本人分没了。”

她说：“已经很棒了，乔。我们一直在吃，还留了很多明天吃呢。我都不记得我们上一次吃得这么好是在什么时候了。”

“我觉得这正是你们需要的，”他说，“要我说，你们身上都没有什么肉了。”

他在他们旁边的地上坐下来，坐到一只脚后跟上，用他那种特别的姿势。

“我知道我们现在很瘦，”琴说，“但已经比之前好看多了。你给我们用来代替芒硝的中药真的是很有效，它把皮肤病都治好了。”

“很好，”他说，“说不定我们可以从关丹多弄一些给你们。”

“那头猪真的是上帝赐予的礼物，”她说，“它，还有水果——我们今天买到了一些青椰子。我们一直都很幸运，没有得脚气病什么的。”

“那是因为我们有新鲜米饭，”弗里思太太出其不意地说，“在乡下，我们能一直吃上新鲜米饭。吃过时的米饭就会患脚气病。”

澳大利亚人若有所思地坐在那里，嚼着一根棍子。“对你们女士来讲，这真是一种有趣的生活，”他终于开口说道，“落到这么一个地方，吃得跟土著一样。这些日本人会遭报应的，他们作了那么多的孽，迟早有人找他们算账。”

他转向琴。“你们在马来亚都做什么？”他问道。

“我们中的大部分人都已经结婚了，”她说，“丈夫在马来亚工作。”

弗里思太太说：“我丈夫是铁路的地区工程处处长，我们曾经在加影有一间很漂亮的平房。”

哈曼说：“我想，所有的丈夫都被一起关在另一处吧？”

“对的，”普莱斯太太说，“我的亚瑟在新加坡。他在波德申时，我听到过他的消息。我想他们都在新加坡。”

“你们在这种乡下地方走来走去，他们却舒舒服服地待在战俘营里。”他说。

“是的，”弗里思太太说，“但是，不管怎样，能知道他们没事就很好。”

“在我看来，”哈曼说，“他们把你们踢来踢去，只是因为他们不知道该如何处置你们。对你们而言，在一个地方安顿下来，一直住到战争结束，应该不会很困难。比如说留在这里就很好。”

弗里思太太说：“我们一直就这么想。”

琴说：“我知道。自从弗里思太太提出这个主意，我就一直在考虑它。问题是，日本人给我们提供食物——或者说他们让村子给我们提供食物，却从来不付钱。如果我们要留在村子里，就必须挣钱养活自己，但我不知道我们要怎样才能做得到。”

哈曼说：“这只是个想法。”

过了一会儿他说：“我知道我可以上哪儿去找到几只鸡。如果找着了，后天我往北走的时候就捎给你们。”

琴说：“我们还没付你肥皂的钱呢。”

“算了，”他慢慢地说，“我也没有拿现金来买它，我用一双日本人的胶靴换来的。”他慢悠悠地告诉他们关于靴子的事情，就像在讲一个冷笑话。“你们得到肥皂，日本人得到一双新靴子，本得到一美元，”他说，“皆大欢喜。”

琴说：“你打算用同样的方法，给我们找来一只鸡吗？”

“我会给你们找来一只鸡的，总有办法的，”他说，“你们这些女士需要补充营养。”

她说：“别再冒险了。”

“你只需要管好自己的事情，土著太太，”他说，“有什么就拿什么吧。你别无选择。当你沦为战俘，只能有什么就拿什么。”

她笑道：“好吧。”事实上他叫她土著太太让她很开心，她和这个陌生男人之间，似乎有一种微妙的联系，好像他天生就该拿她的黑皮肤、她的土著穿着，还有她像马来女人那样将婴儿放在臀上的习惯开玩笑似的。“土著”这个词让她记住了澳大利亚，还有那些土著牧工。然后她想起来要问一个问题，部分是出于好奇，部分是由于她知道跟他聊他的祖国会令他愉快。“请告诉我，”她说，“在澳大利亚是不是很热？在你的家乡，是不是比这里还要热？”

“很热，”他说，“哦，老天，说热就热。沃拉华的气温可以高达一百一十八度——天热的时候。但跟这儿的热不一样。那是一种干热，不像在这儿的时候出那么多汗。”他想了想。“我有一次从马上摔了下来，”他说，“在试图给一匹野马戴上马鞍的时候。我摔断了大腿，被送往了医院。他们用一种灯照着我的大腿，他们叫它紫外线灯，说是能帮助肌肉康复之类的。你们在英国也有这样的东西吗？”

她点点头。“你们那里的热，就像被那种灯照着一样，是不是？”

“是的，”他说，“既温暖又干燥，是那种对你有好处，让你想喝冰镇啤酒的热。”

“那个国家看起来怎么样？”她问道。跟这个男人谈家乡能令他愉快。她想令他愉快，因为他对他们太好了。

“是红色的，”他说，“整个爱丽丝都是红色的，还有我的家乡也是。红色的土，红色的山。麦克唐奈，莱维斯，还有科诺特，都是红色的大山，坐落在蓝色的天空下。晚上它们会变紫，变成其他各种颜色。雨季过后，山上一片绿油油的。旱季时，它们有一部分变成银色，因为长了三齿桴。”他顿了顿，又道，“我想每个人都会喜欢自己的家园，”他轻轻地说，“爱丽丝周围的乡下地区就是我的家。人们坐甘号列车从阿德莱德和南方来。他们说爱丽丝是个差劲的地方。我只去过阿德莱德一次，我觉得它才差劲呢。斯普林斯周边的地方，对我来讲都很美。”

他陷入了沉思。“艺术家从南方过来，尝试把它画下来，”他说，“我只见过一个画得像的，他是一个土著，叫作艾伯特，住在赫曼斯堡。有一次有人给了他一把刷子和一些颜料，他就开始画，画出来比任何人都好。哦，老天，他画得真好。但他是个土著，他在画自己的家园。我想正是这个原因使他的画与众不同。”

他转向琴。“你的家乡在哪里？”他问，“你从哪里来？”

她说：“南安普敦。”

“轮船驶往的地方？”

“是的，就是那里。”她说。

“那儿是怎么样的？”他问。

她将婴儿挪到臀上，在纱笼里轻轻晃动双脚。“很安静，很凉快，很开心，”她边想边说，“不是特别美丽，尽管周围有漂亮的乡村——新森林，还有怀特岛。那里是我的家，就像你的斯普林斯。如果我能够熬过去，我就一定要回去，因为我太喜欢它了。”她顿了顿，“那里有个溜冰场，”她说，“当我还在上学的时候，常常在溜冰场上跳舞。总有一天我会回去，再去溜冰场跳舞。”

“我从来没有见过溜冰场，”从爱丽丝来的男人说，“我有见过照片，在电影里也见过。”

她说：“那实在是太有趣了……”

过了一会儿，他起身要走，她像往常一样把婴儿背在臀上，和他一起穿过马路向卡车走去。“我明天没法跟你见面了，”他说，“我们黎明就要出发。但后天我会沿路返回。”

“我想那天我们应该走在去薄海的路上。”她说。

“我会看看能不能给你找来那些鸡。”他说。

她转过身，面对着他，他站在她旁边，在被月光照得发亮的路中央，在热带夜晚的阵阵声响中。“喂，乔，”她说，“如果那意味着麻烦，我们不需要肉。你能给我们找到那些肥皂已经很了不起了。但你确实大大冒了一次险，偷了那家伙的靴子，让人后怕。”

“那没什么大不了的，”他慢悠悠地说，“只要你能找到窍门，就可以捉弄这些日本人。”

“你为我们做了很多了，”她说，“这些猪肉，还有药，还有肥皂。过去这几天我们的生活发生了极大的变化。我知道这些东西都是你冒险得来的。请一定要小心。”

“不用担心我。”他说，“我会尝试找些鸡肉，但如果我发现事情变得很危险，就会放弃。我不会把脖子伸出去让人砍的。”

“你发誓？”琴问道。

“不用担心我，”他说，“你自己已经有一堆麻烦事了，老天。只要我们活下来，就一定能熬过去。我们现在要做的就是活下去。活下去，再等两年，等战争结束。”

“你认为战争会打那么久吗？”她说。

“关于战争什么的，本比我在行，”他说，“他觉得大概要两年。”他向她微笑。“你们最好能拿到几只鸡。”

“请务必小心。”她说，“如果你被抓住，并为此付出生命的代价，我一辈子都不会原谅自己。”

“我不会有事的。”他说。他伸出手，好像要执起她的手，但又放下了。“晚安，土著太太。”他说。

她笑道：“你要是再叫我土著太太，我就用椰子打碎你的头。晚安，乔。”

“晚安。”

他们第二天早上没有看见他，不过听见了卡车开走的声音。那天他们按照习惯在薄卡坡休息，第二天继续步行去薄海。大约中午的时候，哈曼和莱格特驾驶的两辆卡车从他们身边经过，空车往北驶向而连突，两位司机都向女人们挥手致意，她们也挥手回应。坐在司机旁边的日本看守皱了皱眉头。没有鸡从卡车里掉出来，卡车也没有停下来。琴暂时松了一口气。她现在稍微摸到一点这些男人的脾气了。他们会无端把卡车停下来，不论冒多大的危险，都要获得他们认为对女人们有帮助的东西。没有鸡意味着没有麻烦，那一天余下的时间，她继续步行，踏实舒坦。

当天晚上，他们投宿于薄海的一座房子。一个马来小男孩拿着一个绿色的帆布袋去找琴，说是甘帮的一个中国人让他送来的。袋子里是五只黑色的小公鸡，全部活着，脚被绑住。在东部，家禽一般都是活着运输的。

它们的到来使琴左右为难。她找弗里思太太商量。她们不可能瞒过看守，暗地里把这些鸡杀死、拔毛并煮熟。看守发现后会问的第一个问题就是，这些公鸡是从哪里来的？如果琴知道这个问题的答案，编起谎话来就容易多了。她们认为，可以说这是用澳洲人给的钱买的，但如果中士问是从薄海什么地方买的，她们就答不上来了。不幸的是，薄海是一个不怎么友好的村子，让村子腾出一间屋子给女人们住都难上加难，而且她们并不寄希望于通过欺骗手段取得村民们的合作。最后她们决定，说她们用澳洲人给的钱买了这些鸡。在薄卡坡的时候，离马路两到三英里开外有一个叫利茂的小村庄，她们在那里付了钱，请村民把这几只小公鸡送到薄海给她们。这是一个不太经得起推敲的故事，一调查就会穿帮，但她们看不出来为什么有人要去调查它。

她们万分遗憾地做出了一个决定：分一只小公鸡给看守。牺牲一只公鸡作为礼物可以使得中士变得非常友好，同时把他拖下水，让他放弃对这些鸡的来龙去脉展开仔细认真的调查。于是，琴拿着袋子去找中士。

她向他鞠了一躬，让他的脾气变得好一点。“军曹，”她说，“今晚有好吃的。我们买了鸡。”她打开袋子，给他看躺在底部的几只小公鸡，并伸手进去拿出来一只。“给你。”她使尽浑身解数，尽量让自己看起来天真纯洁一些，微笑着向他说。

这对他来讲是一个很大的惊喜。他不知道她们这么有钱，从他监视她们那天起，她们一直除了椰子和香蕉之外什么都买不起。“你们买的？”他问。

她点点头。“从利茂。我们今晚都有很好的食物。”

“哪来的钱？”他问道。他并没有起疑心，因为她们以前从来没有欺骗过他，他只是感到好奇。

刹那间，有一个想法闪过琴的脑子：她可以说她们卖掉了一些珠宝。她突然产生了一种迅速的感觉，像直觉一样，就是不提澳洲人会更好。但她把这个想法放在了一旁。她必须坚持这个故事，因为它是她们从各个角度准备和考虑过的。“男战俘给我们钱买鸡，”她说，“他们说我们太瘦。现在我们晚上有好吃的，日本人和战俘都有。”

他举起两根手指，说：“两只。”

她怒火中烧。“一只，不是两只，军曹，”她说，“这是给你的礼物，因为你很好，一直带着孩子，而且批准我们慢慢走。只有五只，五只。”她给他看那个袋子，他仔细地数清楚了。直到那个时候，她才发现这几只公鸡大得出奇，而且浑身乌黑，在东方很少见。“一只给你，四只给我们。”

他把袋子放下，点点头，向她笑笑，把公鸡塞到腋下，往厨房走去——他正在那里做晚饭。

那天关丹简直像炸开了锅似的。当地的指挥官是一个渚蒲大尉。1943和1944年期间，这位大尉在泰缅铁路沿线的三〇二战俘营做出了诸多暴行，因此于1946年接受了远东国际军事法庭的审判，并被处死。这个故事发生的时候，他在关丹的职责是拆除马来亚东部铁路，将铁路材料送去海边，装船运往暹罗。他住在前任地区委员的房子里，这位地区委员养了一小批来亨鸡，大约有二十只，是在1939年特地从英国进口的。一天早晨，渚蒲大尉醒来时发现他二十只黑来亨鸡中的五只不见了，随之消失的还有一个绿色的袋子，那原来是用来装地区委员的邮件的，现在用来装家禽饲料。

渚蒲大尉是一个极易动怒的男人。他召来军事警察，命令他们马上展开调查。澳大利亚的卡车司机马上成为嫌疑对象，因为他们在该地区有一些小偷小摸的记录。而且，他们有很多作案机会，他们的工作性质决定了他们有很多自由时间——卡车的维修和加油一般都在漆黑的晚上进行，那时很难知道每一个人的确切位置。军事警察当天就搜查了卡车司机的战俘营，以期发现泄露秘密的羽毛或者袋子，但除了司机们从军需官仓库那里偷来的罐头食物和香烟之外，军警们一无所获。

渚蒲大尉很不满意，比以往任何时候都要生气。这演变成关乎面子问题的大事，因为小偷胆敢染指指挥官的财产，这种行为明显是对这个职位，甚至是对日本皇军的侮辱。他下令对整个关丹镇进行搜查。第二天，听令于军事警察的部队搜查了每一座房子，势必要找到黑色羽毛和绿色袋子的踪迹。但也是白费工夫。

大尉日夜冥思苦想，发誓要洗刷掉泼在他制服上的奇耻大辱。他命令对他手下士兵的兵舍进行搜查，但同样毫无发现。

还有一条线索。有三辆由澳洲人开的卡车是沿着大路往北走的，或者从而连突开过来。第二天渚蒲派了一辆轻便的卡车，配备了四名军事警察，出发去搜查这些卡车，审讯司机、看守以及任何有可能知情的人。在薄海和布拉特之间，他们遇到一群女人和孩子，这群人正背着包裹沿路往南走。一个日本中士走在最前面，一边肩上挂着来复枪，另一边挂着一个绿色的袋子。卡车尖声刹车，停了下来。

在接下来的两个小时里，琴坚持说她的故事：她用澳洲人给的钱在利茂买了这些鸡。他们把她赶到路中央，对她进行刑讯逼供，连续不断地问她重复的问题：当他们觉得她走神了，就扇她耳光，踢她小腿，或者穿着军靴踩在她的光脚上。她用绝望的决心坚持讲这个故事，知道它太蹩脚，知道他们不相信她，但她不知道除此之外还可以说什么。最后，由三辆卡车组成的车队沿路开了过来。第二辆车的司机，乔·哈曼，马上被中士认了出来，并被用刺刀押着带到琴面前。军警的中士说：“是这个男人吗？”

琴绝望地说：“我一直在告诉他们你给了我们四美元，让我们拿去买鸡吃，乔，但是他们不相信我。”

军警说：“你们从大尉那里偷来这些鸡。这就是那个包。”

牧工看着那个女子血淋淋的脸和脚。“放开她，你们这些该死的浑蛋，”他用慢腾腾的昆士兰腔调愤怒地说，“是我偷了这些该死的鸡，是我把它们给了她。那又怎么样？”

黑暗渐渐笼罩住我在伦敦的起居室。那是一个风雨交加的下午，暮色提前降临。雨仍旧打在窗户上。琴坐在那里，凝视着火焰，沉浸在她悲伤的记忆中。“他们残杀了他。”她轻轻地说，“他们把我们全部带到了关丹，把他的手钉在树上，残忍地打死了他。我们被迫站在旁边，看着他们行刑。”

————————————————————

(1) 马来亚西南部港口城市。

(2) 语见《新约·路加福音》第18章。

(3) 原文是“straits-born”，指海峡殖民地（英国在马六甲海峡沿岸的殖民地，包括新加坡、槟榔屿、马六甲和附近小岛）出生的英国人。

(4) 他说的是“Dinky-die？”，澳洲口语，英国人不使用，所以琴没听懂。

(5) 乔在此处用的是“boong”一词，在澳洲俚语中是“土著”的意思，但在普通英语中，“土著”一般使用“abo”一词，故下文琴问他那是什么意思。后来乔称琴作“土著太太”，用的也是“Mrs Boong”。

(6) 套环（ringer），澳洲用语，所以琴听不懂。

(7) 十九世纪末非常著名的澳大利亚马车公司，至今尚存。

(8) 澳大利亚有六个州和两个领地。北领地为两个领地之一，与昆士兰相邻。

(9) “walkabout”（丛林流浪）在澳洲英语里指在内地的长途旅行，在普通英语中，“walkabout”指的是要人在公共场所的巡行。

第四章

“天啊，”我说，“实在是太悲惨了。”

她抬起头。“不必惊讶，”她说，“战争就是这样的。那是很久之前，到现在差不多有六年了。渚蒲大尉也已经被绞死了——不是因为这件事，而是因为他在铁路上犯下的暴行。时过境迁，我几乎都想不起来了。”

关丹果然没有女子战俘营，渚蒲大尉也不喜欢让许多妇女和孩子打扰他。死刑中午时分在一个游乐场里执行，从那里可以俯瞰一片网球场。双手被钉在树上的身体鲜血淋漓，体无完肤。它一停止扭动，渚蒲大尉马上让这些女人和孩子在他面前站成一排。

“你们都是很坏的人，”他说，“没有给你们的地方。我让你们去哥打巴鲁。你们现在就走。”

他们一言不发，跌跌撞撞地上路了。他们的心被绝望笼罩，只想赶快逃离这个恐怖的地方。护送他们从金马士过来的中士仍然被派作看守，因为他恬不知耻地参与了分赃。命令他继续和他们待在一起，是对他的惩罚，因为在日本人眼里，所有这些战俘都是卑劣无耻的生物，押送他们也是一件下流丢脸的工作，只能由那些最低贱的人来干。一个光荣的日本军人宁可自杀也不会甘心被俘。也许为了强调这一点，那位普通士兵被带走了，所以从关丹开始，这个中士就是他们唯一的看守。

他们就这样再次上路，日复一日地延挨着。他们离开关丹的时候大约是七月中旬。从关丹到哥打巴鲁有大约两百英里路程，算上疾病将引致的耽搁，琴预计这一次至少要走两个月。

第一天他们走到了勿沙莱，海边的一个渔村，沙滩边缘有雪白的珊瑚沙和棕榈树。这个地方风光秀丽，但他们几近无眠，因为几乎所有孩子都因恐怖的记忆失魂丧魄，整夜哭泣，无法入寐。他们无法在如此靠近关丹的地方停留，第二天就继续上路。经过短暂的行程，他们到达巴洛，另一个海边渔村，棕榈树更为繁茂。他们在这里休息了一天。

他们渐渐意识到自己进入了一片新天地。马来亚东北部海岸漂亮宜人，也更加健康。它景色优美，海岬周围岩石满布，满是沙子的海滩绵延曲折，边缘点缀着棕榈树，海风清爽新鲜，悠悠不绝。更重要的是，所有村庄都能供应大量鲜鱼。他们离开帕农至今，第一次获得充足的蛋白质搭配米饭，健康马上好转。大部分人至少每天在温暖的海水里洗一次澡，他们罹患的某些皮肤病——尽管不是全部——也开始在这种盐水疗法中逐渐痊愈。多月来孩子们头一次有充沛的体能玩耍嬉戏。

实际上，除了中士，所有人的状态都变好了。他现在对这群女人疑心重重，几乎不帮她们抱小孩儿，也不以任何其他方式帮助她们了。他似乎对于所受的谴责耿耿于怀，而且也失去了可以交谈的同伴。他总是精神不振，晚上坐得离她们远远的，一脸阴沉。有一两次，琴忽然意识到自己正在故意尝试鼓励他振作，仿佛他倒是战俘，而她却成了看守。一路上他们很少碰到日本人，只是偶尔会看到河村或者小机场上的分队驻地。他们每次经过驻地，中士都会把自己收拾得漂漂亮亮，向主管军官作报告，军官通常会过来检查他们。但在关丹和哥打巴鲁之间几乎没有工业设施和比渔村大的小镇，也没有人认为敌人会袭击马来半岛东部。有好几次，女人们连续一周连一个日本人也没看见，除了中士之外。

他们慢慢沿着海岸往北走，妇女和孩子们的状况大为改善。六个月前，他们无助地从帕农出发，但现在这群战俘已经非同往日。死亡无情地淘汰了那些最弱的成员，把他们的数量减至原来一半左右，这样一来，村子为他们安排住宿和伙食就容易多了。他们的经验也大为增加，学会了怎样使用当地疗法对付疟疾和痢疾，并和当地人一样穿衣、洗澡和睡觉。因此，与他们之前拒向原始条件屈服，努力挣扎维持西方生活方式的时候相比，他们现在拥有的闲暇时间大为增加。每隔一天走十英里已然不再是一个沉重的负担。在休息日，女人们能抽出更多时间陪伴孩子。不久，曾任小学女校长的沃纳太太为孩子们开班授课，上课成了休息日的常规活动。

琴开始教小宝贝罗宾·霍兰走路。他恢复了健壮的体魄，并变得很沉，因为他现在已经十六个月大，琴快要背不动他了。气候炎热，她从未给他穿过任何衣服。他身无挂碍，在棕榈树和木麻黄树荫里，或在阳光下的沙滩上，像个马来婴儿一样赤身裸体地爬来爬去，并晒得跟马来婴儿差不多一样黑。

接下来几周，他们慢慢沿着海岸往北走，经过许多渔村，像乌拉、真德、卡隆、珀农乔角、甘马仕，等等。他们偶尔染病，当很多人都排汗退烧时，就随地停留几天，但再也没有人死去。关丹留给他们的死亡恐惧，是最后一次，每个人都对之讳莫如深，因为没有人想唤起其他人的可怖回忆。但是，每个人却又都暗中认为，这个惨剧恰好是他们命运的转捩点。

弗里思太太的存在大大加深了这个念头。她是一位小个子的虔诚女士，恪守时辰早晚祈祷。正是弗里思太太永远知道哪天是星期天：那天她会大声向任何听众念上一个小时祈祷书和圣经。如果碰上休息日，她会猜算时间，尽量在十一点开始这项服务，因为晨祷理应在此时进行。

弗里思太太试图为他们遇到的每一件事情寻找上帝之手。循着这种思路来冥想他们的经历，她猛然领悟到某种相似性。圣人受难的故事，她烂熟于心，现在她亲眼见证了另外一个。在她心目中，这位澳洲人有治愈疾病的力量，因为他给他们带来的药物治好了她的痢疾和庄妮·霍斯福尔(1)的皮癣。并且，毫无疑问的是，在他为他们牺牲之后，他们每一所遇都仿佛恩受祝福。上帝把儿子(2)送到了巴勒斯坦。难道他(3)在马来亚重演了这个故事？

遭蒙持续巨大苦难的男男女女，被完全切断了和之前生活的联系，过上一种完全异样的生活，常常会形成奇怪的心理特质。弗里思太太并没有把自己的观点强加到其他人身上，然而，她开始逐渐相信的事情还是不可避免地为其他女人所知悉。大家初时心存怀疑，但都认为这件事情比其他一切更需要深刻和谨慎的思考。大部分女人过去一有机会就去教堂，几乎全属低教会派(4)，内心深处一直渴望得到上帝的帮助。随着她们的身体健康一周周改善，宗教思想能力逐步增强，时间也渐渐冲淡了关于澳大利亚人的准确记忆。这种记忆变得充满敬畏，泛着玫瑰色，脱离了现实。如果弗里思太太相信的这个奇迹有可能是真的，实际上意味着她们被置于上帝手中，没有东西可以碰她们，她们会战胜万难，熬过苦境，终将重新获得她们的家园、丈夫和西方生活方式。她们重获力量，继续前行。

琴并没有做任何事来驱散这些幻想，因为它们明显对女人们大有益处，但她自己却不为所动。她最年轻，也是唯一一个未婚姑娘，对于乔·哈曼的印象跟其他人大相径庭。她认识的他不过是一个普通人，一个普通的男人。当他回来跟她谈话的时候，她已经变得更漂亮迷人。她下意识地采取了防范措施，让他一直叫她土著太太。如果她臀上的婴儿使他误会她跟其他女人一样已为人妻，那也无妨。在那些热带村庄的炎热夜晚，他们几乎衣不蔽体。那个地方不守常规，甚至根本毫无规则可言，如果他知道她是个未婚姑娘，她敢说他们两人之间可能发生任何事情，而且可能猝不及防。她因他而起的悲伤，相比其他妇女而言更真实，也深刻得多，并且丝毫不是因为她认为他是个神圣的人。她很肯定他不是。

八月末，他们来到一条名叫瓜拉德朗的村子，大概在关丹和哥打巴鲁的半途。德朗是一条河流，短小泥泞，蜿蜒经过一片平坦的稻米种植区，流入大海，村子就坐落在河流南岸的河口沙洲内。这是一个秀美的地方，棕榈树和木麻黄树青葱茂盛，南中国海的巨浪拍打着绵长的玉白色沙滩，碎成点点银雪。村民以打鱼和种植稻米为生。河里停泊着大约十五艘用于出海捕鱼的渔船，是一种大型开放式帆船，头尾装饰着高高扁扁的奇怪雕像。村子里有一块用作广场的空地，周围聚集着用木头和棕榈叶搭建而成的当地店铺，后面有一个紧靠河岸的米仓。这个米仓当时是空的，女人们带着孩子住在里面。

中士在这里病倒了，发起烧来，很有可能是得了疟疾。关丹一事之后，他性情大变，一路上阴沉忧郁，仿佛深觉孤单寂寞。女人们越来越健壮，他却变得越来越虚弱。一开始她们都觉得很奇怪，因为他以前从未生过病。这个小个子男人怪异、丑陋又野蛮，她们看见他一蹶不振，最初都感到轻松愉快，但随着他日益身心交病，她们反而开始蒙受一种相反的感觉。他和她们共度了漫长的时光，也在职责范围内竭尽所能减轻她们的负担。在路上，他心甘情愿地抱着她们的孩子，孩子去世时，他黯然哭泣。后来他烧得很厉害，她们便轮流帮他拿着来复枪、紧身短上衣、靴子和包裹。所以当这群人到达村子时，走成了一个很奇怪的队列：一个只穿着长裤的小个子黄种男人被沃纳太太牵着，头晕目眩地踉跄而行。他光着脚走更舒服。其他女人走在他们后面，拿着他的整套装备和她们自己的行囊。

琴找到村子的首领，一个大约五十岁，名叫马特·阿明·宾·泰布的男人，向他解释情况。“我们是战俘，”她说，“要从关丹步行到哥打巴鲁，这个日本人是我们的看守。他生病发烧了，我们必须找一间阴凉的屋子让他躺下休息。他有权以日本皇军的名义开具收据，支付我们的食宿费。他康复之后就会这样做的，会给你们开一张收据。我们自己也必须找地方住宿和吃饭。”

马特·阿明说：“我没有能给白人夫人睡觉的地方。”

琴说：“我们已经不再是白人夫人了。我们是战俘，已经习惯了和你们的妇女一样生活。我们需要的只是一个屋顶和一块可以睡觉的地板，并借用锅、米、蔬菜和一点点鱼或肉。”

“我们自己吃的你们都可以吃，”他说，“但看到你们这些夫人如此落魄，真是让人感到奇怪。”

他把中士带进自己的屋子，用椰子纤维填充出一张褥子和一个枕头给他。他想把一个明显是他自己平日用的蚊帐给中士，但妇女们拒绝了，因为她们知道中士需要尽可能多的凉风。她们帮他脱掉裤子，穿上纱笼，扶他躺到床上。她们的奎宁已经用光了，但首领用自己的配方调制了一剂药。她们给中士喝了一点，就把他留给首领的妻子照顾，去找自己落脚的地方和食物。

中士整个晚上都烧得很厉害。她们第二天早上去看望他的时候，他看起来一点也不好。他仍然发着高烧，变得虚弱了很多，她们觉得他好像已经放弃了，那是一个不祥的征兆。那天，她们轮流坐在他身旁，给他洗脸、擦身子，不时跟他说话，试图引起他的兴趣，但并不怎么成功。晚上，琴坐在他身旁，他毫无生气地朝天躺着，汗流如注，她问什么都不答应。

她想找点东西来吸引他的注意，于是拉过他的紧身短上衣，在口袋里摸寻收据本。她在口袋里找到了一张照片，上面有一个日本女人和四个小孩，站在一间屋子的入口处。她说：“军曹，这是你的孩子吗？”然后递给他。他拿过去，一言不发，也没有看。然后他把照片递回给琴，示意她放回去。

她一边把夹克放回原位，一边看着他。眼泪从他的眼中流出，淌下，混入脸颊上的汗珠。她非常轻柔地把它们拭去了。

他越来越虚弱，两天后在夜里去世了。似乎没有特别的理由可以解释他的离世，但在关丹所受的侮辱可能一直重重地压在他的心上，使他失去了活下去的兴趣和愿望。她们第二天把他葬在村子外的穆斯林墓地里，几乎所有人都为他哭了一阵，把他当作一位珍贵的老朋友。

他们因为中士的死而陷入了非常尴尬的处境，成了没有看守的战俘。葬礼当天晚上，妇女们深入而详细地探讨了目前的状况。“我看不出来为什么我们不应该留在这里，原地不动，”弗里思太太说，“这是一个很不错的地方。它确实很不错，不比我们之前去过的任何一个地方差。那是他说的，我们应该找一个地方，不再奔波，安顿下来。”

琴说：“我知道。但我们必须先确定两件事情。第一，日本兵终有一天会发现我们在这里生活，这样一来首领就会因为擅自收留我们而受到惩罚。日本兵很可能会杀了他，大家都很清楚他们是什么人。”

“也许他们根本就不会发现我们呢？”普莱斯太太说。

“我不相信马特·阿明是愿意冒这种险的人，”琴说，“他也毫无冒险的理由。如果我们留下来，他会立刻去找日本兵，告诉他们我们在这里。”她顿了顿，“第二，我们不能仅仅凭着白人夫人的身份，就期望这个村子会一直无限期供养我们十七个人。他们会把我们的消息通知日本兵，只是为了甩掉我们这个包袱。”

弗里思太太精明地说：“也许我们可以自己种粮食。我们来的时候看到有一半的稻田今年尚未播种。”

琴看着她说：“非常正确——那些田现在荒着。我真想知道原因。”

“肯定是因为所有男人都去打仗了，”沃纳太太说，“作为苦力修建那条铁路什么的。”

琴慢慢地说：“大家怎么看？如果我们去告诉马特·阿明，只要他让我们留下来，我们就下地干活，你们觉得怎么样？”

普莱斯太太冷笑道：“我？以我这体型？在齐膝深的泥和水里走来走去，把秧苗插进地里，就像大家看见的马来亚女孩那样？”

琴满怀歉意地说：“那只是一个想法。”

“也是一个很好的想法，”沃纳太太说，“我不介意在稻田里劳动，只要我们能留在这里安安稳稳地生活。”

弗里思太太说：“如果我们能像你说的那样种水稻的话，说不定他们会让我们留下来——我是指日本兵。无论如何，那样我们就能做点贡献，而不用再无所事事地全国各地闲荡，就跟受鞭打的流浪狗一样。”

第二天早上，琴去找首领。她双手交叠，做出致敬的祈祷姿势，向他微笑，并用马来语说：“马特·阿明，我们看到有些稻田没有播种，这是为什么呢？我们来到这里时，看见太多被完全荒置的田地了。”

他说：“大部分的男人，除了渔夫，都在为军队工作。”他指日本军队。

“在铁路上？”

“不，他们在贡卡达。他们正在开路，需要铲平一条长长的陆地，在上面铺上柏油和石头，这样飞机就可以在上面降落了。”

“他们很快就会回来种地了吗？”

“那掌握在真主手中，但我认为他们还要在外度过很多个月。我听说他们在贡卡达做完这个工程之后，还要去另外一个叫作马常的地方，继续做同样的工程，完了还要去檀永麻。一旦落入了日本兵的魔掌，人们就很难逃回自己的家园。”

“那谁来栽种和收割水稻？”

“妇女们会尽其所能去做。明年稻米将很短缺——这里不会，因为我们不会卖掉自己需要吃的稻米。我们将不会有多余的稻米卖给日本人。我不知道他们明年吃什么，但应该没有稻米。”

琴说：“马特·阿明，我有一件很严肃的事情想跟您商量。如果我们之中有一个男人，我会让他来跟您谈，可是没有。如果我请您跟一个代表其他女士的女人来商量正事，希望您不会感到被冒犯。”她现在已经稍稍懂得跟伊斯兰教徒打交道的正确方法。

他向她鞠了一躬，请她去他的屋子商量。那里有一个颤巍巍的小门廊，他们走上去，面对面在地板上坐下来。他两只眼睛靠得很近，头发剪得很短，小胡子修得整整齐齐，腰以上赤裸着，下身穿着纱笼。他面容坚定，但透着仁慈。他厉声吩咐屋子里的妻子把咖啡端出来。

在等咖啡端上来的时间里，琴很有礼貌地与首领寒暄。她从六个月的乡村生活经验中总结出谈判的规矩。端上来的咖啡装在两个厚厚的玻璃杯里，没放牛奶，却甜甜的，加了糖。她向他鞠一躬，举起杯子啜了一口，又把杯子放下。“我们身处困境，”她坦率地说，“看守去世了。现在我们的命运掌握在自己手中——和您的手中。您了解我们的故事。我们在帕农被俘，一路跋山涉水来到这里。没有日本指挥官愿意收留我们，让我们进战俘营，供养我们，在我们生病的时候给予照顾，因为每个指挥官都认为这是其他人的职责。所以他们派看守押送我们从这个镇走到那个镇。这足足持续了六个多月，在这期间我们一半人死在了路上。”

他点点头。

“现在我们的军曹过世了，”她说，“我们要怎么办？即使我们继续走下去，直到碰上一个日本军官，向他报告此事，他也不会收留我们。这整个国家没有人会收留我们。他们不会马上杀掉我们，就像对待男人一样。为了摆脱我们，他们会迫使我们不断走下去，走去别处，也许是沼泽满布的乡下，就像我们之前经过的那些地方。这样我们就会再次生病，一个接一个全部死去。如果我们现在就去告知日本兵，这就是我们的命运。”

他回答道：“《古兰经》上写道：‘凡有血气者，都要尝死的滋味。我以祸福考验你们，你们只被召归我。’(5)”

她飞速思考，迪里特村首领的话在脑海里浮现出来。她说：“《古兰经》上也写道：‘如果你们行善而且敬畏，那末，真主确是彻知你们的行为的。’”

他定定地看着她。“在什么地方？”

她说：“第四章。”

“你也信奉伊斯兰教？”他怀疑地问道。

她摇摇头。“我不想欺骗您。我是一个基督教徒。我们都是基督教徒。路上我们遇到了一位对我们非常仁慈的村子首领，我去答谢他时，他向我说了这句话。我不懂《古兰经》。”

“你是一位非常聪明的女士，”他说，“请告诉我你的请求。”

“我希望我们能留在这里，在这个村子里，”她说，“下地劳动，种植稻米，就像你们的妇女一样。”他瞠目结舌。“这对您来讲很危险，”她说，“我们很清楚。如果日本军官在接到您的报告之前在这里找到我们，肯定会勃然大怒。因此，我希望您这样做。我希望您马上让几位村子里的妇女带领我们下地劳动，教会我们如何种水稻。我们会从早到晚工作，纯粹为了换取食物和栖身之处。两周后，我会自己去找日本军官，向他报告我们的情况。希望您作为村子的首领能跟我一同前往，告诉军官，如果我们被允许留下来继续种地，日本军队就有更多稻米可吃。这就是我的请求。”

“我从未听说过白人夫人在稻田里劳作。”他说。

她问道：“您是否听说过白人夫人像我们一样四处奔波、接连死去？”

他不言语。

“我们的命运掌握在您的手中，”她说，“如果您说，继续上路，到别处去，那我们就必须离开，离开就意味着死亡。到时请您向真主解释。如果您允许我们留下来耕种您的稻田，在您的护荫下平静安全地生活下去，那么当英国的老爷们获胜后重返这个国家时，您将获得巨大的荣誉，因为他们终将赢得这场战争。这些矮子们现在当权，但他们敌不过美国人和世界上所有自由民族。英国老爷们终有一天会回来的。”

他说：“那一天来临的时候，我将不胜欢喜。”

他们默默坐着，抿着咖啡。过了一会儿首领说：“这不是一件能轻易决定的事情，因为它关乎整个村子的安危。我会认真考虑，并和兄弟们详细商量。”

琴离开了。当天晚上晚祷结束后，她看见一群男人坐在首领屋子前面。他们都是老人家，因为当时在瓜拉德朗已经全然看不见年轻男子的踪影，况且，很可能无论如何年轻小伙子也是没有资格参加会议的。稍晚的时候，马特·阿明来到米仓，要求见佩吉特夫人。琴背着婴儿出来迎接他，在一盏小油灯发出的光亮中站着和他交谈。

“我们已经讨论过你提出的请求了，”他说，“让白人夫人在我们的稻田里干活实在有点不近情理。一些兄弟担心白人老爷们回来时无法理解这种情形，并且会发怒说我们违背你们的意志，强迫你们为我们劳动。”

琴说：“我们可以马上给您写一封信。如果他们那样说，您可以把信拿给他们看。”

他摇摇头。“不必如此。等老爷们回来的时候，请你告诉他们，这完全出于你们的意愿就可以了。”

她说：“我们会的。”

她们第二天就开始下地干活。当时他们的队伍有六个已婚女士、琴和十个孩子，包括琴的婴儿。首领把他们带到田里，和名叫法缇玛·宾蒂·妲露丝和蕾哈娜·宾蒂·哈珊的两个马来女孩儿一起工作。作为开端，他让她们耕种七小块杂草丛生的土地。以她们的力气，耕种这几块地游刃有余。旁边有一个带屋顶的平台供她们纳凉休息，大家一起劳动的时候，最小的孩子们就待在那里。

七位女士都非常健壮。艰苦的旅途淘汰了无法承担农活的成员，剩下来的女人都坚定勇敢，士气高昂，风趣幽默。一旦她们适应了在脚踝深的泥土和水里工作的新鲜感，就发现这种劳动并不吃力。她们很快就变得雄心勃勃，想要向村民们证明白人夫人也能干和马来女人一样多的活，甚至更多。

人们把稻米种在小块田地里，田地周围环绕着像矮墙一样的泥垄，以便把溪水引入田中，形成小池塘。把水排干后，稻田底部全是柔软的淤泥，就可以用手拔掉杂草，犁地，准备插秧。人们把稻种撒在类似苗圃的地方，等种子发芽后把秧苗移植到泥土松软的田里插成排，然后重新往田里灌水，让幼苗在水里露出头来，在大太阳底下暴晒几天，之后水被再次排空，好让太阳晒到稻苗根部。在热带气候下，这样的水旱交替能使作物迅速生长，等它们长到差不多跟小麦一样高时，稻秆顶端就开始抽穗，就像长出来毛茸茸的小耳朵一样。收割时，用小刀把耳朵割下，装进袋子拿进村子去糠，把稻秆留在地里。水牛这时就被放进田里吃掉稻秆，使土地更肥沃，并把土地踩个遍。这样这些土地就适于来年重新播种，重复上述循环。这些稻田每年大约能收两造，并且不需要轮作。

习惯之后，在这些田里劳作并无令人不愉快之处。在一个炎热逼人的国家里，戴上一顶用棕榈叶编成的大圆锥形太阳帽，脱掉大部分衣裳，在泥和水里嬉戏，筑起小水坝，把潺潺小溪引流入田，比起从事其他许多工作来要惬意得多。最初两周快要结束的时候，女士们都已经安下心来踏实干活，并且喜欢上了这份工作，而所有的孩子打从一开始就乐此不疲。在那期间，并没有日本兵靠近村子。

第十六天，琴和首领马特·阿明带着中士的来复枪、装备、制服和收据本，一起出发去寻找日本军队。他们去的地方叫作瓜拉拉吉特，大约二十七英里远，有一个日本分队驻扎在那里。

他们花了两天时间步行去瓜拉拉吉特，中途在一个叫作武吉特帕拉的地方过了一个晚上，当地首领接待了他们，琴和村子的妇女一起睡在村子后面的屋子里。他们第二天继续上路，晚上到达瓜拉拉吉特。那是一条很大的村庄，或者说是一个小镇。马特·阿明带琴去当地一个马来政府官员登库·本塔拉·拉雅家中与他见面。登库·本塔拉是一个瘦小的马来人，英语说得非常好。他由衷关心从马特·阿明和琴那里听来的故事。

“真是非常，非常抱歉，”他最后说，“我无法给予你们直接的帮助，因为日本兵控制了我们的一切行为。你们不得不耕种稻田，这实在是太糟糕了。”

“一点儿也不糟糕，”琴说，“实际上我们非常喜欢这份工作。我们想和马特·阿明一起留在那里。如果日本军队在本地有一个女子战俘营，我想他们会把我们送进去，但如果没有的话，我们不想继续步行环游马来亚。在途中我们已经失去了一半成员。”

“请你们今晚务必留下，”他说，“明天我将和这里的日本行政长官谈一谈。总之这里是没有女子战俘营的。”

当天晚上，琴近七个月来第一次睡在床上。她并没有因此觉得很高兴。习惯了在地板上睡觉后，她觉得睡在褥子上反而没那么凉快。她并没有真的下床睡到地板上，不过她差一点就那样做了。然而，泡在浴缸里，拿一个灌满水的葫芦往头上淋浴，倒是件乐事。她洗了很久很久。

早上，登库·本塔拉和马特·阿明带她一起去见日本行政长官，她又讲了一遍她的故事。行政长官曾在加利福尼亚州立大学留学，说一口一流的美式英语。他深感同情，但宣称战俘归军队负责，与他毫不相干。不过，他带他们一起去见军事指挥官，一个松坂大佐。琴对着松坂又讲了一遍她的故事。

松坂大佐显然认为女战俘是令人讨厌的累赘，丝毫不愿意抽调自己的任何兵力来押送他们。如果让他自行裁决，他很可能会让他们继续上路，但是碍着登库·本塔拉和行政长官的情面，又了解到女人们的悲惨遭遇，他没法这样做。最后，他干脆洗手不管，让行政长官作出自认为最妥当的安排。行政长官告诉本塔拉，女人们可以暂时留在原地，琴便和马特·阿明一起出发回瓜拉德朗。

他们一留便是三年。

“那是遗失的三年，被生生从我们的生命中割离开来。”她说。她抬起头来看着我，迟疑着。“至少——我认为是那样。我懂得很多关于马来人的知识，但它们在英国没有多少价值。”

“直到生命结束那一刻，你才能确定那是否是一段毫无意义的时间，”我说，“也许到时你就觉得不是了。”

她点点头。“我想您是对的。”她拿起拨火棍，开始刮掉壁炉铁栏上的灰。“他们对我们太好了，”她说，“用他们拥有的一切，以他们的方式尽可能善待我们。法缇玛，那位最初几周告诉我们如何在田里工作的姑娘——她简直是个完美的宝贝儿。实际上到后来我们情同姐妹。”

“那就是你想回去的地方？”我问道。

她点点头。“现在我继承了这笔钱，想回去为他们做点事情。我们和他们一起生活了三年，他们倾囊相助。如果他们没有收留我们，可能我们都活不到战争结束。现在我这么富有，而他们却如此，如此穷困……”

“别忘了你还未能支配全部遗产，”我说，“马来亚之旅将所费不菲。”

她微微一笑。“我知道。我想为他们做的事情花不了这么多钱——不会超过五十英镑。住在那个村子的时候，我们必须去打水，那是女人的职责，也是一个可怕的任务。是这样，流经村子的河流随海潮涨落，所以河水是咸的，人们可以用它来洗澡或者洗衣服，但如果要喝水，就必须走大约一英里，把泉水打回来。我们一般用葫芦打水，每只手拿两个，中间穿一条棍子提着，早晚一次——去程一英里，回程一英里——一天走四英里。法缇玛和其他姑娘并不觉得有任何不妥，因为村子一直以来都是那样做的，世代因循。”

“那就是你想要去挖一口井的原因？”

她点点头。“那是我能为他们做的事情，为妇女们——可以让她们活得更轻松，就像她们让我们活得更轻松一样。我想在村子正中央挖一个井，离每间屋子都不到一百码。她们早就应该有这么一个井。我敢肯定至多只需要挖十英尺深，因为那里遍地是水源。地下水位不会深于十英尺，至多十五英尺。我想如果我回去雇用一个挖井队替他们做这项工作，应该能把井挖成。做完这件事之后，我就可以清清白白地安心享用这笔钱。”她再次抬起头来看我。“您会不会觉得我很傻？”

“不会，”我说，“我不觉得。但有一点，我希望你不用去那么远的地方。往返马来亚的旅程会花掉一年大部分收入。”

“我知道，”她说，“如果我把钱花光了，我会在新加坡或者其他地方找一份工作，干几个月活，存一点钱。”

“我很想知道，”我说，“为什么你不干脆留在那里找一份工作呢？你对那个国家很熟悉。”

她说：“我当时对那里有点厌倦了——1945年的时候。我们都渴望回家。他们从哥打巴鲁派了三辆卡车来接我们，把我们送到机场。我们坐空中列车飞往新加坡，机组人员都是澳大利亚人。在飞机上我遇到了比尔·霍兰。我必须告诉他关于艾琳、弗雷迪和简的事情。”她的声音低沉了下去。“我必须告诉他所有家庭成员的遭遇，除了罗宾。他那时已经四岁了，是一个很健壮的小家伙。他们让我跟比尔和罗宾一起回家，帮忙照顾罗宾。他很自然地把我当成妈妈了。”

她微微一笑。“比尔想我做他的妻子，”她说，“我做不到。我不可能成为他想要的那种妻子。”

我一言不发。

“我们降落的时候，英国是那么地绿意逼人，那么美丽，”她说，“我想忘却战争，忘却东方，做回一个普通人。我在帕克和利维公司找到了现在这份工作，在那里干了两年了——用于奢侈品贸易的女士手提包和公文包跟战争、疾病和死亡一点关系都没有。总的来说，我在那里过得还算愉快。”

她重返家园时茕茕孑立。她一到新加坡就给母亲发了电报。过了很久，科尔温贝的阿加莎姑姑才通过电报作出回复，向她透露她母亲已经去世的消息。她离开新加坡之前已经听说哥哥唐纳德死在泰缅铁路上。当她重获自由，却发现亲人尽失，肯定深感孤寂。在我看来，她确实展现出了极其坚强的精神，才在彼时彼境拒绝了求婚。她在利物浦着陆，去科尔温贝和阿加莎姑姑待了几周，就南下伦敦找工作。

我问她为什么不和舅舅联系，去找那位住在埃尔的老人家。“老实说，”她说，“我把他忘得一干二净。即使我想起他来，也只会认为他已经去世了。我只见过他一面，那个时候我才十一岁，他看起来就好像行将就木了。我从来没想过他还活着。母亲的财产全部毁于一旦。她的私人文件也几乎全部丢失了，因为遭受轰炸时，它们都放在南安普敦的佩吉特家里。即使我能想起道格拉斯舅舅来，也不知道他住在哪里……”

外面依然下着倾盆大雨。我们决定放弃当天下午外出的主意，干脆留在公寓喝茶。她到我的小厨房烧水沏茶，我则忙于摆桌子，切面包和奶油。当她拿着托盘进来的时候，我说：“那你打算什么时候回马来亚？”

她说：“我想，我会订五月底的票，继续在帕克和利维公司工作到那个时候。”又说，“离现在大概还有六周时间。那个时候我就能存起足够的钱来支付来回路费，我还有从过去两年的工资里省下来的六十英镑。”她开始认真思考这次旅途的费用，并在一艘中等大小的货船上订到一张票，这艘货船会顺路带上十来位乘客到新加坡去，收费比较便宜。“我将不得不从新加坡坐飞机到哥打巴鲁，”她说，“马来航空有经停关丹去哥打巴鲁的飞机。我不知道要怎样从哥打巴鲁去瓜拉德朗，不过我想总会有办法的。”

我想，她从哥打巴鲁走路去瓜拉德朗应该也没有问题。步行穿过马来亚腹地现在对她来讲应该是小菜一碟。她给我讲战时遭遇时，我把地图集拿了出来，看看她说的地方都在哪里。现在我又在看地图。“你可以在关丹下飞机，”我说，“从那里走近一些。”

“我知道，”她说，语气透着悲伤，“我知道那样近一些。但如果让我回到那里，我会发疯。”

为了缓和气氛，我岔开话题道：“我肯定要花很多年才能记住这些马来名字。”

“懂得它们的含义后就简单多了，”她说，“就跟英语名字一样。‘巴鲁’是‘新’的意思，‘哥打’是‘要塞’的意思。就像英语里的纽卡斯尔(6)。”

她继续她在佩里维尔的工作，我也继续我在赞善里的工作，但她的故事在我脑海里挥之不去。我俱乐部里有一位叫怀特的男士，曾经在马来警察局工作，日据期间成为了日本军队的战俘，我想他被关进了樟宜监狱(7)。一个晚上，我坐在他身旁吃饭，无法抑制向他探听此事的冲动。“前几天我的客户告诉我一个关于马来亚的离奇故事，”我说，“日本兵拒绝让一批女人进入战俘营，她是其中一人。”

他放下刀子。“您不是说在帕农被俘后，被迫步行横穿马来亚的那批女士吧？”

“正是她们，”我说，“你知道她们的故事，是不是？”

“哦，是的，”他说，“那真是一件再离奇不过的事了，正如你所说的那样。日本指挥官让她们东奔西走，直到最后她们被允许在东海岸某个村子里安顿下来，在那里一直生活到战争结束。她们的首领是一位非常可敬的姑娘，马来语说得非常流利。她不是什么名人，曾经在吉隆坡一个办事处当打字员，战时却表现出色，堪称楷模。”

我点点头。“她就是我的客户。”

“是吗！我总想知道她后来怎么样了。她现在在干什么？”

我干巴巴地说：“她又当回打字员了，在佩里维尔一个手提包厂工作。”

“真的？”他吃了几口饭，又说，“我总是觉得应该给她颁个奖章什么的。不幸的是，你无法给予那样的人任何奖赏。但如果没有她，那些女士和她们的孩子可能都会死掉。在那批战俘里，其他人都没有她那样的才干。”

“我知道那批战俘有一半去世了。”我说。

他点点头。“我相信那是真的。最后她帮助他们安顿下来，在稻田里劳作，那之后他们都平安无事。”

在琴离开英国之前的六周里，我不时与她见面。她订好了6月2日从伦敦出发去新加坡的船票，并通知了她的公司，她将于五月底离职。她告诉我，他们听到这个消息后非常沮丧，并且马上提出给她十先令的提薪。有鉴于此，她向帕克先生提及遗产的事情，他只好接受了这件不可避免的事情。

我做好安排，给她在渣打银行开了一个账户，使她能在新加坡收到七到九月的收入。随着她的出发时间日益临近，我开始为她担忧，不是怕她大手大脚花钱，而是怕实际花销超出预算，使她陷入困境。在现在这种时世，每年九百英镑对于一个去东方旅行的人来讲有点捉襟见肘。

大约在她出发前一周，我向她提及我的忧虑。“别忘记你现在是一个相当富有的女士了，”我说，“量入而出很正确，实际上我也必须防止你铺张浪费，但是别忘了，根据你舅舅的遗嘱，我对这笔遗产有相当大的酌情权。一旦你陷入任何困难，或者真的急需用钱，请立刻给我发电报。比如说，万一你生病了。”

她莞尔一笑。“您真的是太体贴了，”她说，“不过，老实说，我想我会没问题的。如果我的钱都花光了，我可以指望找一份工作来挣钱。毕竟，我并不需要在一个指定日期之前回英国，也没有什么别的事情迫使我按期回国。”

我说：“别在外逗留太长时间。”

她微微一笑。“我不会的，斯特拉坎先生，”她说，“一旦我完成此事，就没有不得不走的理由。”

既然要出门长期远行，她退掉了伊令公地的房间。她问是否可以把一个大箱子和一个手提箱放在我公寓的储物室里，请我在她回国前替她妥为保管。她出发前一天将两个箱子拿过来，还有一双带冰刀的溜冰鞋，她塞不进箱子。她告诉我她只带一只手提箱做行李。

“你的热带工具包呢？”我问，“把它托运了吗？”

她微微一笑。“我把它放进了我的手提包，”她说，“五十片百乐君，一百片磺胺嘧啶片，一些防蚊膏，还有我的旧纱笼。我不是去马来亚当淑女的。”

除我之外没有人到码头送她。她在世上非常孤单，有可能愿意来送她的朋友也都要上班，没法请假。我叫了一辆出租车送她去码头。她当然很重视这次旅行，但在我看来，我那个时代的姑娘们去一趟奇斯尔赫斯特过周末所做的准备都要比她周全，而她可是要跨越半个地球。轮船是崭新的，一切都洁净光鲜。当乘务员替她打开舱门时，她不胜讶异地后撤了一步，因为他为这个小小的房间饰满了鲜花，里面一片花海。“瞧瞧这些花儿！”她转向乘务员，“它们是从哪儿来的？不是我公司送的吧？”

“昨天晚上放在三个大箱子里送过来的，”他回答，“它们把房间装饰得很漂亮，是不是，小姐？”

她转过身来看着我。“我相信是您送的。”然后她说，“您怎么能这么可爱！”

“这些都是英国的花朵，”我说，“只是想提醒你尽快回家。”甚至在她还没有出发的时候，我肯定就已经预感到她永远都不会回来了。

等我回过神来，她已经把一只手臂环在我的肩上，轻吻了我的嘴唇。“这是多谢你送的这些花朵，诺尔，”她温柔地说，“这些花朵，还有你为我所做的一切。”我实在是太心慌意乱、不知所措了，能说出口的只有这么一句话：“等你回来的时候，我会再送你一次那些花。”

不等开船我就走了，因为离别会让人变得愚蠢，所以最好尽早结束。我回到出租车上，独自返回公寓。我记得自己在公寓的窗前站了很久，看着对面马厩的雕花墙壁，想着她那艘漂亮的蒸汽轮船沿河而下，经过格雷夫德森、蒂尔伯里、舒伯里和北福兰角，带她离开。然后我让自己从想象中醒来，去把她的箱子和手提箱挪到储物室一角，跟其他物品分开存放。我站在那里，手里拿着她的靴子和溜冰刀，她的私人物品，考虑应该安放于何处。最后我把它们拿进卧室，放在我衣橱的最下面，因为如果它们不幸被盗，我将永远无法原谅自己。她正是那种让人很想认作女儿的人，而我们自己又偏偏没有女儿。

她坐这艘不定期货船穿越大半个地球，几乎从每一个停靠的港口城市给我写信，从马赛和那不勒斯，从亚历山大和亚丁(8)，从科伦坡(9)，从仰光(10)，从槟城(11)。怀特总是对她怀有浓厚的兴趣，因为他知道她在马来亚的事迹。我习惯于捎上她写给我的信去告诉他她的行程和近况。他有一个好朋友是哥打巴鲁酋长的英国顾问，一位威尔逊-海斯先生。我让他写航空邮件给威尔逊-海斯先生，告诉这位先生琴·佩吉特的计划，并请这位先生尽量给予她帮助。他告诉我那非常有必要，因为在哥打巴鲁，女士只能跟当地的英国人住在一起。我从威尔逊-海斯先生那里收到了一封非常友好的回信，告诉我他期待她的光临。我给她寄去一封航空快信，在信上告知我们为她所做的一切，她应该能在渣打银行收到它。

她只在新加坡逗留了一个晚上，就坐次日早上的航班去哥打巴鲁。空中列车在马来亚到处飞来飞去，经停许多地方。午后不久飞机就载着她停泊在哥打巴鲁的小机场上。她下了飞机，穿着离开伦敦时穿的浅灰色外套和裙子，威尔逊-海斯已经亲自和妻子一起在那里等候了。

一年后，我在联合大学俱乐部见到了正在度假的威尔逊-海斯。他又高又黑，很安静，脸很长。他说她发现他亲自来到机场迎接她时有一点窘迫。她似乎没有意识到她在当地这么有名。尽管早在我给他写信之前，威尔逊-海斯理所当然地就已经知道了她所有事情，但战争结束后他就没有听说过她的任何消息。他收到我们的信，知道琴会回来探望瓜拉德朗的村民之后，就捎了个口信给马特·阿明，并安排好把他的吉普车连司机一起借给她，送她走一百多英里去瓜拉德朗。我想他这么做真的是非常周到，向他表达了我的感谢。他说，战争结束后，英国人在瓜拉德朗地区的声望之所以能高于战前，主要归功于这位姑娘和他们这批战俘，他想，让这辆吉普车替她服务几天，也是应分的。

她在官邸住了两个晚上，从当地商店买了一些简单的小物品。第三天早上坐吉普车离开的时候，她换上了当地衣服。她把手提箱和大部分物品留给威尔逊-海斯太太看管，只随身带着当地体面妇女日常携带的物品。她穿着一条褪了色的旧蓝白方格纱笼，一件白色紧身短上衣。但柔嫩的双脚让她被迫妥协，穿上了拖鞋。她带了一把朴素的茶色中国伞遮阳，按当地样式把头发盘到头顶上，中间插了一个大大的梳子。她拿着一个小小的棕榈叶篮子，但威尔逊-海斯太太告诉她丈夫说里面其实没有什么东西。她带了牙刷，但没带牙膏，带了一条毛巾和一块抗菌肥皂，还有几样药品。她带了一套换洗的衣服：一条新纱笼和一件用来配它的碎花棉上衣；还有三个小小的伍尔沃思胸针和两只戒指，作为送给朋友的小礼物，但没带任何化妆品。那大概就是她的全部行装。

“我想她的做法非常聪明，”威尔逊-海斯说，“如果她把自己打扮成一个英国淑女，见面时会让村民们很尴尬。有些英国居民听到她穿着当地服饰去瓜拉德朗时感到很难过——她也是接受过正规教育的，怎么能穿得如此暴露，全是那一类的话。我必须说，看到她出发时的模样，我觉得她的选择非常正确。”他顿了顿，“毕竟，在战争期间她一直穿成那样，当时也没有人说过她穿着暴露。”

坐吉普车从哥打巴鲁到瓜拉德朗需要一天时间，漫长而痛苦。路面情况很糟糕，而且途中要跨越四条河流的干流，必须把吉普车开到渡轮上过河。除此之外还要经过很多浅滩。她花了十四个小时才走完这一百多英里路，到达瓜拉德朗时天已经黑了。吉普车驶进夜色朦胧的村子时，惹起一阵激动的嘈杂声。村民们一边系上纱笼一边从屋子里走出来。那是一个月圆之夜，月亮的清辉足以帮助司机看清道路。车子停在首领屋子前面，她下了车，稍带倦容，举起双手做出祈祷的姿势向首领走去，用马来语说：“我回来了，马特·阿明，唯恐您误以为，当白人夫人不再需要你们时，就把你们抛诸脑后。”

他说：“你们离开之后，我们一直念念不忘，时常谈起你们。”随后人们过来聚集在他们周围。她看见法缇玛走过来，抱着一个婴儿，一个学步的小童紧紧抓住她的纱笼。琴从人群中挤过去，牵着她的手，说：“时间过得太快了。”然后她看见蕾哈娜，萨菲娅·宾蒂·雅各布和萨菲娅·宾蒂·泰布；还有那个总是眯着眼睛看她的小不点儿易卜拉欣，他现在已经长成了一个年轻小伙儿；还有他的哥哥萨马特，还有老祖贝达、梅里亚姆和很多其他人。其中有一些是她不认识的，因为她离开马来亚后不久，男人们就结束苦役回来了，现在这里有很多新面孔。

法缇玛和一个叫作德拉曼·宾·伊斯梅尔的年轻小伙儿结了婚。她把他带上前介绍给白人夫人。琴向他鞠躬，心想要是她带了一块头巾来遮住脸就好了，这样被介绍给陌生男士时才显得知书识礼。她把手举起来挡住脸，说：“请原谅我没戴面纱。”他向她鞠躬，说：“请别介意。”然后法缇玛插进来说：“他知道的，所有人都知道白人夫人和我们住在一起的时候从来不戴面纱。因为不同民族有不同规矩。迪恩(12)啊，你能回来真是太让人高兴了。”

琴和马特·阿明一起为司机安排好住宿，然后和法缇玛到她丈夫屋子里去。他们问琴是否已经吃过饭，琴说没有，他们就给琴做了一顿虾酱米饭。虾酱是用极辣的生鱼虾肉糊做成的，马来人把它们保存在倒立起来的混凝土排水管里。不久，精疲力竭的琴用她的棕榈叶袋子做了一个枕头，就像过去上千次那样躺到一个垫子上，把围在腰上的纱笼松开，进入了梦乡。说她在过了三年有床可睡的生活之后，在地板上睡得很安稳并不完全准确。她一晚上醒来了很多次，听着晚上各种声响，看着洒满屋子的月光，满心高兴。

次日早上，她跟法缇玛、梅里亚姆和老祖贝达围坐在房子后面的锅旁聊天，以免受到男士们打扰。“我离开后每天都想起这个地方。”她说，这并非绝对真实，但也八九不离十。“我工作和生活的时候，就想起你们所有人的工作和生活。我在英国工作，在办公室做案头工作，就跟我们国家其他不得不工作的女士一样。因为，正如你们所知，我很贫穷，必须一辈子工作来养活自己，直到找到一位如意郎君，而我又那么挑肥拣瘦。”女人们笑了，老祖贝达说：“女人要以那种方式自己养活自己还真是件怪事。”

梅里亚姆说：“我们民族有一个女人在瓜拉拉吉特的银行工作。我从窗户里看见过她。她正在用手指头敲一个机器，机器发出像钟一样的踢踏踢踏声。”

琴点点头。“我在我的国家就是这样挣钱的，用类似那样的机器替我的老爷打印信函。但最近我的舅舅去世了。他住得离我很远，只与我见过一次面，但他没有其他亲戚了，我继承了他的遗产。所以现在我不需要工作了，除非我乐意。”女人们发出一阵赞羡的低语声。此时又有几个人加入了谈话的圈子，她们的队伍越发壮大了。“现在，我人生头一回有了这么多钱，我比以前任何时候都更加想念在瓜拉德朗的你们，想念我们身为战俘住在这里时，你们给予我们的恩惠。我意识到我必须报恩。我将以一个女人的身份送给瓜拉德朗的女人一件礼物，这件礼物跟男士们毫无关系。”

在她周围的女人之间爆发出一阵愉快兴奋的低语声。老祖贝达说：“这倒是真的，男人们什么都不缺。”有几个女人听到这个异端邪说，震惊得目瞪口呆。

“我考虑了很多遍，”琴说，“认为这个地方应该有一口井，这样你们就不需要早晚去泉边打水，而只需走出房子，最多走个五十步就有一口井，井里有新鲜水，旁边放着水桶，每当你们需要凉快的新鲜水时，都可以随时出来打。”又是一阵赞赏的低语声。“井的周围应该有光滑的石头，在年轻小伙子们替你们用桶打水的时候，你们可以坐在石头上聊天。我会在井边修建一个用聂帕榈做顶的屋子给你们用来洗衣服，里面有光滑的长条石板，或者混凝土板，那样你们就可以面对面洗衣服，边洗边聊。屋子四面用聂帕榈墙围起来，那样男人们就看不见你们在做什么了。”低语声变成一阵兴奋的喧闹声。“这就是我想做的事情，作为我对你们恩惠的回报。我会请一个挖井队过来挖井，并付钱给泥瓦匠，让他们弄好井旁的石头，还会请木匠过来修建洗衣房。但我想请几位经验丰富的女士给我提提建议，告诉我应该如何进行室内布置——关于洗衣板的高度，混凝土水池或者水渠，等等。这是女人送给女人的礼物，在这件事情上，男人要对女人唯命是从。”

接下来是一阵长时间的热烈讨论。一些女人怀疑男人们会不会允许这么一件事物的存在，有一些则怀疑，她们的祖母和母亲都对目前的打水方式相当满意，希望改变它是不是会有不虔诚的嫌疑。但如果这一革新有可能成为现实，几乎所有女人都对它充满渴望。一旦她们不再对这个主意大惊小怪，就开始反反复复地思考它，检查每一个细节，讨论井、洗衣间、混凝土水池和水渠的最佳位置。两个多小时后，她们都全心全意接受了这个主意。琴满心欢喜，因为它将使她们真正受惠，也是她们目前最想要的礼物。

那天晚上，她和马特·阿明面对面坐在他屋子前面的小门廊上，就像以前无数次一样。她要跟他谈谈与女人们切身相关的事情。她抿了一口咖啡。“我要来和您谈一谈，”她说，“因为我想回报此地对我们的恩惠，好让人们记住，白人夫人曾经来过这里，你们对她们非常仁慈。”

他说：“今天一整天我妻子净在和其他女人一起谈这件事情。她们说你想挖一口井。”

琴说：“是真的。这是一份送给瓜拉德朗的感恩之礼，来自所有英国夫人。但因为我们是女人，所以这份礼物送给此地女性比较合适。当我们住在这里的时候，打水任务非常繁重，我们早晚都要去泉边打水。在英国的时候，每次想起她们我都觉得非常难过。这就是我打算在村子中央挖一口井，作为感恩之礼的原因。”

他说：“对于她们之前的母亲和祖母而言，能够喝上泉水就已经心满意足了。如果她们有一口井，难免会生出很多与其地位不相配的念头。”

她耐心地说：“那样一来，她们将会有更多精力来尽忠尽责地伺候您，脾气也会变得更加温柔，马特·阿明。您还记得蕾哈娜·宾蒂·伊斯梅尔吗？她去打水的时候失去了肚子里三个月大的孩子。”她能说出这件事情来，使他倍感震惊，但英国夫人一向口无遮拦。“后来她病了整整一年，我不认为她以后还会对丈夫好声好气的。如果当时她们有这个作为感恩礼物献给您的井，悲剧就不会发生了。”

他说：“真主安排女人的命运，就像他安排男人的命运一样。”

她温柔地笑了。“我需要提醒您吗，马特·阿明？《古兰经》上写道：‘人性是贪吝所支配的。如果你们行善而且敬畏，那末，真主确是彻知你们的行为的。’”

他用手拍打大腿，大笑道：“你住在这里时，每次想管我要点什么，就过来向我唠叨这句话。但你走了之后我就再也没听到过它了。”

“让女人们拥有她们的井，确是行善的。”她说。

他仍然笑着，回答道：“我这样跟你说吧，琴小姐。当女人们像渴望这口井一样渴望一样东西时，她们一般都会得到它。但这是关乎整个村子的大事，我必须和兄弟们商量。”

第二天早上，男人们聚集在聂帕榈棚屋市场的阴凉处开会，全都坐在脚跟上。不久他们把琴叫过来。琴在他们身旁坐下，稍稍别过身子去，女士这样坐是很得体的。他们问她打算把井挖在哪里，以及聂帕榈洗衣房的位置。她说一切都掌握在他们手中，不过如果在蔡山的店铺前面那块空地上挖井，并把聂帕榈洗衣房建在井的西面，对着阿罕默德的屋子，对于女人们来讲会很方便。他们都站起来去视察地形，从所有角度展开了讨论。村子里所有女人都站着围观，见证她们的主人做出这个重要的决定。而迪恩则加入了他们的讨论，好像她也是他们当中平等的一员。

她并没有催促他们匆忙下决定。她在这个村子里住了三年，知道他们思考过程非常缓慢，也知道他们在面临任何革新的时候有多么小心翼翼。他们花了两天时间，最终决定拥有一口井是好事，如果他们着手挖井，真主的愤怒不会落到他们头上。

挖井是一件技术性很强的差事，沿海一带只有一个家庭可堪重任。他们住在离关丹大约五英里远的地方。马特·阿明口授了一封信给当地的阿訇，请他写成爪哇文，然后村民们把信带到瓜拉拉吉特寄出去。琴托人从哥打巴鲁送来五袋水泥，并在瓜拉德朗安顿下来，打算工程进行期间在村子里住几天。

她常常跟渔夫们一起出海，要不然就坐在沙滩上和孩子们一起玩耍。她教他们堆沙堡，用手指在沙地上画出方格玩画圈打叉游戏。她常常在海里洗澡和游泳，水稻收割时节在稻田里劳动了一周。她和这里的人一起生活了很久，所以也很耐心地悠然度日。况且，既然已经没有必要继续上班，她也需要利用这段时间来思考新的人生目标。她闲居了三周，一点儿也不觉得无聊。

挖井队和水泥大约同时到达，工程开始了。挖井队是一家人，灰胡子的父亲叫苏莱曼，两个儿子叫雅各布和侯赛因。他们花了一天时间勘察土地，所有关于在哪里挖井的争论又重演了一遍，好让这些专家满意。后来终于可以开始动工了，工程进行得又快又好。挖井队从黎明一直忙活到黄昏，一个人在洞底，另外两个人在上面将挖出来的土堆在洞外。他们一边挖一边从上往下铺砖，用插入洞壁的木桩支撑砖墙。

那位父亲老苏莱曼对村子而言是一座信息的宝矿，因为他在马来亚东海岸走南闯北，修建和维修水井，不时走遍大部分村庄。瓜拉德朗的男男女女都习惯坐在周围，一边看他们挖井，一边和老人家扯些闲话，打听沿岸熟人和亲属的信息。一天下午，琴坐在一旁，向他说道：“您是从关丹来的吗？”

“从巴图沙瓦，”那位老人家说，“从关丹步行需要两个小时。我们的家在那里，但我们总是在旅行。”

琴沉默了一会儿，然后问道：“您还记得战争第一年主管关丹军事的那位日本军官，渚蒲大尉吗？”

“当然记得，”那位老人家回答说，“他是一个很坏的人，他离任时我们都很高兴。接替他的市野大尉要好一些。”

他似乎不知道渚蒲大尉已经死了，琴感到很惊讶。她以为战争犯罪委员会会去关丹调查取证。她告诉他：“渚蒲大尉现在已经死了。他后来被派往负责修建泰缅铁路，在那里滥施暴行，还谋杀了很多人。但同盟国战后逮捕了他，他以谋杀罪名接受审判，在槟城被处决了。”

“这个消息真是大快人心，”老人家回答，“我要告诉我儿子。”他向井里大声说出这个新闻，几位男士进行了简短的讨论后便继续工作。

琴问：“他在关丹做了很多邪恶的事情吗？”其中一件仍然留在她脑海里，记忆犹新，但她不想听见自己把它说出来。

苏莱曼说：“很多人被折磨死了。”

她点点头。“我自己就看见过一次。”话已经藏不住了，而且她在这位不相干的老人家面前无须顾忌。“那时我们都在挨着饿，生着病，一个被俘的士兵向我们伸出了援手。日本人抓住了他，对他施以酷刑，把他的手钉在树上打死了他。”

“我记得那件事，”老人家说，“那个人就在关丹的医院里。”

琴睁大双眼看着他说：“老人家，他什么时候在医院里？他死了。”

“也许是两个人吧。”他向井里的雅各布喊道，“那个战争第一年在关丹被施以酷刑，被打伤的英国士兵，这位英国夫人认识他。告诉我们，那个英国人死了吗？”

侯赛因插进来说：“被打的是个澳大利亚人，不是英国人。他是因为偷鸡被打的。”

“确实如此，”那位老人家说，“就是因为偷了黑公鸡。但他死了还是没死？”

雅各布从井底往上喊道：“那天晚上渚蒲大尉把他放了下来，他们把钉子从他手里拔掉。他没死。”

————————————————————

(1) 原文如此，但庄妮·霍斯福尔在乔出场之前就已经去世了（第三章）。

(2) 指耶稣。

(3) 指上帝。

(4) 属于基督教新教会圣公会派，主要观点包括反对烦琐的宗教仪式，强调基督教徒要提高对现实世界的责任心，等等。

(5) 《古兰经》第21章35节。

(6) 纽卡斯尔的英语是Newcastle，new是“新”的意思，castle是“城堡”的意思。

(7) 在新加坡。

(8) 也门首都。

(9) 斯里兰卡首都。

(10) 缅甸首都。

(11) 马来亚港口城市。

(12) “琴”的音误。

第六章

当琴·佩吉特走下星宿号的舷梯，双脚踏上达尔文机场的时候，心里荡漾着阵阵难以名状的狂喜。我想，事实上直至彼时她才真正走出了战争的阴影。归国后，她来到英格兰，在帕克和利维公司工作了两年，高质高效，但在为人处世上，她一直把自己当成一个五十岁的人。她活着，但如槁木死灰一般。关丹的悲剧一再在她脑海深处重演，慢慢绞杀着她的青春。只有那一次，当她告诉我，她觉得自己已经七十岁时，才流露出了真情实感。

她于八点十五落地，夜幕已降临。下飞机的时候，澳航已经帮她在达尔文酒店预订了一个房间。她踏上混凝土地面，有人给她指路去位于飞机库内的海关。三位年轻小伙儿在舷梯脚下仔细打量她。那时她以为他们是机场官员，后来才知道是澳大利亚各家报社的记者。他们毫无疑问摊上了所有新闻工作中最糟糕的差事：在达尔文机场迎接每架飞机降落，希望从飞机上下来一位首相，或是长了两个脑袋的女人。

她一过关，其中一个记者就走向她。这班飞机的乘客平淡无奇，很难从他们身上挤出故事来。然而，一个满脸洋溢着快乐的姑娘却可能暗藏玄机。他说：“请问是佩吉特小姐吗？听机组成员说您在这里下飞机，并且要住进达尔文酒店。您是否愿意搭我的便车进城？我的名字是斯图尔特·霍普金森，这儿《悉尼监督报》的代表。”

她说：“您真是太好了，霍普金森先生。但我不想让您为了我而兜远路。”

他说：“我自己就住在那里。”他有一辆小型沃克斯豪尔，泊在飞机库外面。他帮她拿手提箱，把它放在后座上，然后两人上了车，一边闲聊星宿号和这次飞行。不久，当他们驶过维斯提屠宰场时，他说：“您是英国人吧，佩吉特小姐？”她说是。“请问您能否告诉我您来澳大利亚的原因？”

她笑道：“恐怕不太方便，霍普金森先生。只是一些私事——编不成一个有趣的新闻故事。我是不是从这里下车自己走？”

“不用，”他说，“我只是随便问问。我已经有一个星期交不出稿了。”

“我要是说我就是觉得达尔文很棒，对您会有帮助吗？‘伦敦打字员对达尔文赞赏有加’？”

“我们不能嘲讽伦敦，在《悉尼监督报》上不行。您是一个打字员吗？”

她点点头。

“出来找对象结婚？”

“我不认为是这样。”

他叹口气。“恐怕您对我的新闻不会有什么贡献。”

“请告诉我，霍普金森先生，”她说，“从这里怎么坐公共汽车去爱丽丝斯普林斯？我想去那里，但手头并不宽裕，所以我想还是坐公共汽车吧。有去那里的公共汽车吗？”

“当然了，”他说，“今天早上就有一班车。您要等到周一，周末不发车。”

“要坐多久？”

“两天。您周一出发，当天晚上到达戴利沃特斯，周二晚上到达爱丽丝。一路上不会太辛苦，但热得很。”

他把她送到旅馆，帮她把包拿进走廊。她居然能在那样一个人满为患的地方订到一个单人房，而且房间还带有可以俯览海港美景的阳台，实在是太幸运了。达尔文很热，是一种让人恹恹缩缩的湿热，即便是最轻微的动作也会令她汗流不断。这对她而言并非什么新鲜事，因为她对热带天气已经习以为常。她把门锁好，脱掉衣服，洗了一个淋浴，在洗手盆里洗刷一番，几乎一丝不挂地睡下了。

第二天她一早醒来。黎明的空气凉爽清新，她继续躺了一会儿，思考自己的处境。现在的头等大事是找到乔·哈曼并和他好好谈谈。然而，和霍普金森先生碰过面后，她也警惕到未来可能会遇到的困难。不管这些年轻人看起来有多么友善，他们的任务是为报纸探寻新闻。她一点儿也不希望自己的名字出现在报纸头条，但她来澳的目的一旦被发现，这将无可避免。“英国姑娘飞越重洋，追寻为己受刑之士兵……”如果她是男人的话，就没有这些烦恼了。

然而她不是。她开始给自己编造一个故事：她去阿德莱德找姐姐，后者嫁给了在当地邮局工作的霍姆斯先生。这个故事似乎很稳妥。她取道达尔文和爱丽丝斯普林斯，是因为她有一个叫作乔·哈曼的远房表兄应该是在那里工作，但已经有九年没有写信回家，她的舅舅想知道他是不是还活着。她将从爱丽丝坐火车南下阿德莱德。

这不太能解释她坐星宿号去达尔文的原因，不过她可以说，想去达尔文别无他径。她躺在床上，反复推敲这个故事，觉得它似乎滴水不漏。当她起床下楼吃早饭的时候，决定要在斯图尔特先生身上试验一下这个故事的效果。他当天早上告诉她怎么去公共汽车订票处时，她找到了机会。在超过半小时的谈话中，她把它分成风趣的小片段讲了出来，《悉尼监督报》的记者对之深信不疑，她都感到有点羞愧了。

他带她去一个牛奶吧，给她点了一杯可口可乐。“乔·哈曼……”他说，“九年前他在爱丽丝干什么？”

她吮着吸管。“他是牛场上的牛仔。”她故作天真地说，希望自己的表演并未过火。

“牧工？你还记得那个牛场的名字吗？”

“沃拉华，”她说，“那个牛场叫作沃拉华。在爱丽丝斯普林斯附近，是不是？”

“不知道，”他说，“我给你问问。”

午饭后，他回去找她，和《阿德莱德先驱报》的哈尔·波特一起。“沃拉华离爱丽丝斯普林斯远着呢，”波特先生说，“那儿的牧场住宅离爱丽丝肯定有一百二十英里远。您是说汤米·杜维恩的牛场吧？”

“我想是的，”她说，“有没有从爱丽丝斯普林斯去那里的公共汽车？”

“没有公共汽车，也没有其他办法，除了开卡车或者越野车去。”

霍普金森说：“艾迪·麦克莱恩会在那里停站吧，是不是？”

“你这么说我想起来了。”波特转向琴，“麦克莱恩航空公司每周都会飞一遍那些牛场派送邮件，”他说，“你应该可以坐飞机去那儿。那是最轻松的方式了。”

她受到电影的影响，对记者怀有一种成见。但她惊讶地发现，在现实生活中，他们彬彬有礼、善良友好、乐于助人。她由衷地向他们表达了感激之情。他们带她在达尔文四处兜风。她看到仙境一般的雪白沙滩和碧蓝的大海，高兴得大喊大叫，建议举行一个游泳派对。

“有几样东西会破坏这个派对，”波特先生说，“其中之一是鲨鱼。如果你走进齐膝深的水里，它们就会把你拖走。另外一样是短吻鳄。然后还有石头鱼——它不声不响地躺在沙滩上，看起来跟石头一模一样。如果你不小心踩到它，它就会向你喷出一品脱的毒液。僧帽水母也不怎么友好。但真正让我望而却步的是珊瑚耳朵。”

“那是什么？”

“一种长在脑里的肿瘤，由于这些幼细的珊瑚沙进入耳朵而引起的。”

琴得出了结论，也许她还是不要在达尔文游泳了。

但她后来还是去游了一次。周日的时候，他们开车带她顺着一条马路往南走了大约四十英里，到达一个叫作贝里斯普林斯的地方。那是某条河流上的一个深水池塘，非常适合游泳。当她换上两件套泳衣来到两位记者面前的时候，他们都非常好奇地看着她，因为她在瓜拉德朗那几年一直穿当地衣服，身上被晒黑的地方跟普通人很不一样。这是她犯的第一个错误，他们的脑海里头一次掠过一丝怀疑：只要他们能套出她的话来，这个姑娘身上一定藏有一段曲折离奇的故事。

“乔·哈曼……”哈尔·波特若有所思地对斯图亚特·霍普金森说，“我敢肯定之前在哪儿听过这个名字，但想不起来了。”

游完泳后开车往回走时，记者们向她介绍达尔文的情况。他们描画的图片暗淡阴沉。“这里发生的一切都没有好下场，”哈尔·波特说，“屠宰场关门好几年了，因为劳资纠纷——员工罢工太频繁，后来不得不关门大吉。铁路本打算往南修到爱丽丝，连接上从爱丽丝去阿德莱德的铁路——贯穿大陆南北。如果这个工程能够完成，可能会带来一些好处，但后来只修到伯德姆就断了。天晓得现在修得怎么样了。这条马路修好后，差不多把铁路的生意都抢光了——之前做过的所有生意。以前这里有一家冰工厂，但也倒闭了。”他顿了顿，“你在这里每经过一个地方，都能看见许多废墟，都是某些人尝试过却失败了的事业。”

“为什么呢？”琴问，“这个地方还挺不错的，有一个很好的港口。”

“你说得不错。这个地方应当是一个了不起的大港——像新加坡那样。这是北方沿岸唯一一个颇具规模的城市。我不知道。我在这里待的时间实在是太长了，它使我心生畏惧。”

斯图尔特·霍普金森嘲讽地说：“这里有内地症。”他向琴微微一笑，“这在澳大利亚很常见，尤其是在北方。”

她问：“爱丽丝斯普林斯也这样吗？”六年前乔·哈曼向她倾诉的回忆繁华艳丽，与他们对内地的描述非常不一样。

“嗯，”霍普金森说，“爱丽丝不太一样。爱丽丝很好。”

“为什么不一样？”她问。

“我也说不清楚。当然了，它是铁路起点，人们将牛从那里运送至南面的阿德莱德——那是其中一个原因。但它是一个方兴未艾的城市，那里的一切都欣欣向荣。我向上帝许愿，希望《先驱报》会派我去那儿，而不是到这个鬼地方来。”

那天晚上，她和两位朋友告别。第二天黎明，她坐上公共汽车，出发去爱丽丝斯普林斯。这是一辆大型现代贝德福德，流线型的车身沉重厚实，拉着用于装货物和行李的拖车。车上虽然没有空调，但也相当舒适。它沿着宽敞空旷的柏油路往南走，马不停蹄，车速每小时五十英里左右，司机是一位前海军船员。

车子一直开到凯瑟琳才停下，大家下车吃午饭。这是一个郊区，长着非常茂密的桉树。这些桉树非常矮小，琴发现人们把它们叫作胶树。树丛之间是开阔的野草地，没有放过牧，未被开发，荒无人烟。她有一个旅伴是银行检查员，要去藤南特克里克。两人一起讨论这个郊区的情况，他告诉她这一带沿海地区都无法用于农耕，出于某种她无法理解的原因。过了凯瑟琳，土地渐渐变得更荒芜，树木也更稀少干枯。傍晚，他们已经进入了一个沙漠附近的郊区。

薄暮时分，他们停在一个叫作戴利沃特斯的地方过夜。她发现，戴利沃特斯除了一个旅馆、一个邮局和一个大型飞机场之外，就没别的任何东西了。旅馆其实就是许多分散的单层小木屋和男女宿舍，对琴而言非常陌生，但也相当舒服。她晚饭前漫步走出门外，在暮色中东张西望。旅馆前面有三个年轻小伙儿坐在地上。他们一条腿坐在脚跟上，另一条腿伸着，跟乔·哈曼的坐姿一式一样。他们穿着一种骑马裤，脚蹬一种用松紧带扎边的薄底靴子，专心致志地在地面上打扑克。她意识到这是她头一次在这里看到牧工。

她饶有兴味地仔细观察他们。乔·哈曼在参军前就跟他们一样打扮。她真想上前去问其中一人是否认识乔，但这种行为实在有些荒唐，她最终还是抑制住自己。

公共汽车第二天黎明就启程了，继续沿柏油路一直往南开，经过米尔纳潟湖、纽卡斯尔沃特斯、玛奇蒂波，到达藤南特克里克。沿路植被越来越稀疏，太阳也越来越热，他们在藤南特克里克停车吃饭和休息的时候，已经置身于一片纯粹的沙漠中。一个小时后，他们重新出发，沿着酷热的马路南下，时速五十到五十五英里，途经只有两三间房子的小地方。这些地方寂寂无闻，却都取了名字来自抬身价：沃科普、巴罗克里克和艾勒朗。时近傍晚，他们发现自己马上要经过麦克唐纳山脉。在淡蓝的天空下，荒瘠的红色山坡绵延不尽。薄暮时分，他们缓缓进入了爱丽丝斯普林斯，下榻塔尔伯特兵器旅馆。

琴走进旅馆，开了一个面朝阳台的房间。旅馆是单层平房，跟爱丽丝斯普林斯所有其他房子一样。他们一到达旅馆就吃晚饭。她已经知道，在澳大利亚乡村旅馆，如果不准时去吃饭，就什么都吃不上。饭后，她换了一身衣服，走到镇上。她沿着郊区宽阔的道路不紧不慢地散步，仔细观察这个小镇。

她发现这个地方确实就如乔·哈曼所描述的一样，是一个令人愉快的地方，有很多年轻人，朝气蓬勃。尽管地处热带，房子都是平房，但爱丽丝斯普林斯隐约间透着一丝英国郊区的影子，恍惚间有一种家乡的熟悉感。这里也有带花园的独栋房子，花园四周有栅栏或者树篱，围出一片片小天地。街道修得像英国一样，路边种有行道树。如果不去看麦克唐纳山脉，就仿佛回到了儿时的巴西特。大家都说爱丽丝很棒，她现在理解他们的意思了。她知道，她可以在这里为自己营造出快乐的人生，住在其中一栋郊外房子里，也许还有两三个孩子。

她寻路回到主街道，去看沿街的商店。此地名不虚传，任何一个正常的女孩都能在这里找到她想要的一切——美发沙龙、几间好服装店、两间电影院……九点左右，她走进牛奶吧，点了一杯冰淇淋苏打。她想，如果内地都像这里一样，也胜过很多地方。

第二天早晨吃完早饭后，她去旅馆办公室找老板娘，一位德赖弗太太。她说：“我想试着跟一个远房表哥取得联系，他有十年没写信回家了。”她告诉德赖弗太太，自己从伦敦来，要去阿德莱德见姐姐，途经爱丽丝。“我告诉舅舅，我会路过爱丽丝斯普林斯，可以试试看能不能打探到乔的消息。”

德赖弗太太非常感兴趣。“他叫什么名字？”

“乔·哈曼。”

“乔·哈曼！在沃拉华工作的乔？”

“没错，”琴说，“他现在还在那里吗？”

那个女人摇摇头。“战争刚结束时他常常来我的旅馆，但只在这里住了六个月左右。我是战争期间才来到这里的，不太了解之前的情况。他是日本兵的战俘，没错。他们折磨他。他回来时手上有伤疤，他们用钉子刺穿了他的手，还毒打他。”

琴装出一副惊讶和恐惧的样子。“您知道他现在在哪里吗？”“我肯定不知道。可能其中一个牧工会知道。”

在爱丽丝住了三十年的杂工总管老阿特·福斯特说：“乔·哈曼？他回昆士兰了，那是他的故乡。战后他在沃拉华住了六个月左右，后来找到一份牧场经理的工作，好像在海湾地区附近。”

琴问：“您不知道他的地址？”

“不。沃拉华的汤米·杜维恩应该知道。”

“他常常到镇里来吗？”

“是的，他周五在镇里。每隔三到四周就过来一次。”

琴故作天真地问：“我想乔·哈曼去昆士兰时，是举家过去的吧？他们不会还住在这儿吧？”

老人家盯着她说：“我从未听说过乔·哈曼成家的事。他没结婚，至少就我所知没有。”

她自我解嘲说：“我在英国的舅舅以为他已经成家了。”

“我从未听说过他有一个妻子。”老人家说。

琴想了一会儿，然后和德赖弗太太说：“在沃拉华有电话吗？我是说，如果杜维恩先生知道他的地址，我很想给杜维恩先生打电话要这个地址。”

“那里一个电话也没有，”她说，“当然了，在沃拉华，人们通过收音机每天早晚收发消息。”这个地区有一个巨大的电台网络，由医院的航空出诊服务部门经营，医院的接线生每天早晚坐在广播站里，把四五十个牛场都呼叫一遍，通过广播互通消息，传递新闻，并大致确认一切安好。牛场的主妇们在另一头操作。“杜维恩太太今天晚上肯定会收听广播，因为她姐姐艾米正住院待产，伊蒂丝肯定想知道孩子是否已经生了下来。如果你写一份电报，拿给医院的泰勒先生，他今晚就会把消息转达给他们。”

琴回到房间，写了一份得体的电报，拿去医院给泰勒先生，他同意帮忙转交至沃拉华。“八点左右再回来吧。如果他们手头有这个地址，可能到时就已经给我回复了。如果他们一时找不着，可能会明早通过广播把地址告诉我。”这样一来，她那天余下的时间都空闲无事。她回到牛奶吧，又点了一份冰淇淋。

她在牛奶吧交到一个朋友，一个名叫露丝·索耶的姑娘，大约十八岁，牵着一条苏格兰粗毛猎狗。索耶小姐每天下午在服装店上班。她听说琴来自英国，对琴产生了很大兴趣，两人谈论了一段时间英国的情况。“你觉得爱丽丝怎么样？”她过了一会儿问道，语气中透出一丝习惯性的轻蔑。

“我喜欢它，”琴直率地说，“我见过很多不如它的地方。我相信你在这里过得挺愉快的。”

那姑娘说：“嗯，我觉得它还不错。以前我们在纽卡斯尔生活，后来我爸要来这里当银行经理。我们都以为这个地方很糟糕。我所有朋友都说这些内地地方糟糕透顶。我原以为自己在这里住不了多久，但现在已经是第十五个月了，我觉得还行。”

“爱丽丝比内地大部分地方要好，是不是？”

“他们是这么说的——我还没去过别的地方。当然了，这一切都只是在不久前建起来的。他们说战前还没有这些商店。”

琴了解到这个镇的一些历史，其发展之迅速令她非常惊讶。1928年的时候它只有三间房子和一个酒吧，就是铁路从乌德纳达塔修到这里那年。1930年，航空出诊服务系统开始运营，政府在爱丽丝周边地区修建了一些小医院。护士们眨眼间全部嫁出去了。琴了解到，当地绝大部分老住户的女主人是当年的护士。1939年，爱丽丝的人口大约有三百。战争爆发时，这个小镇成为军事物资中转站。战后，人口在1945年增加到大约七百五十，琴在那里的时候大约有一千两百。“战后，所有这些新房子和商店都拔地而起，”索耶小姐说，“现在人们似乎不停涌入这里。”

她建议琴下午晚些时候过来游泳。“麦克莱恩太太有一个很漂亮的游泳池，就在飞机场外面。”她说，“我会打电话给她，问能否带上你。”

她那天下午五点钟去接琴，琴参加了在游泳池举行的游泳派对。坐在黄昏的太阳底下悠然陶醉，远远望着风刀霜剑在厄特瓦山上刻出的线条，她渐渐融入了爱丽丝斯普林斯的社交生活。大部分姑娘和已婚妇女都不到三十岁，她发现她们善良好客，知书达理。她们热切关注英国的消息，有些人很自然地把英国叫作“家”，尽管她们都不曾去过英国。每个人都怀着一个理想，希望有一天能够回“家”旅行。到了晚上，琴满心惭愧，因为这些讨人喜欢的人对她的国家是如此了解，而她却对她们的国家知之甚少。

饭后，她在清凉的夜色中信步走到医院。杜维恩太太一时未能找到乔·哈曼的地址，但她证实了他在海湾地区某处经营着一个牛场。她会请丈夫在次日早晨的通话时间告知乔的地址。

那天晚上，琴仔细考虑拿到地址之后应该做什么。她想了很多。毫无疑问，她刚开始的担忧是多余的。乔·哈曼康复情况良好，能够继续在内地工作。他竟然能够康复至此等程度，她深感惊讶，这个男人太顽强了。虽然现在与他相见已不再是紧迫之事，但她觉得不能不再见他一面就离开澳大利亚。他们两人一别多年，时过境迁，人物皆非。她不害怕再见到他时心生尴尬，她感到自己可以坦诚相告，说她听说他没有死，就过来找他，希望看到他幸福安稳。如果那之后会发生点什么，好吧，那只是那些无可避免的事情之一。

她不知不觉睡着了，嘴边挂着一丝微笑。

第二天早上广播时间结束后，她去到医院，了解到乔·哈曼是米德赫斯特牛场的经理。这个牛场在威尔斯镇附近，她以前从来没有听说过它。泰勒先生非常亲切地拿出一份澳大利亚地图。这份地图经过专门设计，清楚标示出内地牛场各种广播设施和频道频率。他指出威尔斯镇给她看，就在卡奔塔利亚湾吉尔伯特河河口。

“那个地方怎么样？”她问他，“跟这里像吗？”

他笑道：“那儿可是个鬼地方。”他研究了一下地图。“但有一个机场。我不认为它还有点别的什么。我从没去过那儿，也从未听说有谁去过。”

“我要去那里。”她说，“我走了这么远的路，一定要见到乔·哈曼。”

“那儿的生活似乎很艰苦，”他说，“哦，老天。”

“那里会有旅馆吗？”

“哦，那儿会有旅馆的。他们需要一个喝格罗格酒的地方。”

她离开医院，一边想一边走到牛奶吧。她点了一杯冰淇淋苏打，不知为何，她觉得上一次喝它已经是很久以前的事了。喝完后，她沿着大街走了一小段路，拐进一间书店，买了一份澳大利亚地图、一份公共汽车时刻表和一份飞机时刻表。然后她回到牛奶吧，又点了一杯冰淇淋苏打，边喝边研究这几份印刷品。

不久露丝·索耶牵着小狗走了进来。琴说：“我知道乔·哈曼住在什么地方了。现在我要弄清楚怎样去那里。好像没有去那里的公共汽车。”

她们一起研究时刻表。“坐飞机去是最容易的，”露丝说，“现在所有人都那样做。那是贵一些，但不用花那么多时间，因为如果走陆路的话，你要在路上吃很多顿饭，还要住在旅馆里。我下周一会坐麦克莱恩的航班去克朗克里。”

这意味着要在爱丽丝斯普林斯多停留几天，但似乎是最佳选择了。“你可以来跟我们住在一起，”露丝说，“爸妈肯定很欢迎来自英国的人。住旅馆不太舒服，对不对？不过当然了，我从来没住过。”

“那里的人有点醉醺醺的。”琴说。她已经意识到，在澳大利亚有一条严格的规矩：女人决不能踏进酒吧半步。“我很愿意去你家住，如果那肯定不会给你造成很大麻烦的话。”

“我们很欢迎你来。在这里，几乎不可能找到另一个来自英国的人一起谈话。”她们绕路回索耶家，路上遇到了年轻的麦克莱恩太太，一头金发，推着婴儿车。她们停下脚步，琴说：“我必须到海湾地区的威尔斯镇去见乔·哈曼。我可不可以在您的飞机上预订一个周一去克朗克里的座位？”

“我想应该没问题。我正要去办公室，我会让他们把你加入周一的旅客名单。我要不要请他们给你安排从克朗克里继续到威尔斯镇的行程？我想你能直接从克里去威尔斯镇。但如果你想那样做的话，他们要先查一下，看能不能订到机票。”

“您实在是太好了，”琴说，“有劳他们费心了。”

“没问题。今晚来不来游泳池？”

“好的，麻烦了。”

她们继续走到索耶家。那是一间坐落在小花园中的平房，非常漂亮，蔷薇花爬满屋顶，花园里种满了英国花朵，一个洒水器在草地上浇着水。索耶太太头发灰白，是一个很实在的人，对琴的款待热情周到。她带着所有澳大利亚女人对旅馆的厌恶说：“你跟我们一起住比住在那个鬼地方好多了。你来了真好，佩吉特小姐。露丝昨天把你的事情告诉了我们。见到同乡真让人高兴。”

琴回旅馆收拾手提箱，半路在邮局停下。她要写一份电报给乔·哈曼，告诉他她打算去找他。她花了三刻钟吮吸铅笔头，斟酌措辞。最后她写道：

近闻你从关丹酷刑中恢复倍感高兴。我兹在澳大利亚并计划下周去威尔斯镇见你。

琴·佩吉特

她带着手提箱坐出租车去索耶家安顿下来。她和这些友善的人一起待了四天。第三天，她实在不忍心继续向她们隐瞒自己的秘密了，告诉了露丝和露丝的妈妈在马来亚发生的一切，以及她寻找乔·哈曼的原因。她深恐此事被登上报纸，求她们不要告诉其他人。她们同意了，但请她等索耶先生下班后，把她的故事再讲一次给他听。

那天晚上，索耶先生有很多使她感兴趣的话要说。“乔·哈曼可能了解到那儿的潜力。”他说，“海湾地区现在还很荒僻，但他是一个年轻人。在澳大利亚，一切都可能发展神速。二十年前这个镇还什么也没有，但看看现在！海湾地区有一个优势，就是雨水。我们这儿每年有六到七英寸的雨——大概是伦敦的四分之一。乔·哈曼那儿可能有三十英寸——比英国还要多。从长远来看，那肯定是一个巨大的优势。”

他吮着吸管。“提醒你注意，”他说，“那些雨目前对他们来说并未产生什么实际利益，因为它们全部集中在两个月的时间里，并且直接流入海中，并不像你们在英国那样，雨水是分散在全年的。但我去年遇到一个从家乡来的小伙儿，他说要不是每条河上每隔三英里左右就有一个堰，你们英国大部分的雨水也一样直接流入大海。那是澳大利亚人还未能抽出时间来做的事情——保护牧场水源。他们在这方面做了一些工作，但并不很多。”

住在索耶家的那几天里，琴不可避免地听说了露丝·索耶的爱情生活。它有失严肃，主要围绕一个比利·韦克林先生展开。这位先生有路修的时候就去修路。“他在战争中的表现太出色了，”她告诉琴，“二十三岁就当了上尉，但他跟你的乔·哈曼没法比，他还不曾为我受过酷刑……”

“我并没有和乔·哈曼谈恋爱，”琴颇带尊严地说，“我只是想知道他现在平安无事。”

露丝仍在四处寻找适合她的工作。

“我喜欢商店，”她说，“我不可能去学习速记，像你那样。我觉得商店就很好了，但我不知道在服装店工作有那么多意想不到的困难。衣服不上身，我就永远不知道它适合什么人穿。所以我想我永远成不了一个服装设计师。我想经营一个牛奶吧，那是我的理想。我想，开个牛奶吧一定会很有趣……”

琴去银行拜访索耶先生，他以专业人员的身份接待了她。她请他帮忙，等她离开后，把任何到达她账户的收入都汇至威尔斯镇。她周一上午依依不舍地离开了爱丽丝斯普林斯，索耶一家和麦克莱恩一家也满心不舍。

她乘坐一架蜻蜓号飞机飞了一整天，深受启发。飞机并没有直接飞往克朗克里，而是迂回穿梭于澳大利亚中部的荒地，在各个牛场收取小包邮件，顺带捎上牧工和旅行者，飞行一百或者一百五十英里后又放下他们。在当天的行程中，飞机降落了八到十次，在阿马鲁、哈切特河、库伦地、罗克汉普顿山丘和很多其他牛场。每到一处，他们都会下机喝一杯茶，和牛场经理或者主人闲聊，然后再上机继续行程。那天快要结束的时候，琴·佩吉特已经确切知道了牧场住宅的模样，并渐渐对里面发生的一切了如指掌。

薄暮时分，他们到达克朗克里。克朗克里是一个相当大的镇子，坐落在铁路沿线上，该铁路向东直抵汤斯维尔海边。这里属于昆士兰地区，她一听到当地慢悠悠懒洋洋的昆士兰腔调，乔·哈曼的音容笑貌马上扑进了她的脑海。她坐一辆非常旧的敞篷车到达邮局旅馆，要了一个房间。但饭点已过，她只好走到宽阔的中心大街上，在一片尘土飞扬中找餐馆吃晚饭。她发现，爱丽丝斯普林斯那种干净的魅力，在克朗克里连半点也找不到。这里满镇都是牛的气味，街道宽阔，有很多旅馆和几间商店，人们沿着街道将牛群赶进牲畜栏中。所有房子都是木制的，屋顶是漆成红色的瓦楞铁。旅馆都是两层的，但其他房子几乎都只是平房。

她不得不在那里逗留一天，因为去诺曼顿和威尔斯镇的飞机每周只在周三有一班。早饭后，她趁着空气仍然凉爽，走出旅馆，沿着巨大的中央街道走了半英里，来到镇中心一端，再走四分之一英里就到了另一端。然后她去看了一眼火车站。再看完机场后，就几乎把克朗克里看遍了。她顺路到一个卖玩具和报纸的商店转了一圈，但所有读物都卖光了，只剩下几本女装裁缝杂志。气温开始升高的时候，她回到旅馆，设法从旅馆老板娘那里借到了一本澳大利亚的《女士周刊》，拿回房间。她脱剩勉强能遮羞的衣服，躺到床上，在炎热的白天里，任涔涔热汗兀自流淌。克朗克里大部分其他市民似乎都在做着同样的事情。

饭前不久她就恢复了精神。她洗了个澡，去咖啡店点了一杯冰淇淋苏打。昆士兰人称作“茶”的晚饭，竟是油腻腻的烤牛肉和葡萄干布丁，真让她吃不消。黄昏的门廊暮色阴沉，她在帆布躺椅里坐了一会儿，晚上八点又爬上床睡觉。

她黎明前就被叫醒了，在晨光熹微中赶赴机场。这次的飞机是一架复古龙号，跟上一架一样流连于各个牛场之间，像卡农比、温杜拉和米尔加拉。大约中午的时候，经过四五次降落，他们飞经海边，一片荒寂的沼泽地海岸，之后很快就在诺曼顿降落了。半小时后他们重新起飞，飞往康斯坦茨山丘牛场。他们在那里喝了一杯茶，和经理的妻子聊了会儿天，再次起飞，飞往最后一站——威尔斯镇。

他们下午两三点钟抵达威尔斯镇，琴在飞机降落前盘旋的时候得以鸟瞰这个地方。这个郊区桉树茂密，青翠欲滴，吉尔伯特河奔流入小镇脚下大约三英里处的大海。威尔斯镇及其周边地区肯定深涵地下水，因为她可以看到一个木制码头，吉尔伯特河一直延伸至内陆，以她的目力根本望不到头，远蔽在水汽迷蒙的热霾中。然而，所有其他水道都仿佛干涸了。

这个小镇本身由大约三十栋楼房构成，它们非常稀疏地分散在两条巨大的交叉街道边沿——或者说分布在两条土地的边缘，因为街道尚未铺设好。只有一栋是两层的，她后来知道那是旅馆。有许多泥路从镇中心通往各个方向的郊区。那是在威尔斯镇可以看见的一切，此外还有一个华丽的机场，战争期间出于防御目的而修建，有三条巨大的柏油路跑道，每条长一英里。

他们降落在其中一条跑道上，向一辆停在跑道交会处的卡车滑行。这辆卡车载有两桶汽油和一个用于加油的半回转泵。飞行员从驾驶舱下来时向琴说：“佩吉特小姐，您要在这里下吗？有人接您吗？”

她摇摇头。“我想见一个住在这个地区的人，他在其中一个牛场工作。我想我不得不去旅馆了。”

“您要见谁？阿尔·伯恩斯，那边卡车上的壳牌代理商，他认识这儿每一个人。”

她说：“太好了。我想见乔·哈曼先生。他是米德赫斯特牛场的经理。”

他们一起下了飞机。“早，阿尔，”飞行员说，“她(1)需要加大约四十加仑。我马上就看看你的油。乔·哈曼在镇上吗？”

“乔·哈曼？”卡车里的人说，他身材瘦削，黑头发，年约四十。“乔·哈曼在英国。去度假了。”

琴眨眨眼睛，努力定定神。她已经准备好要听到哈曼在自己的牛场上，甚至去了凯恩斯或者汤斯维尔，但做梦也没想到会听到他在英国。她有一会儿头脑混乱得说不出话来，然后又想笑。她意识到两位男士正好奇地盯着她。“我给他发了一封电报，告诉他我马上来找他。”她愚蠢地说，“我想他没有收到吧。”

“不可能收到。”阿尔·伯恩斯慢慢地说，“什么时候发的？”

“大约四五天前吧，从爱丽丝斯普林斯。”

“哦，不，他不可能收到。可能发到了米德赫斯特牛场的吉姆·伦农那儿。”

“那是真的吗？”飞行员问道，“他去了英国？”

“大约一个月前去的。”那个男人说，“吉姆·伦农前几天晚上说的，十月底之前回来。”

飞行员转向琴：“您要怎么办，佩吉特小姐？您现在想留在这儿吗？这个地方可不怎么样。”

她紧咬嘴唇，思考着。“你们什么时候起飞？”她问，“回克朗克里吗？”

“没错，”他回答，“我们今晚回诺曼顿，在那里过夜，明天早上回克里。趁阿尔给她加油，我先去镇里一趟。大约半个小时后起飞。”

克朗克里是她最不想回的地方。“我需要考虑一下，”她说，“我要留在澳大利亚，直至见到乔·哈曼。待在凯恩斯还不错，是不是？”

“哦，凯恩斯是一个很棒的镇，”他说，“汤斯维尔也是。如果您一定要等六到八周，您不会想留在这儿的，佩吉特小姐。”

“我要怎样去凯恩斯？”她问。

“这个嘛，”他说，“您可以和我一起回克朗克里，然后坐火车到汤斯维尔，再往北坐到凯恩斯。我不太清楚坐火车需要花多长时间——肯定有六百到七百英里的路程。或者您可以在这儿等到下周三，下周的今天，坐空中列车直接到凯恩斯，行程大概两个半小时。”

“从克朗克里坐火车到凯恩斯要花多长时间？”

“哦，那我不知道。我想他们不会每天都从汤斯维尔发车去凯恩斯，但我不是很确定。您就按三天一班作计划吧。”他顿了顿，“当然了，最好的方法就是从克朗克里飞去汤斯维尔，再飞去凯恩斯。”

“我知道，”她对这些长途飞行的花费变得非常敏感，但不坐飞机就只能坐火车，而在内地的火车上度过三个星期简直要热死人，“如果留在这里等下周坐空中列车的话，会便宜很多，是不是？”

飞行员说：“哦，便宜很多。从这儿飞到凯恩斯要花十镑十五先令，飞回克朗克里再飞去汤斯维尔和凯恩斯要花大概三十镑。”

“我想这里的旅馆还挺便宜的？”

“我想大约每天十二先令六便士吧，”他转向正在忙着加油的壳牌代理商，“阿尔，康纳太太那里多少钱一晚上？”

“十先令六便士。”

琴飞快地进行了心算，留在这个地方，花一周时间等空中列车，她会省下十六镑。“我想还是留在这里吧，”她说，“那样比跟你回去便宜很多。我会留下来见吉姆·伦农，并等待下周的空中列车。”

“您知道这儿的旅馆是怎么样的吗，佩吉特小姐？”

“就跟克朗克里的邮局旅馆一样？”

“比那个更简陋一些。人们就在后院方便。”

她笑道：“我是不是应该把自己锁在房间里，在床头放一把左轮手枪？”

他有点被震惊到了。“哦，您会发现这旅馆还挺体面的。但是，嗯，您会发现它有一点简陋。”

“我想我能活下来。”

那时另一辆载着几个人的卡车出现了。车里的人好奇地盯着琴看。飞行员帮她拿手提箱，放在后座上，司机帮她坐上驾驶室，让她坐在自己旁边。逃离炫目的太阳，再次进入阴凉的地方，令人觉得轻松多了。

司机说：“留在威尔斯镇？”

“我想见乔·哈曼，但他们说他出门了。如果康纳太太那里有空房间给我住的话，我会在这里待到下周，再坐空中列车去凯恩斯。”

他好奇地看着她：“乔·哈曼去英国了。您是英国人吧？”

卡车沿着宽广的柏油跑道开起来。“没错。”她回答。

他满面笑容地向她道：“我父母都来自英国。我爸，他在刘易舍姆区出生，我想是伦敦的一个区吧，我妈来自赫尔。”他顿了顿，“我叫斯莫尔，”他说，“森·斯莫尔，就像那个扛着火枪的小伙子一样(2)。”

卡车开离跑道，开始跌跌撞撞、摇摇摆摆地走在通往小镇的土路上。驾驶室里尘土飞扬，引擎轰鸣，蓝色的烟气把他们包裹得严严实实。卡车每一个部分都在嘎吱嘎吱地尖叫。“乔·哈曼为什么要去英国？”她扯着嗓子喊道，以期盖过阵阵喧闹声，“他去那里做什么？”

“我想就是一时心血来潮吧，”斯莫尔先生回答，“他几年前赢了珍宝盒。”这在她听来像希腊文。“这个季节在牛场也没多少活儿。”

她喊道：“你知道旅馆有没有空房间吗？”

“哦，有的，您能开到一个房间的。您刚从英国出来？”

“是的。”

“现在家那边的配给制(3)怎么样？”

她大喊着回答他。她一边说，卡车一边颠簸摇摆着前行，穿过沿路片片风光。他们路过一座修在道路旁边的小木棚屋，五十码后又路过左边的一座，往前一点再路过一座，然后就开上了主街道。他们停在一栋两层楼房前，底层门廊上有一个褪了色的招牌，上面写着：“澳大利亚旅馆”。“就是这里了，”斯莫尔先生说，“进来吧，我去找康纳太太。”

澳大利亚旅馆是一座很大的楼房，有大约十个门朝顶层门廊的小房间。地板和门是木的，其余整栋房子都以木作框架，以瓦楞铁做面。那时琴已经习惯了无处不在的瓦楞铁屋顶，但睡房的瓦楞铁墙对她而言还是件新鲜事物。

斯莫尔先生去找康纳太太时，琴在顶层门廊等待。门廊上有几张床。老板娘睡眼惺忪地来到她跟前。老板娘身材高挑，头发灰白，五十岁左右，看起来是个雷厉风行的人。

琴说：“下午好。我叫琴·佩吉特。我不得不在威尔斯镇住到下周。请问您这里有房间吗？”

那个女人上下打量着她。“嗯，我真的说不好。你是单独旅行吗？”

“是的。其实我是来见乔·哈曼的，但他们告诉我他出门了。我要去凯恩斯。”

“你刚刚错过了去凯恩斯的飞机。”

“我知道。他们说我要等一个星期才能坐上下一班。”

“没错。”女人四处张望，“嗯，我说不好。你瞧，男人们通常睡在这个阳台上。那对你来说不太好。”

森·斯莫尔说：“那两间后屋呢，老妈？”

“对了，她可以住那儿。”她转向琴。“在背面的阳台上，能看到后院。你会看到牧工们都去后院上厕所，但我拦不住他们。”

琴说：“我想我能挺住的。”

“你以前在内地的镇子住过？”

她摇摇头。“我刚刚从英国出来。”

“是嘛！英国现在怎么样了？你们吃得饱吗？”

琴又回答一遍。

“我有一个姐姐嫁给了一个英国人，”那个女人说，“住在一个叫作古尔的地方。我每个月都给她家寄去一个包裹。”

她带琴去看房间。房间很干净，有一个相当不错的蚊帐。房间小小的，但向过道开的门正对着向阳台开的双层落地窗，穿堂风很凉快。“没有人走这边的阳台，除了安娜——她是女仆。她睡另一间，如果你晚上听到任何动静，希望你会告诉我。我盯着那个姑娘。”她把话题转向通风，“你把门打开一条小缝，用你的箱子顶着它，那样就没有人能走错门闯进来了。再开着窗，穿堂风就飕飕的了。我在这个地方一直睡得很好。”

她往下扫了一眼琴的手，说：“你还没结婚？”

“没有。”

“嗯，这个地区的每一个牧工都会到镇里来看看你的。你最好有心理准备。”

琴笑道：“我会的。”

“那——你是乔·哈曼的朋友？”

“我俩是战时认识的，”琴说，“在新加坡等船回国的时候。”至少这比她上一个谎言更接近事实。“后来我来了澳大利亚，就给他发了一份电报，说我想来见见他。我没有收到回复，所以就不管三七二十一先过来了。但他却去‘丛林流浪’了。”

那女人笑道：“看来你学会了一些澳洲土话。”

“乔·哈曼教我的，我俩在战争期间认识的时候。”

森·斯莫尔把琴的手提箱拿了上来，她向他道谢，他窘迫地转身走开了。她走进房间，脱下湿答答的衣服，去浴室洗了一个淋浴，换上干爽的衣服。六点半，铃声响遍整座瓦楞铁楼房，她已经准备好吃晚饭了。

她找到下楼去餐厅的路。那里已经坐着三四个人，他们好奇地望着她。一个发育良好的十六岁女孩儿让她单独坐一张已经摆好的小桌子，后来她知道这女孩儿叫作安妮。“烤牛肉，烤羊肉，烤猪肉，烤火鸡，”她说，“茶还是咖啡？”

天气仍然闷热难耐。餐厅里到处都是苍蝇，扑在琴的脸、嘴唇和手上。“烤火鸡。”她说。了解清楚此处食物的供应情况后，明天尽可以优哉游哉地吃一顿清淡的。“茶。”

安妮端上来一个堆满了肉和蔬菜的盘子，热气腾腾，异常油腻，马上招来了一大堆苍蝇。一会儿茶也来了，里面加了罐头牛奶。土豆看起来很新鲜，但胡萝卜和甘蓝明显是罐头蔬菜。她镇静地想道，这些苍蝇很可能以痢疾收场，但她有应对办法。她有充足的磺胺嘧啶帮她挺过这周。她吃了这份巨大盘餐的四分之一左右，喝了两杯茶，就吃撑了。

她马上跑到外面的新鲜空气中去，逃离苍蝇的攻击。底层门廊大约距离地面三英尺高，上面有两三张帆布躺椅，就放在离酒吧入口不远处。她已经深知澳大利亚规矩不允许女人靠近酒吧，但在旅馆里又找不到其他可以坐的地方，只好在其中一张躺椅上坐下来，一边担心着这样做是否会违反当地礼节。

她点燃一根香烟，边抽边看风景。已是黄昏时分，但太阳仍然猛烈，一大片作为街道使用的土地沙尘滚滚，淹没在一片金色的浮光里。街道另一边，一百码开外，有一坐很大的单层楼房，仿佛经过多次加建，挂着一个牌子——威廉·邓肯杂货店。没有任何迹象表明镇里还有其他商店。邓肯先生的商店外面，有三个非白人牧工在一起聊天，其中一个拿着一个马鞍。他们都是人高马大的年轻人，身材健壮，外表很像黑人，同时也像黑人一样，似乎有许多可以嘲笑的事物。

沿着大街另一边更远处，有一条六英寸长的管子，垂直从地上伸出来，高出地面大约八英尺。水从这条管子的顶端喷出，形成一个小喷泉。水仿佛烧得很热，因为有一团水蒸气围绕着小喷泉。水落在地上形成的小溪流一直流向远处，也全程冒着腾腾热气。四分之一英里开外有一座横跨小溪流修建的小屋，这样水可以流进小屋里，从另一面流出，但琴还没有发现这座建筑物的用途。

一阵低语声从酒吧内传进她的耳朵，不时地就有一个男人经过她身旁，走进开着的门。她在这个地方一个女人也没见着。

不久，一个年轻人路过时向她笑道：“晚上好。”她也向他笑道：“晚上好。”

他马上停下脚步，她知道麻烦来了。“我今天下午看见你和森·斯莫尔一起来的。是坐飞机来的吧？”

他是一个外貌整洁的青年庄稼汉，走起路来摇摇摆摆的，一副典型的牧工相。他穿着绿色骑马裤和绑边靴子，一看见它们就知道他的职业。尝试冷语相向是不明智的。“没错，”她说，“我从克朗克里来的。请告诉我，那是天然水资源吗？”

他朝她指的方向看。“天然？那是个钻头。从来没有见过吗？”

她摇摇头。“我刚刚从英国来。”

“从英国来？哦，老天，”他拖着内地那种慢悠悠的腔调说，“英国怎么样？你们吃得饱吗？”

她又回答了一遍。“我老爸来自英国，”他说，“一个叫作伍尔弗汉普顿的地方。离你住的地方近吗？”

“大约两百英里吧。”她回答。

“哦，挺近的。那你应该知道这个家庭。姓氏是弗莱彻。我是彼特·弗莱彻。”

她向彼特解释说英国人还挺多的，又重新回到钻头的话题上。“你们从钻孔钻上来的水是不是都那么热？”

“太对了，”他说，“而且是矿泉水——你不能喝那些水。还有气一起喷上来。我去点着它，如果你想看的话。”他解释说那会喷出大约五六英尺高的火焰。“等天黑一点时我再点给你看。”

她说他人真是太好了，他看起来一脸窘迫。阿尔·伯恩斯，那个壳牌代理人和卡车修理工开车路过，停下来加入他们的谈话。“安顿下来啦，佩吉特小姐？”

“是的，谢谢您。我会在这里待到周三，然后继续去凯恩斯。”

“很好，我们在威尔斯镇很少看到陌生面孔。”

“我正在这里问彼特关于钻孔的事情。彼特，牛喝这些水吗？”

那牧工笑了。“如果它们找不到比它更甜的水就喝。你会发现它们在雨季是不喝这些水的，但旱季时它们喝得挺好。”

“有一些钻头它们是不碰的。”阿尔说，他正在给自己卷烟，“人们在因弗高登放下去一个钻孔，那是这儿和诺曼顿之间的一个牛场——往南一些。人们要往下钻差不多三千英尺才能找到水，真是费了好大力气，哦，老天。钻孔队在那儿干了差不多三个月。后来当他们钻到水的时候，那些水散发着矿物质的恶臭，牛连碰都不碰一下，即使旱季时也不。更可怕的是，那些水连草都种不活。”

又有两个男人过来加入躺椅旁边的小聚会。“请告诉我，”她说，“为什么这个镇的房屋这么分散？为什么不修建得密集一些？”

其中一个四十来岁的新来者说：“过去这儿沿街有很多房子。我有一张这儿的照片，拍于1905年。明天拿来你看。”她后来知道他叫作蒂姆·惠兰，是一个木匠。

“那时这里的居民比现在多吗？”

阿尔·伯恩斯说：“哦，老天。这就是其中一个淘金镇，佩吉特小姐。也许你不知道，但这儿一度有三万人呢。”

另一个新来者说：“八千人。我在一本书上读到的。”

阿尔·伯恩斯固执地说：“我老爸总是说他刚来的时候这儿有三万人。”

这明显是一个古老的辩题。琴问道：“现在有多少人？”

“哦，不知道。”阿尔转向其他人：“你说现在有多少人，蒂姆？”他对一旁的琴说：“他是做棺材的，问他就对了。”

“一百五十人。”惠兰先生说。

森·斯莫尔加入了门廊上的谈话。“目前在威尔斯镇住的还不到一百五十人呢。不会多于一百二十人。”他顿了顿，“当然是指住在镇里的人，不包括牛场的居民。就住在镇上这儿的，不算土著。”

谈话演变成一场小小的争论，所以他们开始坐下来数人数。黄昏的光亮渐渐褪去，琴坐在那里看他们做统计，心想这群人真有趣。最终结果是一百四十六人。数据终于被确认时，她已经听到了镇上大部分人的名字和职业。

“这里以前有金矿吗？”她问。

“没错，”斯莫尔先生说，“他们曾扬言说有一百个呢，都在这些小河沿岸，哦，老天。这儿曾经有十七家旅馆。十七家。”

另一个人说：“那时候轮船从布里斯班驶来这儿——绕过约克角半岛，沿着吉尔伯特河一直往内陆走，去到栈桥那儿。我从未亲眼见到过，都是听我家老头儿说的。”

琴问：“后来发生了什么事？是不是金子都淘光了？”

“是的。他们从河里和礁石表面就能淘出金子，太容易了。后来他们要挖得很深，使用很多机器，那就不值当了。这些镇都一样。克罗伊登是，诺曼顿也是。”

“他们说要在克罗伊登开一个矿——再开一个。”某人说。

“从我记事起他们就老那么说。”

琴问：“但那些房子呢？人们都离开了吗？”

“房子后来就塌了，或者被拆掉，材料用来修补其他房子。”阿尔告诉她，“人们挖光了金子，就不再留在这儿了——他们待不下去。现在这里只剩下牛场了。”

男人们越聊越起劲，琴偶尔插进一两句话或者几个问题。“鬼城，”有人说，“有一次我在书上读到的，他们就这么叫这些海湾小镇。鬼城。那是因为它们都成了鬼魂，只有在过去有金子的时候才是活着的。”

“那并没有持续很长时间，”有人说，“这儿1893年首次发现了金子，到1905年就没多少人了。”

男人们谈话的时候，琴坐着，努力想象这个被抛弃的小城曾经有何等繁盛。那时，它有八千或三万居民，街道交错密布，沿街挤满了十七家旅馆和众多楼房。该镇的设计者，不论是谁，肯定做过一个伟大的梦。当他看见人们源源不断地涌入该镇追求事业，没几天人口就翻一番，自然有理由心生憧憬，要把这里发展成卡奔塔利亚湾的纽约。现在，残留下来的只有许多长方形的泥路，相互交织像一张破烂的网，再也不能称之为街道，其上也不复再见那些木制的楼房。只剩下模样古怪的楼房孤零零地挂在这张网上，仿佛过去梦想的残片。

夜幕降临后，彼特和阿尔出去为琴点燃钻头。他们划了半打火柴来点它，一片火焰猛地向上蹿起，照亮了整个小镇，在水和蒸汽间跳跃闪烁，直到最后被喷上来的一片水浇灭了。他们再次点着了它，琴饱览了该景象。很明显，这是该镇能提供的最佳娱乐节目，他们使尽浑身解数，以博她一笑。“太漂亮了，”她说，“我在英国从未见过类似的景象。”

他们都非常谦虚。“这儿周边大部分小镇都有这么一个可以点燃的钻头。”他们说。

那天的飞行使她非常劳累，九点钟，她向他们告辞，他们都祝她晚安。她走之前把阿尔·伯恩斯稍稍拉到一边。“阿尔，”她说，“我想见吉姆·伦农——他在米德赫斯特工作，是不是？我想在周三出发前见他一面。他会到镇里来吗？”

“他周六会来，”阿尔说，“我敢说他会在这儿过周六，喝格罗格酒。如果我听到任何人去那边，我会托人捎话给他，说你在镇上并且想见他。”

“米德赫斯特的居民会通过广播收发消息吗？”

他摇摇头。“那儿离镇里太近了，不需要那么费事。如果有人生病或者遭遇事故，他们可以带他进城，一个小时左右就到了。护士在医院有收音机。”他顿了顿，“大概明天就有人去那边。如果没有，或者如果吉姆·伦农周六不来，我就周日开卡车送你过去。”

“那真是太好了，”她说，“我不想太麻烦你。”

“不麻烦，”他说，“只是稍稍改变计划而已。”

她上楼睡觉。旅馆用电灯照明，后院有一个油引擎和发电机组，在她房间外面持续地工作着发电。她十点时听到酒吧关门，十点五分引擎停止工作，所有灯都熄灭了。威尔斯镇沉沉睡去。

她第二天在晨光中醒来，房间外面传来人们起床和洗漱的声音。她躺着打盹，聆听早晨的声音。早餐要七点半才开始供应，她起来洗了一个淋浴，准时出现在餐厅。她发现威尔斯镇的标准早餐是半磅牛排，上面盖两个煎蛋。她点了一个煎蛋，不要牛排，这让安妮非常惊讶。“早餐是牛排和鸡蛋。”安妮很耐心地向这位英国女士解释。

“我知道是这样，”琴说，“但我不想吃牛排。”

“好吧，你可以不吃它。”那个姑娘明显感到非常困惑。

“我可不可以只要一个煎鸡蛋，而不要牛排？”琴问。

“你的意思是，只在盘子里放一个煎鸡蛋？”

“没错。”

就食物的问题展开对话在威尔斯镇明显是一种新理念。“我去问问康纳太太。”安妮说，过了一会儿她从厨房回来，端着一个装着一块牛排和盖着两个煎鸡蛋的盘子。“我们只有一种早餐。”她解释道。琴放弃挣扎。

早饭后，她冒险走去大楼外面的厨房，找到康纳太太。“我有一些东西要洗，”她说，“请问我可以用您的洗衣盆吗？还有——您有熨斗吗？”

“安妮会替你做的，”康纳太太说，“把衣服给她吧。”

琴并不打算把衣服托付给安妮。“她有很多活要干，”她说，“而我无所事事。如果我能借用洗衣盆的话，我可以自己洗。”

“那好吧。”

琴整个早上都在底层背面门廊洗熨衣服，就在厨房门口。在那个干燥灼热的地方，把衣服挂在外面的晾衣绳上，十分钟就干了。厨房里的温度肯定接近一百二十度。琴匆忙走进去，从炉子上取走她的熨斗，心想，女人们每天都在这种条件下做三顿热饭，实在是坚毅得令人惊讶。不久安妮走过来，在门廊上东站站西站站，在琴洗衣服的时候偷偷地观察她。

安妮拿起一个装肥皂片的纸板箱。“你放多少这个进水里？”

琴说：“我想每加仑水放一盎司吧，是不是？据我所知就是这样。我就放一点儿。包装上有说明。”

那个女孩儿把包装转过来，细细察看。“在‘使用说明’里写着。”琴说。

康纳太太的声音从她身后的门口传来：“安妮不太认字。”

那个姑娘说：“我能看懂。”

“哦，你会吗？好吧，那你给我们念一念，看包装上写了什么？”

那个姑娘把箱子放下。“我最近练习得太少了。我在学校的时候念得可好了。”

为了缓和气氛，琴说：“你需要做的只是不断把肥皂片放进去，直到水适当起泡。各种水放的量不一样，因为硬度不一样。”

“我用普通肥皂，”安妮说，“我不太会用这种。”

过了一会儿那个姑娘说：“你是护士吗？”

琴摇摇头。“我是个打字员。”

“哦，我还以为你可能是个护士呢。差不多所有来威尔斯镇的女人都是护士。她们在这里都留不长。六个月，然后就受够了。”

大家都不说话。“如果你曾经当过护士，”过了一会儿，那姑娘说，“我想请你开一些药。我最近一起床就觉得很不舒服。今天早上还吐了。”

“那可真糟糕。”琴小心地说。似乎也没别的可说。

“我想我要去医院，”安妮说，“找道格拉斯护士开点药。”

“换我也会这么做。”

当天白天她见到了威尔斯镇大部分有头脸的人物。她穿过马路到杂货店去，尝试买点香烟，但只买到一听烟丝和一包卷烟纸。她在杂货店里和比尔·邓肯聊天，他拿出一块石英石给她看，说里面含有金子。她仔细端详这块石头的时候，学校教师肯莱小姐进来了。半小时后，琴过马路回旅馆，阿尔·伯恩斯来找她，想把她介绍给该郡的文书卡特先生。

下午大部分时间，她和威尔斯镇的其他人一样躺在床上睡觉。白天的热气消散后，她下楼到门廊上，跟昨晚一样坐在帆布躺椅里。牧工们很快就发现了她。他们一个接一个走过来，扭扭捏捏地，在这个英国姑娘面前毫无自信，但又无法抗拒她的吸引力。不久，他们都坐在了门廊上，在她周围形成一个小圈子。

她让他们谈谈他们自己的事情，那好像是让他们放松的最佳办法。“这儿挺好的，”其中一个说，“是一个很不错的牧牛区。这儿的雨水比往南一些的牧场更充足。但我明年就要离开了。我的兄弟在罗克汉普顿的铁路上工作，他说如果我去投奔他，他会让我跟着他们干。”

琴问：“那里的薪水是不是要高一些？”

“嗯，不。我不认为那儿给的薪水很高。我在这儿有五镑十七先令六——当然，那是包食宿和日用的。这是普通骑马放牧人的薪水。”

她感到很惊讶。“那很不错，是不是？对于一个单身男人来讲？”

彼特·弗莱彻说：“这儿的薪水还可以。问题是这个地方实在是太无聊了。”

“你们这里有过电影院吗？”

“有一个小伙子每隔两个星期过来一趟，在郡政厅里放电影——就是那边那栋房子。”她看到一座矮矮的木结构建筑物，像谷仓一样。“他有一个月没来了，但卡特先生说他下周会来。”

“舞会呢？”琴问。

这个问题引起了一阵讽刺的笑声。“他们有时试着举办，但在这个地方很难办起来。姑娘太少了。”

彼特·弗莱彻说：“我们这些来威尔斯镇的牧工大约有五十个，佩吉特小姐，但可以跟我们一起跳舞的未婚姑娘只有两个，多丽丝·纳什和苏西·安德森。我是说年龄在十七到二十二岁之间的姑娘，不包括孩子和已婚女士。”

其中一个牧工坏笑道：“苏西已经不只二十二了。”

琴问道：“但这里的姑娘们都怎么了？这附近肯定还有其他姑娘吧？”

“她们都去市里找工作了，”某人说，“威尔斯镇没有适合女孩儿干的工作。她们去汤斯维尔或者罗克汉普顿——还有布里斯班。”

彼特·弗莱彻说：“那正好是我要去的地方，布里斯班。”

琴说：“这么说，你们不喜欢在牛场上工作？”她想起乔·哈曼和他对于内地的满腔热爱。

“哦，牛场挺好的。”彼特说。他迟疑了一下，不确定该如何准确地向这个英国女士表达他的感受，同时避免一时大意说出脏字。“我的意思是，”他说，“一个小伙子有权利找一个女朋友结婚，就像任何其他人一样。”

她盯着他看：“真是这样吗？”

“这儿是个鬼地方，”有人说，“这儿真是个鬼地方。不是开玩笑，女士。五十个单身汉争夺两个未婚姑娘。老爷们儿在这儿讨不到媳妇儿。”

另一个人向她解释道：“您瞧，佩吉特小姐，如果一个姑娘是正常的，脑子没坏——比如说，就像您这样——就不会留在这儿。一旦到了可以离家的年纪，你就会离开这儿，去一个能找着工作的地方，自己养活自己。老天，你会的。留在威尔斯镇的姑娘都有点笨，在其他地方混不下去，要不就是想留下来照顾老人。”

另一个人说：“那样想的姑娘会带老人一起进城。像埃尔西·弗里曼。”

琴笑道：“你是说，如果你留在威尔斯镇，最终只能娶一个不怎么抢手的姑娘了。”

他们尴尬地面面相觑。“嗯，小伙子都想周游四方……”

“如果你们都进城，周游四方的话，谁来经营这些牛场呢？”琴说。

“让经理为此而头疼吧，”彼特说，“我自己的事儿就够我头疼的了。”

那晚饭后不久，一辆破旧的老雪佛兰越野车开来旅馆。它的车头是一个驾驶室，车身则像卡车一样是敞篷的。司机是一个瘦削的男人，五十来岁，看起来弱不禁风。他旁边坐着一个棕色皮肤的女孩儿，二十到二十五岁，皮肤光滑，面容安详。她不是纯本地人，但很可能只有四分之一白人血统。她穿一条鲜艳的红色连衣裙，抱着一只小猫咪，它显然是她的一大乐趣。他们穿过门廊进入旅馆，男人拿着手提包。他们显然要在旅馆过夜。饭点时，琴看见他们和男人们一起坐在另一张桌子旁边，但几乎不跟别人说话。

饭后琴问康纳太太他们是谁。“那是埃迪·佩吉，”她说，“是卡莱尔牛场的经理，那牛场大约在一百英里开外。那个土著女人是他太太，他们过来购物。”

“明媒正娶的妻子？”琴问。

“哦，是的，他和她是合法结婚的。布什修士会的科普兰修士去年正好在那儿，为他们主持了婚礼。他们时不时来我这儿住。我必须说，她从未惹过任何麻烦。当然了，她是文盲，话也不多，总是带着一只小猫咪或者小狗。她就喜欢小猫小狗什么的。”

琴想起那个男人脆弱却睿智的脸，觉得这对夫妻很不般配。“我真想知道他为什么要这么做。”

康纳太太耸耸肩。“我想是寂寞的缘故吧。”

那晚琴上楼回卧室的时候，看见一个人站在俯瞰后院的阳台上，倚在扶手旁。阳台上只有两个睡房，她的和安妮的。在微弱的光线中，她走向双层落地窗时说：“晚安，安妮。”

那个女孩向琴走来。“我一直感觉很糟糕，”她嘟囔道，“介意我问你件事情吗，佩吉特小姐？”

琴停下脚步。“当然不介意，安妮。什么事？”

“你知道怎样打掉婴儿吗，佩吉特小姐？”

琴在早上的对话后，对这句话早有心理准备。一阵对孩子的深切惋惜涌上心头。“我很抱歉，安妮，但我不知道。我不认为你应该那样做。”

“我去找道格拉斯护士了，她告诉我我的问题。老爸知道了肯定会狠狠揍我一顿。”

琴执起她的手，把她拉进卧室。“进来，告诉我是怎么回事。”

安妮说：“我知道有一些办法，比如吃点什么药，或者去骑马，或者类似的事情。我想也许你以前也被迫这么做过，应该知道办法。”

“我从不需要这么做，安妮。我不知道，为什么你不让他娶你，名正言顺地把孩子生下来？”

那个姑娘说：“我不知道孩子是谁的。他们都会赖账的，不是吗？”

这是一个琴从来不需要面对的问题。“我想他们会的。”

“我想去问问我的姐姐贝西。她应该知道。她结婚前就有俩小孩儿了。”

看来贝西在这方面的知识对她不会有什么用。“护士难道不会帮助你吗？”

“她只说我是个荡妇。那没什么帮助。就算我是个荡妇吧。在这个鬼地方也没别的事情可做。”

琴尽她所能好言相慰，但话语对安妮毫无用处。她关心的不是道德问题，而是现实问题。“老爸知道后，肯定会大发雷霆，”她忧心忡忡地说，“他会打死我的。”

琴无能为力，不久她们各自上床睡觉。琴久久不能入寐，苦苦思索人类遭受的各种痛苦。

她继续在威尔斯镇待了两天，坐在门廊上和牧工们聊天，参观镇上各座建筑物。肯莱小姐带她去学校，道格拉斯护士带她去医院，卡特先生带她去郡政厅——那里的公共图书馆只有少得可怜的几册书。沃特金斯先生带她去苍蝇横飞的银行，海恩斯警察长带她去警察局。周末时，她对威尔斯镇已经非常熟悉了。

吉姆·伦农跟预想一样，周六进镇买格罗格酒。他开着一辆国际越野车，比普通汽车大一号，前座后面拖着一个像卡车那样的车身，装备着七十加仑的油箱和五十加仑的水箱。琴知道那是乔·哈曼的财产。伦农先生身材瘦削，皮肤棕黄，沉默寡言。

“我昨天收到了一封航空邮件，”他拖着那种懒洋洋的昆士兰调子说，“乔已经坐上轮船，启程从英国回来。他说预计十月中旬到达。”

“我知道了。”琴说，“我想在回英国之前见他一面。我已经计划好周三飞去凯恩斯，在那里等他。”

“好的。我觉得你要在这儿等他的话也太无聊了。我想邀请你去米德赫斯特，但那儿更无聊。”

“乔在英国都做了些什么，伦农先生？他告诉您他去那里干什么了吗？”

牧工笑道：“我连他要去英国都不知道。我只知道他要去布里斯班，后来我收到信说他去英国了。我不知道他为什么去。他确实在昨天给我的信里说，他见到了一群属于一位丹尼斯·弗兰普顿先生的赫尔福特牛，那群牛棒极了。也许他把牛运到国外去育种了吧。他什么也没跟我说。”

她告诉他，她的地址就是凯恩斯的海滨旅馆，请他收到乔到达的准确消息后通知她。

那晚，她照常坐在门廊的躺椅上，阿尔·伯恩斯带了一位蓄着胡须的老人家来见她。这位老人家非常腼腆，阿尔费了不少力气才把他从酒吧里拽了出来。他拿着一个袋子。“佩吉特小姐，”阿尔说，“这是杰夫·波科克。”琴站起来和他握手。“我想你会很乐意认识杰夫的，”阿尔兴奋地说，“他是全昆士兰最好的短吻鳄猎人。是不是，杰夫？”

老人家摇摇脑袋。“我从很小的时候就开始捕猎短吻鳄了，”他说，“我想现在还算是个内行吧。”

阿尔说：“他有一张鳄鱼皮要给你看，佩吉特小姐。”他又向老人家说：“把你的鳄鱼皮给她看一下，杰夫。我打赌她从未在英国见过那样的皮。”

杰夫·波科克拿起袋子打开，拿出一小张卷起来的鳄鱼皮。“当然了，”他说，“我已经自己把它洗干净、裁剪好并晒干了。我一般只是用盐腌起来卖给制革厂。”他在她面前的地板上摊开鳄鱼皮，“斑纹很漂亮吧？我敢打赌您在英国没见过这样的鳄鱼皮。”

它惹起了琴的乡愁。她想起了佩里维尔西大道上红彤彤的公共汽车，帕克和利维公司，一排排姑娘们坐在工作台边制作鳄鱼皮鞋、手提包和化妆盒。她笑了。“我在英国见过成百张这样的鳄鱼皮，”她回答道，“这是我真正了解的一样东西。我曾经在一个手提包和化妆箱工厂工作，原材料就是这种皮革。”她拿起鳄鱼皮，轻轻抚摸着，“我想我们用的皮比这张硬。你把它加工得非常好，杰夫。”

又有两三个人过来了。他们添油加醋地流传她的故事。她告诉他们关于帕克和利维公司的一切。他们对此很感兴趣，没有人知道这些皮革被卖出海湾地区后的下落。“我知道他们拿它做鞋子，”杰夫说，“但我一双也没见过。”

琴在脑海里形成了一个模糊的主意。“像这样的皮，你们每年能找到多少张？”她问。

“去年我卖出去八十二张，”那位老人说，“不算很多。几乎都是三十到三十六英寸宽的皮。一条大概十一英尺长的短吻鳄。”

“杰夫，你能把这张卖给我吗？”

“你要来做什么？”

她笑道：“我想用它来给自己做一双鞋子。”她顿了顿，说，“如果蒂姆·惠兰可以给我做一双鞋楦的话。”

他一脸窘迫。“不要钱，”他生硬地说，“我把它送给你吧。”

她和他争论了一小会儿，然后感激地收下了。“我们要找一点小牛皮做鞋底，”她说，“以及更厚一些的材料来做鞋跟。”

她在手里抚弄着这张鳄鱼皮。“真柔软啊，”她说，“让我告诉你们它的用途。”

————————————————————

(1) 指飞机。

(2) 可能是指英国西汉姆联队的足球队员Sam Small（1912—1993）。

(3) 特殊时期（如战争时期或经济危机时期）对某些稀缺资源和商品实行的分配制度，由政府控制配给数量。当时战争刚结束，英国资源紧缺，所以澳大利亚人有此一问。

第七章

那双鞋是琴在卧室的化妆台上做出来的。更准确地说，她失败了两次，才最终成功做出一双能给自己穿的鞋来。

这项工作从蒂姆·惠兰开始。蒂姆时不时为各个鞋匠制作鞋楦，内地的木匠必须十八般武艺俱全。琴把自己的一只鞋借给他，让他在他的木工车间里测量她的脚。他花了几天时间，用围篱树的木头给她做了一双鞋楦。她请彼特·弗莱彻帮忙寻找制作鞋底和鞋跟的皮料，他提供了几张晒干的牛皮，厚度大约适于做鞋底，还有一张用来做鞋跟的公牛皮。最初，衬里是主要的难题，直到有人提议使用幼年沙袋鼠的皮。彼特·弗莱彻出去射杀了一只沙袋鼠，剥下它的皮。由彼特·弗莱彻、阿尔·伯恩斯和当·邓肯组成的委员会负责在比尔·邓肯店子背后将其晒干。这项做鞋工作在威尔斯镇的生活中变得如此重要，琴推迟了去凯恩斯的旅程，一周又一周。

用作衬里的沙袋鼠皮还未完工，所以琴用一块从小商店买来的白缎子做了第一双鞋的衬里。从一个旁观者和办公室职员的角度，她非常熟悉做鞋的每一个步骤，但她毫无实践经验，所以做出来的第一双鞋糟糕透顶。它们看起来是一双鞋，但脚尖部分太紧，箍疼了她的脚趾，鞋跟也宽了四分之一英寸。它们还弄疼了她的脚背。缎子衬里很不成功，顺着手指流下来的汗把整件工作弄得一团糟。但无论如何，它们总算是一双鞋，只要有人的脚恰好是这个形状，还是可以穿上它走路的。

那么丢脸的一双鞋，她是不能拿下楼去给男人们看的。她开始做第二双。她让蒂姆帮忙改一下鞋楦，从小商店买来另一把刀子和一块小研磨石，再次开工。固化剂方面，她使用小管装的德克斯牌，也是从小商店买的。

安妮对整个工作过程都表现出了浓厚的兴趣。在琴修边、打磨鞋底或者小心地把湿鳄鱼皮放到鞋楦上的时候，她常常过来坐在一旁仔细观察。“我觉得你真是太聪明了，居然会做鞋。”她说，“它们差不多就跟你能在商店里买到的那些一样好。”

第二双有所进步。琴穿起来非常合脚，但袋鼠皮衬里不平整，还起块儿。整件工作也还是一团糟，鞋子沾满了汗渍和指纹。她不屈不挠地开始做第三双。既然无法裁剪沙袋鼠皮，这一次她把厚度均匀的小块皮革拼凑在一起做衬里。她大清早起来完成了最后的组装步骤，因为那时双手出汗最少。最终成果是一双水平相当高的鞋子。五颜六色的衬里非常丑陋，不过她可以穿着这双鞋去任何地方。

她拿着三双鞋子下楼，把它们拿给门廊上的阿尔·伯恩斯看。阿尔招呼了另外两三个人过来，康纳太太也来瞧了一眼。“在英国，鳄鱼皮就是这么用的，”琴说，“人们把它们制成这样的鞋子。很漂亮，是不是？”

其中一个男人说：“你自己做的吗，佩吉特小姐？”

她笑道：“去问康纳太太。她知道我把房间搞得有多混乱。”

那个男人把鞋子拿在手里翻来覆去地看。“哦，老天，”他慢慢地说，“就跟在商店里能买到的一样好。”

琴摇摇头。“没有，”她说，“其实没那么好。”她向他指出鞋子的瑕疵。“我没有合适的曲头钉和固化剂。整体也很邋遢。我把它们做出来，只是想让你们看看他们都如何使用从杰夫那里买来的鳄鱼皮。”

“我打赌你可以把它们拿去凯恩斯卖。”那个男人固执地说，“哦，老天，你绝对可以。”

森·斯莫尔说：“这样一双鞋在英国卖多少钱？”

“在商店里吗？”她想了一会儿，“我想大约四镑十五先令吧。我知道有四十五先令是制造商的利润，但还要算上消费品零售税和零售商佣金。”她顿了顿，“当然了，一双真正的好鞋子可能比这贵得多。人们说在有些商店里要卖十镑呢。”

“十镑？那样一双鞋？哦，老天。”

杰夫当时正在镇外沿河检查他布下的陷阱，所以她那天没有办法把鞋子拿给他看。她把鞋子留给男人们拿进酒吧去评头论足，自己去洗澡。那时她已经发现了在威尔斯镇洗澡的最佳去处，是安妮告诉她的。澳大利亚旅馆有女士专用的冷水淋浴，但水通常都很热，因为水箱曝晒于太阳底下。如果想泡个热水浴，完全有另一个办法。

从那个钻头流出来的水形成一条小小的热溪，一座小木屋跨溪而建，与钻头的距离不远不近，屋内水温正好适合洗澡。人们在屋子里修建了一个粗糙的混凝土池子，大得足以并排坐进去两个人。拿着毛巾和肥皂进屋，把自己锁起来，就可以在流经池子的水里舒服地洗一个澡。温暖的流水饱含盐分，清爽非凡。

琴躺在温暖的水中，独自一人锁在小木屋里。阳光从木缝儿里透进来，在水面跳跃嬉戏。自从她看到杰夫·波科克的鳄鱼皮，脑海里就产生了生产皮鞋的念头。从第一次见我并知道自己继承了这么大一笔财产开始，她一直深感困惑，有时甚至很苦恼，不知道该如何确定新的人生目标。她的教育背景或成长环境无法使她从容不迫地过上一种优雅的生活。她是一个有商业头脑的姑娘，习惯勤恳度日。现在她每年有九百英镑收入，放弃在帕克和利维公司的工作再自然不过，但她尚未找到一份新寄托，来填补生命中因此出现的空白。过去六个月中，她一直在下意识地苦苦探寻，希望能找到值得追求的目标。她唯一真正懂行的工作，是关于高级皮具的——用鳄鱼皮制成的鞋、手袋和化妆箱。她确实懂得一点制作和销售那类皮具的知识。

她躺在这池药浴般的温水中，深陷沉思。假设这里有一个小工厂，里面有五个姑娘在工作，工厂外有一个小小的制革厂。她将需要两台手动印刷机和一台旋转抛光机，那意味着需要供电。她可以置办一个小小的发电机组，除非可以从旅馆买电。还要有一台空调来保持工厂凉快，避免姑娘们工作时满手是汗。做出来的鞋子一定要崭新干净，那是至关重要的。

这样一个工厂能挣钱吗？她边躺着洗澡边默默计算。她发现杰夫·波科夫平均每张鳄鱼皮卖七十先令左右。那是未经加工的皮，她知道帕克和利维要为每张加工好的皮付一百八十先令。据她所知，修剪和晒干一张鳄鱼皮至多需要二十先令的成本，并且是以澳大利亚货币计算的。皮革应该会比在英国便宜很多。劳动力也应该更便宜。威尔斯镇的女性劳动力可能会比佩里维尔的便宜。但还要算上把鞋子运往英国的运费和销售商的代理费。

她想知道帕克和利维公司会不会替她销售皮鞋。她知道帕克先生很早就对制鞋业务兴趣冷淡。他们确实也卖其他人的产品——那些由法国公司生产的手提袋，杜克霍·弗夏尔牌。尽管帕克和利维公司自己生产手提包，但也卖别人的……

她想主要的问题不在于工厂本身。在威尔斯镇，劳动力和材料都很便宜，工厂应该是可以开起来的。但她能否将威尔斯镇的姑娘们训练成才，生产出品质过硬的一流产品，足以放在邦德街的商店出售呢？那才是真正的问题。

她躺在这池药浴般的温水中，深陷沉思。

当天晚上，她照常坐在门廊上的帆布躺椅里，森·斯莫尔向她走来。“佩吉特小姐，”他说，“有时间和我谈谈吗？”

“当然了，森。”她说。

“我一直在想你做的那双鞋子，”他说，“我想知道你能否教教我们的茱迪。”

“茱迪多大了，森？”

“十五岁，”他说，“明年十一月满十六岁。”

“你想让她学做鞋吗？”

他说：“我在想，不管是谁，只要能够做出一双真正的女式皮鞋，都可以把鞋子拿到凯恩斯的商店出售。茱迪马上就到找工作的年纪了。这儿没有任何可以让女孩儿糊口的工作。她将被迫像其他姑娘一样进城。嗯，对她母亲来说，那实在是太糟糕了，佩吉特小姐。我们就这么一个女儿——我们有三个男孩儿，一个女孩儿。如果她像其他姑娘一样去布里斯班，她母亲肯定要发疯的。我想，嗯，也许做鞋这件工作她可以留在家里做。无论如何，看来我们能找到你做鞋所需要的一切材料，就在威尔斯镇这儿。”

“不包括皮带扣，”琴思考着说，“我们要设法找到一些皮带扣。”她一半是在自言自语。

她想了一会儿。“森，那是行不通的。”她说，“你认为那双鞋很棒，但它们并不好。它们拿不出手。在英国，那样的鞋子是卖不出去的，高档皮鞋的消费群体是不会买它们的。我不认为你可以在任何一间一流的商店里出售它们，即使是在凯恩斯。”

“我看着挺好。”他固执地说。

她摇摇头。“它们不行。我以前是干这行的，森——我知道一双符合标准的鞋看起来应该是怎么样的。我不是说我们不能在威尔斯镇制造出一双像样的鞋子，我很想尝试一下。但要把这件工作做好，我需要机器、合适的工作台和手工工具，还有合适的材料。我能理解你关于茱迪的想法，也很想看到她在威尔斯镇工作。但如果要她独自应付这件事情的话，恐怕力所不及。”

他敏锐地看着她：“你是在计划一间工厂之类的吗？”

“我不知道。假如有人在这里开设一间类似的工厂，你们有多少姑娘可以上下午全职上班——如果每周给五镑的话？”

“在威尔斯镇这儿？”

“没错。”

“要满多少岁你才收？”

她想了想。“我想，等她们从学校毕业吧。那是十四岁，对不对？”

“你不会付给一个十四岁的小姑娘每周五英镑吧？”

“不。等她们受过充足的训练，成为熟练工之后。”

他仔细算了算。“我想你能找到六七个十六七岁的姑娘，佩吉特小姐。之后还会有更多毕业生。”

她把话题转向设厂的另一方面。“森，修建一个工厂要花多少钱？”

“多大的？”

她四处张望。“大约从这里到门廊尽头那么长，差不多一半宽。”

“那是三十英尺长，十五英尺宽。你是指修建一座木屋，就像临时军用仓那样的，有一个铁屋顶，还有一圈窗户？”

“就是那样。”

他在头脑里慢慢计算。“大约两百镑。”

“我想我要修一个双层屋顶和一个门廊，就像海恩斯警察长住的那间屋子一样。一定要凉快。”

“啊，那会增加成本的。那样一间屋子，还要有四周环绕的门廊，要花差不多四百英镑。”

“要花多长时间才能建好？”

“哦，我不知道。要从诺曼顿买木材。我想蒂姆·惠兰和他的牧工需要用几个月时间把工厂建好。”

还需另建楼房用于晒染皮革。“请告诉我，森，”她说，“这里的人会不会欢迎这么一间工厂？还是会觉得这个念头有点愚蠢？”

“你是说，如果能让这儿的姑娘们留下来挣钱？”

“没错。”

“哦，老天，”他说，“他们会不会欢迎？只要能让姑娘们高高兴兴地留下来并且有活可干，不管是什么事情，这儿的人都会欢迎的。”他顿了顿，陷入沉思，“姑娘们背井离乡，在这个乡下地区很反常。”他慢慢地说，“我和老妈(1)前几晚还谈论过这件事。很反常。”

他们默默地坐了一会儿。“这事还要好好考虑一下，森。”她最后说。

她乘坐下周三的空中列车离开了威尔斯镇，启程去凯恩斯。她花了两天时间才到达，因为空中列车向来就是那么不紧不慢的。飞机下午离开威尔斯镇，经停多个牛场，收发邮件，并把函授课程递送给在凯恩斯、邓巴、米兰达和万鲁克上学的学生。在最后一抹余晖中，他们于诺曼顿降落，开卡车进镇过夜。

诺曼顿的旅馆跟威尔斯镇的很相似，但要大许多。琴和一位叫作麦肯齐的男飞行员一起吃饭。饭后两人一起坐在门廊里。她问诺曼顿是否有制鞋商。“我想没有。”他说。他向一位熟人喊道：“泰德，这里有人做鞋吗？”

泰德摇摇头。“都是从伯恩斯·菲尔浦公司(2)买的，”他说，“是不是想修鞋？”

琴说：“不是——我只是好奇。这里的鞋子都是从城里进货的？”

“没错，”泰德给自己卷了一根香烟，“我小姨在罗克汉普顿一家鞋厂工作。那儿是很多鞋子的产地。厂名叫万宁·库帕，在罗克汉普顿。伯恩斯·菲尔浦公司就是从他们那儿买鞋的。”

琴问：“您小姨是在这附近出生的吗？”

“克罗伊登，”他说，“她们父亲以前是在克罗伊登开旅馆的，但后来关掉了。那儿一家旅馆尽够了。现在就剩下布莱森太太那家。”

“她没结婚吗？”

“谁？埃尔西·彼得斯？”

“就是在万宁·库帕工作的那位？”

“她未婚。现在肯定是个负责人了，手底下有很多姑娘。”

他离开后，琴问飞行员：“他是谁？”

“他？泰德·霍纳。他在这里经营修车厂。”她记下这个名字，以供将来参考。

他们第二天一大早重新出发，飞往凯恩斯。她坐车进镇，去海滨旅馆。她发现凯恩斯是一个繁荣的小镇，大约有两万人，坐落在入海口处，非常漂亮。那里有好几条挤满店铺的商业街，宽阔的马路中央设有花坛。整个小镇清一色的木楼房，几乎都是铁屋顶。凯恩斯很像她在电影上看到的美国南方腹地市镇，门廊覆盖着宽阔的人行道，人们可以站在阴凉之中欣赏商店的橱窗，但它那泼辣明亮的风格几乎与英国无异。她第一眼就喜欢上了凯恩斯。

她从那里给我写信。她在汤斯维尔给我写了两封信。在海滨旅馆，她收到了我给她写的信。我想那封信在那里放了有一段时间了，因为她在威尔斯镇耽搁了一些日子。她写道：

北昆士兰

凯恩斯

海滨旅馆

我亲爱的诺尔：

我昨天到达此地时，收到你二十四日的信，我想我从威尔斯镇写给你的两封信你也已经收到了。真希望我有一台打字机，因为这将是一封长信。我想我要买一台便携打字机，以便将信件副本保存下来——不是说那些写给你的信，但我开始考虑要在这里做生意了。

首先，非常感谢你告诉我你为乔·哈曼所做的一切。你显然对他非常友好，如你所知，对他友好即对我友好。你说他花了那么多钱匆忙跑到英国去，只是为了再见我一面，我到现在还觉得难以置信。但我想这里的人都是那样做事的。我现在可以告诉你澳大利亚人有多么粗鲁，但我也可以说：我在内地遇到的人全都像乔·哈曼一样，很简单，很诚恳，很真实。

好，然后让我谈一下威尔斯镇。我不知道当乔·哈曼再次见到我时，是否会依然如此渴望和我结婚。六年是一段漫长的时间，而人是会变的。我不知道我是否也依然渴望嫁给他。但如果我们到时不改初衷，他向你描述的威尔斯镇绝对是真实的。

那里真的是糟糕透顶，诺尔。内地有些地方可以让人生活得充实愉快，像爱丽丝斯普林斯就是一个很不错的小镇。但威尔斯镇不是其中之一。诺尔，它绝对是最差的。那里没有任何女士用品，除了一个洗衣盆。我知道一个人没有某些东西也能生活下去，例如广播、唇膏、冰淇淋和漂亮的衣服。我就 能过得很好——我在马来亚时就是这样过的，但如果连新鲜牛奶和蔬果都没有，那就有点困难了。我想乔告诉您的一切都是绝对真实的。我不认为任何直接从英国过来的姑娘能在威尔斯镇生活得开心。我不认为我可以。

而且，诺尔，我不希望看到乔尝试改变他的生活方式。他是一流的牛场经理，日后也会做得很好。我向各种各样的人询问米德赫斯特的经营情况，所有人都赞赏有加。当然，如果他能广为游历，学习其他饲养员的技术，会做得更好，但跟海湾地区的其他牛场相比，米德赫斯特已经相当不错了，而且每年都在进步。上一个经理把它搞砸了，他们是这么跟我说的，但乔在那里工作的两年期间表现出色。我所不愿意看见的是，乔只是因为跟一个不能，或者不愿在他工作所在地威尔斯镇生活的富小姐结了婚，就尝试去其他任何地方谋生。

当然了，你很可能会说，他可以在一个好一点的镇附近找一个牛场，也许就在爱丽丝附近。我不确定那是否是一件容易的事情，关于这点我想了很多。但即使那是有可能实现的，我也不会太喜欢这个想法。米德赫斯特是一个很好的地区，雨水比英国更充沛。作为终身事业，我似乎觉得海湾地区比爱丽丝附近任何一个地方都更有发展前途。如果他只是因为我而弃优择劣，我不会感到高兴。那对于一个农场经理的妻子来说，并不是一个好开端。

诺尔，你觉得我可以预支五千镑遗产吗？你总是试图强迫我接受的那个忠告，三思而后行，我将恪守它。如果我见到乔·哈曼，而我们仍旧想跟对方结婚的话，我会先等待一段时间，要是我能使他同意。我想先在威尔斯镇独立工作几年左右，再决定是否把自己的人生永远交付给它。我想看看，自己是否有希望适应那个地方。我想亲身试验一下。我希望看到，即使我是在英国长大的，也能够在海湾地区生活得很好，因为那里的居民都是如此正直。

我想尝试经营一间小型工厂，用鳄鱼皮制作鞋子和手提包。我在上一封信里曾经告知。我了解这件工作，在海湾地区也能轻易找到除了金属配件以外的所有材料。我今早写了一封长信给帕克先生，问他如果鞋子质量过关的话，他是否愿意替我在英国出售它们，并请他告诉我，鞋子运抵佩里维尔后，他能为其开出的最高价格。此外，我还请求他给我列一张单子，写明我开办一间雇用多达十位姑娘的工厂可能会需要的东西，以及它们的成本，像打包机、带钻头抛光机和奈顿六号的缝纫机，等等。

缝纫机是用于加工皮革的重型机器，是最昂贵的单项。我估计一切项目，包括修建工厂大楼所需的四百英镑在内，总共要花两千英镑左右。但恐怕我的计划并不仅限于此。如果我要给姑娘们开一间工厂，她们必须有地方消费。我想再开一间卖女士用品的店铺。

不是大商店，只是一间小店铺。我想把它办成一间冰淇淋吧，有镀铬的椅子和玻璃面的桌子。我想在那里卖新鲜蔬果，如果实在无法从附近进货，就从凯恩斯空运过来。在内地，人们很愿意为新鲜蔬果花钱。我还想卖新鲜牛奶。乔将需要养几头奶牛。我想卖糖果，还有像唇膏、粉底、面霜和杂志那样的小东西。

当然了，在此地设店的一笔巨大花销是冰箱和空调。我想这部分预算至少需要五百镑，再加上店面和店内陈设——总共需要大约一千两百英镑。那会形成大约两千五百英镑的资本支出。如果我能预支五千英镑遗产，就能够解决店铺和工厂的库存问题，雇用五六个姑娘，并且头一年无须出售任何产品。我想一年后就有盈利了。如果那失败了，好吧，那就实在是太糟糕了，我所有钱都赔进去了。

我想做这件事情，诺尔。不仅仅是为了乔·哈曼和我，威尔斯镇的居民都善良正直，但他们的生活太贫瘠了。我想在那里工作几年，就当作自我磨炼，好让我在如此富有的条件下，不至于丧失谋生技能。我想，即使没有乔·哈曼，我也会想做它，但在我和他见面交谈之前，我还不能下定决心，并采取任何实际步骤。

所以我想要的是五千英镑。拜托了，诺尔。如果我想继续实行我的计划，我能够得到这笔钱吗？

琴

五天后，我通过航空邮件收到了这封信。我把包含预算的段落用红色铅笔标注出来，在顶上做了一点笔记，然后把它送到列斯特办公室请他看。当天晚一点的时候，我走进他办公室。“你看过那位佩吉特姑娘写的信了吗？”我问道。

他从面前的桌子上拿起它。“是的，我一直在看遗嘱。这个自由裁量条款是你自己起草的吗？”

“是我起草的。”

他微笑道：“我想它真是一个杰作。你完全可以在它的保护下解冻这笔钱。”

“那大约占了遗产的百分之九，”我说，“用作商业投资，她打算亲自全职打理它。”

“立遗嘱人并不了解她，是不是？”

我摇摇头。

“她二十七岁？”

“是的。”

“我想我们可以让她拿到这笔钱，”他说，“不然的话，扣留这笔钱的做法太极端了。在你起草的自由裁量条款下，我们完全有权力解冻这笔钱。她似乎是一个很负责任的人。”

“我想花一天左右好好考虑清楚。”我说，“在我看来，对于她的计划而言，这笔资本好像太小了。”

我把她的信放在一旁，晾了几天，因为我从不喜欢匆忙行事。经过细致的回忆，我似乎觉得，如果能尽我之力避免琴·佩吉特在这笔投资上亏损，已故的道格拉斯·麦法登先生就不会怪责我。我拿起电话，打给帕克和利维公司的帕克先生。

我说：“帕克先生，这是欧文、达尔豪西和彼得斯律师事务所的斯特拉坎。我相信您收到了琴·佩吉特小姐的来信，她是我的客户。”

“是的，没错，”他说，“您是她的律师，是不是？她的遗产托管人？”

“是的，”我说，“我也收到了她的信。我在想，也许您愿意与我见面详谈信中所写事项，帕克先生。”

“嗯，正合我意。”他回复道，“她问我要一张单子，列上她开这个小工厂所需要的东西。我已经把单子写好了，但还没有拿到所有的离岸价。”

我和他约好下周五见面，按计划，他那时会在伦敦处理其他事务。到了约定的时间，他来到我办公室见我。他身材矮胖，精神焕发，是一个典型的工厂经理，手里拿着一个棕色包裹。

“在我们开始谈之前，”他说，“请先看看这个。今天早上送到的。”他在我的桌子上打开包裹，里面是一双鳄鱼皮鞋。我好奇地拿起一只来看。

“这是什么？”我问。

“这是她给自己做的皮鞋，在这个叫作威尔斯镇的地方，”他说，“她告诉您做鞋的事儿了吗？”

我摇摇头，兴趣盎然地细看它们，感觉很新鲜。“她自己做的？亲手做的？”

“在旅馆房间里亲手做的，她是这么说的。”他回答。

我把鞋子翻过来。“做得好吗？”

“取决于你如何看它们。”他说，“如果以能否用于贸易为标准，它们糟糕透顶。看这里，这里和这里。”他指出众多不规则和粗糙之处，“这两只鞋甚至都不对称。但她知道这个问题。不过，一个从未做过鞋的打字员，能够在没有任何设备的情况下，在自己床上做出这样一双鞋，嗯，已经很了不起了。”

我把鞋放下，递给他一根香烟。“她告诉您她的计划了吗？”

他把从她那里听到的消息告诉我，我告诉他一些她写信告知我的内容，我们谈了四十五分钟。谈话快要结束的时候，我问他：“您实际上怎样看待她的计划，帕克先生？”

“我不认为她能成功，”他直截了当地说，“实际情况跟她想的不一样。我认为她对制鞋行业了解得还不够，很难获得成功。”

我必须说我很失望，但总算知道了真相。“我知道了。”我轻声说。

“您瞧，”他解释道，“她没有经验。她是一个好女孩儿，斯特拉坎先生，而且很有商业头脑，但她没有制鞋出售的经验，也缺乏管理经验，管不住这些姑娘，无法迫使她们为了拿到薪水而卖命工作。她甚至要面对和英国不同的局面。对她来说，这些澳大利亚乡下姑娘们就像一大群外国人一样。她们也许愿意给她干活，但她们从来没有见过一个工厂——她们对工厂完全没有概念。她必须一边自己学习这件新工作，一边教会其他人。嗯，她做不来。”

“我知道了。”我重复道。

“我愿意帮助她，”小个子男人说，“但她要稍微改变一下想法。她再好好想想，就会发现她拥有很多有利条件。我必须说，读到她在信上说她花七十先令买到了一张未经修剪的鳄鱼皮，我惊讶得目瞪口呆。而且还是澳大利亚先令——也就是五十六英国先令吧。这儿每张未经修剪的鳄鱼皮要花我一百七十到八十先令，这些年一直是这么贵，我还以为自己捡了便宜！我跟利维先生说，我说，我们就是两个大傻瓜。”

“您有什么好建议呢？”我问。

“我是这么想的，”他说，“如果她能聘请一个女工头，并支付来回路费，我会让我手下的一个姑娘过去，在她开厂的头一年替她工作。我有一个干得不耐烦的姑娘——嗯，她至少有三十五岁了。她已经结婚了，但不和丈夫住在一起——分居很久了。她是战时国土辅助自卫队(3)的中士，有一段时间在埃及服役，所以很了解热带国家。她叫阿姬·托普。让阿姬·托普负责的话，就永远不会有女孩儿胆敢在店里调皮捣蛋。”

“佩吉特小姐认识她吗？”我询问道。

“哦，是的，琴认识阿姬。阿姬也认识琴。事实上，阿姬昨天来递交辞职信。我把信还给她，好言相劝了很久。她每几个月就闹一次辞职，就像我说的那样，干得不耐烦了。后来我问她，去澳大利亚跟着佩吉特小姐工作一年怎么样，她说她愿意去任何地方，只要不用再排队领取那该死的口粮。如果琴需要她，她会出去一年的。她们都很喜欢琴。”

我说：“你能放她走吗？”

“反正她也留不长。”他说，“我不想失去她，也许我不会。如果她能去澳大利亚旅行，看见其他地方还不如英国好，可能就会回来，在我们公司重新安顿下来，并打消辞职的念头。”

我们就此事谈论了一段时间。这位女士赴澳期间的路费和薪资总计大概三百英镑，但在我看来，如果它能帮助这笔投资成功度过开始的几年，倒也不算贵。帕克先生认为琴对其余部分的估价偏低，但也算不上离谱。“在高级皮鞋贸易中，你无法维持高度机械化生产的成本。”他说，“你必须不断更新款式。”

关于皮鞋款式，他的建议是，他们可以时不时地通过航空邮件寄送样本到威尔斯镇，让琴的工厂依图生产。他非常愿意替她售卖鞋子。“注意，以我们的价位，我不知道她做不做得来。”他说，“我会告诉她我们的进货价，卖不卖由她自己决定。但我必须说，我想尝试一下跟她合作。因为有管制，在这个国家生产皮鞋已经变得非常困难。而且，人总是希望尝试点新鲜事物。”

我诚恳地向他表达了谢意，他离开了。我把全部谈话内容写在信中，通过航空邮件寄给琴·佩吉特。我相信帕克先生也会以同样方式给她寄信。这两封信寄到后，她并没有立刻收到，因为她已经南下罗克汉普顿，寻找供职于制鞋厂的埃尔西·彼得斯。她非常节约地选择了火车，大约七百英里的旅程缓慢酷热。直到那时，她才意识到昆士兰是一个多么地广人稀的地区。飞机压缩了这个地区，去罗克汉普顿的五十一个小时把它重又延展开来。

她找到了埃尔西·彼得斯。这次只持续了十分钟的会面是一次彻底的惨败。她们在鞋厂附近一个咖啡厅见面，琴一提出在海湾地区工作的话题，埃尔西马上告诉她不必白费口舌了。埃尔西很不情愿地承认，在海湾地区开办事业可能是件好事，但那与她无关。开弓没有回头箭，她是不会回去的。

琴走出咖啡厅，在某种意义上，她感觉轻松了一些，但也深感沮丧。她不会雇用怀有那种心情的人，但她在这位陌生女士身上寄托了许多希望。她很清楚自己缺乏管理经验。组建工厂的想法萌芽时，困难还没有那么明显，但在筹备期间，它们开始接踵而至。她在旅馆非常沮丧地过了一晚，次日飞回凯恩斯，仿佛要报复那漫长的火车旅途。她发现飞机票价格几乎与火车票持平。

她回到海滨旅馆后，发现我们的信都已经在那里等着她。她的精神也恢复了。她清楚地记得那个憔悴而严厉的阿姬，如果阿姬已经准备好要来昆士兰一年，对实现她的计划将大有帮助。我想，她在凯恩斯等待乔·哈曼期间，置身于如此多陌生人之中，渐渐开始感到孤独无助。

她拖延了一段时间才给我们回信，因为在见到哈曼之前，她无法做出任何决定。她过后告诉我们，从罗克汉普顿回来后，住在凯恩斯海滨旅馆那三周，是她一生中最难过的时光。每个早晨，她在黎明寒冷的光线中起床，确信她在大大地愚弄着自己，确信自己永远都无法在这个古怪的国家安顿下来，她和哈曼没有任何共同点，可能她根本就不应该来见他。聪明的做法是坐下一班飞机飞往悉尼，买一张便宜的船票回英国，那里才是她的归属。到中午的时候，女侍者和老板娘那种粗朴的澳大利亚式友好，却又在她那反复无常的决心里播下怀疑的种子，整个下午像野草一样疯长。到晚上，她知道如果自己离开那个国家和那个地方，就会终身错失某些非常值得拥有的珍贵事物。所以她重新下定决心，一定要耐心等候。第二天早上，整个循环又重新开始。

当然，从我的信中，她知道了哈曼坐的是哪艘船，很轻易地就打探到了它在布里斯班靠岸的日期。经过谨慎细致的咨询，她获悉他必须取道凯恩斯去威尔斯镇，并确知在船靠岸之后，她还要在凯恩斯等几天，因为他乘坐的船周一在布里斯班靠岸，而飞往海湾地区的飞机每周只有一班，在周二黎明起飞，两者永远接不上。她在威尔斯镇的时候知道了他会住在凯恩斯的海滨旅馆，所以她留在原地等他。

她给他写信，请布里斯班的航运公司转交给他。这封信，她写得很艰难。最后她写道：

亲爱的乔：

斯特拉坎先生寄给我一封信，信上说你在英国的时候去拜访了他，并说你因为错失与我见面的机会而深感沮丧。可巧的是，我也在澳大利亚度过了几个礼拜。我会留在凯恩斯等你，希望在你回威尔斯镇之前可以见上一面。

见面时请不要谈论太多马来亚的事情。我们都知道发生了什么事，让我们尝试把它们忘了吧。

你会让我知道你的动向吗——你什么时候来凯恩斯？我真的很想再见你一面。

祝安！

琴·佩吉特

她周二早上收到一封电报，上面说他将会留在布里斯班见米德赫斯特的主人斯皮尔斯太太，并于周四飞往凯恩斯。她到飞机场接他，感觉自己像个第一次赴约的十七岁女孩一样。这种感受真是荒唐透顶。

我想，当空中列车飞近凯恩斯的时候，乔·哈曼肯定觉得忐忑不安。这六年间，他一直把这个姑娘的形象珍藏于心，但他根本说不出她在现实中的模样。他记忆中的姑娘有一头长长的黑发，扎成马尾，垂在背上，末端用小绳子扎起来，就像一个中国女人。她被晒得很黑，差不多和马来姑娘一样黑。她的上衣褪了色，破旧不堪，像一件衬衣，下面穿一条廉价棉纱笼。她赤着脚走路，一双很黑的脚，还经常脏兮兮的。她总是把一个婴儿背在臀上。实际上，他并不认为她在凯恩斯的模样还跟那时一样。想到自己很可能认不出她来，他感到既苦恼又担忧。不幸的是，她内心的人格光辉，那种令他对她仰慕不已的个性，凭肉眼是看不见的。

他面临的困难对琴来说是显而易见的。她也一直在想，她为了他在房间里把自己打扮得如此花枝招展，不知道他是否能认出自己。她的结论是：他不能。她倒不担心自己认不出他来，因为他的改变肯定比她小。不管怎样，他手上有“圣痕”，那是错不了的。当空中列车在烈日下滑行的时候，她亭亭玉立地站在柏油路跑道的白色围栏旁，等候他的到来。

他一走出飞机，她马上就认出了他的金发蓝眼和宽肩膀。他焦虑地东张西望，目光落在她身上，停留了一会儿，又滑走了。她盯着他，心想她是否看起来人老珠黄。她看见他用那种奇怪僵硬的姿势开始走向航空公司的办公室，心里划过一丝刺痛——关丹那件事在他身上留下了永难磨灭的印记。以她的智慧，她早料到会这样，但第一次见到这种步姿时，她还是觉得万箭穿心。

她离开栏杆，快步穿过柏油路向他走去，喊道：“乔！”他停下脚步，难以置信地盯着她看。他在寻找一个陌生人，然而眼前这个姑娘，身披轻快的连衣裙，时髦漂亮，怎么可能会是她要找的人？最后一次看见她的时候，她站在马来亚的马路上，一脸悲伤，衣衫褴褛，黝黑肮脏，惨遭日本士兵欺负，脸上挨打的地方鲜血淋漓，脚上也血糊糊的。怎么会是同一个人？然后他看见她那个性鲜明的转头动作，回忆蓦地涌上心头——那又是土著太太了，是他这些年来一直记在心里的土著太太。

他无法表达此刻的心情。他有点害羞地咧嘴而笑，说：“你好，佩吉特小姐。”

她饱含深情地握着他的手，说道：“哦，乔！”他用手覆着她的手，俯视她的双眸，然后说：“你住在哪儿？在这里等了多久了？”

她说：“海滨旅馆。”

“真的？我也住在那儿，”他说，“我总是去那儿。”

“我知道，”她说，“斯迈思太太告诉我的。”

这里头有很多他不理解的东西，但他必须先挑要紧的事情做。“我去拿行李，等着我，”他说，“我们可以一起坐车进镇。”

“我叫了一辆出租车，”她说，“别坐公共汽车去。”

他们坐出租车进镇时，她问他：“斯特拉坎先生怎么样，乔？”

“他很好。”他说，“我和他一起住了挺长一段时间，在他的公寓里。”

“是嘛！”她不知道那部分，因为我没有告诉她。我告诉她的只是最关键的少量信息，因为很明显他们要见面的。“你在英国待了多久，乔？”

“大约三周。”

她没有问他去英国的原因，因为她已经知道了答案，而且在出租车司机身后深入谈论它也不太合适。他的问题也阻止了她发问：“你来澳大利亚做什么，佩吉特小姐？”

她没有正面回答。“你不知道我在这里吗？”

他摇摇头。“我只知道斯特拉坎先生告诉我的事情，他说你在东方旅游。如果我在布里斯班收到你的信，我会惊讶得目瞪口呆的。哦，老天，真的。请告诉我，你在凯恩斯做什么？”

一丝微笑滑过她的嘴边。“那你在英国做什么？”

他沉默不语，不知该如何回答。他没有任何现成的谎话。他们穿过镇子的郊区，路过教堂。“我们有很多事情要向对方解释，乔。”她说，“等你到旅馆安顿下来，我们再找个地方好好谈谈。”

他们默默地坐着，一路到旅馆也没有说话。琴有一个朝门廊开的房间，可以俯瞰大海，远眺格莱弗顿海角后面覆满森林的荒山。他们约好，等他洗完澡后在门廊见面。她那时已经知道澳大利亚的一些习惯。“要不要来点啤酒？”她说。

他咧嘴而笑。“好啊。”

她请女侍应多丽丝拿来四瓶啤酒，三瓶给乔，一瓶给自己。大量的冷饮在那个炎热干燥的地方不可或缺。她感到，必须在四瓶啤酒的帮助下，他们才能敞开心扉对话，第一次在对方面前流露出真感情。这是澳大利亚的一个独特之处。

她把两张帆布躺椅拖进她房间外面的阴凉处，啤酒和乔大约同时到达。女侍应离开后，就剩下他们单独相处了，她轻轻地说：“让我好好看看你，乔。”

他站在她面前，细细欣赏她的美貌。他之前在马来亚见到她的时候，做梦都没有想到她是这样一个女孩儿。“你一点儿也没变。”她说，“背伤要不要紧？”

“不怎么要紧，”他说，“不妨碍我骑马，谢天谢地，但我不能抬重物。医院的人告诉我，我永远都不能够再抬重物了，我最好别试。”

她点点头，把他的一只手放到自己手上看。她把他的手翻过来，温柔地捧着，细看掌心和手背的巨大伤疤。他就站在她身旁。“这些呢，乔？”

“它们没事儿，”他说，“我可以抓住任何东西——可以发动卡车，或者做任何事情。”

她转向桌子。“喝点啤酒，”她递给他一个杯子，“你肯定渴了吧。这三瓶是给你的。”

“好啊。”他拿起一杯，喝掉一半。他们一起坐到帆布躺椅上。“请告诉我你们后来怎么样了。”他问，“我知道你说过不要谈关于马来亚的事情，那真是一个鬼地方。我不想再记起它，但我真的很想知道你们后来怎么样了——离开关丹之后。”

她抿着啤酒。“我们继续走，”她说，“渚蒲大尉当天就打发我们继续上路了，在——在那之后。我们继续沿着东海岸北上，只剩下中士一人做看守。我很替中士难过，乔，因为那件事情使他饱受侮辱。他一直对那件事情耿耿于怀，后来他发起了烧，并失去了生存的勇气。他在一个叫作瓜拉德朗的地方去世了，大约在关丹和哥打巴鲁中间的一个地方。那是在大概一个月后。”

“那时他是唯一一个日本看守吗？”他问道。

她点点头。

“嗯，那之后你们怎么办？”

她抬起头。“此后直到战争结束，他们让我们留在原地，”她说，“我们就住在村子里，在稻田里劳动，直到战争结束。”

“你是说，在水里赤着脚踩来踩去，种稻米，像马来亚人一样？”

“没错。”她说。

“哦，老天。”他吸了一口气。

她说：“那种生活并不糟糕。我想，比起战俘营，我更情愿待在那里——一旦我们安顿了下来。战争结束时，我们都非常健康。我们开了一间小学校，教孩子们知识。我们还教了一些马来小孩儿呢。”

“我确实听到过一些类似的传言，”他思考着说，“在南方的朱利亚克里克听到一个飞行员说的。”

她盯着他看：“他怎么知道我们的事情？”

“他是1945年时驾驶飞机把你们带离马来亚的飞行员。”他回答道，“他说，你们被卡车送到哥打巴鲁，他负责开飞机把你们从哥打巴鲁送到新加坡。他现在在跨澳大利亚航空公司(4)工作，飞汤斯维尔到芒特艾萨的航线。那条航线经过朱利亚克里克。我去年五月份在那儿见到他，那时我正在那儿将牲口装上火车。”

“我记起来了，”她慢慢地说，“是一架澳大利亚空中列车带我们离开的。是一个瘦瘦的金发青年吗？”

“应该是他。”

她想了想。“他跟你说什么了，乔？”

“就是我跟你说的这些。他说他把你们送到南边的新加坡。”

“提到我的时候，他怎么说的？”她看着他，眼里泛着笑意。

他害羞地咧嘴而笑，什么也没说。

“告诉我吧，乔。”她说，“再喝一瓶啤酒，然后有话直说。”

“好吧。”他说，拿起一个杯子，但没喝，“他说你是一个单身的女士，土著太太。我一直以为你们所有人都是已婚的。”

“她们都是，除了我以外。那就是你匆忙赶去英国的原因吗？”

他和她四目相投。“没错。”

“哦，乔！那真是浪费钱，你瞧，结果我们还是要在这里见面！”

他跟着她一起笑，喝了一大口啤酒。“好吧，我怎么知道你会在凯恩斯出现呢？”他想了一会儿，“那你到底在这儿干什么呢？”他问，“你还没有告诉我。”

现在轮到她害羞了。“我继承了一笔钱。”她说，“我想诺尔·斯特拉坎告诉过你。”

“没错。”他和善地说。

“那时我不知道自己接下来要做什么，”她说，“我不想继续在伦敦郊区当打字员。后来我想到一个主意，我要为收留了我们三年的瓜拉德朗做点什么。我想给他们挖口井。”

“一口井？”

她手里拿着一杯啤酒，坐在那里给他讲瓜拉德朗的故事，她在那里交到的朋友，还有洗衣房和那口井。接下来就不那么好讲了。“挖井队从关丹来，”她说，“那时我以为你已经死了，乔。我们都是那样想的。”

他咧嘴而笑。“我也差不多死了。”

“挖井队告诉我你没死，”她说，“他们说你被送往了医院，后来康复了。”

“没错，”他说，“我尝试让医院的人告诉我你们后来的遭遇，但他们说不知道。或者即使他们知道也不会说。我想他们都被那个渚蒲吓坏了。”

她点点头。“我去了关丹。那里现在非常平静。人们在网球场上打网球，在那棵可怕的大树下坐着聊天。在医院，他们告诉我你曾经问起我们，”她笑道，“你叫我土著太太。”

他咧嘴而笑。“但你是从那儿来的澳大利亚吗？”

她点点头。“是的。”

“为了什么？”

“嗯，”她尴尬地说，“我想来看看你是否安好。我想也许你还躺在医院里之类的。”

“是真的吗？”他问道，“你是因为我才来的澳大利亚？”

“某种意义上是的，”她说，“不要想多了。”他咧嘴而笑。“即使你是个土著我也会那样做的。”

“嗯，让你来说我浪费钱真是再合适不过了。”他说，“如果你留在英国的话，我们就会顺顺利利地见上面了。”

她生气地说：“哼，我又怎么知道你会跑到英国去，还健康得像只跳蚤一样？”

他们坐着喝了一会儿啤酒。“你是怎样来这儿的？”他问，“你先去的哪儿？”

她说：“我知道你以前在沃拉华工作，我想那里的人应该会认识你。所以我从新加坡飞过来，去到达尔文，然后坐公共汽车南下爱丽丝。”

“哦，老天。你去了爱丽丝斯普林斯？你去郊区沃拉华见汤米·杜维恩了吗？”

她摇摇头。“我在爱丽丝住了一周左右，后来通过医院的广播站从杜维恩先生那里拿到你在米德赫斯特的地址。所以我飞去威尔斯镇——我在米德赫斯特给你寄了一封电报，告诉你我正要来找你。但是，当然，那里的人告诉我你在英国。”

他盯着她看。“那是真的吗？你去过威尔斯镇？”

她点点头。“在那里住了三周左右。”

“三周！”他盯着她看，“你住在哪儿？”

“在旅馆里，和康纳太太一起。”

“但为什么是三周？对于大多数人来说，三个小时就够受的了。”

“我必须找个地方待着。”她说，“如果你跑到英国去了，想见你的人就必须找个落脚处。你回去后，很可能会发现澳大利亚旅馆里满是这样的人。”

他咧嘴而笑。“哦，老天，我会的。你在那儿都做了些什么？”

“闲坐着，跟阿尔·伯恩斯、彼特·弗莱彻、森·斯莫尔和其他所有人聊天。”

“你肯定引起了轰动。”他顿了顿，深深地思考这个新情况，“你去米德赫斯特了吗？”

她摇摇头。“我一直留在威尔斯镇。不过我见到了吉姆·伦农。”

楼下响起了晚饭的铃声。“我们最好下楼，乔。”她说，“如果你迟到了，他们会不高兴的。”

“我知道。”他拿起杯子，一饮而尽。但他拿着空杯子坐着，一动不动。最后他说：“你觉得威尔斯镇怎么样，佩吉特小姐？”

她笑道：“瞧，乔，把佩吉特小姐忘了吧。你可以叫我土著太太或者琴，但如果你还叫我佩吉特小姐，我明天就回家。”

他微微一笑。“好吧，土著太太。你觉得威尔斯镇怎么样？”

“乔，如果我们开始谈这个话题，就会错过饭点的。”

“告诉我。”他说。

她看着他，眼里含着笑意。“我觉得那真是个糟糕的地方，乔，”她轻轻地说，“我真不明白为什么有人能够忍受在那里生活。”她把手放到他小臂上，“我想和你谈谈它，但现在我们必须下楼吃饭。”

他从椅子上站起来，放下杯子。“太对了，”他沉重地说，“那个地方对于女人来说真是糟糕透了。”

他们下楼喝茶，同坐一张桌子。乔陷入了深深的忧郁之中。点完菜后，琴说：“乔，你还可以留多久？必须什么时候回米德赫斯特？”

他抬起头，咧嘴一笑。“当我准备好要回去的时候。”他说，“我离开了这么久，再多待几天也不会有什么差别。”他顿了顿，说，“你呢？”

“我只是过来看看你是否平安健康，乔。”她说，“我想我会南下布里斯班，下周就找船回家。”

他们的饭来了，乔点了烤牛肉，琴要了冷火腿片和沙拉。“你来到凯恩斯之后，都做了些什么？”他不久问道，“去看大堡礁了吗？”

她摇摇头。“我去了趟罗克汉普顿，还跟一个白人旅游团去了阿瑟顿高原，在那里过了一晚。我没去其他地方。”

“哦，老天，”他说，“你一定要看过大堡礁再回家。”他顿了顿，然后说，“你想去格林岛过周末吗？”

她瞟着他说：“格林岛是什么样的？”

“就是一个礁石上面的珊瑚岛，”他解释道，“一个小小的圆形岛屿，大约半英里宽。岛上有一个餐馆，树丛中间有一些供人住宿的小木屋。如果你喜欢游泳，那是一个很棒的小地方。可以整天穿着泳衣。”

琴想，她要好好考虑一下，树丛中间的小木屋是不是暗藏玄机，但这个提议自有其醉翁之意。他们对彼此几乎一无所知，有太多地方需要了解，太多话需要谈。她穿着泳衣和乔·哈曼在一个珊瑚岛上过周末，不管可能会发生什么事情，可以肯定的是，相比在气氛拘谨的凯恩斯，他们在那里能更深入地了解彼此。

“我很乐意，乔，”她说，“我们要怎样去那里？”

他满心欢喜地微笑了，她替他高兴。“吃完饭后，我出去找厄尼，”他说，“他很可能在海兹的酒吧里。他有一条船，我让他明早开船送我们去那儿。路上需要花三个小时左右，我们最好八点左右出发，趁太阳还不是很猛。我会请他下周一左右帮忙出来接我们。”

“好的。”她同意了，“但是，乔——我们实行荷兰制(5)。”他没听懂这个词。“我的意思是，你付一程的船，我付另一程，我们各埋各的单。”他强烈反对。“如果不那样，乔，我就不去了，”她说，“我会疑心你要对我图谋不轨。”

他咧嘴笑了。“太对了。”然后说，“好吧，土著太太，我们各付各的钱。”

他饭后离开，半小时后回到门廊找她。他找到了厄尼，预订好来回的船，还买了一大篮水果带去。黄昏稍纵即逝，夜幕很快就降临了。他们一起坐了几小时，谈论除了威尔斯镇以外的一切。她了解到很多信息，关于他早年在各个牛场的生活，他在克朗克里及周围的亲戚，他的军役，以及米德赫斯特。“上个雨季，我们有三十四英寸的雨。在南方的爱丽丝，有十英寸就算得上是一个好年头了。我一直想让斯皮尔斯太太同意在河流的源头修两个水坝来蓄水——一个在袋鼠溪上游，一个在干树胶河上游。”

“她同意了吗？”

“她同意出钱。”他说，“当然了，问题是很难找到人来修。你请不到小伙子过来内地工作。那是个鬼地方。”

“为什么呢？”她问。她自己就很清楚，但她想听听他的意见。

“我不知道，”他说，“他们全都想到镇上工作。”

她没有纠缠这个话题，以后有的是谈论它的时间。他们谈起令人愉快的闲事，她发现他非常焦急地想回到米德赫斯特去见他的马和狗。“我有一条叫莉莉的小母狗，”他说，“它母亲是一条蓝牧牛犬，和一头野狗交配了，所以莉莉有一半野狗血统。它真是一条很棒的狗。嗯，我出发去英国前，让它和另一条蓝牧牛犬交配，现在应该已经生小狗了，这样它们都有四分之一野狗血统。野狗和牧牛犬杂交的话，能生出很出色的小狗，但必须减弱野狗的血统，不然生出的小狗就很野。战前在沃拉华的时候，我有一条狗就是有四分之一野狗血统的，它可好了。”

他告诉她，他的牛场有大约六十匹驯马和驮马，但它们与他的关系远没有狗那么亲近。“狗会到牧场住宅里来，坐在你身旁，陪你度过晚上的时间。”他说。她可以想象那个画面，那些漫长而孤寂的夜晚，那就是他平常所过的生活。“在内地，如果没有狗，日子都不知道怎么熬下去。”

十点钟，他们各自上床睡觉，准备次日一早出发。他们在她房门前的黑暗中一起站了一会儿。“我是不是变了很多，乔？”她问。

他咧嘴而笑。“我完全认不出你来了。”

“我想也是。六年真的很长。”

“实际上你一点也没变，”他说，“你的内心还跟从前一样。”

“我想你说得对，”她慢慢地说，“战后我觉得自己就像一个老太太，乔。经过了关丹那件事情后，我以为我再也不会因为什么事情而快乐起来了。”她笑道，“比如说去格林岛过周末。”

“在那儿没什么可做，”他说，“游游泳，坐玻璃底的船出海看珊瑚和鱼。”

“我知道。那肯定会很有趣。”

他们第二天早晨坐上厄尼的渔船出发了，那是一艘带顶棚的汽艇。他们在一片光滑的海面上嘎嚓嘎嚓地前进了两个小时。他们在船后拖了一条钓鱼绳，钓到两条颜色鲜艳的大马鲛鱼。一个小时后，他们看到了格林岛，海平线上出现了椰子树的树顶；再驶近一些，就能看见小小的圆形岛屿，白色的珊瑚沙沙滩把它完全包围起来。一条长长的栈桥，一直修到珊瑚礁的浅水之上。他们下了船，一起走上这栈桥，停下来看猩红色和蓝色的鱼儿在下面的珊瑚丘周围嬉戏。

岛上没有其他过夜的游客，他们要了两间绿树掩映的小木屋。这些小木屋两端通透，微风习习，有用于保护隐私的简易窗户。他们约好马上在沙滩见面，一起游泳。琴穿上一套新的两件式泳衣，乔一看见就赞赏不已。“就像画儿一样漂亮，”他说，“哦，老天。”

她笑道：“布太少了，都不够填满一个画框的。”

“太对了，”他说，“但这儿周围又没有老古板。”

“我要小心点，别被晒伤。”她说，“我敢打赌，在这里游过泳的女人之中，我是最白的。”

“你的肤色不均匀。”他说。他站着盯着她看，简直没有办法把目光从她的美貌上移开。“不过你曾在烈日下曝晒。”

她的肩膀和双臂都晒黑了，乳房上有一条明显的分界线，上面是棕色的，下面是白的。“我在马来亚时把纱笼拉到这里，”她说，“在他们挖井的时候。住在村子时，我们常常把纱笼穿得高高的，拉到手臂底下。那样穿真的非常凉快，还可以保护身体大部分地方不被晒伤。而且也相当得体。”

“你带纱笼来了吗？”他问。

她点点头：“我打算一会儿穿。”

他们转身走进海水时，她第一次看到他的背部，上面布满了一道道巨大的疤痕。疤痕扭曲了整个背部，使它看起来皱巴巴的。看到这一景象，她的内心涌上一阵深深的怜悯。这个男人已经为她受足了伤害，她绝对不能再伤害他了。他回头看她，说：“我们到齐膝深的地方就好了，最好不要往深里走。这附近有很多鲨鱼。”然后他仔细地看着她，说，“怎么了？”

她马上笑道：“是太阳，”她说，“晒得我都流眼泪了。我真该戴上太阳镜。”

“我去给你拿。放在哪儿了？”

“我不想戴了，真的。”她说，一下子向前猛扎进沙上的浅水处，下到大约两英尺深的水里，然后翻了一个身，背朝下，甩掉脸上的水。“太美妙了！”她说。他也往前一扑，打了几个滚，坐在她身旁。珊瑚沙上的海水温暖宜人。“请告诉我，乔，”她说，“鲨鱼当真会游到这么近的地方来吗？”

“它们会把你扯进刚齐腰深的水里，”他说，“哦，老天，它们会的。我不知道这会儿这儿有没有鲨鱼。问题是，你永远都不会知道。马来亚没有鲨鱼吗？”

“我想有吧。”她说，“村民从不走进深过膝盖的海水，所以我们也没试过。河里还有鳄鱼呢。”她笑道，“总之，在热带国家，还是在游泳池游泳最好。”

他们在蔚蓝清澈的海水里嬉戏，阳光穿过海面的涟漪，闪闪烁烁地，在他们周围的珊瑚沙上淌成银白色的流光。“我从未在游泳池里游过泳。”他说，“他们把游泳池的一头修得很浅，是吗？可以让人像这样坐上去？”

“当然了，一头浅一头深，深的那头有跳水板。在澳大利亚这里不也有游泳池吗？”

“哦，老天。在南方有，像悉尼和墨尔本那样的地方。我听说过有些牛场主在他们的土地上修建了游泳池，但像凯恩斯、汤斯维尔和麦基，它们就在海边上，所以不需要游泳池。”

“麦克莱恩太太在爱丽丝斯普林斯有一个游泳池。”她说。

“我知道，他们一两年前才修的。我还从来没有见过呢。”

她翻了一个身，背朝上躺着，注视着一只海鸥从小岛飞到海上，在热气中翱翔。“你们可以在威尔斯镇修一个游泳池，”她说，“就这样任凭从钻孔喷出来的水在镇中心白白流淌，实在是太浪费了。你们可以在旅馆对面修一个漂亮的游泳池。”

“那些水并没有被浪费掉，”他说，“哦，老天。旱季的时候牛就喝它。”

“即使我们先把水借来灌满游泳池，也不会对牛造成任何伤害，”她说，“而且它们喝起来会更甜。”

“如果是你在池里游泳的话，喝起来会更甜一些，”他同意，“但如果是我在里面游，那就不知道了。”

他最多只让她在水里泡三刻钟。“你会晒伤的，”他说，“像这样的大毒日头，在海里就跟在陆地上一样容易晒伤。你的皮肤那么白，要特别注意。”他们从沙滩上起身，走到树荫中，坐着抽了会儿烟，然后回到小木屋添些衣服去吃午饭。她发现，在澳大利亚的旅馆吃饭必须非常注意着装。在凯恩斯，即使是在夏天最热的时候，男士去餐厅时要是不穿上外套并系好领带，就没有人愿意接待他，女士也不会穿着休闲裤去吃饭。

哈曼给她点了一顿清淡的午饭，冷火腿片和水果。他为了能让她度过一个愉快的周末费尽了心思，令她非常感动。她问道：“乔，为什么像威尔斯镇那样的地方没有新鲜水果？水果在那儿不长吗？”她一边说一边努力想以一种优雅的方式吃掉一个芒果。

“芒果长得挺好的，”他说，“我们在米德赫斯特有三四棵芒果树。镇上没有吗？我还以为肯定有呢。”

“我相信没有。我从未在旅馆里见过水果，其他地方也没有卖的。”

“哦，好吧，也许你是见不到水果的。人们似乎并不拿它当回事。在有些地方，所有的行道树都是芒果树。如果你在初夏的时候开车经过库克镇，就会看到沿路种满了芒果树。”

“人们不喜欢新鲜水果和蔬菜吗？我是说，如果不吃它们的话，就会得各种各样的皮肤病。”

“对于老人家来说，在园子里干活太热了，就像在其他地方一样，”他说，“乡下没有足够的人手来种那样的东西。我们甚至都请不到人到牛场做牧工——我们不得不用三分之二的土著牧工，甚至更多。那里就是人手不够。他们都不愿意来内地。”

她思考着说：“爱丽丝斯普林斯有大量新鲜蔬菜。”

“啊，是的，”他回答，“爱丽丝是不一样的。爱丽丝是一个很棒的小镇。”

饭后热浪来袭的时候，他们各自上床睡觉，晚饭前再去游泳。晚间凉风送爽，他们走到码头边钓鱼。他们抓到一些青嘴龙占，还有三四条红蓝相间的鱼——这些闪闪发光的鱼有毒，不能吃，还会蜇人，必须戴上手套来对付它们。厌倦了这项无利可图的运动后，他们收起钓鱼线，一起坐着，看太阳从地平线上的阿瑟顿高原背后落下。“这真是一件很有趣的事情，”琴说，“去到一个新国家，原本希望一切都是新鲜的，却发现有很多东西并不陌生。在英国，遇到晴朗的夏日黄昏，也能看见跟这里一模一样的日落。”

“你能在这儿看到很多和英国相似的景象吗？”他问。

她微微一笑。“在格林岛上不能。在威尔斯镇也看不到多少。但在凯恩斯——很多。停在大街上的沃克斯豪尔和奥斯丁汽车，告诉人们买英国货的政治家，大英北方保险公司(6)，塔特沙尔花格毛料，旅馆里收听《又是那个家伙》(7)的银行职员。就连街上的报童——‘快来看报纸！’闭起眼睛听着他们的声音，就像身在英国。我住在伊令公地的时候，他们天天那样喊，喊声一模一样。”

“伊令是你上班时住的地方吧？在伦敦附近，是不是？”

“没错。其实它是伦敦的一部分——伦敦的一个郊区。”

“你回国后还会回那儿住吗？”

“不知道，”她慢慢地说，“我不知道接下来要做什么，乔。”

黄昏的光线斜斜地照下来，风平浪静，他们一起坐在码头，看着海那边的日落。她希望他能够循着她的话追问下去，但他没有，她深感失望。除此之外，她对他还怀有更多期望，但并无一个得以实现，她开始觉得心烦意乱。她原本还期望自己整个周末都要刻意防范着他，譬如说，像抵御入侵者一样，但到目前为止，事态仿佛完全在朝另一个方向发展。乔·哈曼对她的行为无可指责，他并没有试图吻她，甚至不曾制造与她发生身体接触的机会。如果不是他确实去过英国，不为别的只为去找她，她很可能会认为他对她根本毫无兴趣。那天结束的时候，他的坐怀不乱令她深为担忧。他已经为她遭受了太多痛苦。

他们回屋睡觉的时候，事情并无任何好转。她情愿被吻，在安静的夜色中，在婆娑的棕榈树树影下，但乔没有这么做。他们用最循规蹈矩的方式互道晚安，甚至连手都没有握一下，然后各自回屋，就像那些恪守礼节的老古板一样。琴醒着躺了一会儿，焦躁不安，苦恼不已。她想当然地认为他们会在格林岛上取得某种感情上的进展，但如果事情就这样发展下去，他们下周一就会一无所获地离开。那样的话，她就不得不南下布里斯班坐船回家。没有任何借口去做任何其他事情。这个想法简直让她无法忍受。

她知道她的英式做派对他来讲很陌生，他不可能知道她有多么愿意让自己融入他的昆士兰式生活。另外，也许她的钱成为了两人之间的障碍。她不认为一个男人会真诚或诚恳到在娶一个有钱的女士时犹豫不决，但这笔钱也可能使他对她望而却步。她有一种感觉，她这个陌生的英国贵小姐，和一个来自凯恩斯的澳大利亚姑娘有着天壤之别。如果乔·哈曼对一个来自凯恩斯的姑娘如此感兴趣，这个姑娘早就已经和他同床共枕了。然而他甚至都还未曾吻过她。

她躺了很久，难以入寐。

第二天也并无任何进展。早晨空气凉爽，他们在清澈得不可思议的海里游泳。退潮时，他们走到礁石上，去看色彩缤纷的珊瑚。他们坐在一艘用玻璃做底的船上，划着它四处转悠，观赏五颜六色的鱼儿，两人中间一直隔着足足有六英寸的距离。吃饭的时候，他们都发现自己已经谈够了无关痛痒的话题。克制变成一种负担，当他们两人似乎都无话可说的时候，那漫长的沉默显得相当尴尬。

傍晚的光线柔和温暖，他们决定到环岛的沙滩上散步。她把他留在她的小屋门前，说：“给我几分钟时间，乔。我不想穿着这条连衣裙在沙滩上散步。”她把其中一块窗帘拉起来，把自己遮住。换衣服时，她想他们就剩一天时间了，有那么多需要解决的问题，但他们甚至还没开始进入正题。不入虎穴，焉得虎子，如果是为了乔，冒点险还是值得的。

她在昏暗的光线中走出小屋的时候，他转过身来。他仿佛回到了六年前的马来亚。她又穿着那条褪了色的旧棉布纱笼，或者是一条很相似的纱笼，拉得很高，在手臂下打一个结。她棕色的肩膀和棕色的手臂露在外面。她光着脚，头发垂下来扎成长长的辫子，尾部用一条小绳子扎起来，就像在马来亚的时候一样。她不再是那个陌生的英国贵小姐，她又变回了土著太太，这些年来他一直记在心里的那位土著太太。她很羞涩地走向他，把双手放到他的肩膀上，说：“这样是不是好一点，乔？”

她永远无法非常清楚地记得接下来五分钟发生的事情。她站着，被他的手臂紧紧拥抱着，他发狂地吻她的脸、她的脖子和双肩，一边用手抚摸她的身体。在横扫全身的激动和兴奋中，她知道，从未有任何人比这个男人更想得到她。她站在他的双臂中，并没有抵抗，她从没想过要挣扎或者逃走。但是过了一会儿，当她得以喘口气说话时，她说：“哦，乔！屋子里的人会看见我们！”

她意识到的下一件事情，就是他们已经在她的小木屋里了。她永远不知道他们是怎么进去的，但过后想想，她得出了结论，他肯定是把她抱了进去。这时发生了另一件让她担心的事情。如果不乱动，在胸部上方用一个紧结扎起来的纱笼可以整天都保持在合适的地方，但它抵挡不住活力四射的男性力量。她可以感觉到它渐渐松开并往下掉。她身上没穿任何其他衣服。

她仍然顺从地站在他的手臂中，被他的吻窒息，她想，这就是它了。然后她想，这件事情总有一天要发生的，我很开心对方是乔。然后她想，它不是他的错，是我引诱他的。然后她想，我必须坐下来，或者怎么样，要不然就会一丝不挂了。想到这里，她往后一撤，从他的手臂里逃了出来，坐到床上。

他跟着她坐下，笑着，她一边试图把纱笼拉起来，并用手遮着双乳，一边含笑望着他。然后她又落入了他的双臂，他不让她把纱笼穿上。然后他很直白地说：“你介意吗？”

她伸出右臂，环着他的肩膀，温柔地说：“亲爱的乔，如果你想要的话，我不介意。但如果你能够等到我们结了婚再说，我会更加乐意。但不管你现在做什么，我都一样爱你。”

他俯视着她，看进她的双眸：“再说一遍。”

她把他的头拉到自己面前，吻他。“亲爱的乔。我当然爱你。你以为我来澳大利亚是为了什么？”

“你愿意嫁给我吗？”

“我当然愿意嫁给你。”她抬起头看着他，眼里充满深情和笑意，“所有看见我们现在这副样子的人都会说我们已经是夫妻了。”

他咧嘴而笑。他现在更加温柔地抱着她。“不知道在你眼里我是个什么样的人。”

“我要告诉你吗？”她拿起他一只受过伤的手，轻抚巨大的伤疤，“在我眼里，你就是那个我想嫁给他，并且为他生小孩的男人。”纱笼似乎已经滑落到她的腰部，但现在那已经不重要了。“我倒更情愿等几个月，把我们的生活先安排一下，乔。婚姻是一件大事。在我们结婚之前，是有很多事情需要做的。但如果你说我们等不了了，那我明天就跟你结婚，或者今天晚上。”

他温柔地把她拉过来，吻她的指尖。“我可以等。我都为这一刻等了六年了，我可以再等一阵子。”

她轻柔地说：“可怜的乔。我会试着把事情弄得容易一些。我不会把你逗急的。我今天这样做真不应该。”她从他的手臂中抽出身来，把纱笼拉上，裹住身体。“请出去等一会儿，我要多穿点衣服。”

他说：“你不需要那样做。我不会做任何事情，除了不时吻吻你。今晚就这样吧，就当这儿是马来亚。”

“只限今天晚上。”她说。他们不久走到沙滩上，站在明亮的月光下，紧紧拥抱着对方。“我从来不知道一个男人可以如此开心。”他说。

半小时后，她说：“乔，我们现在都很累了，是时候上床睡觉了。我们有太多东西要谈了，但最好留到明早再谈。今晚我只想跟你说一件事。只要你觉得你一刻也不能等，你来告诉我，好不好？如果你那样来找我，我保证我们马上就结婚，或者更快。”

他温柔地说：“我可以为你等很久很久，在这之后。”

“亲爱的乔。我会尽我所能不让你久等的。”

她太累了，所以回到小屋后没有点蜡烛，而是倒在床上，像个马来人一样松开纱笼，几乎马上就睡着了。第二天，她在晨光中醒来，躺着回忆昨晚发生的事情，感到出奇地高兴。最后，她觉得他们两人之间的事终于走上了正轨。太阳升起时，她起床跑去小心翼翼地窥探乔的小屋和餐厅。到处都没有一点人的动静，所以她穿上泳衣，到海里洗了个澡。太阳升起后，她躺在浅水中，发现身上有一些瘀痕。她回忆起自己是如何惊险逃脱了比死亡更可怕的命运。

她蹑手蹑脚地回到小屋，穿上连衣裙，走去餐厅。餐厅开着门，但里面没有人。她把水壶放到油炉上，泡了一壶茶。她拿着一杯茶去乔的小屋，小心地往里窥探。

他穿着一条短裤躺在床上，还未睡醒。她在那里站了几分钟，看着他睡觉的模样。因困扰而生的皱纹已经从他脸上消失，他安稳合目而睡，像个小男孩儿。他背上的疤痕凶狠地凸出来，与这张恬静的脸形成了鲜明的对比。她深情地看了他一段时间，知道自己在未来几乎每一个早晨都会看见他现在这个样子，这个想法令她很高兴。

她挪了一下位置，放下杯子。当她再去看他的时候，他已经睁开了眼，也在看着她。“早，乔，”她说，一边想她是不是应该像只兔子一样逃之夭夭，“我给你泡了一杯茶。”

他用一只手臂撑起身来。“请告诉我，”他说，“我以为昨天发生过的事情真的发生了吗？”

“我想是的，乔，”她说，“我想那肯定发生了。我浑身上下都是瘀痕。”

他伸出一只手。“过来，让我吻吻你。”

她后撤了。“想都别想。你先起来洗个澡，穿好衣服，到时我会给你一个吻。”

他笑道：“你不去洗澡吗？”

“我洗过了，”她说，“你还在睡觉的时候我就已经起来了，磨蹭了差不多有一个小时。我下去看着你洗。”

他问道：“你睡得好吗？”

她点点头。“像根木头一样。”

“我也是。”他们心有灵犀地一笑。“给我几分钟，我马上去沙滩。”她坐在沙子上，在他洗澡时和他聊天。然后他上来去刮胡子，不久就穿上一件干净的衬衣和干净的卡其色休闲裤来到琴跟前。她走进他的双臂，给了他一个吻。然后，既然不见有任何早饭的动静，他们紧紧偎依着，一起坐在沙滩上，在清爽的晨风中绵绵不绝地谈着话。他们现在找起话题来毫无困难，即使相对无言，也觉亲密无间。

吃过早饭后，他们坐着喝最后一杯咖啡，一边抽烟，他说：“我一直在想，一等斯皮尔斯太太找到另外一个经理，我就离开米德赫斯特。”她愕然地听着。接下来是什么？“如果我们可以找到一个用于育肥的牧场，在阿德莱德北边，在马拉拉、哈姆利布里奇、巴拉克拉瓦，或者其他类似的地方，在爱丽丝斯普利斯的铁路沿线上，离屠宰场不是很远，那就符合我的理想了。我想我们能找到那样一个地方，离城市大约五十英里，以便随时进城。”

她默默地坐了一会儿。这需要慎重应对。“你为什么想这样做，乔？米德赫斯特有什么不好？”

“它离任何一个地方都太远了，”他说，“也许对一个单身汉来讲没问题，但对一对夫妇来讲就不行。阿德莱德现在是一个很棒的城市。我是昆士兰人，但我喜欢阿德莱德多于布里斯班。我没去过悉尼和墨尔本，但阿德莱德是一个很棒的城市，哦，老天。有一条又一条的商业街，还有有轨电车、电影院和舞厅，它也是一个漂亮的地方，背后有山脉，还有葡萄园，里面种的葡萄用来酿酒。如果我们能在阿德莱德附近找到一个农场，就能过上很棒的生活。”

“但是，乔，”她说，“那是你想要的工作吗？只是从内地把牛买来进行育肥？我听着觉得太无聊了。你是不是受够内地了？”

他把烟头扔到地上，用脚后跟辗灭。“有些地方适合单身汉，有些地方适合已婚的人。”他说，“结婚后，人必须做出一些改变。”

他们中间隔着早餐桌，对于这一份新建立的亲密关系而言，这个距离太远了。她无法在不触碰他的情况下处理一件这么严肃的事情。“让我们出去谈。”她说。于是他们走出餐厅，在沙滩边缘的树荫下找到一块满是沙子的草地，在那里一起坐下。“我不认为那是对的，乔，”她慢慢地说，“我认为你不应该只是为了要娶我就离开内地。”

他向她笑道：“海湾地区没有适合女人住的地方，”他说，“除非她是在内地出生并长大的，有时候这样也不行。我见过一些从英国来的已婚夫妇试着适应内地的生活，但从来没听过有成功的。内地的生活跟英国太不一样，太艰苦了。”

她慢慢地说：“我知道不一样，也很艰苦。我在威尔斯镇住了三周，乔，对它有一些了解。”她捧起他的手，在自己双手间轻抚那巨大的伤疤。“我知道你害怕什么。你害怕像我这样一个直接从英国来的女孩儿在内地会过得不开心，乔。你害怕我会焦躁不安，开始找借口离开，住在城市里，为着牙医，为着商店，还有那一类东西。你害怕，如果我们在米德赫斯特开始我们的婚姻，你会把我逼得太苦，然后我们的婚姻就会出问题。”

她抬起双眼望着他。“你害怕的就是这个，是不是，乔？”

他看着她的眼睛。“没错，”他说，“一个男人没有权力让一位英国姑娘住在像威尔斯镇那么糟糕的地方。”

她笑道：“不仅是英国姑娘，乔。就连澳大利亚姑娘，生在威尔斯镇的姑娘们，也不惜背井离乡地逃离它。”

他咧嘴而笑。“没错，如果连她们都不能忍受它，你又怎么能呢？”

“我不知道我能不能。”她思考着说，做人要诚实。“所有海湾地区的镇子都一样吗？”

他点点头。“诺曼顿大一点，有三个酒吧，而不是一个，还有一个教堂。”

接下来是一段长长的沉默。“我有一点恐惧。”她最后说。

他执起她的手。他们的新生活仿佛触手可及，她却心怀畏惧，真让人发疯。她昨天晚上真是勇气可嘉。“恐惧什么？”他温柔地问。

她说：“我害怕你换工作。”她顿了顿，说，“我觉得你的想法完全行不通。一个男人怎么能因为自己的妻子无法忍受他能忍受的生活，就嚷嚷着要换工作呢？你习惯了在一块大约两千平方英里的土地上工作，乔，时不时赶着驮马消失三个礼拜，但从不离开你自己的土地。像你这样的男人，在一千英亩地上能做什么？”

他虚弱地咧嘴而笑。她点到了他的痛处。“我相信我会很快适应的。”

“我知道你行，”她轻轻地说，“你甚至可以做得非常好。但离开了海湾地区之后，你永远不会真正感到满足。电影院，或者一条又一条的商业街，又或者是舞厅，都无法弥补这种落差。当我们偶尔吵起架来——我们会吵架的，乔——你就会想起过去在海湾地区的生活，想到你是怎样为了我而放弃了它，我知道你会怪在我的身上，那我们之间就会一直心存芥蒂。那才是我害怕的事情，乔。我想我们应该留在海湾地区，你工作的地方。”

“你刚刚才说你不能忍受威尔斯镇。”他抗议道，“伯克敦和克罗伊登——嗯，它们都一样的。”

“我知道，”她体贴地说，“我有点前言不搭后语，是不是？开始我说我不能忍受在那样一个地方生活，然后又说你不应该有去任何其他地方生活的念头。”

“没错，”他既困扰又苦恼，“我们要试着想办法解决它，看看怎样对我们两人都合适。”

“只有一个办法，乔。”

“是什么？”

她向他微笑道：“我们要做点什么来改变威尔斯镇。”

————————————————————

(1) 指康纳太太。

(2) 澳大利亚主要的航运和贸易公司。

(3) 简称ATS，二战时期英国军队的妇女分队。在本书中，琴的母亲曾在一战时参加妇女辅助军团（WAAC），该辅助军团就是ATS的前身。

(4) 于1992年并入澳洲航空公司（Qantas Airways）。

(5) 即AA制。

(6) 英国一家保险公司，总部设在爱丁堡。

(7) “It's That Man Again”的简称，BBC的一个喜剧节目，1939—1949年播出，对战时英国人民的抗侵略斗争产生了很大影响。

第八章

他们度过了很特别的一天，时而卿卿我我，时而讨论生意问题。“你说一个降雨量三倍于北领地的地区，无法发展出一个和爱丽丝一样好的镇子，那是不合逻辑的。”期间她有一次说，“我知道爱丽丝有铁路，威尔斯镇有雨，我还知道我自己更情愿在哪个地方养牛。如果你还说要换工作，乔，我就自己坐开去。我们还没结婚呢。”她把他的手拉过来，吻了一下。

“养牛需要的不单是雨水，”他说，“不过当然，饲料越多，就有更多小牛能挺过旱季，也有更多牛可以拿去卖。但除此之外，还有很多其他事情，哦，老天。”

“还有其他什么？告诉我，乔。”她紧紧握住他的手。

“其中一件是，”他说，“下雨的时候，你必须想办法蓄水。米德赫斯特确实有很多雨水，但转眼间就全部流走了。我们的降水从十二月中旬持续到二月底，那时你就会看到小河都涨得满满的，简直要泛滥成灾。但三周后，到三月底，它们就又全部重新变干了，整个地区又变得像往常一样干燥。”

“这就是你要在袋鼠溪和干树胶河上修建水坝的原因？”

“没错。”他说，“我想开始的时候先修建一些小型拦河坝来储水。从每条小溪的源头开始，一点一点慢慢往下修。沿着那些小溪，每隔两三英里储备出一个小水池，直到它们流入吉尔伯特河。当然了，旱季时无法蓄水，因为太阳太猛烈了。但如果米德赫斯特有那样的水坝，饲料数量就会大大增加。哦，老天，肯定会的。”

她放开他的手。“乔，米德赫斯特有多大？”

“一千一百平方英里。”

“上面养了多少头牛？”

“大概九千头吧。应该还可以养更多，但牛场的北部边界很干，非常干。”

“假设你所想象的这些小水坝全都可以建起来，那时可以养多少头？”

他想了一会儿。“我不明白为什么不能养现在的两倍。那大概是每平方英里养十六头。有那么多的雨水，我们应该能做到。”

“今年你们卖了一千四百头，是不是？”

“没错。”

“每头卖多少钱？”

“四镑十六先令。”

她又抓住他的手，把它紧紧攥在自己手里。“乔，我在想，如果你在牛场上多养一倍的牛，每年就能多卖一千四百头。那就是——那就是每年能多卖六七千镑。那样你每年就能卖出价值一万两三千镑的牛了，乔。投点成本在水坝上，就能使营业额增加那么多，如此良机绝对不能错过，是不是？”

他对她另眼相看。“嗯，我就是那样想的。我告诉过斯皮尔斯太太，说我想聘请一个由三个男员工和一些土著组成的固定团队来专门负责这件事。从源头开始，每年修一点。一年差不多要花一千五百镑。第一年的利润会低一些，但那之后利润就会稳步上升，直到接近翻番。我就是那样跟她说的。”

“她同意了吧？”

“她同意出钱。但这只是开头，让她出钱倒不难，问题是我可能要花很多年才能雇到这些人。”

她难以置信地看着他。“很多年？”

“太对了，”他沉重地说，“要想出这个计划来很容易，但真正将它付诸实践要费很大工夫。可能要等五年才能开工。在米德赫斯特只有我们三个人——我是指白人——我、吉姆·伦农和戴夫·霍普。我们必须再找三个人，他们必须整个礼拜都在距离牧场住宅四十英里的偏远地区工作，差不多天天用鹤嘴锄和铁铲干活。他们还必须负责可靠，这样我们只需每周或每两周去跟进一次。嗯，根本就雇不到那样的人。海湾地区的人口每年都在减少。如果没有土著牧工，我都不知道要怎么办。”

“真的只有你们三个白人在经营米德赫斯特吗？”

他用手臂环着她的肩膀。“你来了之后就有四个了。”

她想可能很快就有五六个了，但忍住没把这个想法说出来。“你们的理想人数是多少？”

“你是说，未来养一万八千头牛的时候？”她点点头。“我认为那样一个牛场需要二十人。”他说，“如果我们把经过驯服的公牛都赶进畜栏来改良牲口质量，就不需要太多人。到时将要修建篱笆和畜栏，还有其他杂七杂八的东西。我可能需要二十个白人牧工，此外再请一些别的帮手。”

她慢慢地说：“彼特·弗莱彻说有五十个牧工去了威尔斯镇，在那里成家立业。”

“差不多吧。”他说。

“如果所有的牛场都像你说的那样发展起来，”她说，“那意味着牧工数量要增加到现在的七倍，因为现在你们只有三个人。这个地区将会有三四百个牧工，还有他们的妻子和家庭，这些人需要商店、酒吧、车库、无线电台和电影院。威尔斯镇可以发展成两三千人的小镇，乔。”

他微微一笑。“下一步你就要把它发展得跟布里斯班一样大了。”

她严肃地说：“乔。在马来亚当战俘的时候，我们当中有一位叫作弗里思太太的老妇，她觉得你肯定是耶稣托世，因为你曾经为我们受难。我尝试告诉她，你不是。如果她看见你现在的所作所为，就很可能会相信我。”

他们谈论了一会儿弗里思太太，然后把话题转到更加世俗的事务上。“乔，”她说，“听我说。如果我说我想在威尔斯镇创业，你会不会觉得我很愚蠢？”

他盯着她。“创业？你能在威尔斯镇做什么生意？”

“你知道我在英国的工作吗？”她问道。

“速记打字员，是不是？”他问。

她拿起他的手，在自己双手间摩挲着。“你太不了解我了，”她说，“我有太多事情要告诉你。”她先告诉他帕克和利维公司，然后说到帕克先生、短吻鳄鱼皮鞋，还有阿姬·托普。半小时后，她说：“那就是我想要做的事情，乔。你会觉得这有点疯狂吗？”

“我不知道。”然后，他很有点出人意料地说，“我去逛过邦德街的商店。”

她转向他，一脸惊讶。“真的吗，乔？”

他点点头。“我问斯特拉坎先生应该去伦敦什么地方参观，他问我知道多少伦敦的历史，我告诉他我没上过多少学。所以他就让我去参观圣保罗大教堂和威斯敏斯特教堂，然后坐公共汽车去皮卡迪利广场，往北走上摄政街，沿着牛津街走到邦德街，再沿着皮卡迪利广场走回来。他说走那条路线的话我就能看见所有最好的商店。”

她点点头。伦敦仿佛远隔万水千山之外。海洋的微风拂面而来，只听见头顶上椰子树低低的沙沙声。

“我看到了很多鳄鱼皮鞋，”他说，“还有一些化妆箱。”他转向她，“我看见它们的时候，心想也许它们的皮就来自老杰夫·波科克捕获的那些鳄鱼，真是有趣。那让我感到挺亲切的。它们都制作得非常漂亮，手工很好。但价钱——哦，老天。它们几乎都不带价签，但其中有一个很小的女用鳄鱼皮箱，里面装了一些银白色的小玩意儿，这样一个箱子竟然要卖一百基尼。”

她很兴奋。“乔，我敢打赌那是帕克和利维公司制作的。我们做的全是那一类生意。”

“你不是在想，在威尔斯镇也能生产那些东西吧？”

“不做皮箱，乔。只做鞋——至少以做鞋开始。一间小工厂，雇用六七个姑娘制作鳄鱼皮鞋。成本不会很高，乔——万一出了问题，也不会超出我所能承受的范围。但我不知道——也许不出问题呢？如果进展顺利，有利可图，对于小镇来讲是一件好事。”

“六七个姑娘，全都在威尔斯镇工作挣钱？”他若有所思地说，“你留不住她们的。最多六周，她们就会全部嫁出去——哦，老天，她们会的。”

她笑道：“那我就再找六七个。”她站起身来，“我们去游泳吧，不然一会儿就太热了。”

他们换好衣服，躺在干净的银白色海水中，身下是幼细的珊瑚沙。“看看这些瘀痕，”她说，“你真会欺负人。下次欺负一个跟你一样健壮的人试试看。”过了一会儿她又说，“我还有一个疯狂的主意。现在就告诉你——可别晕倒在水里。我想开一间冰室。”

“哦，老天。”

“我要付给这些姑娘很高的薪水，乔，”她严肃地说，“我要把它们挣回来。”

他看着她，不能确定她是否在开玩笑。“在威尔斯镇开一间冰室？”他说，“那挣不了钱的。”

“且看我每个冰淇淋卖多少钱。”她说，“我不仅要卖冰淇淋，乔——以后还要卖蔬果、速冻食品、女士杂志、化妆品和所有其他女士想要的小玩意儿。有一个很漂亮的姑娘想来帮我打理这间冰室，名叫露丝·索耶，现在住在爱丽丝。”

他慢慢地说：“如果店里有那样一个女孩儿，女士们就挤不进去。牧工会把它挤得满满当当。”

“那也没关系，”她说，“只要他们买我的冰淇淋。”她转向他，“乔，你有没有去过爱丽丝过周日？”

他摇摇头。“我想没有。至少开战以来没有。”

“我也知道原因，”她说，“周日所有酒吧都不开门。”

他咧嘴笑道：“太对了。”

“威尔斯镇的酒吧周日也不开门。”

“酒吧是关了，”他说，“但你通常可以从康纳老妈那儿买到酒，从旅馆后面。”

她在水里翻了一个身。“我必须向海恩斯中士通风报信，乔。星期天是爱丽丝的冰室生意最好的日子。泡了一个礼拜酒吧的男人会带着妻子和小孩去冰室，大口大口喝冰淇淋汽水和可口可乐。那个地方周日的生意兴隆得不得了。”

“确实如此，”他思考着说，“不然人们也没别的事情可做。”

不久他们从海里上来，坐到树荫里。他不允许她在太阳底下坐太久，以免晒伤。他们一起在树底下抽烟的时候，他说：“你想做的这一切将会花掉一大笔钱。我看要三四千镑吧，甚至更多。”

“我有足够的钱。”她说。

他转向她。“斯特拉坎先生告诉我，你是一个有钱的姑娘。”他轻轻地说，“那确实让我非常担心，不过后来我慢慢接受了这个现实。你有多少钱？别告诉我你情愿保守秘密。如果我知道你有多少身家，就能帮你出更好的主意。”

“我当然会告诉你。”她说。经过昨晚之后，他们之间已经没有隔阂。“斯特拉坎先生说我有大概五万三千英镑。但这笔钱全部被托管，托管期要到我三十五岁才结束。如果我想在那之前使用这笔钱，就必须先经他同意。”

“哦，老天。”

“那真是很大一笔钱，是不是？”她说，“从某种意义上说，我很高兴它被托管了，因为我现在根本不知道拿它来干什么。而且诺尔又是如此可亲可爱。”她顿了顿，“我想拿它来做点有意义的事情，”她说，“但我不知道真正做起生意来是怎么样的。我唯一懂行的也就只有高档皮制品生意了。我想，如果我们可以开办一个类似的工厂，和一个售卖女士用品的商店——嗯，即使不能财源滚滚，那也是把钱花在了该花的地方上，在像威尔斯镇那样的地方。”

他弯下腰来吻她。“还有一件事，乔。”她说，“我不知道，但我有一种感觉，雇用这些姑娘可能会带来连锁效应。你说牧工都要离开海湾地区，外面的男人也不愿意来内地。嗯，他们当然不愿意，如果在内地找不到姑娘结婚的话。并且，所有的姑娘都因为找不到工作而离开内地。我每给一个姑娘提供一份工作，就能同时给你招来一个愿意在米德赫斯特工作的男人。你觉得是不是这样？”

“不知道。”他的视线越过大海，落到高原暗淡的灰蓝线条上，“如果那儿能有一群姑娘，自然好多了。住在内地的人，常常会感到孤独寂寞，哦，老天。”

体会到这种深不见底的孤寂，她猛然一阵心酸。那些牧场住宅里没有尽头的漫漫长夜，使得“在内地，没有狗就熬不下去”。她想起那张敏感睿智的脸，想起卡莱尔牛场的埃迪·佩吉，想到他跟那个没有文化又不善言辞的土著女人结了婚。她马上理解了他的话，并对他生出无限同情。她转向他。“我真不忍心让你继续等我。”她说。他执起她的手，紧紧握了一下。“但我确实很想在我们结婚之前，开始尝试做这些生意，乔。”她说。她向他微笑道：“你是一个精力充沛的爱人，我相信我们很快就会迎来第一个孩子。”

他咧嘴笑道：“我不会催迫你的。”

“我也想尽快生儿育女，”她说，把他的头拉到自己面前吻他，“但那意味着我们结婚后，我只有六个月时间来打理生意，然后就不得不开始考虑其他事情。乔，你们什么时候开始集合？”

“雨季后。”他说，“今年是三月集合，因为雨季来迟了。往常我们都是二月中旬开始集合。”

“要集合多长时间？”

“大概三周或者一个月。之后就要给小牛打烙印并把牛赶到朱利亚克里克。”

“我们可以等集合结束后再结婚吗，乔？比如说四月上旬？”

“当然可以。”

她思考着说：“那意味着从现在开始，我有大约一年的时间，把生意发展到可以离开我一两个月的阶段，好让我能专心生孩子。我认为时间很充裕。如果这些生意离开了我，连一个月也经营不下去，那它们也没什么前途，最好直接关门大吉。”

他说：“我当然也可以帮你照看一段时间。”

她笑道：“让你向年轻姑娘递雪糕和卖唇膏吗？我不会叫你做这种事情的，乔。”

他思考这个计划。“吉姆可以独自把牲口赶到朱利亚克里克，”他说，“在我们忙着操办婚礼的时候。我会派布尔纳维尔和其他土著跟他一起去。婚礼结束后，我们可以开越野车追他，应该能在他差不多到达的时候赶上他，和他一起把牛赶上火车。就当是度蜜月了。”

她微微一笑。“我喜欢你这个度蜜月的主意。”他咧嘴笑了。“在朱利亚克里克，除了喝啤酒，还有其他事情可做吗？”

“哦，老天，”他说，“在朱利亚克里克可做的事情多着呢。”

“有什么呀？”

“把一万五千头牛赶上火车，”他向她咧嘴一笑，“没多少英国姑娘能有机会度一个这么特别的蜜月呢。”他说。

他们回去换衣服吃午饭。吃饭时他说：“关于晒干和加工鳄鱼皮的工作，我希望能把它承包出去。”他对于在威尔斯镇做这件工作很反感。那是一件邋里邋遢的工作，不适合女孩儿干，又找不到男人来干。他告诉她，凯恩斯有皮革厂，可以加工她送去的皮革。“是一个叫作戈登的家伙经营的，”他说，“他去年离开了海湾地区。如果你愿意，我们下午就可以去见他。”

“你觉得他那里有白色小山羊皮吗？”

“可能有。即使没有，他也很可能有办法搞到手。”

他有丰富的牛场管理知识，提出的建议对她的开厂计划大有帮助。“我觉得，既然你决定要建一个厂房，就应该把它修得又大又好。”他说，“把木材运到威尔斯镇才是花钱最多的地方。”他想了想，“如果一切顺利的话，将有三个新姑娘到威尔斯镇来生活，”他说，“你、露丝·索耶和阿姬·托普。为什么不把工厂修得大一些，在其中一头隔出三个坐卧室？可以用墙将它们和其他地方隔开来，设一个单独的出入口。那样你们就不必住在旅馆里，自己住得舒舒服服。然后，如果生意越做越大，你们可以把墙拆掉，把坐卧室和生产车间打通。”这在她听来真是一个非常好的主意。

午饭后，他们找来纸和铅笔，草草写下他们回到凯恩斯后要办的几件事情和需要订购的东西。然后他们回到各自的小屋，在白天热气蒸腾时呼呼大睡。乔在屋子外面叫醒了她。“来游泳吧，”他在说，“差不多五点了。”

她迅速把床单拉起来遮住身体。“我马上就来。你没偷看吧？”

“我不会做那种事的。”

“希望我能相信你。”她把窗帘拉严，换上泳衣去沙滩找他，和他一起躺在蔚蓝的银白色海水中。海水很温暖，身子底下是细滑的沙子。她说：“乔，你想不想我们现在就订婚，用一个戒指或者随便别的什么东西？”

“你想这么做吗？”

她摇摇头。“不，除非那能让你安下心来。我四月上旬就嫁给你，乔——绝不骗你。”他微微一笑。“但就目前来说，我相信如果我们不正式订婚会相处得更好。”她转向他，“回到威尔斯镇后，我将做出一系列标新立异的举动，威尔斯镇的人肯定会认为这些举动很疯狂。其中一些确实会很疯狂，因为总会出点问题。我不想只是因为我们订了婚就把你牵扯进来。你最好置身事外。”

“如果人们认为，不管你做什么，我总是和你并肩作战，那不是很好吗？”

她微笑着，翻了一个身，吻他。“你真可爱。你要是每个周六晚上都和酒吧里面的人打起来，只是因为有人对你的未婚妻骂了粗口，对我的生意又有什么帮助呢？”他咧嘴而笑。“他们肯定会说些不中听的话。他们肯定会觉得我疯了。”

过了一会儿，他们从海里上来，坐在树荫里，绵绵不绝地谈论未来。“乔，”她说，“如果一个土著走进冰室买汽水，我该怎么办？一个土著牧工？我就在这个冰室里卖给他，还是要另给他们开一家店？”

他挠挠头。“我不知道那种事情在威尔斯镇有没有发生过。他们会去比尔·邓肯的商店买东西。我想你不能在冰室里招待他们，因为柜台后面站的是一个白人姑娘。”

她坚定地说：“那我就给他们另开一家店，请个土著姑娘来招待他们。那里有很多土著牧工，乔——我们不能把他们排除在外。我们要开两家冰室，厨房就修在两家冰室之间，冷冻柜也共用。”她用手指在白沙上画了一幅小小的布局图。“就像这样。”

“哦，老天，”他说，“你会在威尔斯镇引起很多议论的。”

她点点头。“我知道。那就是我不想那么早订婚的缘故。”

晚上，他们在两人的小屋之间互吻晚安时，她说：“回到威尔斯镇后，我们将要保持距离了。我会终生铭记这个格林岛的，乔。”

他咧嘴而笑：“如果你喜欢的话，我们四月再来。在去朱利亚克里克之前。”

第二天早上艾迪开摩托艇来带他们离开格林岛，下午一早就在凯恩斯上了岸。他们把提包拿回旅馆后，就直接去制革厂见戈登先生，花了一个小时和他讨论鳄鱼皮和其他制鞋材料的问题。他建议他们放弃用山羊皮做衬里的想法。“任何可以用山羊皮做的东西，我们都会给你换成沙袋鼠皮来做，”他说，“你们那儿有很多沙袋鼠，而且沙袋鼠皮和山羊皮一样好——手感、外观、漂白、磨光——任何方面。”哈曼做好安排，等下一辆卡车从威尔斯镇去凯恩斯时，顺道给他送去半打皮革作样品处理。“稍微控制沙袋鼠的数量是件好事，”他说，“它们在牛场上吃掉的饲料实在是太多了。它们的数量太多。”

他们下午剩下的时间都花在购物和订购上，黄昏时精疲力竭地回到旅馆。他们已经订好了早晨回威尔斯镇的机票。琴说：“乔，我有一件事情必须今晚完成，赶在离开凯恩斯之前。我必须写信给诺尔·斯特拉坎，告诉他所发生的一切。”

昆士兰海边初夏的夜晚温暖恬适，花香袅袅。饭后，她坐在门廊上给我写了一封长信。她写信的时候，乔·哈曼坐在她身旁安静地抽烟，一脸平和。

她很会写信，直到现在仍然如此。她依旧每周给我写信。我记得很清楚，我是在十一月上旬收到那封信的。那是一个雾蒙蒙的阴天，烟雨茫茫。我不得不开着电灯吃早饭，对面的皇家马厩几乎消失在浓雾中。出租车经过楼下的街道，把泥水溅到潮湿的木墙上。

那是一封长信，写信人是一个沉浸在幸福中的姑娘，满纸都是她和乔的爱情。我读到这个消息当然很高兴。我坐着读这封信，把早餐晾在面前，又把信从头到尾看了一遍，然后读了第三遍。等我回到现实中时，咖啡已经冷了，荷包蛋在我面前的盘子里冻成又冷又硬的油膏状，但我太过沉迷于她的消息，对早餐失去了兴趣。我进卧室去穿鞋和大衣，准备去办公室。当我打开衣橱拿大衣时，看见她的靴子和溜冰刀，那是我一直在为她保存，等她回来取走的。老人家有时候会变得非常愚蠢。我不得不说，在看见它们的那一瞬间，我仿佛挨了重重的一击——因为她不会回来取走它们了。她永远也不会再回英国了。

我走到前门。我的保姆在公寓里，正好从餐厅走出来。“有一个好消息，尚贝太太。”我说，“你还记得佩吉特小姐吗？时不时来这里做客的那位。她订婚了，马上就要结婚了，跟一位澳大利亚人，在昆士兰。”

“哦，真让人高兴，”她说，“她真是个不错的女士呢。”

“是啊，”我重复道，“真是个不错的女士。”

她说：“您还没吃早饭，先生。早餐没什么问题吧？”

“嗯，没什么问题，谢谢，尚贝太太。”我说，“我今儿早上什么都不想吃。”

街上阴冷生寒，那些灰黄色的早晨总是沉雾迷蒙，冰冷中带着臭味，让人止不住咳嗽。我一直往前走去办公室，半梦半醒地，想着沙袋鼠和带着笑脸的土著牧工，想着流过白色珊瑚沙的蓝色海水，想着琴·佩吉特，以及在那个所有衣服都是负担的热带国家里，纱笼带给她的麻烦。然后我的头顶上方猛然传来一阵撕心裂肺的尖叫声，我感到右臂上重重挨了一下，踉跄了几步，差不多跌倒了。我发现自己正站在蓓尔美尔街正中央，一辆出租车横在我面前。那一刹那，我不知道自己身在何方，然后我听到一脸煞白的司机说：“看在上帝的分上，你还活着就真是谢天谢地了！”

“我很抱歉，”我说，“我没看路。”

“你怎么能没头没脑地横冲到马路上！”他愤怒地说，“都这么大年纪了，走路还不带眼睛！我撞伤你了吗？”

周围开始聚集起一圈小小的人。“只是撞到了手臂。”我说。我动动它，好像没什么问题。“没事儿。”

“哼，那可真是个奇迹。”他说，“下次好好看路！”他挂上挡，发动出租车开走了。我继续向办公室走去。

秘书像往常一样把信拿给我过目，但我把它们放到一边，满心只想着我胸前口袋里的另一封信。我想，那天早上我接待了一两个客户，我通常都会接待这么多。我想我给他们提供了一些建议，但我的灵魂似乎飞到了一万两千英里外。有一次列斯特·罗宾逊进来跟我商量一些工作上的事情，或者别的事情，我对他说：“你记得我的佩吉特姑娘吗——麦法登先生的遗产继承人？她订婚了，并打算嫁给一个澳大利亚人。他似乎是一个很不错的小伙子。”

他嘟哝着说：“我忘记了。那会终止我们的托管吗？”

“不，”我说，“还要等一段时间，直到她三十五岁。”

“真遗憾，”他说，“这个托管条款给你增添了很多工作。真希望托管期尽快结束。”

“我不觉得麻烦，真的。”我说。那天快要结束的时候，我想我已经把她的信都记在脑子里了，尽管它有八张四开纸那么长，但我还是把它带去了俱乐部。我在酒吧里喝了一杯雪利酒，告诉莫尔她订婚了，因为他稍微了解她的故事。晚饭后我跟丹尼森、斯特里克兰和卡拉汉一起坐下来打了几局桥牌，每天晚上都是我们四个一起玩儿。我把她的事情告诉了他们。

大约十一点，我从桌子旁站起身来，走进图书馆，在步行穿过公园回公寓之前抽最后一根烟。那个空荡荡的大房间里只有我和怀特两个人，他曾经在马来警察局工作，知道她的故事。我在他旁边的一张椅子上坐下来，说：“你还记得那个佩吉特姑娘吗？我想以前我跟你提过几次。”

他微微一笑：“是的。”

“她订婚了，马上要结婚了，”我告诉他，“和一个牛场的经理，在北昆士兰。”

“真的？”他说，“他怎么样？”

“我见过他，”我说，“他是一个很好的小伙子。她很爱他，我想他们会过得非常幸福。”

“她结婚前会回英格兰吗？”他问。

我坐在那里，盯着墙上的一排排书和天花板角落凸着花纹的金饰。“不，”我说，“我想她再也不会回英国了，再也不了。”

他不言语。

“太远了，”我说，“我想她现在会选择在昆士兰安居乐业。”

接下来是一阵长长的沉默。“无论如何，她没有任何回英国的理由，”我终于说道，“她回来干什么呢？她在这里又没有牵绊。”

然后他说了一句很愚蠢的话。他也许是出于好意，但说那样的话确实愚蠢之极。我站起来离开他，回到我那幽暗空荡的公寓。那之后有一段时间我都躲着他。我那个秋天已经七十三岁了，年纪大得足以当她的祖父，怎么可能爱上了她？

第十章

越野车慢慢在帐篷前停了下来，布尔内维尔骑着马跟在旁边。她挂了停车挡，把车停下来，大大松了一口气。她坐在驾驶室里，乔走向她。“戴夫呢？”他问，“他没回来吗？”

她把情况告诉他。“我想我最好试着自己开车来。”她说，“我之前只开过大概三次车。我肯定把它开坏了，乔。”

他后撤几步。“看起来没问题。”他说，“你撞到什么了吗？”

“什么都没撞到。但有时候我挂不上挡，它就发出可怕的声音。”

“它还走得动吗？”

“哦，我想可以。”

“那就没问题。小河怎么样？”

“水挺深的，”她说，“都漫过驾驶室的地板了。”

他嘟囔了一声。“赶紧回去。希望这该死的雨快点停。”

她问：“柯蒂斯先生在这里吗，乔？”

他点点头。“在帐篷里。”

“他怎么了？”

“腿断了，”他说，“有创骨折——你们把断骨刺穿皮肤的骨折叫作有创骨折吧？我想他的脚踝也断了。”

她惊讶地噘起嘴唇。“我把你那个装着夹板和绷带的箱子带来了。”

他问：“你知道怎样处理骨折吗？从前有没有当过护士什么的？”

她摇摇头。“没当过。”

“我看了一眼并清洗了伤口。”他说，“我已经尽力了，但它实在是太糟糕了。我今早做了一块长条形的夹板，把它绑在伤腿上。我们要把他送去医院，越快越好。已经两天了。”

他们开始撤营，把帐篷从伤员上方移开。唐第一次见到琴。“你好，佩吉特小姐，”他说，“你不记得我了吧？我在威尔斯镇见过你，在你抵达那天。”

她向他微笑。“你很快就会回到威尔斯镇。我们要把你送进医院。”

她忙活的时候，突然满脸困惑地转向乔。“我们这是在谁的土地上，乔？”

“米德赫斯特啊，”他说，“为什么这么问？”

她扫了一眼畜栏。“那是用来做什么的？”

“那个东西？”他说，“哦，没什么特别用途，我们偶尔会把牛赶进去打烙印什么的。”

她没有再说话，继续低头干活。她的嘴唇几度漾起一丝微笑。他们把唐放在地上，在灌木床底下放了一条毯子，再放下越野车的车尾板。然后，他们用尽力气，小心万分地把他搬到床上，再把床搬到越野车的车身上。躺在车身上的男人脸色煞白，汗流如注。他把嘴唇都咬破了，但他们没有办法舒缓他的疼痛。

大约九点钟，他们开车返回。乔负责开越野车，琴在后面陪伴伤员，布尔内维尔骑马跟在车后，牵着两匹马。他们路过钻头，往前走了大约五英里，来到第一条小河的岸边。跟琴几小时前经过的时候相比，水位上涨了很多。

他们顺利涉过了这条河，不过河水已经漫进了越野车的驾驶室，差一点就漫上车身的底板，而伤员就躺在底板上。过了河之后，他们继续往前走。第二条河的水位更高。乔停在河边，向琴和布尔内维尔咨询他们之前过河的情况。琴当时经过的地方似乎比现在浅五十码，那应该是水位比较低的地方了。乔让布尔内维尔骑马走进水里，听人和马在水里行走时发出的声音。看来没什么问题，于是他把越野车开进河里。

河水很快就变深了，他加速保持前行。黄色的洪水快速旋流，水底下的河床非常崎岖。巨大的汽车在河床的大石头上颠簸着前进。突然间，车子重重地撞到某个东西上，发出一阵金属的嘎吱声，一动不动。

乔说：“天啊。”他使劲儿摁发动键，但引擎毫无反应。油迹开始渗上水面，顺着旋流的黄色河水流走，拖出黄黑色的尾巴。他盯着这些油，大惊失色。

琴说：“怎么了，乔？”

“我把该死的机油箱撞破了。”他简短地说。

他从驾驶室上下来，在河水里小心翼翼地探路。水已经漫过他的膝盖，差不多深及腰部了。他喊来布尔内维尔，并让琴从卡车背后递给他一卷绳子。越野车只离岸十码远。他们制作了一个串联式的套索，把一头套在三匹马的前鞍上，另一头系在越野车的后轴上。这一切都在水底下摸索着进行，两人一边干活一边气急败坏地向对方喊话。十分钟后，汽车已经被拉上了岸，其效率之高，令琴惊叹不已。

她从车身上下来，走向躺在前轴下的乔。她俯下身去，和他一起查看情况，发现用生铁制成的汽油箱被撞碎了。“情况严重吗，乔？”她轻声说。

他向她咧嘴笑道：“这下惨了。”他从破洞里把生铁碎片掏出来，从车底下抽出身来，从驾驶室里找来启动曲柄，小心地转动引擎。他松了一口气。“曲轴轴承没问题，”他说，“只是机油箱坏了。”

他手里拿着启动曲柄，站着深思了一会儿。倾盆大雨扑在他们身上。她问道：“我们现在去哪里？”

“我能补好它，”他说，“开回家没问题。但现在也没油了。以河流现在的上涨速度，去把卡车叫来也没用。”他站着观察了几分钟河水。“卡车到这儿的时候也过不了河。”他最后说，“现在只有一个办法。用飞机把他送走。”

周围满是岩石和茂密的树林。“这里有给飞机降落的地方吗？”她问。

“我知道一个可以降落的地方，”他说，“飞机需要一条五百码长的平整跑道。”

他骑马去南边。琴和布尔内维尔在河边打开帐篷，支起来遮住唐·柯蒂斯，给他挡雨。伤员一度虚弱地说：“乔·哈曼的驾驶技术真差，开着车肯定偷不到牛。不过他的偷牛技术还真不赖。”琴笑道：“你们这对穷凶极恶的罪犯。我要跟柯蒂斯太太好好谈谈。”

“千万别，”他说，“她对此一无所知。”

她说：“好好躺着，别说话。乔出去找一个能给飞机降落的地方，让飞机来接你走。”

“希望他这次的表现比开那辆破车时好一些。”柯蒂斯先生说。

三刻钟后乔回来了。“我想我们可以清理出一条跑道。”他说，“离这儿只有一英里。”他和布尔内维尔一起，用套索把由三匹马组成的马队套在卡车的前轴上，启程穿越树林。琴负责控制方向盘，马队拉着越野车在绿树之间迂回行进。

不久他们来到一块空地上，那儿有一块狭长的草地，上面稀疏地长着一些矮灌木。这块草地超过五百码长，但两头都有树木。他们可以把它清理成一条跑道。“把这些灌木砍掉，”乔说，“再砍掉两头的树。我见过他们在比这儿糟糕得多的地方降落。”

斧头和铲子是越野车的常规装备。他们不缺工具，但以两人的力气无法完成这项体力劳动。“我们必须把米德赫斯特的牧工都叫来，”他说，“并派人去威尔斯镇请求他们派一辆飞机过来。”

她说：“让我和布尔内维尔一起骑马回牧场住宅吧，乔。他可以把牧工都带回来，我继续骑马去威尔斯镇。”

他盯着她：“你骑不了那么远。”

“有多远？”

“从这儿到威尔斯镇有四十英里。”

“至少我可以骑回米德赫斯特。”她说，“如果我到时骑不动了，就派月光捎一张便条给海恩斯中士。我们最好找中士，是不是？”

“没错。这样的话，你就不必自己一个人骑马上路了。如果你要继续从米德赫斯特骑到威尔斯镇，一定要带上月光或者其他牧工。我不允许你自己一个人骑马过河。”

她把手放在他的手臂上。“没问题，乔。我会带人和我一起去。”她顿了顿，“我可以从威尔斯镇发送广播消息，”她说，“那样就可以从温德米尔找人来帮你了，是不是？”

“没错。”他说，“要是米德赫斯特有无线电收发机就好多了。”他顿了顿，“他们肯定想知道一件事情，”他说，“就是这个地方的准确位置。我们距离新钻头大约六英里，西—南—西方向。记住了吗？”

“记住了，乔，”她说，“距离新钻头大约六英里，西—南—西方向。”她顿了顿，“你接下来打算怎么做？”她问。

“我会在这儿扎营。”他环视四周，“搭起帐篷来挡住越野车的车身，”他说，“在找到担架之前，尽量不要再次移动他。搭好帐篷后，我就开始砍树，给飞机开道。”

“你的后背行吗？”她问。

“没问题。”

她想象双手挥舞斧子砍树的动作。“你之前砍过树吗，乔？”

“没有，但没问题的。”

她说：“如果你要砍树，我就要收回我的话。我要自己骑马去威尔斯镇，让月光和其他牧工一起来这里帮你。”

“你别这样，”他说，“你一个人过河不安全。”

“你挥斧头砍树也不安全。”她说，“如果你在这里把后背弄坏了，对谁都没有好处，乔。”她又把手放在他的手臂上，“我们都要理智一点，”她说，“你那点活儿，土著们来了以后一个小时就干完了。没必要冒险，乔。”

他向她微笑。“好吧。但你不能自己一个人骑马。”

“我保证不。”她说。

大约十点半的时候，他们扶她骑上乔的马罗宾。罗宾的个头比她之前骑过的马都要大得多，她非常害怕它。跨上罗宾并不比跨上其他马困难多少。乔的马鞍比她之前所用的休闲马鞍大得多，又软又破，因为长期使用而变得柔顺服帖，但仍然很好用，维护得也很好。他们替她调整好马镫后，她发现坐在上面非常舒服。

她和布尔内维尔一起出发，小跑着穿过树丛。一个艰苦卓绝的壮举就这样开始了。此后许多年里，她每次想起此事都心有余悸。罗宾脾气温顺，反应迅速，精力充沛，小跑起来的时候，步履矫健从容。不过，不能否认的是，此前她只骑过六次马，每次不超过一个半小时。

他们来到河边时雨停了。他们涉过翻腾不已的黄色河水，布尔内维尔从旁保护。过河后，他们继续前行，一会儿慢走，一会儿小跑。一个小时后，他们来到第二条河的岸边。这条河很宽，布尔内维尔帮助她把脚从马镫里抽出来，作好抓住鬃毛游泳过河的准备。但实际上并不需要游泳，他们从容不迫地过了河。再也没有小河阻碍余下的行程了。

“这两条河太深了，越野车肯定开不过去。”她说。

“是的，小姐。它太深了，现在。”

他们和米德赫斯特之间已经没有河流的阻隔了。雨又开始下，雨水混进涌流而出的汗水，使她浑身湿透。她的臀部和大腿不断和马鞍摩擦，很快开始蹭伤，她感到越来越痛苦，但一筹莫展。她拍过胸脯保证自己会骑马的，所以必须咬牙坚持。

她发现，当道路通畅时，她能骑得比布尔内维尔还要快。她骑乘的马精神充足，也更加强壮，而他的马已经跟着越野车跑了一程，疲惫不堪。在罗宾可以小跑前进的时候，她不得不频频放慢速度，边走边等他。这有助于缓解她的疲劳。

他们大约两点半回到米德赫斯特的牧场住宅。她口渴难耐，疲劳不堪。月光和另外几个牧工跑出来，拿过她的缰绳，帮助她下马。她的腿伸展不开了，无法自己从马镫上下来。她说：“布尔内维尔，请让月光备好鞍，准备和我一起去威尔斯镇。我喝完茶和吃完东西就出发。你带上全部牧工回去找哈曼先生，好吗？”

他说：“好的，小姐。”她猛然意识到，如果连她都觉得劳累不堪，那他肯定已经精疲力竭。他一直坐在马鞍上，马不停蹄地赶了二十四小时的路。她看着那张皱纹密布的黑脸，说：“布尔内维尔，你能行吗？累坏了吧？”

他露齿而笑。“我不累，小姐。吃完东西后和牧工们一起回去哈曼先生那里。”他边走开边喊道：“棕榄，棕榄。你去厨房，给小姐泡茶和做饭。你去厨房，快。”

她疲倦地瘫坐在门廊的椅子上，棕榄很快就给她端来了一壶茶和一块盖着两个鸡蛋的牛排。那块牛排简直无从下口。她吃了鸡蛋，在牛排边上啃了一口，喝下去六大杯茶。她不敢换衣服或者检查疼痛的地方，因为她知道，一旦开始做那种事情，就会彻底打消继续上路的念头。吃完东西后，她把月光唤来，下去院子里。那些深色皮肤的牧工正在那里给自己的马备鞍，在雨中扎好包裹，绑在驮马背上。他们扶她上马，她再次启程，在月光的陪伴下朝威尔斯镇前进。

短暂的休息使她浑身僵硬，她鼓起所有的勇气才敢面对前头的二十英里。她身上每一块肌肉都拉伤了，疼痛不已。她几乎无法靠自己的双腿稳坐在马鞍上，但位于大腿上下方的角状物开始起作用，把她牢牢地固定住。

他们涉过现在对于汽车而言太深的小河，继续前行。他们沿着车道骑行，一路通畅。她现在成为落后的一方，因为月光的马很精神，而罗宾已经累了。最后十英里，她眼冒金星，骑着罗宾疲倦地慢走或者小跑。最后五英里，皮肤棕黑的牧工紧挨着她前进，好让自己能在她掉下来的时候接住她。但她挺住了。大约七点钟，她骑着马踏进了夜色茫茫的威尔斯镇。那时的她，是一个疲劳困顿的姑娘，骑着一匹同样疲劳困顿的马，旁边跟着一个棕色皮肤的牧工。她骑过旅馆和渗着彩光的冰室，来到海恩斯中士的警察局和住所外面，在一个小摊前停下。她已经连续在马背上度过了大约八个小时。

月光下了马，抓住罗宾的头。她鼓起最后一丝力量，抬起右脚，跨过马鞍，滑到地上。刚下马的时候，她连站都站不稳，只好扶着罗宾的马鞍。海恩斯中士已经出来了。

“你怎么来了，佩吉特小姐？”他拖着慢悠悠的昆士兰腔调说，“从哪儿来的？”

“从乔·哈曼那儿。”她说，“他在米德赫斯特的北部边界找到唐·柯蒂斯了，唐断了一条腿。中士，请告诉月光怎样处置这两匹马，然后扶我进去详细说。”

他让月光把马牵进警察局的畜栏，晚上和负责跟踪脚印的警察一起住在宿舍里，然后转向琴。“进屋吧。”他说，“这儿，扶着我的手臂。你骑了多远？”

“四十英里。”她说。终于走完了这么长的路，尽管累得虚脱，她还是感到一丝自豪。“乔·哈曼留下来陪伴柯蒂斯先生。米德赫斯特的其他牧工都去那里了，他们要清理出一条跑道来。乔说只能用飞机把他接走。越野车过不了河。”

他扶她在安有防蚊网的门廊上坐下，海恩斯太太端来一杯茶。他扫了一眼挂钟，不紧不慢地坐下来听她讲。他错过了凯恩斯救护站七点钟的值班守听时间，现在必须要等三刻钟才能采取下一步行动。“距离新钻头大约六英里，西—南—西方向。”他思考着说，“我知道了，那附近有一块开阔的空地。我一会儿在广播上发送消息，吩咐飞机明早出发。”

“乔在想，如果你在广播上发送消息，是否可以请一些温德米尔的牧工过去帮他清理跑道？”她说，“让他们去帮他砍树。我不许他亲自上阵，因为他后背有伤。”

他点点头。“我会同时通知温德米尔。”然后他说，“我从不知道你是个骑手，佩吉特小姐。”

“我不是的，”她说，“我之前只骑过六次马。”

他微微一笑，然后说：“哦，老天，你觉得疼吗？”

她疲惫地站起身来。“我要回家睡觉。”她扶着椅背说，“如果我继续留在这里，这双腿就该残废了。”

“坐着别动，”他说，“我去开越野车把你送到医院。”

“我不想去医院。”

“我不管你想不想去，”他说，“但你必须去。你最好在那儿过夜，道格拉斯护士会把你照顾得好好的。”

半个小时后，她被清洗得干干净净，乖乖地躺在病床上，身上涂满了青霉素药膏，感觉自己像个幼童。海恩斯中士回到办公室，在无线电收发机前坐下来。

“第八区查理女王，第八区查理女王，”他说，“这是第八区爱麦克呼叫第八区查理女王。第八区查理女王，如果你听到第八区爱麦克的呼叫，请回话。报文完，请回复！”

他转动旋钮，机器上方的扬声器传来一个姑娘的声音：“第八区爱麦克，这是第八区查理女王，我能听见你说话，音量为三。请告诉我你的消息。完毕。”

他说：“第八区查理女王，我们发现唐·柯蒂斯了。乔·哈曼在米德赫斯特北部边界找到了他。他的伤情是有创骨折，左腿，两天半，很可能左脚踝也骨折了。扎营地点距离哈曼的新钻头大约六英里，西—南—西方向。收信悉否？完毕。”

扬声器里的女声说：“哦——我真是太高兴了，我们这边都担心死了。收信悉，但我会重复一遍。”她重复了一遍。“报文完，请回复！”

他说：“好的，杰姬。现在请向巴尔内斯先生转达一条信息。内容是：请求救护飞机从威尔斯镇尽快准备丛林降落。请复述一遍。完毕。”

她向他复述了一遍。

“好的，杰姬，”他说，“现在请替我呼叫温德米尔，我要跟他们说话。完毕。”

她说：“第八区能人乔治，第八区能人乔治，第八区查理女王呼叫第八区能人乔治。如果你能听见我的呼叫，第八区能人乔治，请回话。报文完，请回复！”

从三十个牧场住宅的三十个扬声器中传出一个战栗的女声。“第八区查理女王，这是第八区能人乔治。我都听到了，杰姬。上帝回答祈祷者的方式真是奇妙啊！哦，我的天啊，我高兴得不知道说什么好。我确定我们今晚都应该下跪，感谢上帝的仁慈。我确定我们都应该那样做。哦——完毕。”

培根小姐转动她的旋钮。“我确定大家今晚都会感谢上帝，海伦。现在海恩斯中士正等着跟你说话呢。请注意守听，把开关旋到‘接收’上，海伦。第八区爱麦克，请回话，完毕。”

在威尔斯镇，海恩斯中士说：“第八区爱麦克呼叫第八区能人乔治。柯蒂斯太太，你已经听说了乔·哈曼目前在米德赫斯特北部边界陪伴你丈夫。他必须清理出一条能让救护飞机降落的跑道，并已经命令米德赫斯特的全体牧工都去帮忙。你能把目前留在温德米尔的所有人员派去帮忙吗？我会把位置告诉你，请用铅笔和纸记下来。”他顿了顿，“跑道距离他的新钻头六英里，西—南—西方向。距离他的新钻头六英里，西—南—西方向。我希望你能派目前留在温德米尔的所有人员去帮助他，并把该信息传达给邓肯警员，如果他在你身边。柯蒂斯太太，收文悉否？完毕。”

那个震颤着的声音说：“收文悉，中士。距离乔的新钻头六英里，西—南—西方向。我写下来了。埃迪·佩吉在这里，我想菲尔·邓肯今晚就能回来。我会把所有的人都派去那儿。上帝能给予我们的帮助实在是太神奇了。每当我想到上帝对我们这些受苦受难的罪人是多么仁慈，我就会双膝跪地并哭泣。”她顿了顿，然后说，“哦，我又忘了。完毕。”

他转动旋钮，说：“你要感谢的不仅仅是上帝，柯蒂斯太太。”他非常清楚，海湾地区方圆十万英尺以内的几乎所有家庭主妇都在收听广播，而且他也相信好人应该有好报。“佩吉特小姐骑马赶了四十英里路，从米德赫斯特北部边界赶到威尔斯镇，带来了唐的消息。你认识琴·佩吉特吗？她就是那个开办了工厂和冰室的英国姑娘。我们听说唐失踪的那天，她正好在米德赫斯特，她骑了四十英里来告诉我跑道的位置。她之前只骑过六次马，可怜的姑娘浑身疼得连站都站不起来。道格拉斯护士正在医院照顾她，让她安心休息。她过几天就会好起来。完毕。”

她说：“哦，老天。我不知道说什么来感谢她。请向她转达我最深的爱，希望她尽快康复。”她顿了顿，然后说，“她开的那间冰室让我很纠结。在威尔斯镇开一个那样的店铺似乎不太合适，而且它连周日和圣诞节都开门，从不消停。我在《圣经》里找不到任何支持或者反对它的内容，但我一直深感困惑。不过，现在那似乎也是上帝的安排，就像其他一切一样。我真的觉得那间冰室很棒。完毕。”

“没错。”海恩斯中士态度暧昧地说。他自己也一直对于冰室的关门时间心存疑虑，并曾写信到总部请求指导。他已经很久没有萌生勒令一间店铺关门停业的想法了。“我现在必须结束通话，柯蒂斯太太。第八区查理女王，这是第八区爱麦克。我的事情已经处理完毕，你今晚不必再值班了，杰姬。请你从明天七点开始保持日间守听。收文悉否？完毕。”

培根小姐说：“收文悉，中士。我会告诉巴尔内斯先生。如果你没别的事情要跟我说，我就结束广播。完毕。”

“没有了，杰姬。晚安。通话结束。”

“晚安，中士。通话结束。”

培根小姐满心感激地关掉了她的机器。凯恩斯救护中心并没有要求员工保持二十四小时守听，但现在情况如此紧急，人人都应该尽己所能伸出援手。她前一天就从早晨八点守听到午夜，今天早上又从八点守听到现在。巴尔内斯先生昨晚守夜，并已经准备好今晚再守一夜。她懊恼地想，她错过了亨弗莱·鲍嘉和劳伦·巴考尔(1)，电影已经演了一半了。不过明天晚上还有一场，如果这件事情到那时已经了结，她还能幸运地赶上。她去打电话给巴尔内斯先生。

巴尔内斯先生打电话给澳洲国家航空公司的斯迈思先生，斯迈思先生打电话给他的预备飞行员吉米·科普。科普先生说：“见鬼，希望明早的天气变得好一些，今天飞机绝对飞不过阿瑟顿高原。我看最好六点出发，我会准时抵达飞机库。”

他第二天一大早抵达机场的时候，老飞龙号的两个引擎都已经开动了。它无疑是内地有史以来制作最精良的急救飞机。此时细雨潇潇，云层低压，大约五百英尺高，把机场后面的大山遮盖得严严实实。威尔斯镇大约距离乔所在地点西—北—西方向四百英里。这次飞行的头七十英里要飞越阿瑟顿高原，那里的山脉高达三千五百英尺。没有广播导航的帮助，他将不得不一直用肉眼探路，尽他所能在云层和树顶之间勉强飞行。

他向机场的控制官员说了几句晦气话，便沿跑道起飞。同去的还有一个救护员。一飞上天，他就发现情况糟糕透顶。他在三百英尺的高度飞行，沿着贝伦河北上，向着大山飞去，希望能在低云(2)中找到一个缺口，使他可以在库兰达峡谷内爬升，飞越阿瑟顿高原。灰色的蒸汽紧紧包围着他，机翼擦过覆满森林的峡谷边缘。前面没有任何缺口的迹象，他向右舷方向侧移，在峡谷里勉强拐了一个很危险的弯，最近的时候离峡谷的峭壁只有一百英尺。他随后飞回海边，抬起麦克风说：“凯恩斯发射塔，这是胜利者超能麦克面包师(3)。我无法从库兰达飞往目的地。我将往北飞往海边的库克镇，尝试从那儿飞往目的地。请告诉库克镇，我将在大约一个小时之后在那儿降落，并需要加二十加仑的七十三号汽油。”

他往北飞过昆士兰的热带海岸，飞行高度大约为三百英尺，一个小时后飞抵库克镇。库克镇很小，人口大约三百，但他抵达时，小镇笼罩在乌云中，雨横风狂。他在机场降落并加了油。“我要尝试从这儿飞去威尔斯镇，”他说，“路上不会有太高的障碍。如果状况太糟糕，我就飞回来。我会从这儿直线飞往威尔斯镇。”他这么说，是为了万一他遭遇意外，救援队能找到他。

加完油后，他马上启程，依照罗盘指示方向往内陆飞去。在整个飞行过程中，他从未飞离树顶超过两百英尺。他勉强飞越了大分水岭，离山顶只有五十英尺的距离，总是眼看就要回头了，就看见前面有一个模糊的缺口，迫使他往前飞，逐渐进入北部地区。护理员坐在他身后，紧紧抓住座位，被吓得魂飞魄散，却什么都做不了。他们就这样一直飞了三个小时。靠近卡奔塔利亚湾的时候，飞行员开始发现他认识的地标：一个河湾，一片被烧毁的树林，一弯形似香蕉的沙荒。他飞抵威尔斯镇，在零零落落的房屋上空一百英尺处盘旋，通知他们自己已经抵达，然后在机场降落。他滑行至等候他的卡车前，精神紧张，筋疲力尽。雨仍在下。

在卡车旁边，他、海恩斯中士、道格拉斯护士和阿尔·伯恩斯一起开了一个小会。“我会尝试把他接回来。”他说，“如果下午情况没有好转，他就只能在这儿的医院过夜。在这种天气里我无法把他送到凯恩斯去。明儿的天气很可能会好一些。”他们给他一幅徒手画的铅笔地图，是中士给他准备的，上面标示着小河和米德赫斯特牧场住宅的位置，还有新钻头和跑道的大概位置。大约十一点，他再度启程。

按照地图，他没费多大工夫就找到了目的地。降落地点很明显，因为他们把一块狭长地带清理了出来，还把一小块草地上的灌木都砍光了。他能看到十个人，有的在埋头工作，有的抬起头来望着飞机。他看见一辆越野车停在那儿，上面有一个帐篷。他在低云下盘旋，计算风险。他们清理出来的跑道即使对于一架飞龙号飞机而言也短得可怜。然而，事态紧急，那个男人已经受伤三天了，脓毒病、坏疽或一切其他疾病都可能降临。他咬紧牙关，将飞龙号对准跑道，尝试降落。

他用尽全部勇气，慢慢越过树顶下降，离它们仅有五英尺，小心翼翼地调整速度。他在被砍掉的树木上方减速，向草地俯冲，希望草地是光滑的。眼看就要成功了……不行，他绝对无法及时把飞机停住。轮子离地面不到两英尺的时候，他加大油门，保持高度飞行了片刻，重又攀升离开。

他让飞机在低云下盘旋，使跑道保持在视线范围之内，然后转向身后的护理员。“有铅笔和纸吗？我说你写。”他想了一会儿，“抱歉我无法降落。你们必须把跑道延长一百码，如果可以的话一百五十码。我下午四点再回来。”他们把纸条放进带有彩色饰带的邮袋里，从跑道上空飞过，把邮袋扔到跑道中央。

回到威尔斯镇后，他向他们讲述了事情经过。“他们时间不够，”中士说，“下午应该就没问题了。”中士开车送他去旅馆，阿尔·伯恩斯带他去酒吧，但他除了柠檬水之外什么都不肯喝，因为下午还有一趟困难重重的飞行。

他在旅馆吃完午饭，闲步走进冰室。他上次来威尔斯镇时这间冰室还没开张。他既兴奋又好奇地东看看西瞧瞧，点了一份冰淇淋。露丝·索耶催他赶快吃掉它，因为马上就要打烊了。他问她是不是每天下午都关门，她说她要去医院看望佩吉特小姐。然后，顺理成章地，他听闻了她的英勇举动。

四点钟，他回到米德赫斯特北部边界。雨已经停了，他能够以八百英尺的高度接近跑道。他在上方盘旋了一会儿，仔细观察地面情况。他们把跑道延长了许多，这次的降落很顺利。飞机向下俯冲，在近端降落，在不平整的跑道上蹦蹦跳跳地落了地，颠簸着滑行，渐渐停了下来。

他熄灭引擎并爬出机舱。他们把担架从机舱里抬出来，护理员把唐·柯蒂斯抬上担架，在牧工的帮助下把担架搬上机舱。飞行员点起一根烟，递给哈曼一根。

乔问：“你在威尔斯镇听到任何关于佩吉特小姐的消息了吗？”

飞行员说：“她在医院里。他们说没什么大碍，只是又累又疼。她肯定是个了不起的女孩儿。”

乔说：“太对了。如果你看见任何从医院来的人，请帮我给佩吉特小姐捎个信儿，好吗？请告诉她我明天下午进镇。”

“我会的，”飞行员说，“我今晚会在那儿过夜。现在去凯恩斯太晚了。我无法在这种天气里进行夜间飞行，这架飞机不行。”

护理员和牧工已经把唐搬上了飞机。科普先生回到驾驶座上，护理员转起螺旋桨，他们滑行回跑道的远端。跑道很短，但他能起飞。他发动引擎，沿跑道起飞，以十五英尺的距离呼啸着擦过远端的树顶。半小时后，他在威尔斯镇落地，帮忙把担架搬上卡车，卡车将唐·柯蒂斯送到医院。

当天下午，琴·佩吉特在医院里给露丝·索耶看她的伤口。有些地方皮都蹭掉了，伤口长达六英寸。“多么光荣的伤疤啊，”露丝说，“可惜你不能把它们露出来给别人看。”

“那是因为所有东西都太湿了。”琴说，“但我想我不可能找到一条完全合身的骑马裤。骑马裤是专门针对牧工的皮肤而设计的。”

“换了是我，就再也不想骑马了。”

“短期内我都无法再骑了。”琴说。

过了一会儿，露丝说：“请告诉我，琴，你认为承包商能在这里揽到工程吗？”

琴盯着她。“做什么工程的承包商？”

“修路之类的。建房子也行。”

“你是给爱丽丝的比利·韦克林问的吗？”

露丝点点头。“他给我写信。”她淡淡地道。琴觉得，她如此描述每周三由空中列车送来的七封信，实在是太过于轻描淡写。“他父亲是纽卡斯尔(4)的承包商——有平路机、推土机、蒸汽挖土机和所有那一类的东西。战后他让比利在爱丽丝创业，因为他说爱丽丝正在发展扩大，而那意味着承包商有许多工程可做。但比利说他已经受够了爱丽丝。

“雨季一结束，他就会来威尔斯镇一趟。”她就事论事地添上一句。

“他在这里揽不到任何修路或者建房工程，”琴说，“没人会愿意出钱。不过我知道这里有什么工程可做。乔·哈曼想在米德赫斯特修建一些小水坝。我不知道那是不是在比利的经营范围内。”

“我想应该是吧，”露丝慢慢地说，“反正比利干的就是这种脏活累活。旱季的时候用推土机就能修起来吧，是不是？”

“我对此一窍不通。”琴说，“他能找到推土机吗？”

“他的老爷子在纽卡斯尔有大概四十台呢，”露丝说，“我想应该能腾出一台来给比利吧。”

“不过只是修小型水坝。”琴说。

“嗯，做什么生意都总要有个开头嘛。我想比利也不会期望一个像悉尼海港大桥(5)那样的合同，这才第一年。”

琴问：“能不能用推土机挖一个坑来修游泳池呢？”

“我想可以吧。哦，我想起来了，肯定可以。我有一次和他出去约会，我们去看推土机是怎么工作的。他让我试着开了一下，实在是好玩极了。可以先用推土机把土挖出来，在坑里铺上木头，他们把那叫作构模，然后用混凝土做池壁。”

“这些比利都能做吗？”

“哦，比利都能做。为什么这么问呢，你想修一个游泳池吗？”

琴盯着漆成白色的墙壁。“那只是一个想法。就在钻孔旁边修一个漂亮的大泳池，池边有跳水板和其他一切，大得足够让所有人都跳进去嬉戏。主街道上就水源充足。我们要先修一个木制的东西，好像是叫冷却塔吧，让水流进去冷却后再流进游泳池。还要在旁边修一个草坪，让人们躺在上面晒日光浴。请一个老人家在门口收钱，游一次泳收一先令……”

露丝盯着她。“你都计划好了。你真的要这么做吗，琴？”

“不知道。一个游泳池能增添很多欢乐，而且我相信它就像其他生意一样能挣钱。当然了，我说的是混合游泳池。”

露丝笑道：“老古板们都会站在围栏后面偷看的。”

“那要收他们六便士。”琴说。她转向露丝。“请让比利准备好工程计划和工具，”她说，“雨季结束后把价钱告诉我们。我相信整个海湾地区连一个游泳池也没有。开一个肯定很有趣。”

“我问问他。还有别的吗？”

琴在床上舒展身体。“一个漂亮的美发沙龙兼美容院。”她说，“我要请一个漂亮的法国黑发姑娘来打理它。这个姑娘一定要是个行家，能够把顾客打扮得像丽塔·海华丝(6)那么漂亮。我时不时就想起这个计划来。但我不知道那是不是比利的经营范围。”

“最好不是。”露丝说。

琴第二天起床出院，一瘸一拐地走到工厂。帕克先生寄来了一封航空邮件，内容是关于他从她们那儿收到的空运皮鞋。他故作平淡地指出它们的瑕疵和毛病，提醒她们在进行批量生产时必须予以改正，这一次他们就先替她们处理好了。在信的结尾，他说他会尝试把这批鞋卖掉。琴和阿姬·托普非常了解帕克先生，把这句话理解成对她们的表扬。

“下一批会让他更满意的。”阿姬说。然后她说：“你不在的时候，有两个姑娘来应聘。一个是弗雷德·道森的女儿，弗雷德好像是一个叫作卡莱尔农场的牧工领班什么的。她十五岁，由母亲带着来的。她有点太年轻了，但挺有前途。还有一个十九岁的姑娘，之前在诺曼顿的商店工作。我不是很喜欢她。”

“我不想在售出第一批鞋子之前招聘新员工。”琴说，“如果道森太太再来，就说我们会在雨季结束后答复她。如果可以的话我想聘用这个小姑娘。我想我们就不聘另一个了，你说呢？”

“我想还是不要了。她看起来有点懒。”

她们就工作的细节问题谈论了一个小时。“我们还没把制服拿回来，”阿姬说，“我去找哈里森太太了，但她的背病又犯了。我们必须找另一家帮忙洗。”她们已经向姑娘们作出保证，每周都能让她们穿着干净的制服干活。这些制服的清洗工作对她们来讲是一个问题。

“我们需要的，”琴说，“是一台洗衣机，自己洗制服。我们可以把它接在发电机组上……当然了，还需要热水。”她想了一会儿，“要不这样，”她说，“我们可以把它租给人们洗衣服。不过，目前还是要先找到另一个哈里森太太。”

阿姬说：“所有人都在谈论你骑马的事情，佩吉特小姐。”

“真的？”

她点点头。“就连那个从诺曼顿来的女孩儿也听说了。”

“她到底是从哪儿听来的？”

“就是他们在牛场上使用的那些无线电收发机。”阿姬说，“这里的牧工告诉我，他们每天都收听广播——电报内容什么的他们都知道。他们反正闲着也是闲着。在这个地区，秘密都藏不住。”然后她说，“我今早听见飞机起飞了。那个男人的伤势很严重吗？”

“不太好，”琴说，“护士认为那条腿应该能保住。我们真应该请个医生过来。”

“医生在这个地方没什么活干。”阿姬说，“他们要把他送去哪儿？”

“凯恩斯。凯恩斯有一个很好的医院。”她转向门口，顿了顿，“阿姬，”她说，“你觉得在威尔斯镇修一个游泳池怎么样？人们会去游泳吗？”

乔·哈曼当天下午和彼特·弗莱彻一起骑马进镇。他把马牵进澳大利亚旅馆后面的马厩，然后来找琴。他穿着骑马服，湿淋淋脏兮兮的，因为小河都涨满了。虽然他离开米德赫斯特时打扮得很整洁，对于一个去镇上见女朋友的男士而言非常得体，但路上他必须抓住马的鬃毛和马鞍游过一两条小河，使得他精心打扮的成果付诸东流。他抵达威尔斯镇时，身上已经干了一半。他梳了梳头，把靴子里的水倒干，去冰室问露丝琴在哪里。

他在卧室里找到了正在给我写一封长信的琴。他敲了敲门，她出来迎接他。“我们不能在这里谈话，乔。如果你走进来，人们肯定要没完没了地嚼舌根。我们去冰室吃客冰淇淋吧。”她确信，这是威尔斯镇唯一一个可以让青年男女光明正大地见面聊天的地方。如果是在雨季，他们还可以走进马厩或者谷仓。他们挑了一张靠墙的桌子坐下。她东张西望，看着方方正正的四面墙，邻桌的人对她很有意见。“这不行，”她说，“我要隔出一些雅座，让顾客可以在小角落里说悄悄话。”

“你要吃什么？”他问。

“我要香蕉船，”她说，“我要补充营养。我不知道你是否知道，但我一直都觉得很不舒服。别给钱，乔——冰室请客啦。”

他咧嘴而笑。“你觉得我是那种带女孩儿出去却让她请客的男人吗？”

“如果你那样想，我就来两份。香蕉明天就要变质了。”她请空中列车每周三送来少量水果，很容易就能售罄，价格足以支付航空运费。但问题是它们通常不到一个星期就变质了。

他端着冰冻的甜品回来，和她一起坐下。“好了，乔，”她说，“小牛畜栏是怎么回事？”

他不好意思地露齿而笑，回头看了看。“那是骗人的，”他说，“米德赫斯特没有小牛畜栏。”

“好像有一个吧，”她笑道，“你老实交代。唐·柯蒂斯到底是怎么受的伤？”

“他在我的土地上偷偷摸摸地瞎溜达，他是没有权利这么做的。”乔小心地说，“他找到我用来围住小牛的畜栏——注意，是我的小牛。我把它们关在那儿，让它们冷静一下，因为它们离群了。嗯，唐想把它们偷走。他拿掉上门闩，但那些小牛可野了，它们已经有大概四天没喝水了，只能靠雨水解渴。我猜他弄松第二条门闩的时候，它们把门冲破了，木柱砸在他后背上，把他击倒了。然后它们都从他身上跑过，踩碎了他的脚。它们还向马冲去。唐用缰绳把马系在不知道什么东西上，那些小牛冲向那匹马，把缰绳撞断了，马就跑了。唐就这样倒在那儿，直到我发现他。真是活该，让他乱跑。”

“这些小牛是谁的？老实告诉我，乔。”

“我的。”他坚定地回答。

她微微一笑。“你在哪里发现它们离群了？”

他咧嘴而笑。“温德米尔。但它们是我的小牛。他从我那儿偷走的。我告诉过彼特他在温德米尔有一个小牛畜栏，你也听见了。”

“你畜栏里那些小牛，是不是就是你从他的畜栏里放出来的那些？”她问。她似乎已经开始介入此事了。

“差不多吧，”他说，“你可以说有几头是我顺手牵走作为补偿的。”他顿了顿，“有时候会混在一起分不清。”他说。

“现在小牛在哪儿？”她问，“我是指唐放出来的那些。”

“它们会在米德赫斯特，”他说，“我想是在钻头附近。它们绝对不会离开第一个水源，甚至在雨季时也不会。”

她默默地吃了几口香蕉船，然后说：“嗯，至少你在他住院期间不能去偷他的小牛，乔。那不公平。那样他出院时就会发现所有小牛都被偷光了。”

“我不会做那种事。”

“我敢打赌说你会。我不懂这个游戏的玩法，乔，但我肯定那是违反规则的。”

他咧嘴而笑。“好吧，但他一出院就会来偷我的牛。那肯定错不了。”

“你们为什么不能放过其他人的小牛？”

“即使我放过他的小牛，他也不会放过我的小牛。”他简单地说，“去年我多偷了他五十头。”

琴感觉这个对话不会有成果。在小牛的问题上，乔似乎毫无道德操守可言。她换了一个话题，说：“乔，我想跟你谈谈你在格林岛上提到的那些小水坝。你找到人来修了吗？”

他摇摇头。“等旱季来了再说吧。”

“用推土机能修起来吗？”

“哦，老天，”他说，“如果有人有辆推土机，一个月内就会建起来很多东西。但克里一带没有推土机。”

“可能会有一辆。”她说。她告诉乔露丝·索耶和比利·韦克林的事情。“反正他也要来见她，”她说，“而且她说他想在这里承包工程。我想他和露丝的感情会稳定下来。他来的时候，你最好带他到米德赫斯特去谈一谈。”

“老天，”他说，“如果在威尔斯镇有一个会开推土机的家伙，周边的牛场将会发生很大的变化。”

“威尔斯镇也会改头换面。”她说，“乔，如果我们就在钻头附近修一个相当不错的游泳池，配上跳水板、换装的小屋和可以晒日光浴的草坪，再请一位老人家负责修剪并打理草坪——人们会去游泳吗，乔？如果我们收一先令的入场费？”

他们就游泳池的话题讨论了一段时间，如果一个小镇只有一百五十个居民，修一个游泳池是无利可图的。“只是发展速度的问题，”他说，“游泳池和其他东西一样，也能促进它的发展。整个海湾地区没有一个镇有游泳池。”

“冰室绝对能挣钱。”琴说，“如果能保持食物的质量，应该很快就会上轨道。要是我能从诺尔·斯特拉坎那儿预支一笔钱，下一步我想试试游泳池。”

他微笑着，好奇地问道：“游泳池之后是什么？”

她的目光落在外面一大片潮湿泥泞的土地上，威尔斯镇的街道荒凉寂寞。“他们游泳时会把头发弄湿，所以我要开一间美容院。”她说，“我想那是下一步。之后是一间露天影院，然后是水洗洗衣房，再然后是一间漂亮的服装店。”她转向他，“别笑我，乔。我知道那听起来有点疯狂，但看看我的成绩。我开了一间冰室给露丝打理，年轻的韦克林就冲着她来到了威尔斯镇，还带来了一辆推土机，这样你的水坝也修好了。”

“你说早了，”他说，“还没开始修呢。”

“很快就会开始了。”

他环视冰室。“如果你的所有计划都像这个冰室一样顺利，”他慢慢地说，“威尔斯镇很快就会变得跟爱丽丝斯普林斯一样棒了。”

“那就是我想要的，”她说，“一个像爱丽丝的小镇。”

————————————————————

(1) 亨弗莱·鲍嘉和劳伦·巴考尔都是著名的美国演员，亨弗莱曾获得奥斯卡最佳男主角奖。两人于1945年结婚。

(2) 低云的高度一般在2500米以下，大部分会产生降水。

(3) 科普先生的代号。

(4) 指澳大利亚的纽卡斯尔。

(5) 位于悉尼，建成于1932年，被誉为世界第一单孔桥，是悉尼的标志性建筑之一。

(6) 二十世纪四十年代红极一时的美国女星，以性感美艳著称。

第十一章

转眼间，差不多三年过去了。

我无法否认，当时她的每一封信都给我带来了无穷的乐趣。我的生活寂静空虚，不知不觉间，它们成为了我的精神寄托。我想，在经历了柯蒂斯先生和“迷盗小牛”事件之后，她终于融入了海湾地区的生活。甚至还在结婚之前，她给我写来的信就已经发生了微妙的变化。她的口吻不再像一个流落他乡的英国女子，那片土地对她而言，似乎不再陌生，也不再荆棘满布。渐渐地，她笔下的人物不再是异乡人，她描画的地方也变成了她的家园。当然，这可能仅仅是我的幻觉。也许是因为我太沉迷于她的信，每一封都反复细读了，并用专门的文件夹把它们珍藏在公寓里，所以才能察觉出它们的微妙差别。这些差别是如此细微，一个马虎的读者可能根本不会注意到。

四月的集合结束后，她兑现了自己的诺言，和乔·哈曼结了婚。布什修士会的一位英国巡回牧师为他们主婚。碰巧的是，这位牧师曾经在金士顿的圣约翰教堂当过教区牧师，这个教堂距离我之前在温布顿的住所还不到十英里。他们在郡政厅成婚，因为威尔斯镇当时没有教堂，尽管人们正在计划第二年修一个。所有乡下居民都参加了婚礼。他们去格林岛度蜜月，或者蜜月的一部分。我猜她一定带上了纱笼，尽管她没有告诉我。

婚后头两年，她透支了相当大一部分财产。她精通投资之道，在同时开办冰室和工厂之后，总是步步为营，等一桩生意上了轨道再开始下一桩。她会把所有的账目表都寄给我，它们都是由一位年轻的银行职员莱恩·詹士制作的。尽管如此，她还是每隔半年就会问我要三四千镑，直到她第二个儿子出生。她用我的名字给他命名。到那时她已经透支了一万八千英镑来开办各种当地生意了。尽管它们似乎都有盈利，列斯特和我还是越来越担心自己未能恪尽托管义务，虽然麦法登先生的遗嘱给予了我们充分的裁量权。我们的职责是在她满三十五周岁的时候把财产完好无损地交到她手中。我开始担心澳大利亚陷入经济萧条，或者横遭某种未知的灾难，使得我们预支给她的三成遗产血本无归。她多少有点孤注一掷，而且她的投资虽然成绩斐然，却不能被视为托管股票。

今年二月，她生下诺尔后不久，从威尔斯镇给我写来一封长信，请求我给她预支一笔空前的巨款。她问我是否愿意当诺尔的教父，那当然让我非常高兴，尽管以我的年纪，已经不太可能对他恪尽教父的义务了。她打算请韦克林做第二位教父。既然他大约六个月前已经和露丝·索耶成婚，并似乎要在那个地区成家立业，她多给孩子找一个住在世界另一边的老教父，对孩子也没任何坏处。当然了，我马上对我的遗嘱作了相应的修改。

她接着在信里谈到米德赫斯特的事务。“乔现在是唯一的经理，”她写道，“他做得相当出色。他刚到这个牛场的时候，这里有大约八千头牛，但现在已经增长到一万两千或一万三千头。我们今年将会卖出超过两千头牛，无法一趟全部赶到朱利亚克里克，所以乔要跑两趟。接下来两年应该还会稳步增长，因为每年旱季比尔(1)·韦克林都会给我们新修一些水坝，牧草的数量连年增长。”

她继续向我介绍牧场主人斯皮尔斯太太的情况。“她丈夫大约十年前去世，她随后离开了海湾地区，”她说，“现在住在布里斯班。去年十月，乔和我去她家里住了几个晚上。我那时没告诉你这件事，因为我想先把它考虑清楚，还要先确定能不能贷到款。”

她告诉我，斯皮尔斯太太年事已高，想把套在米德赫斯特的资本卖掉变现。她很可能打算在有生之年将财产转移出去，以规避遗产税。“她问我们是否可以购买牧场的一半股份，”她说，“这样我们就能获得剩下一半股份的期权，在她临终时以估算价值购入，不论那将是何年何月。那意味着我们现在要筹集大约三万镑的资金，即一半股份的价值。当然了，土地是向国家租借的，根据现在的租约，还有十七年租期。那意味着要更改租约，把乔的名字加进去，和她联名。”

她告诉我他们已经去过银行了。银行可以贷给他们两万镑。“他们派了一个熟悉牧牛业的检查员来米德赫斯特，”她写道，“乔在海湾地区的名声很好，我想检查员认为我们经营颇为得法。我们现在只差一万镑现金，这就是我的请求。”

她岔开了话题。“米德赫斯特很好，”她说，“我们在此生活愉快。如果我们无法接管它，斯皮尔斯太太很可能会把它卖掉，我们就不得不另寻一个新地方重新开始。那对乔而言太残忍了，因为他在米德赫斯特上倾注了那么多心血。现在让我离开威尔斯镇的话，我将感到痛苦万分，因为它已经逐渐发展为一个颇具规模的地方，镇上的生活也充满了欢乐。如果可以的话，我确实很想留在这里。”

她继续写道：“我知道牛场不属于托管投资，诺尔，跟我的其他投资一样。请你认真考虑此事，并把决定告诉我。如果不行的话，我就要重新想办法，也许就要把我的生意卖掉或者抵押出去。我真不想那样做，因为它们可能落入庸人之手，从此一蹶不振。这个小镇就像一个初生的婴儿——我知道当母亲的感受，诺尔！在它变强壮之前，需要受到细心的呵护。”

这意味着我们要允许她把一半的遗产都投进极具投机性的行业里，并且集中在一个地区。这绝对违反麦法登先生立遗嘱时的意愿。从法律上说，我们几无风险，我悄然加进遗嘱中的自由裁量条款措辞模糊，能保护任何违反托管义务的行为。在把她的信拿给列斯特看之前，我花了几天时间来思考此事。最后，我认为我们的职责是尽量揣测麦法登先生的心意，做出他本人在相同情况下会做出的决定。

那位隐居在埃尔的古怪先生会做出什么决定呢？他虽然身患残疾，但我不觉得他冷酷无情或者蛮不讲理。他并不是因为不信任琴·佩吉特而规定了那么长的托管年限，他根本就不认识她。他这么做完全是为她好，因为他觉得一个二十来岁的未婚姑娘一旦一夜暴富，极容易上当受骗。在这一点上，他很可能是对的。但琴·佩吉特是一个三十岁的已婚女人，已经是两个小孩的母亲，并和一个又明智又可靠的男士结了婚——不管他在“迷盗小牛”上持什么观点。麦法登先生在此种情况下是否还会坚持原定托管办法？

我想不会。他是一个仁慈的人——我很确定——既然那是她的家，也是她情之所钟，他肯定也希望她能得到米德赫斯特。然而，他是一个谨慎的苏格兰人，我想他更加关心的是这笔投资的细节，确保这一万镑能带来丰厚的回报。就此而论，我认为必须解决租期问题。十七年太短，无法让乔收回在水坝和其他新建设施上投入的成本。如果不经过谈判延长租期，他将很可能无法继续进行资本改良。

然后我把她的信拿给我的合伙人看，并就此谈了很长时间。他的观点和我一样，认为租期是这件事情的核心问题。“我觉得，在托管这件事情上，我们不能太死板。”他说，“我想你的做法是对的，尝试把自己代入立遗嘱人的角色。他妹夫在世的时候，他并没有提任何托管的事情，因为他觉得妹夫可以帮助妹妹妥善处理这笔财产。他在妹夫去世后才想到要把财产托管。嗯，现在他外甥女已经结婚了。如果让他现在处理这笔钱，很可能不会费心将它托管了。”

“你的看法挺有道理的，”我说，“我没想到这一点。”

“我不认为我们应该无视托管义务。”他说，“我们应该以此为契机，帮她获得一个合乎理想的新租约。我们可以放话，必须修改租约，在我们对所作修改感到满意之前，不会解冻一分钱。我觉得这样她就能达成所有目标。”

我微微一笑。“我不会把这点告诉她。”

第二天，我坐下来起草了一封回信。“我认为我们可以考虑你的请求，”我写道，“但非常抱歉，我们对目前的租约非常不满意，你们必须先修改它。根据目前的租约，很可能你们十七年后就会无家可归，你们和斯皮尔斯太太在牛场上投入的资本也会血本无归。根据我目前所得到的信息，所有新建设施都要无偿收归国有。”后来我才知道事实并非如此。

接下来，我亮出这封信的主要观点：“毫无疑问，你已经有一个值得信赖的律师，但如果我能帮助你处理此事，我将很愿意去拜访你，在昆士兰住几周，确保在你将此笔巨资投进米德赫斯特之前，租期一事得到妥善解决。我多年不曾离开英国，深感后悔。我已到了风烛残年之时，可以用来周游世界的时间已经不多了。我想给自己放一个长假，在变得老朽无能之前出去走走。如果我能帮助你处理租约一事，将不胜欣喜，并马上付诸行动。”我添了一句话，“赘言一句，我将自费出行。”

大约十天后，琴通过夜间电报给我回复。她催促我尽快去拜访他们，并建议我四月底坐飞机去，因为那时昆士兰即将入冬，天气就跟英国的夏天一样。她正在给我列一张单子，写上我要带去的衣物、药品和旅途所需物品。我有点感动。

第二天，我去温坡街的诊所拜访我的医生肯尼迪。“有没有什么特别的理由阻止我飞去昆士兰？”我问。

他一脸疑惑地看着我。“准确地说，我不应该建议你这么做。你非去昆士兰不可吗？”

“我非常想去，”我说，“我想在那里住一个月左右，处理一点私事。”

“你最近走路怎么样？”

向他撒谎没有任何意义。“早上我一般步行至特拉法尔加广场，”我说，“从那里打车去办公室。”

“你无法全程走路上班？”

“不，”我说，“我有一些日子没那么做了。”

“如果中间不停歇，你能爬俱乐部的楼梯上二层吗？”

我摇摇头。“我总是坐电梯上去。但我在昆士兰不用爬楼梯，所有的房子都是平房。”

他微笑道：“请脱掉外套和衬衫，让我给你检查一下。”

检查结束后，他说：“嗯。你打算自己一个人去吗？”

我点点头。“我会跟朋友们住在一起，他们会去机场接我。”

“你真的觉得非去不可？”

我们四目相迎。“我想去。真的很想。”

“好吧，”他说，“你也很了解自己的情况。没有什么新问题——只是一些正常的退化。战争期间你减了十年寿。总的来说，我想你坐飞机去是明智的。我想你飞越红海时会感到非常劳累。”他继续告诉我可以做的事和绝对不能做的事，都是些老生常谈。

我回到办公室，跟列斯特说了我的计划。“我将给自己放三个月左右的假，”我说，“从四月底开始。我会坐飞机去，不知道要去多久。如果我去程时觉得坐飞机太辛苦，回程就坐船。”我顿了顿，“总之你就当我要放长假吧。反正我也很快退休了。”

“你真的觉得有必要亲自去吗？”他问。

“是的。”

“好吧，诺尔。我只是希望你不要在这件事情上消耗太多精力。这毕竟是件小事。”

“我不能同意这句话，”我说，“我开始觉得，在我这辈子处理过的所有案子之中，这才是最重要的。”

我在一个周一早上离开了伦敦，坐同一班机一直飞到悉尼，落地时已经是周三深夜。这趟飞机经停开罗、卡拉奇、加尔各答、新加坡和达尔文。我必须说，这架飞机很舒适，空姐也相当善解人意，温柔体贴。当然了，在躺椅上睡两个晚上让人疲倦不堪，落地时我倍感轻松高兴。我在悉尼休息了两晚，下午租了一辆汽车进城兜风。第二天，我坐飞机去凯恩斯，一路上风景秀美宜人，布里斯班以北的昆士兰海岸线尤其漂亮。临近降落的时候，飞机沿着凯恩斯和汤斯维尔之间的欣钦布鲁克海峡北上，那一定是世界上最迷人的海岸线之一。

我们晚上在凯恩斯降落。我收到了一个很大的惊喜，因为乔·哈曼在机场迎接我。他说，空中列车现在每周往海湾地区飞两趟，部分是由于威尔斯镇发展迅速。他是坐周五的飞机来的，打算周一带我去威尔斯镇。“我要在这儿处理几件小事情，”他说，“我的律师本·霍普也在凯恩斯。我想，您可能愿意利用这个周末了解一下米德赫斯特的基本情况，并与他会面。”

自从他三年前离开伦敦之后，我至今不曾听到过慢悠悠的昆士兰腔调。他开车送我去旅馆。那是一座形状古怪的楼房，坐落在一个相当漂亮的地方。旅馆内的酒吧规模巨大，似乎是人们的活动中心。我们正好在开饭前到达——这里的人把晚饭称作“茶”——下了车就走进餐厅坐下。他问我要喝茶、啤酒还是普朗克(2)。

“廉价酒？”我问。

“普朗克是一种红酒，”他说，“我自己很少喝，但那些懂酒的家伙说它还不错。”

我从酒水单上选了亨特河酒，喝起来相当不错。“琴不能亲自来接您，她觉得很抱歉。”他说，“我们可以托人照顾小乔，但她还在给诺尔喂奶，所以来不了。她周一开车去威尔斯镇接您。”

“她最近怎么样？”我问。

“她很好。”他说，“生小孩对她有好处，她变得越来越漂亮了。”

饭后，我们在卧室外面的门廊上坐下来，开始讨论米德赫斯特的事情。他带来了牛场过去三年的账目表，打印得很整洁，字迹清晰可辨。我对它们作出了评论，他说：“我在这方面不怎么在行。琴住院前就把它们做好了，她负责管账。我告诉她我想在牛场上做什么，她就让我知道我还剩多少钱可以花。她受的教育比我多。”

然而，我发现他是一个很精明的男人。在租期和资本改良方面有一些很复杂的问题，但他理解起来毫不费力。我们那个晚上聊了好几个小时，谈到他的牛场和琴在镇上开办的各种生意。他对那些生意非常感兴趣。

“她请了二十二个姑娘在工厂工作，”他说，“她们现在制作皮鞋、公文包和女士手提包。工厂和其他生意相比要差一些。”他把账目表翻给我看。“今年挣钱了，但去年损失了两百多镑——两百二十七镑。但所有其他生意——哦，老天。”他给我看冰室、美容院、游泳池、电影院、洗衣房和服装店的数字，“它们都很好。蔬果店也不错。”我们把数字加总，发现去年这七项一共带来了两千六百七十三镑的净利润。“即使工厂亏损，她照样挣钱，”他说，“姑娘们要把自己在牧工面前打扮得漂漂亮亮的，牧工也要带姑娘们出去消费，钱又回到她腰包里了。”

我为工厂感到一丝担忧。“能否通过扩大生产规模来降低日常管理开支水平？”我问。

他对此抱着怀疑的态度。“她已经把杰夫·波科克和另外两个人送过来的所有皮都用上了，”他说，“沙袋鼠的数量也减少了。我认为她的工厂没什么拓展空间，她也不想这么做。她有一种预感，可能再过几年就可以把这间工厂关掉。威尔斯镇会变得很大，到时一间只聘请二十个姑娘的工厂就会变得无关紧要了。”

“我知道了。”我思考着说，“威尔斯镇现在有多大？”

“现在有大约四百五十人住在威尔斯镇，”他说，“不包括土著，也不包括住在牛场上的人。人口在过去三年里增加了两倍。”

“全部归功于工厂吗？”我问。

他慢慢地说：“我想一定是——仔细想想，所有东西都跟它有关。不仅是工厂。她请了两个姑娘来打理冰室，还有一个土著姑娘。美容院请了两个，服装店三个，蔬果店两个，电影院三个。她可请了不少人呢。”

我感到困惑不解。“但工厂里只有二十个姑娘，她们能给这么多其他姑娘创造工作机会吗？”

“好像没那么简单。”他说，“前几天我们算了一笔总账。在任何一个时点上，她聘请的姑娘从未超过三十五个。但自从她开办工厂以来，已经有四十二个姑娘结了婚并辞职。她们基本上都嫁给了牧工。嗯，威尔斯镇多了四十二个新家庭，就意味着有四十二个女士需要电影院、美容院和新鲜蔬菜，再加上她正在雇用的那三十五个姑娘，就像滚雪球一样。”他顿了顿，“比如说银行。那儿前所未有地请了两个女职员，都是因为业务量增加了。澳大利亚互济公司(3)在我们这儿开设了一个办事处，请了一个姑娘。比尔·韦克林的办公室也请了一个姑娘。”他转向我，“实际上，威尔斯镇现在有大约一百个二十五岁以下的未婚姑娘或者已婚少妇。”他说，“琴来的时候只有两个。”

“还有婴儿！”他说，“婴儿多得数不清。他们派了一个助产士过来。那又是一个女孩儿。她上个月和菲尔·邓肯警员订婚了，所以还会再派一个过来。”

我微笑道：“有足够的男士来满足需求吗？”

“哦，老天，”他说，“现在很容易就能请到小伙子来威尔斯镇工作。我现在请的牧工来自昆士兰各地，还有从北领地来的，他们都想在威尔斯镇附近找一份工作。有一个小伙儿从西澳大利亚的马布尔巴远道而来，走了大约两千英里路呢。现在的劳动力情况和三年前大不一样了。”

那晚我很早就上床休息，躺着思考了很多事情。第二天早上，我去霍普律师的办公室找他，写了一封信给昆士兰土地管理局，提议召开一个会议来讨论米德赫斯特的租期问题。那天下午，我们在凯恩斯四处兜风观光。我觉得凯恩斯是一个怡人的热带小镇，环镇景色清新秀美。周日我们开车北上去阿瑟顿高原，看见许多高高的丘陵农田，耕作方式颇有点英国化。

我们周一上午坐空中列车飞往威尔斯镇，沿途在名叫乔治敦、克罗伊登等地方降落，在每个机场上停留大约二十分钟，接送乘客和装卸货物。我们在乔治敦上空盘旋准备降落的时候，我得以观察这个地方。它很有点凄凉，从天空上能看到四四方方的街道布局。这些街道都很宽阔，也曾繁荣一时，边上有过鳞次栉比的楼房，但现在芳草丛生，雨痕密布。几座寥落的房子站在曾经的街道交会处，大部分都紧紧挨着旅馆。在乔治敦和克罗伊登，旅馆都是唯一一座两层楼房。这两个破败的地方都是被抛弃了的黄金镇。

坐卡车来接机的人们都被晒成了古铜色，健康风趣。男士们几乎都皮肤黝黑、高大健壮，看起来非常能干，女士们则是又朴实又顺从的家庭主妇。

我靠窗坐着，起飞时细细观察克罗伊登，直到它被我们抛在身后。“您能看到这些小镇，我还挺开心的。”我身旁的乔说，“威尔斯镇原来也这样，比它们还要糟糕一点。当然了，它现在还算不上特别出色，但比克罗伊登好。哦，老天。”

我们在威尔斯镇上空盘旋，准备降落。它位于一条大河旁边，布局跟另外两个小镇出奇地相似。宽阔的街道同样构成一个四方形，但这个四方形上盖满了房子。从飞机上俯视小镇，只见每一个瓦楞铁屋顶上都洒满了耀目的阳光，所以当飞机背对太阳盘旋的时候，我必须闭上眼睛以防眩晕。这些房子似乎全部都是簇新的，街道上还有相当多尚未完工的房子。我看见了一座两层高的楼房，大概也是旅馆，对面是主街道，路中央有一条灌木带，把宽阔的牛道隔成双行线，边上还修了柏油人行道。旅馆对面是一个带跳水板的游泳池，周围有一些小木屋，池边还有一块草坪，恰如琴在信中的描述。然后镇子从视线中消失了，我们开始降落，在一条崭新的跑道上滑行，停下。

她坐在一辆福特越野车上等我。那是她的私人座驾，她经常开着它进出威尔斯镇打理生意。现在的她已经成长为一个非常迷人的女人，比我记忆中那个年轻的姑娘成熟多了。她说：“哦，诺尔，见到你真是太高兴了。累坏了吧？”

“我不累，”我说，“只是因为又老了三四岁。你看起来神采飞扬。”

“我很好，”她说，“好得不得了。诺尔，你能来看我们真是太好了。我想请你来，但又觉得这个要求太过分。实在是太远了。快上车，让乔帮你拿包。”

他们马上驾车送我去米德赫斯特。越野车驶过威尔斯镇的主街道，我想下车看看她的生意，但他们不允许。“明天或后天再慢慢看吧，有的是时间，”她说，“我们现在去米德赫斯特，你先稍微休息一下。”

读了那么多她的信，我深知沿途将会看到何等景象。跟我的预想丝毫不差。并没有我们通常所说的道路，她小心翼翼地寻路穿过郊区，沿着重重叠叠的车辙前进，遇到深坑便绕过去。我们来到第一条小河的河边，我惊讶地看到他们修了一条横穿河床的混凝土堤道。河流两岸立了两条巨大的木桩，用于标示堤道的位置。“我们还没发展到修建桥梁的地步，”她说，“但雨季时这条堤道简直就是上帝的恩赐，再也不用担心撞上水底的大石头了。”

牧场住宅跟我想象中相去不远，但前面多了一座花园，里面繁花盛放，鲜艳夺目。还多了一大排我没听说过的木栅栏或者牛栏。“我们现在有三头瘤牛(4)，开始育种后，我们需要更多畜栏。”他的瘤牛是印度瘤牛和英国赫尔福德牛的杂交种。他告诉我，他还养了一小群奶牛，所以还需要修建更多畜栏。

“你现在有多少人手？”我问。

“十一个牧工，”他说，“十个土著。现在这个地区白人差不多比土著还好请。”

他们那天不允许我走路，只让我端着冷饮坐在门廊的一张长椅上。人们在院子里忙活各种工作的时候，我静坐欣赏。这幅景象非常迷人，白人牧工、土著牧工、牛、狗和马，还有一只半大的沙袋鼠到处跳来跳去，一群小狗追着它的尾巴逗它。我可以无休止地坐在那里一直欣赏下去，顺带欣赏琴优雅地在房子里走来走去，照顾孩子并使唤她的土著女仆。我在那里足足坐了三天。

一天早上，她带我进镇，向我展示她的所有杰作。她先是带我去看工厂。进去之前，她先让我围上一条围巾，因为里面很冷。室内温度其实并不低，但比炎热的室外低很多，突然走进去很容易着凉，因为她让空调一年到头都开着。“姑娘们确实也喜欢让它开着，”她说，“就因为有空调，前来应聘的人数总是超过空缺数。”这些姑娘都穿着绿色的制服，正在埋头生产皮制品，看起来又聪明又漂亮。车间一头挂着一面长镜子，墙上钉着几幅从画报上剪下来的图片，都是时下流行的发型和连衣裙图样。“我们经常更换它们，”她说，“我希望她们能把自己最漂亮的一面展示出来。”

工厂是独门独户的，但她把其他店铺修成一排，看上去像一条小小的商业街。她在宽阔的柏油人行道上方修了一个木门廊，给逛街的人遮阳挡雨。她请了一个中年爱沙尼亚女士负责打理美容院，这位漂亮的女士有着深色的皮肤，妆容精致，手下有两个澳大利亚姑娘。店内有四个独立隔间、一个玻璃柜台和一个摆满女士用品的展示柜，雅致干净。美容院旁边是一个小店面，店里有四台家用洗衣机，三个年轻的已婚女士坐在一旁，等洗衣机洗衣服，一边说着家长里短。洗衣店旁边是卖种子、园林工具和水果蔬菜的蔬果店。再旁边就是服装店。这里地方很大，有很多柜台和穿着夏天连衣裙的假人模特。我对于一个被单独隔开的小角落很感兴趣，里面有一个中年店员，老人家可以在这里买到他们惯常所穿的衣服，例如黑裙子、法兰绒衬裙和做工粗糙的厨房围裙。

她带我穿过马路去看电影院和游泳池。那会儿正是酷热难耐的大白天，我有点熬不住了，于是她带我去冰室喝了杯冷饮。她中途离开半小时去处理一些生意上的事情，我便自己一人坐着，观察走进冰室或者路过人行道的人。女人比男人多得多。女士们看起来都很漂亮，似乎至少一半怀有身孕。

过了一会儿，她回来和我一起坐在冰室里。“下一步打算做什么？”我问，“什么时候是个头？”

她笑着把手放在我的手上。“没完没了。”她说，“我会一直缠着你，管你要钱，是不是？事实上，我想我已经攒起足够的利润来实施下一步计划了。”

“是什么计划？”

“开一个自选杂货铺，”她回答，“需求在变化，诺尔。开始的时候，威尔斯镇需要的是娱乐，因为那时所有人都还年轻，都还没结婚。他们不需要那些实在、理智的东西，他们需要的是冰淇淋、游泳池、美容院和电影院。他们现在仍然需要这些东西，但这方面的需求没有太大的增长空间。现在威尔斯镇需要满足年轻家庭的需求。我要开一间合乎理想的杂货店，以尽量低的价格出售种类丰富的优质食品。紧接着我还要开一间日用品商店。你知道在威尔斯镇，连给婴儿做饭用的锅都买不到吗？”

我向对门的商店点点头。“邓肯先生的商店没有卖吗？”

“他毫无想象力。他卖的那些锅大得能把整个婴儿都放进去。”

过了一会儿，我问她：“你的商品是怎样运过来的？肯定不是都走空运吧？”

她摇摇头。“从凯恩斯到福赛斯走铁路，再用卡车把它们从福赛斯运过来。当然了，没有一条像样的路，导致运费出奇地高，因为一辆卡车最多只能开两年。比尔·韦克林说路政委员会正在酝酿一条从威尔斯镇通往马里巴和凯恩斯的路——一条像样的柏油路。当然了，他想承包这个工程。他认为这条路两年内就能修好，因为威尔斯镇发展得这么快。我必须说，这条路将是上帝的恩赐。开车去凯恩斯只需要一天的时间，真是难以想象！”

土地管理局那周晚些时候回复了我们。考虑到飞往威尔斯镇的班机时间，他们建议于下周二或周三召开一个会议。我和乔·哈曼一起飞往布里斯班，在凯恩斯捎上他的律师，和土地管理局的官员开了一个会。会议持续了差不多一天，我们在会上敲定了框架协议。会后，哈曼返回牛场，霍普先生和我则继续留在布里斯班，与土地管理局反复来回交换最终协议的草案，用红色、绿色、蓝色和紫色的墨水进行修改。此外，我还与斯皮尔斯太太的律师保持着联系，洽谈全盘购买米德赫斯特的期权合约。所有这些事务让我在布里斯班忙活了差不多两个星期。在和列斯特交换电报之后，我终于把两份合同都敲定，并把它们带回凯恩斯。乔·哈曼在合同上签名后，我们把它们寄了出去。至此，我在昆士兰的任务已经完成。

我和乔一起回到威尔斯镇，又和他们住了一个星期。我并不是非要多留一个星期不可，只是出于一种老年人的情感。我和琴一起坐在门廊上，她把自选杂货店的布局画了出来，征求我的意见。我们讨论能否把它和五金店合并起来，并去威尔斯镇为杂货店选址。我去找郡文书卡特先生，讨论这块土地的租期。她带我去看游泳池，我们讨论在混凝土上铺瓷砖的成本。我在冰室坐了许多个小时，看年轻漂亮的女士推着婴儿车穿梭于商店之间。

有一次我问她是否会回英国度假。她犹豫了，然后轻轻地说：“绝对不会，诺尔。乔和我打算明年出国度假，但我们想去美国。我们想去旧金山，买一辆旧汽车，沿着西海岸驶往亚利桑那州和得克萨斯州。那样的话，我们肯定能学到很多在威尔斯镇派得上用场的东西。他们肯定也遇到过和我们一样的问题，并且比我们更早着手解决。”

一天晚上，琴建议我留下来跟他们一起住，让我非常感动。“你在英国也没有什么牵挂了，诺尔，”她说，“你实际上已经退休了。为什么不放弃赞善里，放弃伦敦，留在这里和我们一起生活呢？你也知道我们很想和你住在一起。”

这当然是不可能的。老人家和年轻人都需要有自己的独立空间。“谢谢你的邀请，”我说，“我希望可以留下。但你也知道我有儿子和孙子。哈利明年会来伦敦，我们都希望他能回到岸上工作。我想他在海军部的任期已经结束了。”

她说：“那真是太可惜了。乔和我详细谈论过此事，我们希望你能和我们一起长住，和我们一起在这里安家。”

我轻轻地说：“多谢你们的厚意，琴，但我必须回去。”

他们自然亲自开车送我去机场，和我告别。告别是愚蠢的事情，忘得越快越好。我甚至都不记得她说了什么，反正那也不重要。我只能记得自己感激万分，因为那趟空中列车上连一个空中小姐也没有。飞机起飞后，在威尔斯镇上空盘旋，准备进入航线，我最后一次看见那个海湾小镇上簇新的楼房，还有那些耀眼的屋顶。幸好没有人能看见我当时脸上的表情。

现在是冬天，距离我最后一次出门去办公室或者俱乐部已经差不多三个月了。我的儿媳妇，马丁的妻子伊芙一直在照顾我的生活起居。正是因为她的坚持，我聘请了一位护士住在公寓看护我。他们想让我进养老院，但我是不会去的。

这个冬天，我一直在写这个故事。我想，老人家总是喜欢沉溺于回忆之中，而我又有把回忆写下来的癖好。故事写完后，我发现自己已经在不知不觉间深陷其中，难以自拔。在一个新城市拔地而起的时候，从旁协助并非小事一桩。当我坐在这里，看进伦敦沉沉的浓雾，有时不禁会想，琴所作的努力到底意味着什么？她这些成就的重要性，时人能否意识到呢？

我前几天写信给她，告诉她我萌生了一个奇怪的想法。她的财产最初是由詹士·麦法登挣来的。上世纪最后几年，他曾经在西澳大利亚的霍尔斯克里克淘金，并因此一夜暴富。我想，霍尔斯克里克现在已经被抛弃了，就像另一个伯克敦和另一个克罗伊登。我觉得，金子被从这些地方挖走，变成了资本，冥冥之中又回到了家乡，使这些荒凉的土地重又繁荣起来，也不枉这一路上的辗转漂泊。想到这一点，我认为自己对这笔财产的处理非常得当，詹士·麦法登肯定也会赞同我的做法，尽管这跟他儿子那份严格的遗嘱南辕北辙。但毕竟这笔钱是詹士挣来的，并把它从一个像威尔斯镇那样的地方带到了英国。我想，如果他知道自己的甥孙女(5)又把它带回了澳大利亚，一定会倍感欣慰。

我想，也许正是因为我的生活圈子太过狭窄，才会如此喜欢回忆这些勇敢的人和陌生的场景。这几年来，我一直牵挂着这些人和事，感慨良多。这个冬天，我日复一日地坐在这里，终日在椅子里沉睡，几乎分不清自己身在伦敦还是海湾地区，总是梦见炫目的阳光，“迷盗小牛”和土著牧工，梦见凯恩斯和格林岛，梦见一个迟到了四十年的姑娘，梦见她在那个小镇上的生活。那个让我魂牵梦萦的小镇啊，今生无缘再见了！

————————————————————

(1) 比利的昵称。

(2) 乔说的是“plonk”，在英式英语里指廉价酒，所以诺尔感到很奇怪。

(3) 澳大利亚的一家人寿保险服务机构和互助协会，初成立时为非营利组织， 1998年变为营利机构并上市。

(4) 原产印度，因脖子背后有一巨大牛峰而得名。

(5) 原文为great-niece，译为侄孙女或甥孙女，但按前文所述，琴实则为詹士·麦法登的外孙女。此处许是作者笔误。

Chapter 1

James Macfadden died in March 1905 when he was forty-seven years old; he was riding in the Driffield Point-to-Point.

He left the bulk of his money to his son Douglas. The Macfaddens and the Dalhousies at that time lived in Perth, and Douglas was a school friend of Jock Dalhousie, who was a young man then, and had gone to London to become junior partner in a firm of solicitors in Chancery Lane, Owen, Dalhousie, and Peters. I am now the senior partner, and Owen and Dalhousie and Peters have been dead for many years, but I never changed the name of the firm.

It was natural that Douglas Macfadden should put his affairs into the hands of Jock Dalhousie, and Mr Dalhousie handled them personally till he died in 1928. In splitting up the work I took Mr Macfadden on to my list of clients, and forgot about him in the pressure of other matters.

It was not until 1935 that any business for him came up. I had a letter from him then, from an address in Ayr. He said that his brother-in-law, Arthur Paget, had been killed in a motor car accident in Malaya and so he wanted to redraft his will to make a trust in favour of his sister Jean and her two children. I am sorry to say that I was so ignorant of this client that I did not even know he was unmarried and had no issue of his own. He finished up by saying that he was too unwell to travel down to London, and he suggested that perhaps a junior member of the firm might be sent up to see him and arrange the matter.

This fitted in with my arrangements fairly well, because when I got this letter I was just leaving for a fortnight's fishing holiday on Loch Shiel. I wrote and told him that I would visit him on my way south, and I put the file concerning his affairs in the bottom of my suitcase to study one evening during my vacation.

When I got to Ayr I took a room at the Station Hotel, because in our correspondence there had been no suggestion that he could put me up. I changed out of my plus-fours into a dark business suit, and went to call upon my client.

He did not live at all in the manner I had expected. I did not know much about his estate except that it was probably well over twenty thousand pounds, and I had expected to find my client living in a house with a servant or two. Instead, I discovered that he had a bedroom and a sitting-room on the same floor of a small private hotel just off the sea front. He was evidently leading the life of an invalid though he was hardly more than fifty years old at that time, ten years younger than I was myself. He was as frail as an old lady of eighty, and he had a peculiar grey look about him which didn't look at all good to me. All the windows of his sitting-room were shut and after the clean air of the lochs and moors I found his room stuffy and close; he had a number of budgerigars in cages in the window, and the smell of these birds made the room very unpleasant. It was clear from the furnishings that he had lived in that hotel and in that room for a good many years.

He told me something about his life as we discussed the will; he was quite affable, and pleased that I had been able to come to visit him myself. He seemed to be an educated man, though he spoke with a marked Scots accent.“I live very quietly, Mr Strachan,”he said.“My health will not permit me to go far abroad. Whiles I get out upon the front on a fine day and sit for a time, and then again Maggie—that's the daughter of Mrs Doyle who keeps the house—Maggie wheels me out in the chair. They are very good to me here.”

Turning to the matter of the will, he told me that he had no close relatives at all except his sister, Jean Paget.“Forbye my father might have left what you might call an indiscretion or two in Australia,”he said.“I would not say that there might not be some of those about, though I have never met one, or corresponded. Jean told me once that my mother had been sore distressed. Women talk about these things, of course, and my father was a lusty type of man.”

His sister Jean had been an officer in the WAACs in the 1914-1918 War, and she had married a Captain Paget in the spring of 1917.“It was not a very usual sort of marriage,”he said thoughtfully.“You must remember that my sister Jean had never been out of Scotland till she joined the army, and the greater part of her life had been spent in Perth. Arthur Paget was an Englishman from Southampton, in Hampshire. I have nothing against Arthur, but we had all naturally thought that Jean would have married a Scot. Still, I would not say but it has been a happy marriage, or as happy as most.”

After the war was over Arthur Paget had got a job upon a rubber estate in Malaya somewhere near Taiping, and Jean, of course, went out there with him. From that time Douglas Macfadden had seen little of his sister; she had been home on leave in 1926 and again in 1932. She had two children, Donald born in 1918 and Jean born in 1921; these children had been left in England in 1932 to live with the Paget parents and to go to school in Southampton, while their mother returned to Malaya. My client had seen them only once, in 1932 when their mother brought them up to Scotland.

The present position was that Arthur Paget had been killed in a motor accident somewhere near Ipoh; he had been driving home at night from Kuala Lumpur and had driven off the road at a high speed and hit a tree. Probably he fell asleep. His widow, Jean Paget, was in England; she had come home a year or so before his death and she had taken a small house in Bassett just outside Southampton to make a home for the children and to be near their schools. It was a sensible arrangement, of course, but it seemed to me to be a pity that the brother and the sister could not have arranged to live nearer to each other. I fancy that my client regretted the distance that separated them, because he referred to it more than once.

He wanted to revise his will. His existing will was a very simple one, in which he left his entire estate to his sister Jean.“I would not alter that,”he said.“But you must understand that Arthur Paget was alive when I made that will, and that in the nature of things I expected him to be alive when Jean inherited from me, and I expected that he would be there to guide her in matters of business. I shall not make old bones.”

He seemed to have a fixed idea that all women were unworldly creatures and incapable of looking after money; they were irresponsible, and at the mercy of any adventurer. Accordingly, although he wanted his sister to have the full use of his money after his death, he wanted to create a trust to ensure that her son Donald, at that time a schoolboy, should inherit the whole estate intact after his mother's death. There was, of course, no special difficulty in that. I presented to him the various pros and cons of a trust such as he envisaged, and I reminded him that a small legacy to Mrs Doyle, in whose house he had lived for so many years, might not be out of place provided that he was still living with them at the time of his death. He agreed to that. He told me then that he had no close relations living, and he asked me if I would undertake to be the sole trustee of his estate and the executor of his will. That is the sort of business a family solicitor frequently takes on his shoulders, of course. I told him that in view of my age he should appoint a co-trustee, and he agreed to the insertion of our junior partner, Mr Lester Robinson, to be co-trustee with me. He also agreed to a charging clause for our professional services in connection with the trust.

There only remained to tidy up the loose ends of what was, after all, a fairly simple will. I asked him what should happen if both he and his sister were to die before the boy Donald was twenty-one, and I suggested that the trust should terminate and the boy should inherit the estate absolutely, when he reached his majority. He agreed to this, and I made another note upon my pad.

“Supposing then,”I said,“that Donald should die before his mother, or if Donald and his mother should die in some way before you. The estate would then pass to the girl, Jean. Again, I take it that the trust would terminate when she reached her majority?”

“Ye mean,”he asked,“when she became twenty-one?”

I nodded.“Yes. That is what we decided in the case of her brother.”

He shook his head.“I think that would be most imprudent, Mr Strachan, if I may say so. No lassie would be fit to administer her own estate when she was twenty-one. A lassie of that age is at the mercy of her sex, Mr Strachan, at the mercy of her sex. I would want the trust to continue for much longer than that. Till she was forty, at the very least.”

From various past experiences I could not help agreeing with him that twenty-one was a bit young for a girl to have absolute control over a large sum of money, but forty seemed to me to be excessively old. I stated my own view that twenty-five would be a reasonable age, and very reluctantly he receded to thirty-five. I could not move him from that position, and as he was obviously tiring and growing irritable I accepted that as the maximum duration of our trust. It meant that in those very unlikely circumstances the trust would continue for twenty-one years from that date, since the girl Jean had been born in 1921 and it was then 1935. That finished our business and I left him and went back to London to draft out the will, which I sent to him for signature. I never saw my client again.

It was my fault that I lost touch with him. It had been my habit for a great many years to take my holiday in the spring, when I would go with my wife to Scotland for a fortnight's fishing, usually to Loch Shiel. I thought that this was going on for ever, as one does, and that next year I would call again upon this client on my way down from the north to see if there was any other business I could do for him. But things turn out differently, sometimes. In the winter of 1935 Lucy died. I don't want to dwell on that, but we had been married for twenty-seven years and—well, it was very painful. Both our sons were abroad, Harry in his submarine on the China station and Martin in his oil company at Basra. I hadn't the heart to go back to Loch Shiel, and I have never been to Scotland since. I had a sale and got rid of most of our furniture, and I sold our house on Wimbledon Common; one has to make an effort at a time like that, and a clean break. It's no good going on living in the ashes of a dead happiness.

I took a flat in Buckingham Gate opposite the Palace stables and just across the park from my club in Pall Mall. I furnished it with a few things out of the Wimbledon house and got a woman to come in and cook my breakfast and clean for me in the mornings, and here I set out to re-create my life. I knew the pattern well enough from the experience of others in the club. Breakfast in my flat. Walk through the Park and up the Strand to my office in Chancery Lane. Work all day, with a light lunch at my desk. To the club at six o'clock to read the periodicals, and gossip, and dine, and after dinner a rubber of bridge. That is the routine that I fell into in the spring of 1936, and I am in it still.

All this, as I say, took my mind from Douglas Macfadden; with more than half my mind upon my own affairs I could only manage to attend to those clients who had urgent business with my office. And presently another interest grew upon me. It was quite obvious that war was coming, and some of us in the club who were too old for active military service began to get very interested in Air Raid Precautions. Cutting the long story short, Civil Defence as it came to be called absorbed the whole of my leisure for the next eight years. I became a Warden, and I was on duty in my district of Westminster all through the London blitz and the long, slow years of war that followed it. Practically all my staff went on service, and I had to run the office almost single-handed. In those years I never took a holiday, and I doubt if I slept more than five hours in any night. When finally peace came in 1945 my hair was white and my head shaky, and though I improved a little in the years that followed I had definitely joined the ranks of the old men.

One afternoon in January 1948 I got a telegram from Ayr. It read,

Regret Mr Douglas Macfadden passed away last night please instruct re funeral.

Doyle, Balmoral Hotel, Ayr.

I had to search my memory, I am afraid, to recollect through the war years who Mr Douglas Macfadden was, and then I had to turn to the file and the will to refresh my memory with the details of what had happened thirteen years before. It seemed rather odd to me that there was nobody at Ayr who could manage the funeral business. I put in a trunk call to Ayr right away and very soon I was speaking to Mrs Doyle. It was a bad line, but I understood that she knew of no relations; apparently Mr Macfadden had had no visitors for a very long time. Clearly, I should have to go to Ayr myself, or else send somebody. I had no urgent engagements for the next two days and the matter seemed to be a little difficult. I had a talk with Lester Robinson, my partner, who had come back from the war as a brigadier, and cleared my desk, and took the sleeper up to Glasgow after dinner that night. In the morning I went down in a slow train to Ayr.

When I got to the Balmoral Hotel I found the landlord and his wife in mourning and obviously distressed; they had been fond of their queer lodger and it was probably due in a great part to their ministrations that he had lived so long. There was no mystery about the cause of death. I had a talk with the doctor and heard all about his trouble; the doctor had been with him at the end, for he lived only two doors away, and the death certificate was already signed. I took a brief look at the body for identification and went through the various formalities of death. It was all perfectly straightforward, except that there were no relations.

“I doubt he had any,”said Mr Doyle.“His sister used to write to him at one time, and she came to see him in 1938, I think it was. She lived in Southampton. But he's had no letters except just a bill or two for the last two years.”

His wife said,“Surely, the sister died, didn't she? Don't you remember him telling us, sometime towards the end of the war?”

“Well, I don't know,”he said.“So much was happening about that time. Maybe she did die.”

Relations or not, arrangements had to be made for the funeral, and I made them that afternoon. When that was done I settled down to look through the papers in his desk. One or two of the figures in an account book and on the back of the counterfoils of his cheque book made me open my eyes; clearly I should have to have a talk with the bank manager first thing next morning. I found a letter from his sister dated in 1941 about the lease of her house. It threw no light, of course, upon her death, if she was dead, but it did reveal significant news about the children. Both of them were in Malaya at that time. The boy Donald, who must have been twenty-three years old at that time, was working on a rubber plantation near Kuala Selangor. His sister Jean had gone out to him in the winter of 1939, and was working in an office in Kuala Lumpur.

At about five o'clock I put in a trunk call to my office in London, standing in the cramped box of the hotel, and spoke to my partner.“Look, Lester,”I said.“I told you that there was some difficulty about the relations. I am completely at a loss up here, I'm sorry to say. Provisionally, I have arranged the funeral for the day after tomorrow, at two o'clock, at St Enoch's cemetery. The only relations that I know of live, or used to live, in Southampton. The sister, Mrs Arthur Paget, was living in 1941 at No 17 St Ronans Road, Bassett—that's just by Southampton somewhere. There were some other Paget relations in the district, the parents of Arthur Paget. Mrs Arthur Paget—her Christian name was Jean—yes, she was the deceased's sister. She had two children, Donald and Jean Paget, but they were both in Malaya in 1941. God knows what became of them. I wouldn't waste much time just now looking for them, but would you get Harris to do what he can to find some of these Southampton Pagets and tell them about the funeral? He'd better take the telephone book and talk to all the Pagets in Southampton one by one. I don't suppose there are so very many.”

Lester came on the telephone to me next morning just after I got back from the bank.“I've nothing very definite, I'm afraid, Noel,”he said.“I did discover one thing. Mrs Paget died in 1942, so she's out of it. She died of pneumonia through going out to the air raid shelter—Harris got that from the hospital. About the other Pagets, there are seven in the telephone directory and we've rung them all up, and they're none of them anything to do with your family. But one of them, Mrs Eustace Paget, thinks the family you're looking for are the Edward Pagets, and that they moved to North Wales after the first Southampton blitz.”

“Any idea whereabouts in North Wales?”I asked.

“Not a clue,”he said.“I think the only thing that you can do now is to proceed with the funeral.”

“I think it is,”I replied.“But tell Harris to go on all the same, because apart from the funeral we've got to find the heirs. I've just been to the bank, and there is quite a sizeable estate. We're the trustees, you know.”

I spent the rest of that day packing up all personal belongings, and letters, and papers, to take down to my office. Furniture at that time was in short supply, and I arranged to store the furniture of the two rooms, since that might be wanted by the heirs. I gave the clothes to Mr Doyle to give away to needy people in Ayr. Only two of the budgerigars were left; I gave those to the Doyles, who seemed to be attached to them. Next morning I had another interview with the bank manager and telephoned to book my sleeper on the night mail down to London. And in the afternoon we buried Douglas Macfadden.

It was very cold and bleak. and grey in the cemetery, that January afternoon. The only mourners were the Doyles, father, mother, and daughter, and myself, and I remember thinking that it was queer how little any of us knew about the man that we were burying. I had a great respect for the Doyle family by that time. They had been overwhelmed when I told them of the small legacy that Mr Macfadden had left them and at first they were genuinely unwilling to take it; they said that they had been well paid for his two rooms and board for many years, and anything else that they had done for him had been because they liked him. It was something, on that bitter January afternoon beside the grave, to feel that he had friends at the last ceremonies.

So that was the end of it, and I drove back with the Doyles and had tea with them in their sitting-room beside the kitchen. And after tea I left for Glasgow and the night train down to London, taking with me two suitcases of papers and small personal effects to be examined at my leisure if the tracing of the heir proved to be troublesome, and later to be handed over as a part of the inheritance.

In fact, he found the heir without much difficulty. Young Harris got a line on it within a week, and presently we got a letter from a Miss Agatha Paget, who was the headmistress of a girls' school in Colwyn Bay. She was a sister of Arthur Paget, who had been killed in the motor accident in Malaya. She confirmed that his wife, Jean, had died in Southampton in the year 1942, and she added the fresh information that the son, Donald, was also dead. He had been a prisoner of war in Malaya, and had died in captivity. Her niece, Jean, however, was alive and in the London district. The headmistress did not know her home address because she lived in rooms and had changed them once or twice, so she usually wrote to her addressing her letters to her firm. She was employed in the office of a concern called Pack and Levy Ltd, whose address was The Hyde, Perivale, London, NW.

I got this letter in the morning mail; I ran through the others and cleared them out of the way, and then picked up this one and read it again. Then I got my secretary to bring me the Macfadden box and I read the will through again, and went through some other papers and my notes on the estate. Finally I reached out for the telephone directory and looked up Pack and Levy Ltd, to find out what they did.

Presently I got up from my desk and stood for a time looking out of the window at the bleak, grey, January London street. I like to think a bit before taking any precipitate action. Then I turned and went through into Robinson's office; he was dictating, and I stood warming myself at his fire till he had finished and the girl had left the room.

“I've got that Macfadden heir,”I said.“I'll tell Harris.”

“All right,”he replied.“You've found the son?”

“No,”I said.“I've found the daughter. The son's dead.”

He laughed.“Bad luck. That means we're trustees for the estate until she's thirty-five, doesn't it?”

I nodded.

“How old is she now?”

I calculated for a minute.“Twenty-six or twenty-seven.”

“Old enough to make a packet of trouble for us.”

“I know.”

“Where is she? What's she doing?”

“She's employed as a clerk or typist with a firm of handbag manufacturers in Perivale,”I said.“I'm just about to concoct a letter to her.”

He smiled.“Fairy Godfather.”

“Exactly,”I replied.

I went back into my room and sat for some time thinking out that letter; it seemed to me to be important to set a formal tone when writing to this young woman for the first time. Finally I wrote,

Dear Madam,

It is with regret that we have to inform you of the death of Mr Douglas Macfadden at Ayr on January 21st. As Executors to his will we have experienced some difficulty in tracing the beneficiaries, but if you are the daughter of Jean (née Macfadden) and Arthur Paget formerly resident in Southampton and in Malaya, it would appear that you may be entitled to a share in the estate.

May we ask you to telephone for an appointment to call upon us at your convenience to discuss the matter further? It will be necessary for you to produce evidence of identity at an early stage, such as your birth certificate, National Registration Identity Card, and any other documents that may occur to you.

I am,

Yours truly,

for Owen, Dalhousie and Peters,

N. H. Strachan

She rang me up the next day. She had quite a pleasant voice, the voice of a well-trained secretary. She said,“Mr Strachan, this is Miss Jean Paget speaking. I've got your letter of the 29th. I wonder—do you work on Saturday mornings? I'm in a job, so Saturday would be the best day for me.”

I replied,“Oh, yes, we work on Saturday mornings. What time would be convenient for you?”

“Should we say ten-thirty?”

I made a note upon my pad.“That's all right. Have you got your birth certificate?”

“Yes, I've got that. Another thing I've got is my mother's marriage certificate, if that helps.”

I said,“Oh yes, bring that along. All right, Miss Paget, I shall look forward to meeting you on Saturday. Ask for me by name, Mr Noel Strachan. I am the senior partner.”

She was shown into my office punctually at ten-thirty on Saturday. She was a girl or woman of a medium height, dark-haired. She was good-looking in a quiet way; she had a tranquility about her that I find it difficult to describe except by saying that it was the grace that you see frequently in women of a Scottish descent. She was dressed in a dark blue coat and skirt. I got up and shook hands with her, and gave her the chair in front of my desk, and went round and sat down myself. I had the papers ready.

“Well, Miss Paget,”I said.“I heard about you from your aunt—I think she is your aunt? Miss Agatha Paget, at Colwyn Bay.”

She inclined her head.“Aunt Aggie wrote and told me that she had had a letter from you. Yes, she's my aunt.”

“And I take it that you are the daughter of Arthur and Jean Paget, who lived in Southampton and Malaya?”

She nodded.“That's right. I've got the birth certificate and mother's birth certificate, as well as her marriage certificate.”She took them from her bag and put them on my desk, with her identity card.

I opened these documents and read them through carefully. There was no doubt about it; she was the person I was looking for. I leaned back in my chair presently and took off my spectacles.“Tell me, Miss Paget,”I said.“Did you ever meet your uncle, who died recently? Mr Douglas Macfadden?”

She hesitated.“I've been thinking about that a lot,”she said candidly.“I couldn't honestly swear that I have ever met him, but I think it must have been him that my mother took me to see once in Scotland, when I was about ten years old. We all went together, Mother and I and Donald. I remember an old man in a very stuffy room with a lot of birds in cages. I think that was Uncle Douglas, but I'm not quite sure.”

That fitted in with what he had told me, the visit of his sister with her children in 1932. This girl would have been eleven years old then.“Tell me about your brother Donald, Miss Paget,”I asked.“Is he still alive?”

She shook her head.“He died in 1943, while he was a prisoner. He was taken by the Japs in Singapore when we surrendered, and then he was sent to the railway.”

I was puzzled.“The railway?”

She looked at me coolly, and I thought I saw tolerance for the ignorance of those who stayed in England in her glance.“The railway that the Japs built with Asiatic and prisoner-of-war labour between Siam and Burma. One man died for every sleeper that was laid, and it was about two hundred miles long. Donald was one of them.”

There was a little pause.“I am so sorry,”I said at last.“One thing I have to ask you, I am afraid. Was there a death certificate?”

She stared at me.“I shouldn't think so.”

“Oh...”I leaned back in my chair and took up the will.“This is the will of Mr Douglas Macfadden,”I said.“I have a copy for you, Miss Paget, but I think I'd better tell you what it contains in ordinary, non-legal language. Your uncle made two small bequests. The whole of the residue of the estate was left in trust for your brother Donald. The terms of the trust were to the effect that your mother was to enjoy the income from the trust until her death. If she died before your brother attained his majority, the trust was to continue until he was twenty-one, when he would inherit absolutely and the trust would be discharged. If your brother died before inheriting, then you were to inherit the residuary estate after your mother's time, but in that event the trust was to continue till the year 1956, when you would be thirty-five years old. You will appreciate that it is necessary for us to obtain legal evidence of your brother's death.”

She hesitated, and then she said,“Mr Strachan, I'm afraid I'm terribly stupid. I understand you want some proof that Donald is dead. But after that is done, do you mean that I inherit everything that Uncle Douglas left?”

“Broadly speaking—yes,”I replied.“You would only receive the income from the estate until the year 1956. After that, the capital would be yours to do what you like with.”

“How much did he leave?”

I picked up a slip of paper from the documents before me and ran my eye down the figures for a final check.“After paying death duties and legacies,”I said carefully,“the residuary estate would be worth about fifty-three thousand pounds at present-day prices. I must make it clear that that is at present-day prices, Miss Paget. You must not assume that you would inherit that sum in 1956. A falling stock market affects even trustee securities.”

She stared at me.“Fifty-three thousand pounds?”

I nodded.“That seems to be about the figure.”

“How much a year would that amount of capital yield, Mr Strachan?”

I glanced at the figures on the slip before me.“Invested in trustee stocks, as at present—about £1550 a year, gross income. Then income tax has to be deducted. You would have about nine hundred a year to spend, Miss Paget.”

“Oh...”There was a long silence; she sat staring at the desk in front of her. Then she looked up at me, and smiled.“It takes a bit of getting used to,”she remarked.“I mean, I've always worked for my living, Mr Strachan. I've never thought that I'd do anything else unless I married, and that's only a different sort of work. But this means that I need never work again—unless I want to.”

She had hit the nail on the head with her last sentence.“That's exactly it,”I replied.“Unless you want to.”

“I don't know what I'd do if I didn't have to go to the office,”she said.“I haven't got any other life...”

“Then I should go on going to the office,”I observed.

She laughed.“I suppose that's the only thing to do.”

I leaned back in my chair.“I'm an old man now, Miss Paget. I've made plenty of mistakes in my time and I've learned one thing from them, that it's never very wise to do anything in a great hurry. I take it that this legacy will mean a considerable change in your circumstances. If I may offer my advice, I should continue in your present employment for the time, at any rate, and I should refrain from talking about your legacy in the office just yet. For one thing, it will be some months before you get possession even of the income from the estate. First we have to obtain legal proof of the death of your brother, and then we have to obtain the confirmation of the executors in Scotland and realize a portion of the securities to meet estate and succession duties. Tell me, what are you doing with this firm Pack and Levy?”

“I'm a shorthand typist,”she said.“I'm working now as secretary to Mr Pack.”

“Where do you live, Miss Paget?”

She said,“I've got a bed-sitting-room at No 43 Campion Road, just off Ealing Common. It's quite convenient, but of course I have a lot of my meals out. There's a Lyons just round the corner.”

I thought for a minute.“Have you got many friends in Ealing? How long have you been there?”

“I don't know very many people,”she replied.“One or two families, people who work in the firm, you know. I've been there over two years now, ever since I was repatriated. I was out in Malaya, you know, Mr Strachan, and I was a sort of prisoner of war for three and a half years. Then when I got home I got this job with Pack and Levy.”

I made a note of her address upon my pad.“Well, Miss Paget,”I said,“I should go on just as usual for the time being. I will consult the War Office on Monday morning and obtain this evidence about your brother as quickly as I can. Tell me his name, and number, and unit.”She did so, and I wrote them down.“As soon as I get that, I shall submit the will for probate. When that is proved, then the trust commences and continues till the year 1956, when you will inherit absolutely.”

She looked up at me.“Tell me about this trust,”she asked.“I'm afraid I'm not very good at legal matters.”

I nodded.“Of course not. Well, you'll find it all in legal language in the copy of the will which I shall give you, but what it means is this, Miss Paget. Your uncle, when he made this will, had a very poor opinion of the ability of women to manage their own money. I'm sorry to have to say such a thing, but it is better for you to know the whole of the facts.”

She laughed.“Please don't apologize for him, Mr Strachan. Go on.”

“At first, he was quite unwilling that you should inherit the capital of the estate till you were forty years old,”I said.“I contested that view, but I was unable to get him to agree to any less period than the present arrangement in the will. Now, the object of a trust is this. The testator appoints trustees—in this case, myself and my partner—who undertake to do their best to preserve the capital intact and hand it over to the legatee—to you—when the trust expires.”

“I see. Uncle Douglas was afraid that I might spend the fifty-three thousand all at once.”

I nodded.“That was in his mind. He did not know you, of course, Miss Paget, so there was nothing personal about it. He felt that in general women were less fit than men to handle large sums of money at an early age.”

She said quietly,“He may have been right.”She thought for a minute, and then she said,“So you're going to look after the money for me till I'm thirty-five and give me the interest to spend in the meantime? Nine hundred a year?”

“If you wish us to conduct your income-tax affairs for you, that would be about the figure,”I said.“We can arrange the payments in any way that you prefer, as a quarterly or a monthly cheque, for example. You would get a formal statement of account half-yearly.”

She asked curiously,“How do you get paid for doing all this for me, Mr Strachan?”

I smiled.“That is a very prudent question, Miss Paget. You will find a clause in the will, No 8, I think, which entitles us to charge for our professional services against the income from the trust. Of course, if you get into any legal trouble we should be glad to act for you and help you in any way we could. In that case we should charge you on the normal scale of fees.”

She said unexpectedly,“I couldn't ask for anybody better.”And then she glanced at me, and said mischievously,“I made some enquiries about this firm yesterday.”

“Oh... I hope they were satisfactory?”

“Very.”She did not tell me then what she told me later, that her informant had described us as,“as solid as the Bank of England, and as sticky as treacle.”“I know I'm going to be in very good hands, Mr Strachan.”

I inclined my head.“I hope so. I am afraid that at times you may find this trust irksome, Miss Paget; I can assure you that I shall do my utmost to prevent it from becoming so. You will see in the will that the testator gave certain powers to the trustees to realize capital for the benefit of the legatee in cases where they were satisfied that it would be genuinely for her advantage.”

“You mean, if I really needed a lot of money—for an operation or something—you could let me have it, if you approved?”

She was quick, that girl.“I think that is a very good example. In case of illness, if the income were insufficient, I should certainly realize some of your capital for your benefit.”

She smiled at me, and said,“It's rather like being a ward in Chancery, or something.”

I was a little touched by the comparison. I said,“I should feel very much honoured if you care to look at it that way, Miss Paget. Inevitably this legacy is going to make an upset in your condition of life, and if I can do anything to help you in the transition I should be only too pleased.”I handed her her copy of the will.“Well, there is the will, and I suggest you take it away and read it quietly by yourself. I'll keep the certificates for the time being. After you've thought things over for a day or two I am sure that there will be a great many questions to which you will want answers. Would you like to come and see me again?”

She said,“I would. I know there'll be all sorts of things I want to ask about, but I can't think of them now. It's all so sudden.”

I turned to my engagement diary.“Well, suppose we meet again about the middle of next week.”I stared at the pages.“Of course, you're working. What time do you get off from your office, Miss Paget?”

She said,“Five o'clock.”

“Would six o'clock on Wednesday evening suit you, then? I shall hope to have got somewhere with the matter of your brother by that time.”

She said,“Well, that's all right for me, Mr Strachan, but isn't it a bit late for you? Don't you want to get home?”

I said absently,“I only go to the club. No, Wednesday at six would suit me very well.”I made a note upon my pad, and then I hesitated.“Perhaps if you are doing nothing after that you might like to come on to the club and have dinner in the Ladies Annexe,”I said.“I'm afraid it's not a very gay place, but the food is good.”

She smiled, and said warmly,“I'd love to do that, Mr Strachan. It's very kind of you to ask me.”

I got to my feet.“Very well, then, Miss Paget—six o'clock on Wednesday. And in the meantime, don't do anything in a great hurry. It never pays to be impetuous...”

She went away, and I cleared my desk and took a taxi to the club for lunch. After lunch I had a cup of coffee and slept for ten minutes in a chair before the fire, and when I woke up I thought I ought to get some exercise. So I put on my hat and coat and went out and walked rather aimlessly up St James's Street and along Piccadilly to the Park. As I walked, I wondered how that fresh young woman was spending her weekend. Was she telling her friends all about her good luck, or was she sitting somewhere warm and quiet, nursing and cherishing her own anticipations, or was she on a spending spree already? Or was she out with a young man? She would have plenty of men now to choose from, I thought cynically, and then it struck me that she probably had those already because she was a very marriageable girl. Indeed, considering her appearance and her evident good nature, I was rather surprised that she was not married already.

I had a little talk that evening in the club with a man who is in the Home Office about the procedure for establishing the death of a prisoner of war, and on Monday I had a number of telephone conversations with the War Office and the Home Office about the case. I found, as I had suspected, that there was an extraordinary procedure for proving death which could be invoked, but where a doctor was available who had attended the deceased in the prison camp the normal certification of death was the procedure to adopt. In this instance there was a general practitioner called Ferris in practice at Beckenham who had been a doctor in Camp 206 in the Takunan district on the Burma-Siam railway, and the official at the War Office advised me that this doctor would be in a position to give the normal death certificate.

I rang him up next morning, and he was out upon his rounds. I tried to make his wife understand what I wanted but I think it was too complicated for her; she suggested that I should call and see him after the evening surgery, at half past six. I hesitated over that because Beckenham is a good long way out, but I was anxious to get these formalities over quickly for the sake of the girl. So I went out to see this doctor that evening.

He was a cheerful, fresh-faced man not more than thirty-five years old; he had a keen sense of humour, if rather a macabre one at times. He looked as healthy and fit as if he had spent the whole of his life in England in a country practice. I got to him just as he was finishing off the last of his patients, and he had leisure to talk for a little.

“Lieutenant Paget,”he said thoughtfully.“Oh yes, I know. Donald Paget—was his name Donald?”I said it was.“Oh, of course, I remember him quite well. Yes, I can write a death certificate. I'd like to do that for him, though I don't suppose it'll do him much good.”

“It will help his sister,”I remarked.“There is a question of an inheritance, and the shorter we can make the necessary formalities the better for her.”

He reached for his pad of forms.“I wonder if she's got as much guts as her brother.”

“Was he a good chap?”

He nodded.“Yes,”he said.“He was a delicate-looking man, dark and rather pale, you know, but he was a very good type. I think he was a planter in civil life—anyway, he was in the Malay volunteers. He spoke Malay very well, and he got along in Siamese all right. With those languages, of course, he was a very useful man to have in the camp. We used to do a lot of black market with the villagers, the Siamese outside, you know. But quite apart from that, he was the sort of officer the men like. It was a great loss when he went.”

“What did he die of?”I asked.

He paused with his pen poised over the paper.“Well, you could take your pick of half a dozen things. I hadn't time to do a post mortem, of course. Between you and me, I don't really know. I think he just died. But he'd recovered from enough to kill a dozen ordinary men, so I don't know that it really matters what one puts down on the certificate. No legal point depends upon the cause of death, does it?”

“Oh, no,”I said.“All I want is the death certified.”

He still paused, in recollection.“He had a huge tropical ulcer on his left leg that we were treating, and that was certainly poisoning the whole system. I think if he'd gone on we'd have had to have taken that leg off. He got that because he was one of those chaps who won't report sick while they can walk. Well, while he was in hospital with the ulcer, he got cerebral malaria. We had nothing to treat that damn thing with till we got around to making our own quinine solutions for intravenous injection; we took a frightful risk with that, but there was nothing else to do. We got a lot through it with that, and Paget was one of them. He got over it quite well. That was just before we got the cholera. Cholera went right through the camp-hospital and everything. We couldn't isolate the cases, or anything like that. I never want to see a show like that again. We'd got nothing, nothing, not even saline. No drugs to speak of, and no equipment. We were making bed-pans out of old kerosene tins. Paget got that, and would you believe it, he got over cholera. We got some prophylactic injections from the Nips and we gave him those; that may have helped. At least, I think we gave him that—I'm not sure. He was very weak when that left him, of course, and the ulcer wasn't any too good. And about a week after that, he just died in the night. Heart, I fancy. I'll tell you what I'll do, I'll put down for Cause of Death—Cholera. There you are, sir. I'm sorry you had to come all this way for it.”

As I took the certificate I asked curiously,“Did you get any of those things yourself?”

He laughed.“I was one of the lucky ones. All I got was the usual dysentery and malaria, the ordinary type malaria, not cerebral. Overwork was my trouble, but other people had that, too. We were in such a jam, for so long. We had hundreds of cases just lying on the floor or bamboo charpoys in palm huts—it was raining almost all the time. No beds, no linen, no equipment, and precious few drugs. You just couldn't rest. You worked till you dropped asleep, and then you got up and went on working. You never came to an end. There was never half an hour when you could slack off and sit and have a smoke, or go for a walk, except by neglecting some poor sod who needed you very badly.”

He paused. I sat silent, thinking how easy by comparison my own war had been.“It went on like that for nearly two years,”he said.“You got a bit depressed at times, because you couldn't even take time off to go and hear a lecture.”

“Did you have lectures?”I asked.

“Oh yes, we used to have a lot of lectures by the chaps in camp. How to grow Cox's Orange Pippins, or the TT motorcycle races, or Life in Hollywood. They made a difference to the men, the lectures did. But we doctors usually couldn't get to them. I mean, it's not much of an alibi when someone's in convulsions if you're listening to a lecture on Cox's Orange Pippins at the other end of the camp.”

I said,“It must have been a terrible experience.”

He paused, reflecting.“It was so beautiful,”he said,“The Three Pagodas Pass must be one of the loveliest places in the world. You've got this broad valley with the river running down it, and the jungle forest, and the mountains.... We used to sit by the river and watch the sun setting behind the mountains, sometimes, and say what a marvellous place it would be to come to for a holiday. However terrible a prison camp may be, it makes a difference if it's beautiful.”

When Jean Paget came to see me on Wednesday evening I was ready to report the progress I had made. First I went through one or two formal matters connected with the winding up of the estate, and then I showed her the schedule of the furniture that I had put in store at Ayr. She was not much interested in that.“I should think it had all better be sold, hadn't it?”she remarked.“Could we put it in an auction?”

“Perhaps it would be as well to wait a little before doing that,”I suggested.“You may want to set up a house or a flat of your own.”

She wrinkled up her nose.“I can't see myself wanting to furnish it with any of Uncle Douglas's stuff, if I did,”she said.

However, she agreed not to do anything about that till her own plans were more definite, and we turned to other matters.“I've got your brother's death certificate,”I said, and I was going on to tell her what I had done with it when she stopped me.

“What did Donald die of, Mr Strachan?”she asked.

I hesitated for a moment. I did not want to tell so young a woman the unpleasant story I had heard from Dr Ferris.“The cause of death was cholera,”I said at last.

She nodded, as if she had been expecting that.“Poor old boy,”she said softly.“Not a very nice way to die.”

I felt that I must say something to alleviate her distress.“I had a long talk with the doctor who attended him,”I told her.“He died quite peacefully, in his sleep.”

She stared at me.“Well then, it wasn't cholera,”she said.“That's not the way you die of cholera.”

I was a little at a loss in my endeavour to spare her unnecessary pain.“He had cholera first, but he recovered. The actual cause of death was probably heart failure, induced by the cholera.”

She considered this for a minute.“Did he have anything else?”she asked.

Well, then of course there was nothing for it but to tell her everything I knew. I was amazed at the matter-of-fact way in which she took the unpleasant details and at her knowledge of the treatment of such things as tropical ulcers, until I recollected that this girl had been a prisoner of the Japanese in Malaya, too.“Damn bad luck the ulcer didn't go a bit quicker,”she said coolly.“If there'd been an amputation they'd have had to evacuate him from the railway, and then he wouldn't have got the cerebral malaria or the cholera.”

“He must have had a wonderfully strong constitution to have survived so much,”I said.

“He hadn't,”she said positively.“Donald was always getting coughs and colds and things. What he had got was a wonderfully strong sense of humour. I always thought he'd come through, just because of that. Everything that happened to him was a joke.”

When I was a young man, girls didn't know about cholera or great ulcers, and I didn't quite know how to deal with her. I turned the conversation back to legal matters, where I was on firmer ground, and showed her how her case for probate was progressing. And presently I took her downstairs and we got a taxi and went over to the club to dine.

I had a reason for entertaining her, that first evening. It was obvious that I was going to have a good deal to do with this young woman in the next few years, and I wanted to find out about her. I knew practically nothing of her education or her background at that time; her knowledge of tropical diseases, for example, had already confused me. I wanted to give her a good dinner with a little wine and get her talking; it was going to make my job as trustee a great deal easier if I knew what her interests were, and how her mind worked. And so I took her to the Ladies Annexe at my club, a decent place where we could dine in our own time without music and talk quietly for a little time after dinner. I find that I get tired if there is a lot of noise and bustling about, as in a restaurant.

I showed her where she could go to wash and tidy up, and while she was doing that I ordered her a sherry. I got up from the table in the drawing-room when she came to me, and gave her a cigarette, and lit it for her.“What did you do over the weekend?”I asked as we sat down.“Did you go out and celebrate?”

She shook her head.“I didn't do anything very much. I'd arranged to meet one of the girls in the office for lunch on Saturday and to go and see the new Bette Davis film at the Curzon, so we did that.”

“Did you tell her about your good fortune?”

She shook her head.“I haven't told anybody.”She paused, and sipped her sherry; she was managing that and her cigarette quite nicely.“It seems such an improbably story,”she said, laughing.“I don't know that I really believe in it myself.”

I smiled with her.“Nothing is real till it happens,”I observed.“You'll believe that this is true when we send you the first cheque. It would be a great mistake to believe in it too hard before that happens.”

“I don't,”she laughed.“Except for one thing. I don't believe you'd be wasting so much time on my affairs unless there was something in it.”

“It's true enough for that.”I paused, and then I said,“Have you thought yet what you are going to do in a month or two when the income from the trust begins? Your monthly cheque, after the tax has been deducted, will be about seventy-five pounds. I take it that you will hardly wish to go on with your present employment when those cheques begin to come in?”

“No...”She sat staring for a minute at the smoke rising from her cigarette.“I don't want to stop working. I wouldn't mind a bit going on with Pack and Levy just as if nothing had happened, if it was a job worth doing,”she said.“But—well, it's not. We make ladies' shoes and handbags, Mr Strachan, and small ornamental attaché cases for the high-class trade—the sort that sells for thirty guineas in a Bond Street shop to stupid women with more money than sense. Fitted vanity cases in rare leathers, and all that sort of thing. It's all right if you've got to earn your living, working in that sort of place. And it's been interesting, too, learning all about that trade.”

“Most jobs are interesting when you are learning them,”I said.

She turned to me.“That's true. I've quite enjoyed my time there. But I couldn't go on now, with all this money. One ought to do something more worth while, but I don't know what.”She drank a little sherry.“I've got no profession, you see—only shorthand and typing, and a bit of book- keeping. I never had any real education—technical education, I mean. Taking a degree, or anything like that.”

I thought for a moment.“May I ask a very personal question, Miss Paget?”

“Of course.”

“Do you think it likely that you will marry in the near future?”

She smiled.“No, Mr Strachan, I don't think it's very likely that I shall marry at all. One can't say for certain, of course, but I don't think so.”

I nodded without comment.“Well then, had you thought about taking a university course?”

Her eyes opened wide.“No—I hadn't thought of that. I couldn't do it, Mr Strachan—I'm not clever enough. I couldn't get into a university.”She paused.“I was never higher than the middle of my class at school, and I never got into the Sixth.”

“It was just a thought,”I said.“I wondered if that might attract you.”

She shook her head.“I couldn't go back to school again now. I'm much too old.”

I smiled at her.“Not quite such an old woman as all that,”I observed.

For some reason the little compliment fell flat.“When I compare myself with some of the girls in the office,”she said quietly, and there was no laughter in her now,“I know I'm about seventy.”

I was finding out something about her now, but to ease the situation I suggested that we should go into dinner. When the ordering was done, I said,“Tell me what happened to you in the war. You were out in Malaya, weren't you?”

She nodded.“I had a job in an office, with the Kuala Perak Plantation Company. That was the company my father worked for, you know. Donald was with them, too.”

“What happened to you in the war?”I asked.“Were you a prisoner?”

“A sort of prisoner,”she said.

“In a camp?”

“No,”she replied.“They left us pretty free.”And then she changed the conversation very positively, and said,“What happened to you, Mr Strachan? Were you in London all the time?”

I could not press her to talk about her war experiences if she didn't want to, and so I told her about mine—such as they were. And from that, presently, I found myself telling her about my two sons, Harry on the China station and Martin in Basra, and their war records, and their families and children.“I'm a grandfather three times over,”I said ruefully.“There's going to be a fourth soon, I believe.”

She laughed.“What does it feel like?”

“Just like it did before,”I told her.“You don't feel any different as you get older. Only, you can't do so much.”

Presently I got the conversation back on to her own affairs. I pointed out to her what sort of life she would be able to lead upon nine hundred a year. As an instance, I told her that she could have a country cottage in Devonshire and a little car, and a daily maid, and still have money to spare for a moderate amount of foreign travel.“I wouldn't know what to do with myself unless I worked at something,”she said.“I've always worked at something, all my life.”

I knew of several charitable appeals who would have found a first-class shorthand typist, unpaid, a perfect god-send, and I told her so. She was inclined to be critical about those.“Surely, if a thing is really worth while, it'll pay,”she said. She evidently had quite a strong business instinct latent in her.“It wouldn't need to have an unpaid secretary.”

“Charitable organizations like to keep the overheads down,”I remarked.

“I shouldn't have thought organizations that haven't got enough margin to pay a secretary can possibly do very much good,”she said.“If I'm going to work at anything, I want it to be something really worth while.”

I told her about the almoner's job at a hospital, and she was very much interested in that.“That's much more like it, Mr Strachan,”she said.“I think that's the sort of job one might get stuck into and take really seriously. But I wish it hadn't got to do with sick people. Either you've got a mission for sick people or you haven't, and I think I'm one of the ones who hasn't. But it's worth thinking about.”

“Well, you can take your time,”I said.“You don't have to do anything in a hurry.”

She laughed at me.“I believe that's your guiding rule in life—never do anything in a hurry.”

I smiled.“You might have a worse rule than that.”

With the coffee after dinner I tried her out on the Arts. She knew nothing about music, except that she liked listening to the radio while she sewed. She knew nothing about literature, except that she liked novels with a happy ending. She liked paintings that were a reproduction of something that she knew, but she had never been to the Academy. She knew nothing whatsoever about sculpture. For a young woman with nine hundred a year, in London, she knew little of the arts and graces of social life, which seemed to me to be a pity.

“Would you like to come to the opera one night?”I asked.

She smiled.“Would I understand it?”

“Oh yes. I'll look and see what's on. I'll pick something light, and in English.”

She said,“It's terribly nice of you to ask me, but I'm sure you'd be much happier playing bridge.”

“Not a bit,”I said.“I haven't been to the opera or anything like that for years.”

She smiled.“Well, of course I'd love to come,”she said.“I've never seen an opera in my life. I don't even know what happens.”

We sat talking about these things for an hour or more, till it was half-past nine and she got up to go; she had three-quarters of an hour to travel out to her suburban lodgings. I went with her, because she was going from St James's Park station, and I didn't care about the thought of so young a woman walking across the park alone late at night. At the station, standing on the dark, wet pavement by the brightly lit canopy, she put out her hand.

“Thank you so much, Mr Strachan, for the dinner, and for everything you're doing for me,”she said.

“It has been a very great pleasure to me, Miss Paget,”I replied, and I meant it.

She hesitated, and then she said, smiling,“Mr Strachan, we're going to have a good deal to do with each other. My name is Jean. I'll go crackers if you keep on calling me Miss Paget.”

“You can't teach an old dog new tricks,”I said awkwardly.

She laughed.“You said just now you don't feel any different as you get older. You can try and learn.”

“I'll bear it in mind,”I said.“Sure you can manage all right now?”

“Of course. Goodnight, Mr Strachan.”

“Goodnight,”I said, lifting my hat and dodging the issue.“I'll let you know about the opera.”

In the following weeks while probate was being granted I took her to a good many things. We went together to the opera several times, to the Albert Hall on Sunday afternoons, and to art galleries and exhibitions of paintings. In return, she took me to the cinema once or twice. I cannot really say that she developed any very great artistic appreciation. She liked paintings more than concerts. If it had to be music she preferred it in the form of opera and the lighter the better; she liked to have something to look at while her ears were assailed. We went twice to Kew Garden as the spring came on. In the course of these excursions she came several times to my flat in Buckingham Gate; she got to know the kitchen, and made tea once or twice when we came in from some outing together. I had never entertained a lady in that flat before except my daughters-in-law, who sometimes come and use my spare room for a night or two in London.

Her business was concluded in March, and I was able to send her her first cheque. She did not give up her job at once, but continued to go to the office as usual. She wanted, very wisely, to build up a small reserve of capital from her monthly cheques before starting to live on them; moreover, at that time she had not made up her mind what she wanted to do.

That was the position one Sunday in April. I had arranged a little jaunt for her that day; she was to come to lunch at the flat and after that we were going down to Hampton Court, which she had never seen. I thought that the old palace and the spring flowers would please her, and I had been looking forward to this trip for several days. And then, of course, it rained.

She came to the flat just before lunch, dripping in her dark blue raincoat, carrying a very wet umbrella. I took the coat from her and hung it up in the kitchen. She went into my spare room and tidied herself; then she came to me in the lounge and we stood watching the rain beat against the Palace stables opposite; wondering what we should do instead that afternoon.

We had not got that settled when we sat down to coffee before the fire after lunch. I had mentioned one or two things but she seemed to be thinking about other matters. Over the coffee it came out, and she said,

“I've made up my mind what I want to do first of all, Mr Strachan.”

“Oh?”I asked.“What's that?”

She hesitated.“I know you're going to think this very odd. You may think it very foolish of me, to go spending money in this way. But—well, it's what I want to do. I think perhaps I'd better tell you about it now, before we go out.”

It was warm and comfortable before the fire. Outside the sky was dark, and the rain streamed down on the wet pavements.

“Of course, Jean,”I replied.“I don't suppose it's foolish at all. What is it that you want to do?”

She said,“I want to go back to Malaya, Mr Strachan. To dig a well.”

Chapter 2

I suppose there was a long pause after she said that. I remember being completely taken aback, and seeking refuge in my habit of saying nothing when you don't know what to say. She must have felt reproof in my silence, I suppose, because she leaned towards me, and she said,“I know it's a funny thing to want to do. May I tell you about it?”

I said,“Of course. Is this something to do with your experiences in the war?”

She nodded.“I've never told you about that. It's not that I mind talking about it, but I hardly ever think about it now. It all seems so remote, as if it was something that happened to another person, years ago—something that you'd read in a book. As if it wasn't me at all.”

“Isn't it better to leave it so?”

She shook her head.“Not now, now that I've got this money.”She paused.“You've been so very kind to me,”she said.“I do want to try and make you understand.”

Her life, she said, had fallen into three parts, the first two so separate from the rest that she could hardly reconcile them with her present self. First, she had been a schoolgirl living with her mother in Southampton. They lived in a small, three-bedroomed house in a suburban street. There had been a period before that when they had all lived in Malaya, but they had left Malaya for good when she was eleven and her brother Donald was fourteen, and she had only confused memories of that earlier time. Apparently Arthur Paget had been living alone in Malaya when he met his death, his wife having brought the children home.

They lived the life of normal suburban English children, school and holidays passing in a gentle rhythm with the one great annual excitement of three weeks holiday in August in the Isle of Wight, at Seaview or at Freshwater. One thing differentiated them slightly from other families, in that they all spoke Malay. The children had learned it from the amah, of course, and their mother encouraged them to continue talking it in England, first as a joke and as a secret family language, but later for a very definite reason. When Arthur Paget drove his car into the tree near Ipoh he was travelling on the business of his company, and his widow became entitled to a pension under the company scheme. He had been a competent and a valuable man. The directors of the Kuala Perak Plantation Company, linking compassion with their quest for first-class staff, wrote to the widow offering to keep a position for the boy Donald as soon as he became nineteen. This was a good opening and one that they all welcomed; it meant that Donald was headed for Malaya and for rubber-planting as a career. The Malay language became a matter of importance in giving him a good start, for very few boys of nineteen going to the East for their first job can speak an Oriental language. That shrewd Scotswoman, their mother, saw to it that the children did not forget Malay.

Jean had liked Southampton well enough, and she had had a happy childhood there in a gentle orbit of home, school, the Regal cinema, and the ice-skating rink. Of all these influences the one that she remembered best was the ice rink, connected in her mind inevitably with Waldteufel's Skaters Waltz.“It was a lovely place,”she said, staring reminiscently into the fire.“I suppose it wasn't much, really—it was a wooden building, I think, converted out of something that had been put up in the first war. We skated there about twice a week ever since I can remember, and it was always lovely. The music, and the clean, swift movement, and all the boys and girls. The coloured lights, the crowd, and the ring of skates. I got quite good at it. Mummy got me a costume—black tights and bodice, and a little short skirt, you know. Dancing was wonderful upon the ice...”

She turned to me.“You know, out in Malaya, when we were dying of malaria and dysentery, shivering with fever in the rain, with no clothes and no food and nowhere to go, because no one wanted us, I used to think about the rink at Southampton more than anything. It was a sort of symbol of the life that used to be—something to hold on to in one's mind.”She paused.“Directly I got back to England I went back to Southampton, as soon as I could—I had something or other to do down there, but really it was because all through those years I had promised myself that one day I would go back and skate there again. And it had been blitzed. It was just a blackened and a burnt-out shell—there's no rink in Southampton now. I stood there on the pavement with the taxi waiting behind me with my boots and skates in my hand, and I couldn't keep from crying with the disappointment. I don't know what the taxi-driver thought of me.”

Her brother had gone out to Malaya in 1937 when Jean was sixteen. She left school at the age of seventeen and went to a commercial college in Southampton, and emerged from it six months later with a diploma as a shorthand typist. She worked then for about a year in a solicitor's office in the town, but during this year a future for her in Malaya was taking shape. Her mother had kept in contact with the chairman of the Kuala Perak Plantation Company, and the chairman was very satisfied with the reports he had of Donald from the plantation manager. Unmarried girls were never very plentiful in Malaya; and when Mrs Paget approached the chairman with a proposal that he should find a job for Jean in the head office at Kuala Lumpur it was considered seriously. It was deemed undesirable by the Company that their manager should marry or contract liaisons with native women, and the obvious way to prevent it was to encourage unmarried girls to come out from England. Here was a girl who was not only of a family that they knew but who could also speak Malay, a rare accomplishment in a shorthand typist from England. So Jean got her job.

The war broke out while all this was in train, and to begin with, in England, this war was a phoney war. There seemed no reason to upset Jean's career for such a trivial matter; moreover in Mrs Paget's view Jean was much better in Malaya if war was to flare up in England. So Jean left for Malaya in the winter of 1939.

For over eighteen months she had a marvellous time. Her office was just round the corner from the Secretariat. The Secretariat is a huge building built in the more spacious days to demonstrate the power of the British Raj; it forms one side of a square facing the Club across the cricket ground, with a perfect example of an English village church to one side. Here everybody lived a very English life with tropical amenities; plenty of leisure, plenty of games, plenty of parties, plenty of dances, all made smooth and easy by plenty of servants. Jean boarded with one of the managers of the Company for the first few weeks; later she got a room in the Tudor Rose, a small private hotel run by an Englishwoman which was, in fact, more or less a chummery for unmarried girls employed in the offices and the Secretariat.

“It was just too good to be true,”she said.“There was a dance or a party every single night of the week. One had to cry off doing something in order to find time to write a letter home.”

When war came with Japan it hardly registered with her as any real danger, nor with any of her set. December the 7th, 1941, brought America into the war and so was a good thing; it meant nothing to the parties in Kuala Lumpur except that young men began to take leave from their work and to appear in uniform, itself a pleasurable excitement. Even when the Japanese landed in the north of Malaya there was little thought of danger in Kuala Lumpur; three hundred miles of mountain and jungle was itself a barrier against invasion from the north. The sinking of the Prince of Wales and the Repulse was a catastrophe that didn't mean a thing to a girl of nineteen who had just rejected her first proposal.

Soon the married women and the children were evacuated to Singapore, in theory at any rate. As the Japanese made headway down the peninsula with swift encirclements through the jungle that no troops had ever penetrated before, the situation began to appear serious. There came a morning when Jean's chief, a Mr Merriman, called her into the office and told her bluntly that the office was closing down. She was to pack a suitcase and go to the station and take the first train down to Singapore. He gave her the name of their representative at an address off Raffles Place, and told her to report there for a passage home. Five other girls employed in the office got the same orders.

The Japanese at that time were reported to be near Ipoh, about a hundred miles to the north.

The serious nature of the position was obvious to everyone by then. Jean went to the bank and drew out all her money, about six hundred Straits dollars. She did not go to the station, however; if she had, it is doubtful whether she would have been able to get down to Singapore because the line by that time was completely blocked with military traffic coming up to the Front. She might have got away by road. Instead of that, she went to Batu Tasik to see Mrs Holland.

Batu Tasik is a place about twenty miles north-west of Kuala Lumpur, and Mr Holland was a man of forty, the manager of an opencast tin mine. He lived in quite a pleasant bungalow beside the mine with his wife Eileen and their three children, Freddie aged seven, Jane aged four, and Robin, who was ten months old. Eileen Holland was a comfortable, motherly woman between thirty and thirty-five years old. The Hollands never went to parties or to dances; they were not that sort. They stayed quietly at home and let the world go by them. They had invited Jean to come and stay with them soon after she arrived, and she had found their company restful. She had been to see them several times after that, and once, when she had had a slight attack of dengue, she had spent a week with them recuperating. In Kuala Lumpur on the previous day she had heard that Mr Holland had brought his family into the station but had been unable to get them on the train, so they had all gone home again. Jean felt she could not leave without seeing the Hollands and offering her help with the children; Eileen Holland was a good mother and a first-rate housewife, but singularly unfitted to travel by herself with three children in the turmoil of evacuation.

Jean got to Batu Tasik fairly easily in a native bus; she arrived about lunch-time and she found Mrs Holland alone with the children. All trucks and cars belonging to the mine had been taken by the army, and the Hollands were left with their old Austin Twelve with one tyre worn down to the canvas and one very doubtful one with a large blister on the wall. This was the only vehicle that they now had for their evacuation, and it didn't look too good for taking the family to Singapore. Mr Holland had gone into Kuala Lumpur to get two new outer covers; he had gone in at dawn and Mrs Holland was already in a state of flutter that he had not come back.

In the bungalow everything was in confusion. The amah had gone home or had been given notice, and the house was full of suitcases half packed, or packed and opened again. Freddie had been in the pond and was all muddy, Jane was sitting on her pot amongst the suitcases, crying, and Mrs Holland was nursing the baby and directing the cooking of lunch and attending to Jane and worrying about her husband all at the same time. Jean turned to and cleaned up Freddie and attended to Jane, and presently they all had lunch together.

Bill Holland did not come till nearly sunset, and he came empty-handed. All tyre stocks in Kuala Lumpur had been commandeered. He found out, however, that a native bus was leaving for Singapore at eight that morning, and he had reserved seats for his family on that. He had had to walk the last five miles for lack of any other transport, and walking five miles down a tarmac road in the middle of the afternoon in the heat of the tropics is no joke; he was soaked to the skin and with a raging thirst, and utterly exhausted.

It would have been better if they had started for Kuala Lumpur that night, but they didn't. All movement on the roads at night was prohibited by the military, and to start out in the Austin in the dark would have been to risk a burst of fire from trigger-happy sentries. They decided to leave at dawn, which would give plenty of time to get to Kuala Lumpur before eight. Jean stayed the night with them in the bungalow, wakeful and uneasy. Once in the middle of the night she heard Bill Holland get up and go out into the veranda; peering out through her mosquito net she could see him standing motionless against the stars. She climbed out from under the net and slipped on her kimono; in Malaya one sleeps with very little on. She walked along the veranda to him.“What is it?”she whispered.

“Nothing,”he said.“Just thought I heard something, that's all.”

“Someone in the compound?”

“No—not that.”

“What?”

“I thought I heard guns firing, very far away,”he said.“Must have been fancy.”They stood tense and listening against the great noise of the crickets and the frogs.“God,”he said presently,“I wish it was dawn.”

They went back to bed. That night the Japanese advanced patrols infiltrated behind our forces lining the Bidor and penetrated as far as Slim River, less than fifty miles away.

They were all up before dawn and loading up the Austin with the first grey light; with three adults and three children and the luggage for all of them the Austin was well loaded down. Mr Holland paid the boys off and they started down the road for Kuala Lumpur, but before they had gone two miles the tyre that was showing canvas burst. There was a strained pause then while they worked to put the spare on, the one with the blister on the wall; this took them for another half mile only before going flat. In desperation Mr Holland went on on the rim; the wire wheel collapsed after another two miles, and the Austin had run to its end. They were then about fifteen miles from Kuala Lumpur, and it was half past seven.

Mr Holland left them with the car and hurried down the road to a plantation bungalow about a mile away; there was no transport there, and the manager had left the day before. He came back disappointed and anxious, to find the children fretful and his wife only concerned to get back to their bungalow. In the circumstances it seemed the best thing to do. Each of the adults took one child, and carrying it or leading it they set out to walk the five miles home again, leaving the luggage in the car, which they locked.

They reached home in the first heat of the day, utterly exhausted. After cold drinks from the refrigerator. they all lay down for a little to recover. An hour later they were roused by a truck stopping at the bungalow; a young officer came hurrying into the house.

“You've got to leave this place,”he said.“I'll take you in the truck. How many of you are there?”

Jean said,“Six, counting the children. Can you take us into Kuala Lumpur? Our car broke down.”

The officer laughed shortly.“No I can't. The Japs are at Kerling, or they were when I last heard. They may be further south by now.”Kerling was only twenty miles away.“I'm taking you to Panong. You'll get a boat from there to get you down to Singapore.”He refused to take the truck back for their luggage, probably rightly; it was already loaded with a number of families who had messed up their evacuation, and the Austin was five miles in the direction of the enemy.

Kuala means the mouth of a river, and Kuala Panong is a small town at the entrance to the Panong River. There is a District Commissioner stationed there. By the time the truck reached his office it was loaded with about forty men, women, and children picked up for forcible evacuation from the surrounding estates. Most of these were Englishwomen of relatively humble birth, the wives of foreman engineers at the tin mines or gangers on the railway. Few of them had been able to appreciate the swiftness and the danger of the Japanese advance. Plantation managers and those in the Secretariat and other Government positions had had better sources of information and more money to spend, and these had got their families away to Singapore in good time. Those who were left to be picked up by truck at the last moment were the least competent.

The truck halted at the DC's office and the subaltern went inside; the DC came out presently, a very worried man, and looked at the crowded women and children, and the few men amongst them.“Christ,”he said quietly as he realized the extent of the new responsibility.“Well, drive them to the accounts office over there; they must sit in the veranda for an hour or two and I'll try and get something fixed up for them. Tell them not to wander about too much.”He turned back into the office.“I can send them down in fishing-boats, I think,”he said.“There are some of those left. That's the best I can do. I haven't got a launch.”

The party were unloaded on to the veranda of the accounts office, and here they were able to stretch and sort themselves out a little. There were chatties of cold water in the office and the veranda was shady and cool. Jean and Bill Holland left Eileen sitting on the veranda with her back against the wall with the children about her, and walked into the village to buy what they could to replace the luggage they had lost. They were able to get a feeding-bottle for the baby, a little quinine, some salts for dysentery, and two tins of biscuits and three of tinned meat; they tried for mosquito nets, but they were all sold out. Jean got herself a few needles and thread, and seeing a large canvas haversack she bought that, too. She carried that haversack for the next three years.

They went back to the veranda about teatime and displayed their purchases, and had a little meal of biscuits and lemon squash.

Towards sunset the lighthouse-keepers at the river mouth telephoned to the DC that the Osprey was coming into the river. The Osprey was the customs launch that ran up and down the coast looking for smugglers from Sumatra across the Malacca Strait; she was a large Diesel-engined vessel about a hundred and thirty feet long, normally stationed at Penang; a powerful, seagoing ship. The DC's face lit up; here was the solution to his problems. Whatever was the mission of the Osprey she must take his evacuees on board, and run them down the coast out of harm's way. Presently he left his office, and walked down to the quay to meet the vessel as she berthed, to interview the captain.

She came round the bend in the river, and he saw that she was loaded with troops, small stocky men in grey-green uniforms with rifles and fixed bayonets taller than themselves. With a sick heart he watched her as she came alongside, realizing that this was the end of all his endeavour.

The Japanese came rushing ashore and arrested him immediately, and walked him back up the jetty to his office with guns at his back, ready to shoot him at the slightest show of resistance. But there were no troops there to resist; even the officer with the truck had driven off in an attempt to join his unit. The soldiers spread out and occupied the place without a shot; they came to the evacuees sitting numbly in the veranda of the accounts office. Immediately, with rifles and bayonets levelled, they were ordered to give up all fountain-pens and wristwatches and rings. Advised by their men folk, the women did so silently, and suffered no other molestation. Jean lost her watch and had her bag searched for a fountain-pen, but she had packed it in her luggage.

An officer came presently, when night had fallen, and inspected the crowd on the veranda in the light of a hurricane lamp; he walked down the veranda thrusting his lamp forward at each group, a couple of soldiers hard on his heels with rifles at the ready and bayonets fixed. Most of the children started crying. The inspection finished, he made a little speech in broken English.“Now you are prisoners,”he said.“You stay here tonight. Tomorrow you go to prisoner camp perhaps. You do good things, obedience to orders, you will receive good from Japanese soldiers. You do bad things, you will be shot directly. So, do good things always. When officer come, you stand up and bow, always. That is good thing. Now you sleep.”

One of the men asked,“May we have beds and mosquito nets?”

“Japanese soldiers have no beds, no mosquito nets. Perhaps tomorrow you have beds and nets.”

Another said,“Can we have some supper?”This had to be explained.“Food.”

“Tomorrow you have food.”The officer walked away, leaving two sentries on guard at each end of the veranda.

Kuala Panong lies in a marshy district of mangrove swamps at the entrance to a muddy river; the mosquitoes are intense. All night the children moaned and wailed fretfully, preventing what sleep might have been possible for the adults. The night passed slowly, wearily on the hard floor of the veranda; between the crushing misery of captivity and defeat and the torment of the mosquitoes few of the prisoners slept at all. Jean dozed a little in the early hours and woke stiff and aching and with swollen face and arms as a fresh outburst from the children heralded the more intense attack from the mosquitoes that comes in the hour before the dawn. When the first light came the prisoners were in a very unhappy state.

There was a latrine behind the accounts office, inadequate for the numbers that had to use it They made the best of that, and there was nothing then to do but to sit and wait for what would happen. Holland and Eileen made sandwiches for the children of tinned meat and sweet biscuits, and after this small breakfast they felt better. Many of the others had some small supplies of food, and those that had none were fed by those who had. Nothing was provided for the prisoners that morning by the Japanese.

In the middle of the morning an interrogation began. The prisoners were taken by families to the DC's office, where a Japanese captain, whom Jean was to know later as Captain Yoniata, sat with a lieutenant at his side, who made notes in a child's penny exercise book. Jean went in with the Hollands; when the captain enquired who she was she explained that she was a friend of the family travelling with them, and told him what her job was in Kuala Lumpur. It did not take very long. At the end the captain said,“Men go to prisoner camp today, womans and childs stay here. Men leave in afternoon, so you will now say farewell till this afternoon. Thank you.”

They had feared this, and had discussed it in the veranda, but they had not expected it would come so soon. Holland asked,“May we know where the women and children will be sent to? Where will their camp be?”

The officer said,“The Imperial Japanese Army do not make war on womans and on childs. Perhaps not go to camp at all, if they do good things, perhaps live in homes. Japanese soldiers always kind to womans and to childs.”

They went back to the veranda and discussed the position with the other families. There was nothing to be done about it, for it is usual in war for men to be interned in separate camps from women and children, but none the less it was hard to bear. Jean felt her presence was unwanted with the Holland family, and went and sat alone on the edge of the veranda, feeling hungry and wondering, with gloom tempered by the buoyancy of youth, what lay ahead of her. One thing was certain; if they were to spend another night upon the veranda she must get hold of some mosquito repellent. There was a chemist's shop just up the village that they had visited the afternoon before; it was probable that in such a district he had some repellent.

As an experiment she attracted the attention of the sentry and pointed to her mosquito bites; then she pointed to the village and got down from the veranda on to the ground. Immediately he brought his bayonet to the ready and advanced towards her; she got back on to the veranda in a hurry. That evidently wouldn't do. He scowled at her suspiciously, and went back to his position.

There was another way. The latrine was behind the building up against a wall; there was no sentry there because the wall prevented any exit from the accounts office except by going round the building to the front. She moved after a time and went out of the back door. Sheltered from the view of the sentries by the building, she looked around. There were some children playing in the middle distance.

She called softly in Malay,“Girl. You, you girl. Come here.”

The child came towards her; she was about twelve years old. Jean asked,“What is your name?”

She giggled shyly,“Halijah.”

Jean said,“Do you know the shop that sells medicine? Where a Chinese sells medicine?”

She nodded.“Chan Kok Fuan.”

Jean said,“Go to Chan Kok Fuan, and if you give my message to him so that he comes to me, I will give you ten cents. Say that the Mem has Nyamok bites”—she showed her bites—“and he should bring ointments to the veranda, and he will sell many to the Mems. Do this, and if he comes with ointments, I will give you ten cents.”

The child nodded and went off. Jean went back to the veranda and waited; presently the Chinaman appeared carrying a tray loaded with little tubes and pots. He approached the sentry and spoke to him, indicating his wish to sell his wares; after some hesitation the sentry agreed. Jean got six tubes of repellent and the rest was swiftly taken by the other women. Halijah got ten cents.

Presently a Japanese orderly brought two buckets of a thin fish soup and another half full of boiled rice, dirty and unappetizing. There were no bowls or utensils to eat with. There was nothing to be done but to eat as best they could; at that time they had not fallen into the prisoner's mode of life in which all food is strictly shared out and divided scrupulously, so that some got much more than others, who got little or none. There were still food supplies, however, so they fell back on the biscuits and the private stocks to supplement the ration.

That afternoon the men were separated from their families, and marched off under guard. Bill Holland turned from his fat, motherly wife, his eyes moist“Goodbye, Jean,”he said heavily.“Good luck.”And then he said,“Stick with them, if you can, won't you?”

She nodded.“I'll do that. We'll all be in the same camp together.”

The men were formed up together, seven of them, and marched off under guard.

The party then consisted of eleven married women, and two girls, Jean and an anaemic girl called Ellen Forbes who had been living with one of the families; she had come out to be married, but it hadn't worked out. Besides these there were nineteen children varying in age from a girl of fourteen to babies in arms; thirty-two persons in all. Most of the women could speak no language but their own; a few of them, including Eileen Holland, could speak enough Malay to control their servants, but no more.

They stayed in the accounts office for forty-one days.

The second night was similar to the first, except that the doors of the offices were opened for them and they were allowed to use the rooms. A second meal of fish soup was given to them in the evening, but nothing else whatever was provided for their use—no beds, no blankets, and no nets. Some of the women had their luggage with them and had blankets, but there were far too few to go round. A stern-faced woman, Mrs Horsefall, asked to see the officer; when Captain Yoniata came she protested at the conditions and asked for beds and nets.

“No nets, no beds,”he said.“Very sorry for you. Japanese womans sleep on mat on floor. All Japanese sleep on mat. You put away proud thoughts, very bad thing. You sleep on mat like Japanese womans.”

“But we're English,”she said indignantly.“We don't sleep on the floor like animals!”

His eyes hardened; he motioned to the sentries, who gripped her by each arm. Then he hit her four stinging blows upon the face with the flat of his hand.“Very bad thoughts,”he said, and turned upon his heel, and left them. No more was said about beds.

He came to inspect them the next morning and Mrs Horsefall, undaunted, asked for a water supply; she pointed out that washing was necessary for the babies and desirable for everyone. A barrel was brought into the smallest office that afternoon and was kept filled by coolies; they turned this room into a bathroom and washhouse. In those early days most of the women had money, and following the example of Chan Kok Fuan the shopkeepers of the village came to sell to the prisoners, so they accumulated the bare essentials for existence.

Gradually they grew accustomed to their hardships. The children quickly learned to sleep upon the floor without complaint; the younger women took a good deal longer, and the women over thirty seldom slept for more than half an hour without waking in pain—but they did sleep. It was explained to them by Captain Yoniata that until the campaign was over the victorious Japanese had no time to construct prison camps for women. When all Malaya had been conquered they would be moved into a commodious and beautiful camp which would be built for them in the Cameron Highlands, a noted health resort up in the hills. There they would find beds and mosquito nets and all the amenities to which they were accustomed, but to earn these delights they must stay where they were and do good things. Doing good things meant getting up and bowing whenever he approached. After a few faces had been slapped and shins had been kicked by Captain Yoniata's army boots, they learned to do this good thing.

The food issued to them was the bare minimum that would support life, and was an unvarying issue of fish soup and rice, given to them twice a day. Complaint was useless and even dangerous; in the view of Captain Yoniata these were proud thoughts that had to be checked for the moral good of the complainant. Meals, however, could be supplied by a small Chinese restaurant in the village, and while money was available most of the families ordered one cooked meal a day from this restaurant.

They received no medical attention and no drugs whatsoever. At the end of a week dysentery attacked them, and the nights were made hideous by screaming children stumbling with their mothers to the latrine. Malaria was always in the background, held in check by the quinine that they could still buy from Chan Kok Fuan at an ever increasing price. To check the dysentery Captain Yoniata reduced the soup and increased the rice ration, adding to the rice some of the dried, putrescent fish that had formerly made the soup. Later, he added to the diet a bucket of tea in the afternoon, as a concession to English manners.

Through all this time, Jean shared with Mrs Holland the care of the three Holland children. She suffered a great deal from weakness and a feeling of lassitude induced, no doubt, by the change in diet, but she slept soundly most nights until wakened, which was frequently. Eileen Holland suffered much more. She was older, and could not sleep so readily upon the floor, and she had lost much of the resilience of her youth. She lost weight rapidly.

On the thirty-fifth day, Esmé Harrison died.

Esmé was a child of eight. She had had dysentery for some time and was growing very thin and weak; she slept little and cried a great deal. Presently she got fever, and for two days ran a temperature of a hundred and four as the malaria rose in her. Mrs Horsefall told Captain Yoniata that the child must see a doctor and go to hospital. He said he was very sorry, but there was no hospital. He would try and get a doctor, but the doctors were all fighting with the victorious army of the Emperor. That evening Esmé entered on a series of convulsions, and shortly before dawn she died.

She was buried that morning in the Moslem cemetery behind the village; her mother and one other woman were allowed to attend the burial. They read a little of the service out of a prayer book before the uncomprehending soldiers and Malays, and then it was over. Life went on as before in the accounts office, but the children now had nightmares of death to follow them to sleep.

At the end of six weeks Captain Yoniata faced them after the morning inspection. The women stood worn and draggled in the shade of the veranda facing him, holding the children by the hand. Many of the adults, and most of the children, by that time were thin and ill.

He said,“Ladies, the Imperial Japanese Army has entered Singapore, and all Malaya is free. Now prisoner camps are being built for men and also for womans and childs. Prisoner camps are at Singapore and you go there. I am very sad your life here has been uncomfortable, but now will be better. Tomorrow you start to Kuala Lumpur, not more than you can go each day. From Kuala Lumpur you go by train to Singapore, I think. In Singapore you will be very happy. Thank you.”

From Panong to Kuala Lumpur is forty-seven miles; it took a minute for his meaning to sink in. Then Mrs Horsefall said,“How are we to travel to Kuala Lumpur? Will there be a truck?”

He said,“Very sorry, no truck. You walk, easy journeys, not more than you can go each day. Japanese soldier help you.”

She said,“We can't walk, with these children. We must have a truck.”

These were bad thoughts, and his eyes hardened.“You walk,”he repeated.

“But what are we to do with all the luggage?”

He said,“You carry what you can. Presently the luggage is sent after you.”He turned, and went away.

For the remainder of the day they sat in stunned desperation; those who had luggage sorted hopelessly through their things, trying to make packs that would hold the essentials and yet which would not be too heavy. Mrs Horsefall, who had been a schoolmistress in her time and had assumed the position of leader, moved among them, helping and advising. She had one child herself, a boy of ten called John; her own position was better than most, for it was possible for a woman to carry the necessities for one boy of that age. The position of the mothers with several younger children was bad indeed.

Jean and Mrs Holland had less of a problem, for having lost their luggage they had less to start with and the problem of selection did not arise. They had few clothes to change into, and what they had could easily go into Jean's haversack. They had acquired two blankets and three food bowls between them, and three spoons, and a knife and fork; they decided to make a bundle of these small possessions in the blankets, and they had a piece of cord to tie the bundle with and to make a sling, so that one could carry the haversack and one the bundle. Their biggest problem was their shoes, which had once been fashionable and were quite unsuitable for marching in.

Towards evening, when the children had left them and they were alone with the baby in a corner, Mrs Holland said quietly,“My dear, I shan't give up, but I don't think I can walk very far. I've been so poorly lately.”

Jean said,“It'll be all right,”although deep in her mind she knew that it was not going to be all right at all.“You're much fitter than some of the others,”and this possibly was true.“We'll have to take it very slowly, because of the children. We'll take several days over it.”

“I know, my dear. But where are we going to stay at night? What are they going to do about that?”

Nobody had an answer to that one.

Rice came to them soon after dawn, and at about eight o'clock Captain Yoniata appeared with four soldiers, who were to be their guard upon the journey.“Today you walk to Ayer Penchis,”he said.“Fine day, easy journey. Good dinner when you get to Ayer Penchis. You will be very happy.”

Jean asked Mrs Horsefall,“How far is Ayer Penchis?”

“Twelve or fifteen miles, I should think. Some of us will never get that far.”

Jean said,“We'd better do what the soldiers do, have a rest every hour. Hadn't we?”

“If they'll let us.”

It took an hour to get the last child out of the latrine and get the women ready for the march. The guards squatted on their heels; it was a small matter to them when the march started. Finally Captain Yoniata appeared again, his eyes hard and angry.“You walk now,”he said.“Womans remaining here are beaten, beaten very bad. You do good thing and be happy. Walk now.”

There was nothing for it but to start. They formed into a little group and walked down the tarmac road in the hot sun, seeking the shade of trees wherever they occurred. Jean walked with Mrs Holland carrying the bundle of blankets slung across her shoulders as the hottest and the heaviest load, and leading the four-year-old Jane by the hand. Seven-year-old Freddie walked beside his mother, who carried the baby, Robin, and the haversack. Ahead of them strolled the Japanese sergeant; behind came the three privates.

The women went very slowly, with frequent halts as a mother and child retired into the bushes by the roadside. There was no question of walking continuously for an hour and then resting; the dysentery saw to that. For those who were not afflicted at the moment the journey became one of endless, wearisome waits by the roadside in the hot sun, for the sergeant refused to allow the party to move on while any remained behind. Within the limits of their duty the Japanese soldiers were humane and helpful; before many hours had passed each was carrying a child.

Slowly the day wore on. The sergeant made it very clear at an early stage that there would be no food and no shelter for the party till they got to Ayer Penchis, and it seemed to be a matter of indifference to him how long they took to get there. They seldom covered more than a mile and a half in the hour, on that first day. As the day went on they all began to suffer from their feet, the older women especially. Their shoes were quite unsuitable for walking long distances, and the heat of the tarmac swelled their feet, so that before long many of them were limping with foot pains. Some of the children went barefoot and got along very well. Jean watched them for a time, then stooped and took her own shoes off, savouring the unaccustomed road surface gingerly with her bare feet. She walked on carrying her shoes, picking her way with her eyes upon the ground, and her feet ceased to pain her though from time to time the tarmac grits hurt her soft soles. She got along better barefoot, but Eileen Holland refused to try it.

They stumbled into Ayer Penchis at about six o'clock that evening, shortly before dark. This place was a Malay village which housed the labour for a number of rubber plantations in the vicinity. The latex-processing plant of one stood near at hand and by it was a sort of palm thatch barn, used normally for smoking sheets of the raw rubber hung on horizontal laths. It was empty now and the women were herded into this. They sank down wearily in a stupor of fatigue; presently the soldiers brought a bucket of tea and a bucket of rice and dried fish. Most of them drank cup after cup of the tea, but few had any appetite for the food.

With the last of the light Jean strolled outside and looked around. The guards were busy cooking over a small fire; she approached the sergeant and asked if she might go into the village. He understood that, and nodded; away from Captain Yoniata discipline was lax.

In the village she found one or two small shops, selling clothes, sweets, cigarettes, and fruit. She saw mangoes for sale, and bought a dozen, chaffering over the price with the Malay woman to conserve her slender cash. She ate one at once and felt better for it; at Kuala Panong they had eaten little fruit. She went back to the barn and found that the soldiers had provided one small lamp with an open wick fed by coconut oil.

She distributed her mangoes to Eileen and the Holland children and to others, and found they were a great success. Armed with money from the women she went down to the village again and got four dozen more, and presently all the women and children were in mango up to their ears. The soldiers came in with another bucket of tea and got a mango each for their pains, and so refreshed the women were able to eat most of the rice. Presently, they slept, exhausted, weak, and ill.

The barn was full of rats, which ran over them and round them all night through. In the morning it was found that several of the children had been bitten.

They woke aching in new places with the stiffness and fatigue of the day before; it did not seem possible that they could march again. The sergeant drove them on; this time the stage was to a place called Asahan. It was a shorter stage than the day before, about ten miles, and it had need to be, because they took as long getting to it. This time the delay was chiefly due to Mrs Collard. She was a heavy woman of about forty-five with two children, Harry and Ben, aged about ten and seven. She had suffered from both malaria and dysentery at Panong, and she was now very weak; she had to stop and rest every ten minutes, and when she stopped they all stopped since the sergeant would not allow them to separate. She was relieved of all load and the younger women took turns to walk by her and help her along.

By the afternoon she had visibly changed colour; her somewhat ruddy face had now gone a mottled blue, and she was complaining constantly of pains in her chest. When they finally reached Asahan she was practically incapable of walking alone. Their accommodation was another rubber-curing barn. They half carried Mrs Collard into it and sat her up against the wall, for she said that lying down hurt her, and she could not breathe. Somebody went to fetch some water, and bathed her face, and she said,“Thank you, dearie. Give some of that to Harry and Ben, there's a dear.”The woman took the children outside to wash them, and when she came back Mrs Collard had fallen over on her side, and was unconscious. Half an hour later she died.

That evening Jean got more fruit for them, mangoes and bananas, and some sweets for the children. The Malay woman who supplied the sweets refused to take money for them.“No, mem,”she said.“It is bad that Nippon soldiers treat you so. This is our gift.”Jean went back to the barn and told the others what had happened, and it helped.

In the flickering light of the cooking fire outside the barn Mrs Horsefall and Jean held a conference with the sergeant, who spoke only a very few words of English. They illustrated their meaning with pantomime.“Not walk tomorrow,”they said.“No. Not walk. Rest—sleep—tomorrow. Walk tomorrow, more women die. Rest tomorrow. Walk one day, rest one day.”

They could not make out if he understood or not.“Tomorrow,”he said,“woman in earth.”

It would be necessary to bury Mrs Collard in the morning. This would prevent an early start, and would make a ten-mile stage almost impossible. They seized upon this as an excuse.“Tomorrow bury woman in earth,”they said.“Stay here tomorrow.”

They had to leave it so, uncertain whether he understood or not; he squatted down on his heels before the fire with the three privates. Later he came to Jean, his face alight with intelligence.“Walk one day, sleep one day,”he said.“Womans not die.”He nodded vigorously, and she called Mrs Horsefall, and they all nodded vigorously together, beaming with good nature. They were all so pleased with each other and with the diplomatic victory that they gave him a banana as a token of esteem.

All that day Jean had walked barefoot; she had stubbed her toes two or three times and had broken her toenails; but she felt fresher that evening than she had felt for a long time. The effect of the march upon the women began to show itself that night in very different forms, according to their age. The women under thirty, and the children, were in most cases actually in better condition than when they left Panong; they were cheered by the easier discipline, and stimulated by the exercise and by the improvement in the diet brought by fruit and sweets. The older women were in much worse case. For them exhaustion outweighed these benefits; they lay or sat listlessly in the darkness, plagued by their children and too tired to eat. In many cases they were too tired even to sleep.

In the morning they buried Mrs Collard. There was no burial ground at hand but the Malay headman showed them where they could dig the grave, in a corner of the compound, near a rubbish heap. The sergeant got two coolies and they dug a shallow grave; they lowered Mrs Collard into it covered by a blanket, and Mrs Horsefall read a little out of the Prayer Book. Then they took away the blanket because they could not spare that, and the earth was filled in. Jean found a carpenter who nailed a little wooden cross together for them, and refused payment; he was a Moslem or perhaps merely an animist, but he knew what the Tuans did for a Christian burial. They wrote JULIA COLLARD on it and the date of death with an indelible pencil, hoping it would survive the rain, and then they had a long discussion over the text to put underneath it. This interested every woman in the party, and kept them happy and mentally stimulated for half an hour. Mrs Holland, rather surprisingly, suggested Romans, xiv, 4;“Who art thou that judgest another man's servant? to his own master he standeth or falleth”, meaning the sergeant who had made them march that day. But the other women did not care for that, and finally they compromised on“Peace, perfect peace, with loved ones far away”. That pleased everybody.

They sat around and washed their clothes after the burial was over. Soap was getting very scarce amongst them, but so was money. Mrs Horsefall held a sort of meeting after rice and examined the money situation; half the women had no money left at all, and the rest had only about fifteen dollars between them. She suggested pooling this, but the mothers who had money left preferred to keep it for their own children; as there was so little in any case it did not seem worth while to worry them by making an issue of it. They all agreed, however, to share rations equally, and after that their feeding times were much better organized.

Captain Yoniata turned up about midday, driving into Kuala Lumpur in the District Commissioner's car. He stopped and got out, angry to find that they were not upon the road. He abused the sergeant for some minutes in Japanese; the man stood stiffly to attention, not saying a word in explanation or defence. Then he turned to the women.“Why you not walk?”he demanded angrily.“Very bad thing. You not walk, no food.”

Mrs Horsefall faced him.“Mrs Collard died last night. We buried her this morning over there. If you make us walk every day like this, we shall all die. These women aren't fit to march at all. You know that.”

“What woman die of?”he inquired.“What illness?”

“She had dysentery and malaria, as most of us have had. She died of exhaustion after yesterday's march. You'd better come inside and look at Mrs Frith and Judy Thomson. They couldn't possibly have marched today.”

He walked into the barn, and stood looking at two or three women sitting listless in the semi-darkness. Then he said something to the sergeant and walked back to his car. At the door he turned to Mrs Horsefall.“Very sad woman die,”he said.“Perhaps I get a truck in Kuala Lumpur. I will ask.”He got into the car and drove away.

His words went round the women quickly; he had gone to get a truck for them, and they would finish the journey to Kuala Lumpur by truck; there would be no more marching. Things weren't so bad, after all. They would be sent by rail from Kuala Lumpur to Singapore, and there they would be put into a proper camp with other Englishwomen, where they could settle down and organize their lives properly, and get into a routine that would enable them to look after the children. A prison camp would have a doctor, too, and there was always some kind of a hospital for those who were really ill. They became much more cheerful, and the most listless ones revived, and came out and washed and made themselves a little more presentable. Their appearance was a great concern to them that afternoon. Kuala Lumpur was their shopping town where people knew them; they must get tidy before the truck came for them.

Captain Yoniata appeared again about an hour before sunset; again he spoke to the sergeant, who saluted. Then he turned to the women.“You not go to Kuala Lumpur,”he said.“You go to Port Swettenham. English destroy bridges, so railway to Singapore no good. You go to Port Swettenham now, and then ship to Singapore. ”

There was a stunned silence. Then Mrs Horsefall asked,“Is there going to be a truck to take us to Port Swettenham?”

He said,“Very sorry no truck. You walk slow, easy stages. Two days, three days, you walk to Port Swettenham. Then ship take you to Singapore.”

From Asahan to Port Swettenham is about thirty miles. She said,“Captain Yoniata, please be reasonable. Many of us are quite unfit to walk any further. Can't you get some transport for the children, anyway?”

He said,“English womans have proud thoughts, always. Too good to walk like Japanese womans. Tomorrow you walk to Bakri.”He got into his car and went away; that was the last they ever saw of him.

Bakri is eleven miles in the general direction of Port Swettenham. The change in programme was the deepest disappointment to them, the more so as it showed irresolution in their destiny. Mrs Holland said despairingly,“I don't see why he shouldn't have known at Panong that the bridges were down, and not sent us to Kuala Lumpur at all. It makes one wonder if there's going to be a ship when we get to Port Swettenham....”

There was nothing for it, and next morning they started on the road again. They found that two of the privates had been taken away, and one remained to guard them, with the sergeant. This was of no consequence to their security because they had no desire to attempt to escape, but it reduced by half the help the guards had given them in carrying the younger children, so that it threw an extra burden on the mothers.

That day for the first time Jean carried the baby, Robin: Mrs Holland was walking so badly that she had to be relieved. She still carried the haversack and looked after Freddie, but Jean carried the bundle of blankets and small articles, and the baby, and led Jane by the hand. She went barefoot as before; after some experiments she found that the easiest way to carry the baby was to perch him on her hip, as the Malay women did.

The baby, curiously, gave them the least anxiety of any of the children. They fed it on rice and gravy from the fish soup or stew, and it did well. Once in the six weeks it had seemed to be developing dysentery and they had given it a tiny dose or two of Glauber's salt, and it recovered. Mosquitoes never seemed to worry it, and it had not had fever. The other children were less fortunate. Both had had dysentery from time to time, and though they seemed now to be free of it they had gone very thin.

They slept that night in the bungalow that had belonged to the manager of the Bakri tin mine, an Englishman. In the seven or eight weeks since he had abandoned it it had been occupied by troops of both sides and looted by the Malays; now little remained of it but the bare walls. Marvellously, however, the bath was still in order though filthily dirty, and there was a store of cut wood for the furnace that heated water. The sergeant, true to his promise, allowed them a day of rest here, and they made the most of the hot water for washing their clothes and themselves. With the small improvement in conditions their spirits revived.

“I should think there'd be hot water on the ship,”said Mrs Holland.“There usually is, isn't there?”

They marched again next day to a place called Dilit; this was mostly a day spent marching down cart tracks in the rubber plantations. The tracks were mostly in the shade of the trees and this made it pleasant for them, and even the older women found the day bearable. They had some difficulty in finding the way. The sergeant spoke little Malay and had difficulty in understanding the Malay women latex-tappers that he asked for directions from time to time. Jean found that she could understand the answers that the women gave, and could converse with them, but having got the directions they required she had some difficulty in making the sergeant understand. They reached an agreement by the end of the day that she should talk to the women, who talked to her less shyly in any case, and she developed a sign language which the sergeant understood. From that time onwards Jean was largely responsible for finding the shortest way for the party to go.

In the middle of the afternoon Ben Collard, the younger son of Mrs Collard who had died, trod on something while walking barefoot in the grass that bit him with poison fangs and got away. He said afterwards that it looked like a big beetle; possibly it was a scorpion. Mrs Horsefall took charge and laid him on the ground and sucked the wound to draw the poison from it, but the foot swelled quickly and the inflammation travelled up the leg to the knee. It was obviously painful and he cried a great deal. There was nothing to be done but carry him, and this was no easy matter for the women in their feeble condition because he was a boy of seven and weighed five stone. Mrs Horsefall carried him for an hour and after that the sergeant took him and carried him the rest of the way. By the time they got to Dilit the ankle was enormous and the knee was stiff.

At Dilit there was no accommodation for them and no food. The place was a typical Malay village, the houses built of wood and palm thatch raised about four feet from the ground on posts, leaving a space beneath where dogs slept and fowls nested. They stood or sat wearily while the sergeant negotiated with the Malay headman: very soon he called for Jean, and she joined the tri-lingual discussion. The village had rice and could prepare a meal for them, but the headman wanted payment, and was only with difficulty induced to agree to provide rice for so many on the word of the sergeant that they would be paid some day. As regards accommodation he said flatly that there was none, and the party must sleep under the houses with the dogs and poultry; later he agreed to move the people from one house, so that the thirty prisoners had a roof to sleep under on a floor about fifteen feet square.

Jean secured a corner for their party, and Eileen Holland settled into it with the children and the baby. A few feet from them Mrs Horsefall was working on Ben Collard. Somebody had some permanganate crystals and someone else an old razor blade; with this they cut the wound open a little, in spite of the child's screams, and put in crystals and bound it up; then they applied hot fomentations. There was nothing Jean could do, and she wandered outside.

There was a sort of village kitchen, and here the Japanese private was superintending the activities of women of the village who were preparing rice. At a house nearby the headman was sitting at the head of the steps leading up to his house, squatting on his heels and smoking a long pipe: he was a grey-haired old man wearing a sarong and what once had been a khaki drill jacket. Jean crossed to him and said rather shyly in Malay,“I am sorry we have been forced to come here, and have made trouble for you.”

He stood up and bowed to the Mem.“It it no trouble,”he said.“We are sorry to see Mems in such a state. Have you come far?”

She said,“From Bakri today.”

He made her come up into the house: there was no chair and she sat with him on the floor at the doorless entrance. He asked their history, and she told him what had happened, and he grunted. Presently the wife came from within the house bearing two cups of coffee without sugar or milk; Jean thanked her in Malay, and she smiled shyly, and withdrew into the house again.

Presently the headman said,“The Short One”—he meant the Japanese sergeant—“says you must stay here tomorrow.”

Jean said,“We are too weak to march each day. The Japanese allow us to rest a day between each day of marching. If we may stay here tomorrow it will help us a great deal. The sergeant says he can get money for the food.”

“The Short Ones never pay for food,”the headman said.“Neverthe-less you shall stay.”

She said,“I can do nothing but thank you.”

He raised his grey old head.“It is written in the Fourth Surah, ‘Men's souls are naturally inclined to covetousness; but if ye be kind towards women and fear to wrong them, God is well acquainted with what ye do’.”

She sat with the old man till rice was ready; then she left him and went to her meal. The other women looked at her curiously.“I saw you sitting with the headman, chatting away,”said one.“Just as if you were old chums.”

Jean smiled.“He gave me a cup of coffee.”

“Just fancy that! There's something in knowing how to talk to them in their own language, isn't there? What did he talk about?”

Jean thought for a minute.“This and that—about our journey. He talked about God a little.”

The women stared at her.“You mean, his own God? Not the real God?”

“He didn't differentiate,”Jean said.“Just God.”

They rested all next day and then marched to Klang, three or four miles outside Port Swettenham. Little Ben Collard was neither better nor worse: the leg was very much swollen. The chief trouble with him now was physical weakness: he had eaten nothing since the injury for nothing would stay down, and none of the children by that time had any reserves of strength. The headman directed the villagers to make a litter for him in the form of a stretcher of two long bamboo poles with spreaders and a woven palm mat between and they put him upon this and took turns at carrying it.

They got to Klang that afternoon, and here there was an empty schoolhouse: the sergeant put them into this and went off to a Japanese encampment near at hand, to report and to arrange rations for them.

Presently an officer arrived to inspect them, marching at the head of a guard of six soldiers. This officer, whom they came to know as Major Nemu, spoke good English. He said,“Who are you people? What do you want here?”

They stared at him. Mrs Horsefall said,“We are prisoners, from Panong. We are on our way to the prisoner-of-war camp in Singapore. Captain Yoniata in Panong sent us here under guard, to be put on a ship to Singapore.”

“There are no ships here,”he said.“You should have stayed in Panong.”

It was no good arguing, nor had they the energy.“We were sent here,”she repeated dully.

“They had no right to send you here,”he said angrily.“There is no prison camp here.”

There was a long, awkward silence: the women stared at him in blank despair. Mrs Horsefall summoned up her flagging energy again.“May we see a doctor?”she asked.“Some of us are very ill—one child especially. One woman died upon the way.

“What did she die of?”he asked quickly.“Plague?”

“Nothing infectious. She died of exhaustion.”

“I will send a doctor to examine you all. You will stay here for tonight, but you cannot stay for long. I have not got sufficient rations for my own command, let alone feeding prisoners.”He turned and walked back to the camp.

A new guard was placed upon the schoolhouse: they never saw the friendly sergeant or the private again. Presumably they were sent back to Panong. A Japanese doctor, very young, came to them within an hour; he had them all up one by one and examined them for infectious disease. Then he was about to take his departure, but they made him stay and look at little Ben Collard's leg. He ordered them to continue with the hot fomentations. When they asked if he could not be taken into hospital he shrugged his shoulders and said,“I inquire.”

They stayed in that schoolhouse under guard, day after day. On the third day they sent for the doctor again, for Ben Collard was obviously worse. Reluctantly the doctor ordered his removal to the hospital in a truck. On the sixth day they heard that he had died.

Jean Paget crouched down on the floor beside the fire in my sitting-room; outside a change of wind had brought the London rain beating against the window.

“People who spent the war in prison camps have written a lot of books about what a bad time they had,”she said quietly, staring into the embers.“They don't know what it was like, not being in a camp.”

Chapter 3

They stayed in Klang eleven days, not knowing what was to become of them. The food was bad and insufficient, and there were no shops in the vicinity: if there had been shops they could not have done much with them, because their money was now practically gone. On the twelfth day Major Nemu paraded them at half an hour's notice, allocated one corporal to look after them, and told them to walk to Port Dickson. He said that there might be a ship there to take them down to Singapore; if there was not they would be walking in the general direction of the prison camps.

That was about the middle of March 1942. From Klang to Port Dickson is about fifty miles, but by this time they were travelling more slowly than ever. It took them till the end of the month; they had to wait several days in one village because Mrs Horsefall went down with malaria and ran a temperature of a hundred and five for some time. She recovered and was walking, or rather tottering, within a week, but she never recovered her vigour and from that time onwards the leadership fell more and more upon Jean's shoulders.

By the time they reached Port Dickson their clothes were in a deplorable condition. Very few of the women had a change of any sort, because burdens had been reduced to an absolute minimum. Jean and Mrs Holland had nothing but the thin cotton frocks that they had worn since they were taken; these were now torn and ragged from washing. Jean had gone barefoot since the early stages of the march and intended to go on without shoes: she now took another step towards the costume of the Malay woman. She sold a little brooch for thirteen dollars to an Indian jeweller in Salak, and with two of the precious dollars she bought a cheap sarong.

A sarong is a skirt made of a tube of cloth about three feet in diameter; you get into it and wrap it round your waist like a towel; the surplus material falling into pleats that permit free movement. When you sleep you undo the roll around your waist and it then lies over you as a loose covering that you cannot roll out of. It is the lightest and coolest of all garments for the tropics, and the most practical, being simple to make and to wash. For a top, she cut down her cotton frock into a sort of tunic which got rid of the most tattered part, the skirt, and from that time she was cooler and more at ease than any of them. At first the other women strongly disapproved of this descent to native dress: later most of them followed her example as their clothes became worn out.

There was no haven for them at Port Dickson, and no ship. They were allowed to stay there, living under desultory guard in a copra barn, for about ten days; the Japanese commander then decided that they were a nuisance, and put them on the road to Seremban. He reasoned, apparently, that they were not his prisoners and so not his responsibility; it was the duty of those who had captured them to put them into a camp. His obvious course was to get rid of them and get them out of his area before, by their continued presence, they forced him to divert food and troops and medical supplies from the Imperial Japanese Army to sustain them.

At Siliau, between Port Dickson and Seremban, tragedy touched the Holland family, because Jane died. They had stayed for their day of rest in a rubber-smoking shed: she had developed fever during the day's march and one of the two Japanese guards they had at that time had carried her for much of the day. Their thermometer had been broken in an accident a few days before and they had now no means of telling the temperature of malaria patients, but she was very hot. They had a little quinine left and tried to give it to her, but they could not get her to take much of it till she grew too weak to resist, and then it was too late. They persuaded the Japanese sergeant to allow them to stay at Siliau rather than to risk moving the child, and Jean and Eileen Holland stayed up with her, sleepless, fighting for her life in that dim, smelly place where the rats scurried round at night and hens walked in and out by day. On the evening of the second day she died.

Mrs Holland stood it far better than Jean had expected that she would.“It's God's will, my dear,”she said quietly,“and He'll give her Daddy strength to bear it when he hears, just as He's giving us all strength to bear our trials now.”She stood dry-eyed beside the little grave, and helped to make the little wooden cross. Dry-eyed she picked the text for the cross:“Suffer little children to come unto Me”. She said quietly,“I think her Daddy would like that one.”

Jean woke that night in the darkness, and heard her weeping.

Through all this the baby, Robin, throve. It was entirely fortuitous that he ate and drank nothing but food that had been recently boiled; living on rice and soup, that happened automatically, but may have explained his relative freedom from stomach disorders. Jean carried him every day, and her own health was definitely better than when they had left Panong. She had had five days of fever at Klang, but dysentery had not troubled her for some time, and she was eating well. With the continual exposure to the sun she was getting very brown, and the baby that she carried on her hip got browner.

Seremban lies on the railway, and they had hoped that when they got there there would be a train down to Singapore. They got to Seremban about the middle of April, but there was no train for them; the railway was running in a limited fashion but probably not through to Singapore. Before very long they were put upon the road to Tampin, but not till they had lost another member of the party.

Ellen Forbes was the unmarried girl who had come out to get married and hadn't, a circumstance that Jean could well understand by the time she had lived in close contact with her for a couple of months. Ellen was a vacuous, undisciplined girl, good humoured, and much too free with Japanese troops for the liking of the other women. At Seremban they were accommodated in a schoolhouse on the outskirts of the town, which was full of soldiers. In the morning Ellen simply wasn't there, and they never saw her again.

Jean and Mrs Horsefall asked to see the officer and stated their case, that a member of their party had disappeared, probably abducted by the soldiers. The officer promised to make inquiries, and nothing happened. Two days later they received orders to march down the road to Tampin, and were moved off under guard.

They stayed at Tampin for some days, and got so little food there that they practically starved; at their urgent entreaty the local commandant sent them down under guard to Malacca, where they hoped to get a ship. But there was no ship at Malacca and the officer in charge there sent them back to Tampin. They plodded back there in despair; at Alor Gajah Judy Thomson died. To stay at Tampin meant more deaths, inevitably, so they suggested it was better for them to continue down to Singapore on foot, and a corporal was detailed to take them on the road to Gemas.

In the middle of May, at Ayer Kuning, on the way to Gemas, Mrs Horsefall died. She had never really recovered from her attack of malaria or whatever fever it was that had attacked her two months previously; she had had recurrent attacks of low fever which had made Jean wonder sometimes if it was malaria that she had had at all. Whatever it was it had made her very weak; at Ayer Kuning she developed dysentery again, and died in two days, probably of heart failure or exhaustion. The faded little woman Mrs Frith, who was over fifty and always seemed to be upon the point of death and never quite made it, took over the care of Johnnie Horsefall and it did her a world of good; from that day Mrs Frith improved and gave up moaning in the night.

They got to Gemas, three days later; here as usual in towns they were put into the schoolhouse. The Japanese town major, a Captain Nisui, came to inspect them that evening; he had known nothing about them till they appeared in his town. This was quite usual and Jean was ready for it; she explained that they were prisoners being marched to camp in Singapore.

He said,“Prisoner not go Singapore. Strict order. Where you come from?”

She told him.“We've been travelling for over two months,”she said, with the calmness borne of many disappointments.“We must get into a camp, or we shall die. Seven of us have died upon the road already—there were thirty-two when we were taken prisoner. Now there are twenty-five. We can't go on like this. We must get into camp at Singapore. You must see that.”

He said,“No more prisoner to Singapore. Very sorry for you, but strict order. Too many prisoner in Singapore.”

She said,“But, Captain Nisui, that can't mean women. That means men prisoners, surely.”

“No more prisoner to Singapore,”he said.“Strict order.”

“Well, can we stay here and make ourselves a camp, and have a doctor here?”

His eyes narrowed.“No prisoner stay here.”

“But what are we to do? Where can we go?”

“Very sad for you,”he said.“I tell you where you go tomorrow.”

She went back to the women after he had gone.“You heard all that,”she said calmly.“He says we aren't to go to Singapore after all.”

The news meant very little to the women; they had fallen into the habit of living from day to day, and Singapore was very far away.“Looks as if they don't want us anywhere,”Mrs Price said heavily.“Bobbie, if I see you teasing Amy again I'll wallop you just like your father. Straight, I will.”

Mrs Frith said,“If they'd just let us alone we could find a little place like one of them villages and live till it's all over.”

Jean stared at her.“They couldn't feed us,”she said slowly.“We depend upon the Nips for food.”But it was the germ of an idea, and she put it in the back of her mind.

“Precious little food we get,”said Mrs Frith.“I'll never forget that terrible place Tampin in all my born days.”

Captain Nisui came the next day.“You go now to Kuantan,”he said.“Woman camp in Kuantan, very good. You will be very glad.”

Jean did not know where Kuantan was. She asked,“Where is Kuantan? Is it far away?”

“Kuantan on coast,”he said.“You go there now.”

Behind her someone said,“It's hundreds of miles away. It's on the east coast.”

“Okay,”said Captain Nisui.“On east coast.”

“Can we go there by railway?”Jean inquired.

“Sorry, no railway. You walk, ten, fifteen miles each day. You get there soon. You will be very happy.”

She said quietly,“Seven of us are dead already with this marching, Captain. If you make us march to this place Kuantan more of us will die. Can we have a truck to take us there?”

“Sorry, no truck,”he said.“You get there very soon.”

He wanted them to start immediately, but it was then eleven in the morning and they rebelled. With patient negotiation Jean got him to agree that they should start at dawn next day; this was the most that she could do. She did, however, get him to provide a good supper for them that night, a sort of meat stew with the rice, and a banana each.

From Gemas to Kuantan is about a hundred and seventy miles; there is no direct road. They left Gemas in the last week of May; on the basis of their previous rate of progress Jean reckoned that it would take them six weeks to do the journey. It was by far the longest they had had to tackle; always before there had been hope of transport of some sort at the end of fifty miles or so. Now six weeks of travelling lay ahead of them, with only a vague hope of rest at the end. None of them really believed that there were prison camps for them at Kuantan.

“You made a mistake, dearie,”said Mrs Frith,“saying what you did about us staying and making a camp here. I could see he didn't like that.”

“He just wants to get rid of us,”Jean said wearily.“They don't want to bother with us—just get us out of the way.”

They left next morning with a sergeant and a private as a guard. Gemas is a railway junction and the East Coast railway runs north from there; the railway was not being used at all at that time, and there was a rumour that the track was being taken up and sent to some unknown strategic destination in the north. The women were not concerned with that; what concerned them was that they had to walk along the railway line, which meant nearly walking in the sun most of each day, and there was no possibility of getting a ride in a train.

They went on for a week, marching about ten miles every other day; then fever broke out among the children. They never really knew what it was; it started with little Amy Price, who came out in a rash and ran a high temperature, with a running nose. It may have been measles. It was impossible in the conditions of their life to keep the children segregated, and in the weeks that followed it spread from child to child. Amy Price slowly recovered, but by the time she was fit to walk again seven of the other children were down with it. There was nothing they could do except to keep the tired, sweating little faces bathed and cool, and change the soaked clothes for what fresh ones they could muster. They were at a place called Bahau when the sickness was at its height, living at the station in the ticket office and the waiting-room, and on the platform. They had bad luck because there had been a doctor in Bahau three days before they arrived, a Japanese army doctor. But he had gone on in his truck in the direction of Kuala Klawang, and though they got the headman to send runners after him they never made contact with him. So they had no help.

At Bahau four children died, Harry Collard, Susan Fletcher, Doris Simmonds, who was only three, and Freddie Holland. Jean was most concerned with Freddie, as was natural, but there was so little she could do. She guessed from the first day of fever that he was going to die; by that time she had amassed a store of sad experience. There was something in the attitude of people, even tiny children, to their illness that told when death was coming to them, a listlessness, as if they were too tired to make the effort to live. By that time they had all grown hardened to the fact of death. Grief and mourning had ceased to trouble them; death was a reality to be avoided and fought, but when it came—well, it was just one of those things. After a person had died there were certain things that had to be done, the straightening of the limbs, the grave, the cross, the entry in a diary saying who had died and just exactly where the grave was. That was the end of it; they had no energy for afterthoughts.

Jean's care now was for Mrs Holland. After Freddie was buried she tried to get Eileen to care for the baby; for the last few weeks the baby had been left to Jean to feed and tend and carry, and the had grown very much attached to it. With both the older children dead Jean gave the baby, Robin, back to its mother, not so much because she wanted to get rid of it as because she felt that an interest must be found for Eileen Holland, and the baby would supply it. But the experiment was not a great success; Eileen by that time was so weak that she could not carry the baby on the march, and she could not summon the energy to play with it. Moreover, the baby obviously preferred the younger woman to its mother, having been carried by her for so long.

“Seems as if he doesn't really belong to me,”Mrs Holland said once.“You take him, dear. He likes being with you.”From that time on they shared the baby; it got its rice and soup from Eileen, but it got its fun from Jean.

They left four tiny graves behind the signal box at Bahau and went on down the line carrying two litters of bamboo poles; the weakest children took turns in these. As was common on the journey, they found the Japanese guards to be humane and reasonable men, uncouth in their habits and mentally far removed from western ideas, but tolerant to the weaknesses of women and deeply devoted to children. For hours the sergeant would plod along carrying one child piggyback and at the same time carrying one end of the stretcher, his rifle laid beside the resting child. There was the usual language difficulty. The women by that time were acquiring a few words of Japanese, but the only one who could talk Malay fluently was Jean, and it was she who made inquiries at the villages and sometimes acted as interpreter for the Japanese.

Mrs Frith surprised Jean very much. She was a faded, anaemic little woman of over fifty. In the early stages of the journey she had been very weak and something of a nuisance to them with her continued prognostications of evil; they had trouble enough in the daily round without looking forward and anticipating more. Since she had adopted Johnnie Horsefall Mrs Frith had taken on a new lease of life; her health had improved and she now marched as strongly as any of them. She had lived in Malaya for about fifteen years; she could speak only a few words of the language but she had a considerable knowledge of the country and its diseases. She was quite happy that they were going to Kuantan.“Nice over there, it is,”she said.“Much healthier than in the west, and nicer people. We'll be all right once we get over there. You see.”

As time went on, Jean turned to Mrs Frith more and more for comfort and advice in their predicaments.

At Ayer Kring Mrs Holland came to the end of her strength. She had fallen twice on the march and they had taken turns in helping her along. It was impossible to put her on the litter; even in her emaciated state she weighed eight stone, and they were none of them strong enough by that time to carry such a load very far. Moreover, to put her on a litter meant turning a child off it, and she refused even to consider such a thing. She stumbled into the village on her own feet, but by the time she got there she was changing colour as Mrs Collard had before her, and that was a bad sign.

Ayer Kring is a small village at a railway station; there were no station buildings here, and by negotiation the headman turned the people out of one house for them, as had been done several times before. They laid Mrs Holland in a shady corner and made a pillow for her head and bathed her face; they had no brandy or any other stimulant to give her. She could not rest lying down and insisted on sitting up, so they put her in a corner where she could be supported by the walls. She took a little soup that evening but refused all food. She knew herself it was the end.

“I'm so sorry, my dear,”she whispered late in the night.“Sorry to make so much trouble for you. Sorry for Bill. If you see Bill again, tell him not to fret. And tell him not to mind about marrying again, if he can find somebody nice. It's not as if he was an old man.”

An hour or two later she said,“I do think it's lovely the way baby's taken to you. It is lucky, isn't it?”

In the morning she was still alive, but unconscious. They did what they could, which wasn't very much, but her breathing got weaker and weaker, and at about midday she died. They buried her in the Moslem village cemetery that evening.

At Ayer Kring they entered the most unhealthy district they had passed through yet. The central mountains of Malaya were now on their left, to the west of them as they marched north, and they were coming to the head waters of the Pahang river, which runs down to the east coast. Here the river spreads out into numerous tributaries, the Menkuang, the Pertang, the Belengu, and many others, and these tributaries running through flat country make a marshy place of swamps and mangroves that stretched for forty miles along their route, a country full of snakes and crocodiles, and infested with mosquitoes. By day it was steamy and hot and breathless; at night a cold wet mist came up and chilled them unmercifully.

By the time they had been two days in this country several of them were suffering from fever, a fever that did not seen quite like the malaria that they were used to, in that the temperature did not rise so high; it may have been dengue. They had little by that time to treat it with, not so much because they were short of money as because there were no drugs at all in the jungly villages that they were passing through. Jean consulted with the sergeant, who advised them to press on, and get out of this bad country as soon as possible. Jean was running a fever herself at the time and everything was moving about her in a blur; she had a cracking headache and it was difficult to focus her eyes. She consulted with Mrs Frith, who was remarkably well.

“What he says is right, dearie,”Mrs Frith declared.“We won't get any better staying in this swampy place. I think we ought to walk each day, if you ask me.”

Jean forced herself to concentrate.“What about Mrs Simmonds?”

“Maybe the soldiers would carry her, if she gets any worse. I don't know, I'm sure. It's cruel hard, but if we've got to go we'd better go and get it over. That's what I say. We shan't do any good hanging around here in this nasty place.”

They marched each day after that, stumbling along in fever, weak, and ill. The baby, Robin Holland, that Jean carried, got the fever; this was the first ailment he had had. She showed him to the headman in the village of Mentri, and his wife produced a hot infusion of some bark in a dirty coconut shell; Jean tasted it and it was very bitter, so she judged it to be a form of quinine. She gave a little to the baby and took some herself; it seemed to do them both good during the night. Before the day's march began several of the women took it, and it helped.

It took them eleven days to get through the swamps to the higher ground past Temerloh. They left Mrs Simmonds and Mrs Fletcher behind them, and little Gillian Thomson. When they emerged into the higher, healthier country and dared to stay a day to rest, Jean was very weak but the fever had left her. The baby was still alive, though obviously ill; it cried almost incessantly during its waking hours.

It was Mrs Frith who now buoyed them up, as she had depressed them in the earlier days.“It should be getting better all the time from now on,”she told them.“As we get nearer to the coast it should get better. It's lovely on the east coast, nice beaches to bathe on, and always a sea breeze. It's healthy, too.”

They came presently to a very jungly village on a hilltop; they never learned its name. It stood above the river Jengka. By this time they had left the railway and were heading more or less eastwards on a jungle track that would at some time join a main road that led down to Kuantan. This village was cool and airy, and the people kind and hospitable; they gave the women a house to sleep in and provided food and fresh fruit, and the same bark infusion that was good for fever. They stayed there for six days revelling in the fresh, cool breeze and the clear, healthy nights, and when they finally marched on they were in better shape. They left a little gold brooch that had belonged to Mrs Fletcher with the headman as payment for the food and kindness that they had received, thinking that the dead woman would not have objected to that.

Four days later, in the evening, they came to Maran. A tarmac road runs through Maran crossing the Malay peninsula from Kuantan to Kerling. The road runs through the village, which has perhaps fifty houses, a school, and a few native stops. They came out upon the road half a mile or so to the north of the village; after five weeks upon the railway track and jungle paths it overjoyed them to see evidence of civilization in this road. They walked down to the village with a fresher step. And there, in front of them, they saw two trucks and two white men working on them while Japanese guards stood by.

They marched quickly towards the trucks, which were both heavily loaded with railway lines and sleepers; they stood pointing in the direction of Kuantan. One of them was jacked up on sleepers taken from the load, and both of the white men were underneath it working on the back axle. They wore shorts and army boots without socks; their bodies were brown with sunburn and very dirty with the muck from the back axle. But they were healthy and muscular men, lean, but in good physical condition. And they were white, the first white men that the women had seen for five months.

They crowded round the trucks; their guard began to talk in staccato Japanese with the truck guards. One of the men lying on his back under the axle, shifting spanner in hand, glanced at the bare feet and the sarongs within his range of vision and said slowly,“Tell the mucking Nip to get those mucking women shifted back so we can get some light.”

Some of the women laughed, and Mrs Frith said,“Don't you go using that language to me, young man.”

The men rolled out from under the truck and sat staring at the women and the children, at the brown skins, the sarongs, the bare feet.“Who said that?”asked the man with the spanner.“Which of you speaks English?”He spoke deliberately in a slow drawl, with something of a pause between each word.

Jean said laughing,“We're all English.”

He stared at her, noting the black hair plaited in a pigtail, the brown arms and feet, the sarong, the brown baby on her hip. There was a line of white skin showing on her chest at the V of her tattered blouse.“Straits-born?”he hazarded.

“No , real English—all of us,”she said.“We're prisoners.”

He got to his feet; he was a fair-haired powerfully built man about twenty-seven or twenty-eight years old.“Dinky-die?”he said.

She did not understand that.“Are you prisoners?”she asked.

He smiled slowly.“Are we prisoners?”he repeated.“Oh my word.”

There was something about this man that she had never met before.“Are you English?”she asked.

“No fear,”he said in his deliberate way.“We're Aussies.”

She said,“Are you in camp here?”

He shook his head.“We come from Kuantan,”he said.“But we're driving trucks all day, fetching this stuff down to the coast.

She said,“We're going to Kuantan, to the women's camp there.”

He stared at her.“That's crook for a start,”he said slowly.“There isn't any women's camp at Kuantan. There isn't any regular prisoner camp at all, just a little temporary camp for us because we're truck drivers. Who told you that there was a women's camp at Kuantan?”

“The Japanese told us. They're supposed to be sending us there.”She sighed.“It's just another lie.”

“The bloody Nips say anything.”He smiled slowly.“I thought you were a lot of boongs,”he said.“You say you're English, dinky-die? All the way from England?”

She nodded.“That's right. Some of us have been out here for ten or fifteen years, but we're all English.”

“And the kiddies—they all English too?”

“All of them,”she said.

He smiled slowly.“I never thought the first time that I spoke to an English lady she'd be looking like you.”

“You aren't exactly an oil painting yourself,”Jean said.

The other man was talking to a group of the women; Mrs Frith and Mrs Price were with Jean. The Australian turned to them.“Where do you come from?”he inquired.

Mrs Frith said,“We got took in Panong, over on the west coast, waiting for a boat to get away.”

“But where did you come from now?”

Jean said,“We're being marched to Kuantan.”

“Not all the way from Panong?”

She laughed shortly.“We've been everywhere—Port Swettenham, Port Dickson—everywhere. Nobody wants us. I reckon that we've walked nearly five hundred miles.”

“Oh my word,”he said.“That sounds a crook deal to me. How do you go on for tucker, if you aren't in a camp?”

She did not understand him.“Tucker?”

“What do you get to eat?”

“We stay each night in a village,”she said.“We'll have to find somewhere to stay here. Probably in a place like this it'll be the school. We eat what we can get in the village.”

“For Christ's sake,”he said.“Wait while I tell my cobber.”He swung round to the other.“You heard about the crook deal that they got?”he said.“Been walking all the time since they got taken. Never been inside a prison camp at all.”

“They've been telling me,”the other said.“The way these bloody Nips go on. Makes you chunda.”

The first man turned back to Jean.“What happens if any of you get sick?”

She said cynically,“When you get sick, you get well or you die. We haven't seen a doctor for the last three months and we've got practically no medicines left, so we mostly die. There were thirty-two of us when we were taken. Now we're seventeen.”

The Australian said softly,“Oh my word.”

Jean said,“Will you be staying here tonight?”

He said,“Will you?”

“We shall stay here,”she said.“We shall be here tomorrow too, unless they'll let us ride down on your trucks. We can't march the children every day. We walk one day and rest the next.”

He said,“If you're staying, Mrs Boong, we're staying too. We can fix this bloody axle so it will never roll again, if needs be.”He paused in slow thought.“You got no medicines?”he said.“What do you want?”

She said quickly,“Have you got any Glauber's salt?”

He shook his head.“Is that what you want?”

“We haven't got any salts at all,”she said“We want quinine, and something for all these skin diseases that the children have got. Can we get those here?”

He said slowly,“I'll have a try. Have you got any money?”

Mrs Frith snorted,“After being six months with the Japs? They took everything we had. Even our wedding rings.”

Jean said,“We've got a few little bits of jewellery left, if we could sell some of those.”

He said,“I'll have a go first, and see what I can do. You get fixed up with somewhere to sleep, and I'll see you later.”

“All right.”

She went back to their sergeant and bowed to him because that pleased him and made things easier for them. She said,“Gunso, where yasme tonight? Children must yasme. We see headman about yasme and mishi?”

He came with her and they found the headman, and negotiated for the loan of the schoolbuilding for the prisoners, and for the supply of rice for mishi. They did not now experience the blank refusals that they formerly had met when the party was thirty strong; the lesser numbers had made accommodation and food much easier for them. They settled into the school building and began the routine of chores and washing that occupied the bulk of their spare time. The news that there was no women prisoners' camp in Kuantan was what they had all secretly expected, but it was a disappointment, none the less. The novelty of the two Australians made up for this, because by that time they were living strictly from day to day.

At the trucks the Aussies got back to their work. With heads close together under the axle, the fair-haired man that Jean had talked to said to his cobber,“I never heard such a crook deal. What can we do to fix this bastard so as we stay here tonight? I said I'd try and get some medicines for them.”

They had already rectified the binding brake that had heated up the near side hub and caused the stoppage. The other said,“Take the whole bloody hub off for a dekko, 'n pull out the shaft from the diff. That makes a good show of dirty bits. Means sleeping in the trucks.”

“I said I'd try and get some medicines.”They worked on for a little.

“How you going to do that?”

“Petrol, I suppose. That's easiest.”

It was already growing dark when they extracted four feet of heavy metal shafting, splined at both ends, from the back axle; dripping with black oil they showed it to the Japanese corporal in charge of them as evidence of their industry.“Yasme here tonight,”they said. The guard was suspicious, but agreed; indeed, he could do nothing else. He went off to arrange for rice for them, leaving them in charge of the private. Who was with him.

On the excuse of a benjo, the fair-haired man left the trucks and in the half light retired behind a house. He slipped quickly down behind a row of houses, and came out into the street a couple of hundred yards down, towards the end of the village. Here there was a Chinaman who ran a decrepit bus; the Australian had noted this place on various journeys through Maran; they plied regularly up and down this road.

In his deliberate manner he said quietly,“Johnnie, you buy petrol? How much you give?”It is extraordinary how little barrier an unknown language makes between a willing buyer and a willing seller. At one point in the negotiation they resorted to the written word, and the Australian wrote GLAUBER'S SALT and QUININE and SKIN DISEASE OINTMENT in block letters on a scrap of wrapping paper.

He slunk back behind the houses carrying three two-gallon cans and a length of rubber hose, which he hid behind the latrine. He came back to the trucks presently, ostentatiously buttoning his shorts.

In the darkness, early in the night, he came to the school-house; it may have been about ten o'clock. One of the Japanese soldiers was supposed to be on guard all night, but in the five weeks that they had been with this pair of guards the women had not shown the slightest inclination to escape, and their guards had long given up watching them at night. The Australian had made sure where they were, however, and when he had seen them squatting with the truck guards he came silently to the school.

At the open door he paused, and said quietly,“Which of you ladies was I talking to this afternoon? The one with the baby.”

Jean was asleep; they woke her and she pulled up her sarong and slipped her top on, and came to the door. He had several little packages for her.“That's quinine,”he said.“I can get more of that if you want it. I couldn't get Glauber's, but this is what the Chinese take for dysentery. It's all written in Chinese, but what he says it means is three of these leaves powdered up in warm water every four hours. That'll be for a grown-up person. If it's any good, keep the label and maybe you could get some more in a Chinese drug shop. I got this Zam-Buk for the skin, and there's more of that if you want it.”

She took them gratefully from him.“That's marvellous,”she said softly.“How much did it all cost?”

“That's all right,”he said in his deliberate manner.“The Nips paid, but they don't know it.”

She thanked him again.“What are you doing here?”she asked.“Where are you going with the trucks?”

“Kuantan,”he said.“We should be back there tonight, but Ben Leggatt—he's my cobber—he got the truck in bits so we had to give it away. Get down there tomorrow, or we might stretch it another day if it suits, though it'ld be risky, I think.”He told her that there were six of them driving six trucks for the Japanese; they drove regularly from Kuantan up-country to a place upon the railway called Jerantut, a distance of about a hundred and thirty miles. They would drive up one day and load the truck with sleepers and railway lines taken up from the track, and drive back to Kuantan the next day, where the railway material was unloaded on to the quayside to be taken away by ship to some unknown destination.“Building another railway somewhere, I suppose,”he said. A hundred and thirty miles is a long way to drive a heavily loaded truck in a day in tropical conditions, and they sometimes failed to reach Kuantan before dark; when that happened they spent the night in a village. Their absence would not be remarked particularly at Kuantan.

He had been taken somewhere in Johore, and had been driving trucks from Kuantan for about two months.“Better than being in a camp,”he said.

She sat down on the top step of the three that led up to the school, and he squatted down before her on the ground. His manner of sitting intrigued her, because he sat down on one heel somewhat in the manner of a native, but with his left leg extended.“Are you a truck driver in Australia?”she asked.

“No bloody fear,”he said.“I'm a ringer.”

She asked,“What's a ringer?”

“A stockman,”he said.“I was born in Queensland out behind Cloncurry, and my people, they're all Queenslanders. My dad, he came from London, from a place called Hammersmith: He used to drive a cab and so he knew about horses, and he came out to Queensland to work for Cobb and Co., and met Ma. But I've not been back to the Curry for some time. I was working in the Territory over to the west, on a station called Wollara. That's about a hundred and ten miles south-west of the Springs.”

She smiled.“Where's the Springs, then?”

“Alice,”he said.“Alice Springs. Right in the middle of Australia, half way between Darwin and Adelaide.”

She said,“I thought the middle of Australia was all desert?”

He was concerned at her ignorance.“Oh my word,”he said deliberately.“Alice is a bonza place. Plenty of water in Alice; people living there, they leave the sprinkler on all night, watering the lawn. That's right, they leave the sprinkler on all night. Course, the Territory's dry in most parts, but there's usually good feed along the creeks. Come to that, there's water all over if you look for it. You take a creek that only runs in the wet, now, say a couple of months in the year, or else not that. You get a sandy billabong, and you'll get water there by digging not a foot below the surface, like as not—even in the middle of the dry.”His slow, even tones were strangely comforting.“You go to a place like that and you'll find little diggings all over in the sand, where the kangaroos and euros have dug for water. They know where to go. There's water all over in the outback, but you've got to know where to find it.”

“What do you do at this place Wollara?”she asked.“Do you look after sheep?”

He shook his head.“You don't find sheep around the Alice region,”he said.“It'd be too hot for them. Wollara is a cattle station.”

“How many cattle have you got?”

“About eighteen thousand when I come away,”he said.“It goes up and down, according to the wet, you know.”

“Eighteen thousand? How big is it?”

“Wollara? About two thousand seven hundred.”

“Two thousand seven hundred acres,”she said.“That's a big place.”

He stared at her.“Not acres,”he said.“Square miles. Wollara's two thousand seven hundred square miles.”

She was startled.“But is that all one place—one farm, I mean?”

“It's one station,”he replied.“One property.”

“But however many of you does it take to run it?”

His mind ran lovingly around the well-remembered scene.“There's Mr Duveen, Tommy Duveen —he's the manager, and then me—I'm the head stockman, or I was. Tommy said he'd keep a place for me when I got back. I'd like to get back to Wollara again, one day...”He mused a little.“We had three other ringers—whites,”he said.“Then there was Happy, and Moonlight, and Nugget, and Snowy, and Tarmac...”He thought for a minute.“Nine boongs we had,”he said.“That's all.”

“Nine what?”

“Black boys—black stockmen. Abos.”

“But that's only thirteen men,”she said.

“That's right. Fourteen if you count Mr Duveen.”

“But can fourteen men look after all those cattle?”she asked.

“Oh yes,”he said thoughtfully.“Wollara is an easy station, in a way, because it hasn't got any fences. It's fences make the work. We've got the Palmer River and the Levi Range to the north, and the sand country over to the west; the cattle don't go there. Then there's the Kernot Range to the south and Mount Ormerod and the Twins to the east. Fourteen men is all right for a station like that; it would be easier if we had more whites, but you can't get them. These bloody boongs, they're always going walkabout.”

“What's that?”she asked.

“Walkabout? Why, an Abo ringer, he'll come up one day and he'll say, ‘Boss, I go walkabout now.’ You can't keep him. He'll leave the station and go wandering off just in a pair of pants and an old hat with a gun if he's got one, or a spear and a throwing stick, maybe, and he'll be away two or three months.”

“But where does he go to?”she asked.

“Just travels. They go a long way on a walkabout—oh my word,”he said.“Four or five hundred miles, maybe. Then when he's had enough, he'll come back to the station and join up for work again. But the trouble with the boongs is, you never know if they'll be there next week.”

There was a short silence; they sat quietly in the tropic night together on the steps of the atap schoolhouse, exiles far from their homes. Over their heads the flying foxes swept in the moonlight with a dry rustling of leathery wings.“Eighteen thousand cattle...”she said thoughtfully.

“More or less,”he said.“Get a good wet, and it'll maybe rise to twenty-one or twenty-two thousand. Then you get a dry year, and it'll go right down to twelve or thirteen thousand. I reckon we lose about three thousand every year by drought.”

“But can't you get them to water?”

He smiled slowly.“Not with fourteen men. There's enough cattle die of thirst each year in the Territory and Northern Queensland to feed the whole of England. Course, the horses make it worse on Wollara.”

“Horses?”

“Oh my word,”he said.“We've got about three thousand brumbies, but you can't do nothing with them—they're vermin. Wollera used to be a horse station years ago, selling horses to the Indian Army, but you can't sell horses now. We use a few, of course—maybe a hundred, with packhorses and that. You can't get rid of them except by shooting, and you'll never get a ringer to shoot horses. They eat the feed the cattle ought to get, and spoil it, too. Cattle don't like feeding where a horse has been.”

She asked,“How big is Wollara—how long, and how wide?”

He said,“Oh, I'd say about ninety miles from east to west, and maybe forty-five to fifty, north to south, at the widest part. But it's a good station to manage, because the homestead is near the middle, so it's not so far in any one way. Over to the Kernot Range is the furthest; that's about sixty miles.”

“Sixty miles from the homestead? That's where you live?”

“That's right.”

“Are there any other homesteads on it?”

He stared at her.“There's only the one homestead on each station. Some have an outstation, a shack of some kind where the boys can leave blankets and maybe a little tucker, but not many.”

“How long does it take you to get to the furthest point, then—to the Kernot Range?”

“Over to the Range? Oh well, to go there and come back might take about a week. That's with horses; in a utility you might do it in a day and a half. But horses are best, although they're a bit slow. You never take a packhorse faster'n a walk, not if you can help it. It isn't like you see it on the movies, people galloping their horses everywhere—oh my word. You'd soon wear out a horse if you used him that way in the Territory.”

They sat together for over an hour, talking quietly at the entrance to the schoolhouse. At the end the ringer got up from his strange posture on the ground, and said,“I mustn't stay any longer, case those Nips come back and start creating. My cobber, too—he'll be wondering what happened to me. I left him to boil up.”

Jean got to her feet.“It's been terribly kind of you to get us these things. You don't know what they mean to us. Tell me, what's your name?”

“Joe Harman,”he said.“Sergeant Harman—Ringer Harman, some of them call me.”He hesitated.“Sorry I called you Mrs Boong today,”he said awkwardly.“It was a silly kind of joke.”

She said,“My name's Jean Paget.”

“That sounds like a Scotch name.”

“It is,”she said.“I'm not Scotch myself, but my mother came from Perth.”

“My mother's family was Scotch,”he said.“They came from Inverness.”

She put out her hand.“Goodnight, Sergeant,”she said.“It's been lovely talking to another white person.”

He took her hand; there was great comfort for her in his masculine handshake.“Look, Mrs Paget,”he said.“I'll try if I can get the Nips to let your party ride down on the truck with us. If the little bastards won't wear it, then we'll have to give it away. In that case I'll see you on the road again before you get to Kuantan, and I'll make darn sure there's something crook with the truck. What else do you want?”

“Soap,”she said.“Could you possibly get us soap?”

“Should be able to,”he said.

“We've got no soap at all,”she observed.“I've got a little gold locket that one of the women had who died, a thing with a bit of hair in it. I was going to see if I could sell that here, and get some soap.”

“Keep it,”he said.“I'll see you get soap.”

“We want that more than anything, now that you've got these medicines for us,”she said.

“You'll have it.”He hesitated, and then said,“Sorry I talked so much, boring you with the outback and all that. There's times when you get down a bit—can't make yourself believe you'll ever see it again.”

“I wasn't bored,”she said softly.“Goodnight, Sergeant.”

“Goodnight.”

In the morning Jean showed the women what she had got.

“I heard you talking to him ever so long,”Mrs Price said.“Nice young man, I'd say.”

“He's a very homesick young man,”Jean said.“He loves talking about the cattle station he comes from.”

“Homesick!”Mrs Price said.“Aren't we all?”

The Australians had a smart argument with their guards that morning, who refused point-blank to let the women ride down on the trucks. There was some reason in this from their point of view, because the weight of seventeen women and children added to two grossly overloaded trucks might well be the last straw that would bring final breakdown, in which case the guards themselves would have been lucky to escape with a flogging at the hands of their officer. Harman and Leggatt had to put the back axle together again; they were finished and ready for the road about the middle of the morning.

Joe Harman said,“Keep that little bastard busy for a minute while I loose off the union.”He indicated the Jap guard. Presently they started, Harman in the lead, dribbling a little petrol from a loosened pipe joint, unnoticed by the guard. It was just as well to have an alibi when they ran out of fuel, having parted with six gallons to the Chinaman.

From Maran to Kuantan is fifty-five miles. The women rested that day at Maran, and next day began the march down the tarmac road. They reached a village called Buan that night. Jean had looked for Joe Harman's truck all day, expecting to see it returning; she was not to know that it had been stranded overnight at Pohoi, short of petrol, and was a day late in the return journey. They stayed next day at Buan in an atap shed; the women took turns with Jean watching for the truck. Their health already was somewhat improved. After the railway track and the jungle paths the tarmac road was easy walking, and the medicines were already having an effect. The country, too, was growing higher and healthier, and the more imaginative of them were already saying they could smell the sea. And finally their contact with the two Australians had had a marked effect on their morale.

They did not see Joe Harman's truck as it passed through. Instead, a Malay girl came to them in the evening with a brown paper parcel of six cakes of Lifebuoy soap; it was addressed to Mrs Paget. Written on the parcel was a note which read,

Dear Lady,

I send some soap which is all that we can find just at present but I will get more later on. I am sorry not to see you but the Nip won't let us stop so I have given this to the Chinaman at Maran and he says he will get it to you. Look out for us on the way back and I will try and stop then.

Joe Harman

The women were delighted.“Lifebuoy,”said Mrs Warner, sniffing it ecstatically.“You can just smell the carbolic in it! My dear, wherever do you think they got it?”

“I'd have two guesses,”Jean replied.“Either they stole it, or they stole something to buy it with.”In fact, the latter was correct. At Pohoi their Japanese guard had taken off his boots to wash his feet at the village well; he washed his feet for about thirty seconds and turned round, but the boots had vanished; it could not have been either of the Australians because they both appeared immediately from the other direction. The mystery was never cleared up. Ben Leggatt, however, was most helpful and stole a pair from a sleeping Japanese that evening and gave them to their guard, who was so relieved that he gave Ben a dollar.

The next day the women marched to Berkapor. They were out into much better country now, a pleasant, relatively healthy part where the road wound round hillsides and was mostly shaded by the overhanging trees. That day for the first time they got coconuts. Mrs Price had an old worn-out pair of slippers that had belonged to Mrs Horsefall; she had carried them for weeks and had never really used them; they traded these at Berkapor as soon as they got in for milk coconuts, one for each member of the party, thinking that the vitamins contained in the fluid would be good for them. At Berkapor they were accommodated in a large atap copra shed beside the road, and just before dusk the two familiar trucks drew up in the village, driven by Ben Leggatt and Joe Harman. As before, they were headed for the coast and loaded high with railway lines and sleepers.

Jean and several of the others walked across the road to meet them, with the Japanese sergeant; the Japanese guards fell into conversation together. Joe Harman turned to Jean.“We couldn't get loaded at Jerantut in time to make it down to Kuantan tonight,”he said.“Ben's got a pig.”

“A pig?”They crowded round Ben's truck. The corpse was lying upon the top of the load, a black, long-nosed Oriental pig, somewhat mauled and already covered in flies. Somewhere near the Tekam River Ben, whose truck was in the lead, had found this pig upon the road and had chased it with the truck for a quarter of a mile. The Japanese guard beside him had fired six shots at it from his rifle and had missed it every time till with the seventh he had wounded it and so enabled Ben to run over it with one of the front wheels. They had stopped and Harman coming close behind them had stopped too, and the two Aussies and the Japanese guard had heaved the pig on to the load and got moving again before the infuriated Chinese storekeeper had caught up with them to claim his property. Harman said quietly to Jean,“We'll have to let the bloody Nips eat all they can and carry away a bit. Leave it to me; I'll see there's some for you.”

That night the women got about thirty-five pounds of boiled pig meat, conveyed to them surreptitiously in several instalments. They made a fire of coconut shells behind the copra store and made a stew with their rice ration, and ate all of this that seemed prudent to them; at that there was enough meat left for the three meals that they would have before they took the road again. They sat about in the shed or at the roadside after they had finished, replete with the first really nourishing meal that they had had for months, and presently the Australians came across to talk to them.

Joe Harman came to Jean.“Sorry I couldn't send over more of that pig,”he said in his slow Queensland drawl.“I had to let the bloody Nips have most of it.”

She said,“It's been splendid, Joe. We've been eating and eating, and there's still lots left for tomorrow. I don't know when we last had such a meal.”

“I'd say that's what you need,”he observed.“There's not a lot of flesh on any of you, if I may say so.”

He squatted down upon the ground beside the women, sitting on one heel in his peculiar way.

“I know we're pretty thin,”Jean said.“But we're a darned sight better than we were. That Chinese stuff you got us as the substitute for Glauber's salt—that's doing the trick all right. It's stopping it.”

“Fine,”he said.“Maybe we could get some more of that in Kuantan.”

“The pig was a god-send,”she said.“That, and the fruit—we got some green coconuts today. We've been very lucky so far that we've had no beriberi, or that sort of thing.”

“It's because we've had fresh rice,”said Mrs Frith unexpectedly.“Being in the country parts we've had fresh rice all through. It's old rice that gives you beriberi.”

The Australian sat thoughtful, chewing a piece of stick.“Funny sort of a life for you ladies,”he said at last.“Living in a place like this, and eating like the boongs. These Nips'll have something coming to them, when it's all added up.”

He turned to Jean.“What were you all doing in Malaya?”he asked.

“Most of us were married,”she said.“Our husbands had jobs here.”

Mrs Frith said,“My hubby's District Engineer on the railway. We had ever such a nice bungalow at Kajang.”

Harman said,“All the husbands got interned separately, I suppose?”

“That's right,”said Mrs Price.“My Arthur's in Singapore. I heard about him when we was in Port Dickson. I think they're all in Singapore.”

“All comfortable in a camp while you go walking round the country,”he said.

“That's right,”said Mrs Frith.“Still, it's nice to know that they're all right, when all's said and done.”

“It seems to me,”said Harman,“the way they're kicking you around, they just don't know what they can do with you. It might not be too difficult for you to just stay in one place, as it might be this, and live till the war's over.”

Mrs Frith said,“That's what I've been thinking.”

Jean said,“I know. I've thought of this ever since Mrs Frith suggested it. The trouble is, the Japs feed us—or they make the village feed us. The village never gets paid. We'd have to earn our keep somehow, and I don't see how we could do it.”

Harman said,“It was just an idea.”

He said presently,“I believe I know where I could get a chicken or two. If I can I'll drop them off for you when we come up-country, day after tomorrow.”

Jean said,“We haven't paid you for the soap yet.”

“Forget about it,”he said slowly.“I didn't pay cash for it myself. I swapped it for a pair of Nip rubber boots.”With slow, dry humour he told them about the boots.“You got the soap, the Nip got another pair of boots, and Ben got a dollar,”he said.“Everybody's happy and satisfied.”

Jean said,“Is that how you're going to get the chicken?”

“I'll get a chicken for you, one way or another,”he said.“You ladies need feeding up.”

She said,“Don't take any risks.”

“You attend to your own business, Mrs Boong,”he said,“and take what you get. That's what you have to do when you're a prisoner, just take what you can get.”

She smiled, and said,“All right.”The fact that he had called her Mrs Boong pleased her; it was a little tenuous bond between herself and this strange man that he should pull her leg about her sunburn, her native dress, and the baby that she carried on her hip like a Malay woman. The word boong put Australia into her mind, and the aboriginal stockmen, and she asked a question that had occurred to her, partly from curiosity and partly because she knew it pleased him to talk about his own country.“Tell me,”she said,“is it very hot in Australia, the part you come from? Hotter than this?”

“It's hot,”he said.“Oh my word, it can be hot when it tries. At Wollara it can go to a hundred and eighteen—that's a hot day, that is. But it's not like this heat here. It's a kind of a dry heat, so you don't sweat like you do here.”He thought for a minute.“I got thrown once,”he said,“breaking in a brumby to the saddle. I broke my thigh, and after it was set in the hospital they used to point a sort of lamp at it, a sunray lamp they called it, to tone up the muscles or something. Do you have those things in England?”

She nodded.“It's like that, is it?”

“That's right,”he said.“It's a kind of warm, dry heat, the sort that does you good and makes you thirsty for cold beer.”

“What does the country look like?”she inquired. It pleased the man to talk about his own place and she wanted to please him; he had been so very kind to them.

“It's red,”he said.“Red around Alice and where I come from, red earth and then the mountains are all red. The Macdonnells and the Levis and the Kernots, great red ranges of bare hills against the blue sky. Evenings they go purple and all sorts of colours. After the wet there's green all over them. In the dry, parts of them go silvery white with the spinifex.”He paused.“I suppose everybody likes his own place,”he said quietly.“The country round about the Springs is my place. People come up on the 'Ghan from Adelaide and places in the south, and they say Alice is a lousy town. I only went to Adelaide once, and I thought that was lousy. The country round about the Springs is beautiful to me.”

He mused.“Artists come up from the south and try and paint it in pictures,”he said.“I only met one that ever got it right, and he was an Abo, an Abo called Albert out at Hermannsburg. Somebody gave him a brush and some paints one time, and he started in and got it better than any of them, oh my word, he did. But he's an Abo, and he's painting his own place. I suppose that makes a difference.”

He turned to Jean.“What's your place?”he asked.“Where do you come from?”

She said,“Southampton.”

“Where the liners go?”

“That's it,”she said.

“What's it like there?”he asked.

She shifted the baby on her hip, and moved her feet in the sarong.“It's quiet, and cool, and happy,”she said thoughtfully.“It's not particularly beautiful, although there's lovely country round about—the New Forest, and the Isle of Wight. It's my place, like the Springs is yours, and I shall go back there if I live through this time, because I love it so.”She paused for a moment.“There was an ice rink there,”she said.“I used to dance upon the ice, when I was a girl at school. One day I'll get back there and dance again.”

“I've never seen an ice rink,”said the man from Alice.“I've seen pictures of them, and on the movies.”

She said,“It was such fun...”

Presently he got up to go; she walked across the road with him towards the trucks, the baby on her hip, as always.“I shan't be able to see you tomorrow,”he said.“We start at dawn. But I'll be coming back up the road the day after.”

“We shall be walking to Pohoi that day, I think,”she said.

“I'll see if I can get you those chickens,”he said.

She turned and faced him, standing beside her in the moonlit road, in all the noises of the tropic night.“Look, Joe,”she said.“We don't want meat if it's going to mean trouble. It was grand of you to get that soap for us, but you did take a fearful risk, pinching that chap's boots.”

“That's nothing,”he said slowly.“You can run rings round these Nips when you learn how.”

“You've done a lot for us,”she said.“This pig, and the medicines, and the soap. It's made a world of difference to us in these last few days. I know you've taken risks to do these things. Do, please, be careful.”

“Don't worry about me,”he said.“I'll try and get the chickens, but if I find things getting hot I'll give it away. I won't go sticking out my neck.”

“You'll promise that?”she asked.

“Don't worry about me,”he said.“You've got enough troubles on your own plate, my word. But we'll come out all right, so long as we just keep alive, that's all we got to do. Just keep alive another two years, till the war's over.”

“You think that it will be as long as that?”she asked.

“Ben knows a lot more than I do about things like that,”he said.“He thinks about two years.”He grinned down at her.“You'd better have those chickens.”

“I'll leave that with you,”she said.“I'd never forgive myself if you got caught in anything, and bought it.”

“I won't,”he said. He put out his hand as if to take her own, and then dropped it again.“Goodnight, Mrs Boong,”he said.

She laughed.“I'll crack you with a coconut if you say Mrs Boong again. Goodnight, Joe.”

“Goodnight.”

They did not see him next morning, though they heard the trucks go off. They rested that day at Berkapor, as was their custom, and the next day they marched on to Pohoi. The two trucks driven by Harman and Leggatt passed them on the road about midday going up empty to Jerantut; each driver waved to the women as they passed, and they waved back. The Japanese guards seated beside the drivers scowled a little. No chickens dropped from the trucks and the trucks did not stop; in one way Jean was rather relieved. She knew something of the temper of these men by now, and she knew very well that they would stop at nothing, would be deterred by no risk, to get what they considered to be helpful for the women. No chickens meant no trouble, and she marched on for the rest of the day with an easy mind.

That evening, in the house that they had been put into at Pohoi, a little Malay boy came to Jean with a green canvas sack; he said that he had been sent by a Chinaman in Gambang. In the sack were five black cockerels, alive, with their feet tied. Poultry is usually transported in the East alive.

Their arrival put Jean in a difficulty, and she consulted with Mrs Frith. It was impossible for them to kill, pluck and cook five cockerels without drawing the attention of their guards to what was going on, and the first thing that the guards would ask was, where had the cockerels come from? If Jean had known the answer to that one herself it would have been easier to frame a lie. It would be possible, they thought, to say that they had bought them with money given to them by the Australians, but that was difficult if the sergeant wanted to know where they had bought them in Pohoi. It was unfortunate that Pohoi was a somewhat unfriendly village; it had been genuinely difficult for the village to evacuate a house for the women, and it was not to be expected that they would get much cooperation from the villagers in any deceit. Finally they decided to say that they had bought them with money given to them by the Australians, and that they had arranged at Berkapor for the poultry to be sent to them at Pohoi from a village called Limau, two or three miles off the road. It was a thin tale and one that would not stand up to a great deal of investigation, but they saw no reason why any investigation should take place.

They decided regretfully that they would have to part with one of the five cockerels to their guards; the gift of a chicken would make the sergeant sweet and involve him in the affair, rendering any serious investigation unlikely. Accordingly Jean took the sack and went to find the sergeant.

She bowed to him, to put him in a good temper.“Gunso,”she said,“good mishi tonight. We buy chickens.”She opened the sack and showed him the fowls lying in the bottom. Then she reached down and pulled out one.“For you.”She smiled at him with all the innocence that she could muster.

It was a great surprise to him. He had not known that they had so much money; they had never been able to buy anything but coconuts or bananas before, since he had been with them.“You buy?”he asked.

She nodded.“From Limau. Very good mishi for us all tonight.”

“Where get money?”he inquired. Suspicion had not dawned, for they had never deceived him before; he was just curious.

For one fleeting moment Jean toyed with the idea of saying they had sold some jewellery, with a quick, intuitive feeling that it would be better not to mention the Australians. But she put the idea away; she must stick to the story that they had prepared and considered from all angles.“Man prisoner give us money for chicken,”she said.“They say we too thin. Now we have good mishi tonight, Japanese and prisoner also.”

He put up two fingers.“Two.”

She went up in a sheet of flame.“One, not two, gunso,”she said.“This is a present for you, because you have been kind and carried children, and allowed us to walk slowly. Five only, five.”She showed him the sack, and he counted them carefully. It was only then that she took note of the fact that the birds were rather unusually large for the East, and jet black all over.“One for you, four for us.”

He let the sack fall, and nodded; then he smiled at her, tucked the cockerel under his arm, and walked off with it towards the kitchen where his meal was in preparation.

That day there was a considerable row in progress at Kuantan. The local commanding officer was a Captain Sugamo, who was executed by the Allied War Crimes Tribunal in the year 1946 after trial for atrocities committed at Camp 302 on the Burma-Siam railway in the years 1943 and 1944: his duty in Kuantan at that time was to see to the evacuation of the railway material from the eastern railway in Malaya and to its shipment to Siam. He lived in the house formerly occupied by the District Commissioner of Kuantan, and the District Commissioner had kept a fine little flock of about twenty black Leghorn fowls, specially imported from England in 1939. When Captain Sugamo woke up that morning, five of his twenty black Leghorns were missing, with a green sack that had once held the mail for the District Commissioner, and was now used to store grain for the fowls.

Captain Sugamo was a very angry man. He called the Military Police and set them to work; their suspicion fell at once upon the Australian truck drivers, who had a record for petty larceny in that district. Moreover, they had considerable opportunities, because the nature of their work allowed them a great deal of freedom; trucks had to be serviced and refuelled, often in the hours of darkness when it was difficult to ascertain exactly where each man might be. Their camp was searched that day for any sign of telltale feathers, or the sack, but nothing was discovered but a cache of tinned foods and cigarettes stolen from the quartermaster's store.

Captain Sugamo was not satisfied and he became more angry than ever. A question of face was now involved, because this theft from the commanding officer was a clear insult to his position, and so to the Imperial Japanese Army. He ordered a search of the entire town of Kuantan: on the following day every house was entered by troops working under the directions of the military Police to look for signs of the black feathers or the green sack. It yielded no result.

Brooding over the insults levelled at his uniform, the captain ordered the barracks of the company of soldiers under his command to be searched. There was no result from that.

There remained one further avenue. Three of the trucks, driven by Australians, were up-country on the road to or from Jerantut. Next day Sugamo dispatched a light truck up the road manned by four men of his military police, to search these trucks and to interrogate the drivers and the guards, and anybody else who might have knowledge of the matter. Between Pohoi and Blat they came upon a crowd of women and children walking down the road loaded with bundles; ahead of them marched a Japanese sergeant with his rifle slung over one shoulder and a green sack over the other. The truck stopped with a squeal of brakes.

For the next two hours Jean stuck to her story, that the Australian had given her money and she had bought the fowls from Limau. They put her through a sort of third degree there on the road, with an insistent reiteration of questions: when they felt that her attention was wandering they slapped her face, kicked her shins, or stamped on her bare feet with army boots. She stuck to it with desperate resolution, knowing that it was a rotten story, knowing that they disbelieved her, not knowing what else she could say. At the end of that time a convoy of three trucks came down the road; the driver of the second one, Joe Harman, was recognized by the sergeant immediately, and brought before Jean at the point of the bayonet. The sergeant of the Military Police said,“Is this man?”

Jean said desperately,“I've been telling them about the four dollars you gave me to buy the chickens with, Joe, but they won't believe me.”

The military policeman said,“You steal chickens from the shoko. Here is bag.”

The ringer looked at the girl's bleeding face and at her bleeding feet.“Leave her alone, you bloody mucking bastards,”he said angrily in his slow Queensland drawl.“I stole those mucking chickens, and I gave them to her. So what?”

Darkness was closing down in my London sitting-room, the early darkness of a stormy afternoon. The rain still beat upon the window. The girl sat staring into the fire, immersed in her sad memories.“They crucified him,”she said quietly.“They took us all down to Kuantan, and they nailed his hands to a tree, and beat him to death. They kept us there, and made us look on while they did it.”

Chapter 4

“My dear,”I said.“I am so very sorry.”

She raised her head.“You don't have to be sorry,”she replied.“It was one of those things that seem to happen in a war. It's a long time ago, now—nearly six years. And Captain Sugamo was hung—not for that, but for what he did upon the railway. It's all over and done with now, and nearly forgotten.”

There was, of course, no women's camp in Kuantan, and Captain Sugamo was not the man to be bothered with a lot of women and children. The execution took place at midday at a tree that stood beside the recreation ground overlooking the tennis courts: as soon as the maimed, bleeding body hanging by its hands had ceased to twitch Captain Sugamo stood them in parade before him.

“You very bad people,”he said.“No place here for you. I send you to Kota Bahru. You walk now.”

They stumbled off without a word, in desperate hurry to get clear of that place of horror. The same sergeant that had escorted them from Gemas was sent with them, for he also was disgraced as having shared the chickens. It was as a punishment that he was ordered to continue with them, because all prisoners are disgraceful and dishonourable creatures in the eyes of the Japanese, and to guard them and escort them is an insulting and a menial job fit only for the lowest type of man. An honourable Japanese would kill himself rather than be taken prisoner. Perhaps to emphasize this point the private soldier was taken away, so that from Kuantan onwards the sergeant was their only guard.

So they took up their journey again, living from day to day. They left Kuantan about the middle of July. It is about two hundred miles from Kuantan to Kota Bahru: allowing for halts of several days for illness Jean anticipated it would take them two months at least to get there.

They got to Besarah on the first day: this is a fishing village on the sea, with white coral sand and palm trees at the head of the beach. It is a very lovely place but they slept little, for most of the children were awake and crying in the night with memories of the horror they had seen. They could not bear to stay so close to Kuantan and travelled on next day another short stage to Balok, another fishing village on another beach with more palm trees. Here they rested for a day.

Gradually they came to realize that they had entered a new land. The north-east coast of Malaya is a very lovely country, and comparatively healthy. It is beautiful, with rocky headlands and long, sweeping, sandy beaches fringed with palm trees, and usually there is a freshwind from the sea. Moreover there is an abundance of fresh fish in all the villages. For the first time since they left Panong the women had sufficient protein with their rice, and their health began to show an improvement at once. Most of them bathed in the warm sea at least once every day, and certain of the skin diseases that they suffered from began to heal with this salt water treatment, though not all. For the first time in months the children had sufficient energy to play.

They all improved, in fact, except the sergeant. The sergeant was suspicious of them now; he seldom carried a child or helped them in any way. He seemed to feel the reproofs that he had been given very much, and he had now no companion of his own race to talk to. He moped a great deal, sitting sullenly aloof from them in the evenings; once or twice Jean caught herself consciously trying to cheer him up, a queer reversal of the role of prisoner and guard. Upon this route they met very few Japanese. Occasionally they would find a detachment stationed in a river village or at an airstrip; when they came to such a unit the sergeant would smarten himself up and go and report to the officer in charge, who would usually come and inspect them. But there is very little industry between Kuantan and Kota Bahru and no town larger than a fishing village, nor was there any prospect of an enemy attack upon the eastern side of the Malay Peninsula. On several occasions a week passed without the women seeing any Japanese at all except the sergeant.

As they travelled slowly up the coast the condition of the women and the children altered greatly for the better. They were now a very different party from the helpless people who had started off from Panong nearly six months before. Death had ruthlessly eliminated the weakest members and reduced them to about half the original numbers, which made all problems of billeting and feeding in the villages far easier. They were infinitely more experienced by that time, too. They had learned to use the native remedies for malaria and dysentery, to clothe themselves and wash and sleep in the native manner; in consequence they now had far more leisure than when they had been fighting to maintain a western style of life in primitive conditions. The march of ten miles every other day was now no longer a great burden; in the intervening day they had more time for the children. Presently Mrs Warner, who at one time had been an elementary schoolmistress, started a class for the children, and school became a regular institution on their day of rest.

Jean began to teach her baby, Robin Holland, how to walk. He was quite fit and healthy again, and getting quite a weight for her to carry, for he was now sixteen months old. She never burdened him with any clothes in that warm climate, and he crawled about naked in the shade of palm or casuarina trees, or in the sun upon the sand, like any Malay baby. He got nearly as brown as one, too.

In the weeks that followed they moved slowly northwards up the coast, through all the many fishing villages, Ular and Chendar and Kalong and Penunjok and Kemasik and many others. They had a little sickness and spent a few days here and there while various members of the party sweated out a fever, but they had no more deaths. The final horror at Kuantan was a matter that they never spoke about at all, each fearing to recall it to the memory of the others, but each was secretly of the opinion that it had changed their luck.

With Mrs Frith this impression struck much deeper. She was a devout little woman who said her prayers morning and evening with the greatest regularity. It was Mrs Frith who always knew when Sunday was: on that day she would read the Prayer Book and the Bible for an hour aloud to anyone who came to listen to her. If it was their rest day she would hold this service at eleven o'clock as near as she could guess it, because that was the correct time for Matins.

Mrs Frith sought for the hand of God in everything that happened to them. Brooding over their experiences with this in mind, she was struck by certain similarities. She had read repeatedly about one Crucifixion; now there had been another. The Australian, in her mind, had had the power of healing, because the medicines he brought had cured her dysentery and Johnnie Horsefall's ringworm. It was beyond all doubt that they had been blessed in every way since his death for them. God had sent down His Son to earth in Palestine. What if He had done it again in Malaya?

Men and women who are in great and prolonged distress and forced into an entirely novel way of life, divorced entirely from their previous association, frequently develop curious mental traits. Mrs Frith did not thrust her views upon them, yet inevitably the matter that she was beginning to believe herself became known to the other women. It was received with incredulity at first, but as a matter that required the most deep and serious thought. Most of the women had been churchgoers when they got the chance, mostly of Low Church sects; deep in their hearts they had been longing for the help of God. As their physical health improved throughout these weeks, their capacity for religious thought increased, and, as the weeks went on, accurate memory of the Australian began to fade, and was replaced by an awed and roseate memory of the man he had not been. If this incredible event that Mrs Frith believed could possibly be true, it meant indeed that they were in the hand of God; nothing could touch them then; they would win through and live through all their troubles and one day they would regain their homes, their husbands, and their western way of life. They marched on with renewed strength.

Jean did nothing to dispel these fancies, which were evidently helpful to the women, but she was not herself impressed. She was the youngest of all of them, and the only one unmarried; she had formed a very different idea of Joe Harman. She knew him for a very human, very normal man; she had grown prettier, she knew, when he had come to talk to her, and more attractive. It had been a subconscious measure of defence that had led her to allow him to continue to refer to her as Mrs Boong; if the baby on her hip had misled him into classing her with all the other married women, that was just as well. In those villages, in the hot tropic nights when they wore little clothing, in that place of extraordinary standards or no standards at all, she knew that anything might have happened between them if he had known that she was an unmarried girl, and it might well have happened very quickly. Her grief for him was more real and far deeper than that of the other women, and it was not in the least because she thought that he had been divine. She was entirely certain in her own mind that he wasn't.

Toward the end of August they were in a village called Kuala Telang about half way between Kuantan and Kota Bahru. The Telang is a short, muddy river that wanders through a flat country of rice fields to the sea; the village stands on the south bank of the river just inside the sand bar at the mouth. It is a pretty place of palm and casuarina trees and long white beaches on which the rollers of the South China Sea break in surf. The village lives upon the fishing and on the rice fields. About fifteen fishing-boats operate from the river, big open sailing-boats with strange, high, flat figureheads at bow and stern. There is a sort of village square with wood and palm-leaf native shops grouped round about it; behind this stands a godown for the rice beside the river bank. This godown was empty at the time, and it was here that the party was accommodated.

The Japanese sergeant fell ill with fever here, probably malaria. He had not been himself since Kuantan; he had been sullen and depressed, and he seemed to feel the lack of companionship very much. As the women had grown stronger so he had grown weaker, and this was strange to them at first, because he had never been ill before. At first they had been pleased and relieved that this queer, ugly, uncouth little man was in eclipse, but as he grew more unhappy they suffered a strange reversal of feeling. He had been with them for a long time and he had done what was possible within the limits of his duty to alleviate their lot; he had carried their children willingly and he had wept when children died. When it was obvious that he had fever they took turns at carrying his rifle and his tunic and his boots and his pack for him, so that they arrived in the village as a queer procession, Mrs Warner leading the little yellow man clad only in his trousers, stumbling about in a daze. He walked more comfortably barefoot. Behind them came the other women carrying all his equipment as well as their own burdens.

Jean found the headman, a man of about fifty called Mat Amin bin Taib, and explained the situation to him.“We are prisoners,”she said,“marching from Kuantan to Kota Bahru, and this Japanese is our guard. He is ill with fever, and we must find a shady house for him to lie in. He has authority to sign chits in the name of the Imperial Japanese Army for our food and accommodation, and he will do this for you when he recovers; he will give you a paper. We must have a place to sleep ourselves, and food.”

Mat Amin said,“I have no place where white Mems would like to sleep.”

Jean said,“We are not white mems any longer; we are prisoners and we are accustomed to living as your women live. All we need is a shelter and a floor to sleep on, and the use of cooking pots, and rice, and a little fish or meat and vegetables.”

“You can have what we have ourselves,”he said,“but it is strange to see mems living so.”

He took the sergeant into his own house and produced a mattress stuffed with coconut fibre and a pillow of the same material; he had a mosquito net which was evidently his own and he offered this, but the women refused it because they knew the sergeant needed all the cooling breezes he could get. They made him take his trousers off and get into a sarong and lie down on the bed. They had no quinine left, but the headman produced a draught of his own concoction and they gave the sergeant some of this, and left him in the care of the headman's wife, and went to find their own quarters and food.

The fever was high all that night; in the morning when they came to see how he was getting on they did not like the look of him at all. He was still in a high fever and he was very much weaker than he had been; it seemed to them that he was giving up, and that was a bad sign. They took turns all that day to sit with him and bathe his face, and wash him; from time to time they talked to him to try and stimulate his interest, but without a great deal of success. In the evening Jean was sitting with him; he lay inert upon his back, sweating profusely; he did not answer anything she said.

Looking for something to attract his interest, she pulled his tunic to her and felt in the pocket for his paybook. She found a photograph in it, a photograph of a Japanese woman and four children standing by the entrance to a house. She said,“Your children, gunso?”and gave it to him. He took it without speaking and looked at it; then he gave it back to her and motioned to her to put it away again.

When she had laid the jacket down she looked at him and saw that tears were oozing from his eyes and falling down to mingle with the sweat beads on his cheeks. Very gently she wiped them away.

He grew weaker and weaker, and two days later he died in the night. There seemed no particular reason why he should have died, but the disgrace of Kuantan was heavy on him and he seemed to have lost interest and the will to live. They buried him that day in the Moslem cemetery outside the village, and most of them wept a little for him as an old and valued friend.

The death of the sergeant left them in a most unusual position, for they were now prisoners without a guard. They discussed it at some length that evening after the funeral.“I don't see why we shouldn't stay here, where we are,”said Mrs Frith.“It's a nice place, this is, as nice as any that we've come to. That's what He said, we ought to find a place where we'd be out of the way, and just live there.”

Jean said,“I know. There's two things we'd have to settle though. First, the Japs are bound to find out sometime that we're living here, and then the headman will get into trouble for having allowed us to stay here without telling them. They'd probably kill him. You know what they are.”

“Maybe they wouldn't find us, after all,”said Mrs Price.

“I don't believe Mat Amin is the man to take that risk,”Jean said.“There isn't any reason why he should. If we stay he'll go straight to the Japanese and tell them that we're here.”She paused.“The other thing is that we can't expect this village to go on feeding seventeen of us for ever just because we're white mems. They'll go and tell the Japs about us just to get rid of us.”

Mrs Frith said shrewdly,“We could grow our own food, perhaps. Half the paddy fields we walked by coming in haven't been planted this year.”

Jean stared at her.“That's quite right—they haven't. I wonder why that is?”

“All the men must have gone to the war,”said Mrs Warner.“Working as coolies taking up that railway line, or something of that.”

Jean said slowly,“What would you think of this? Suppose I go and tell Mat Amin that we'll work in the rice fields if he'll let us stay here? What would you think of that?”

Mrs Price laughed.“Me, with my figure? Walking about in mud and water up to the knee planting them little seedlings in the mud, like you see the Malay girls doing?”

Jean said apologetically,“It was just a thought.”

“And a very good one, too,”said Mrs Warner.“I wouldn't mind working in the paddy fields if we could stay here and live comfortable and settled.”

Mrs Frith said,“If we were growing rice like that, maybe they'd let us stay here—the Japs I mean. After all, in that way we'd be doing something useful, instead of walking all over the country like a lot of whipped dogs with no home.”

Next morning Jean went to the headman. She put her hands together in the praying gesture of greeting, and smiled at him and said in Malay,“Mat Amin, why do we see the paddy fields not sown this year? We saw so many of them as we came to this place, not sown at all.”

He said,“Most of the men, except the fishermen, are working for the army.”He meant the Japanese Army.

“On the railway?”

“No. They are at Gong Kedak. They are making a long piece of land flat, and making roads, and covering the land they have made flat with tar and stones, so that aeroplanes can come down there.”

“Are they coming back soon to plant paddy?”

“It is in the hand of God, but I do not think they will come back for many months. I have heard that after they have done this thing at Gong Kedak, there is another such place to be made at Machang, and another at Tan Yongmat. Once a man falls into the power of the Japanese it is not easy for him to escape and come back to his home.”

“Who, then, will plant the paddy, and reap it?”

“The women will do what they can. Rice will be short next year, not here, because we shall not sell the paddy that we need to eat ourselves. We shall not have enough to sell to the Japanese. I do not know what they are going to eat, but it will not be rice.”

Jean said,“Mat Amin, I have serious matters to discuss with you. If there were a man amongst us I would send him to talk for us, but there is no man. You will not be offended if I ask you to talk business with a woman, on behalf of women?”She now knew something of the right approach to a Mohammedan.

He bowed to her, and led her to his house. There was a small rickety veranda; they went up to this and sat down upon the floor facing each other. He was a level-eyed old man with close-cropped hair and a small, clipped moustache, naked to the waist and wearing a sarong; his face was firm, but not unkind. He called sharply to his wife within the house to bring out coffee.

Jean waited till the coffee appeared, making small talk for politeness; she knew the form after six months in the villages. It came in two thick glasses, without milk and sweet with sugar. She bowed to him, and lifted her glass and sipped, and set it down again.“We are in a difficulty,”she said frankly.“Our guard is dead, and what now will become of us is in our own hands—and in yours. You know our story. We were taken prisoner at Panong, and since then we have walked many hundreds of miles to this place. No Japanese commander will receive us and put us in a camp and feed us and attend to us in illness, because each commander thinks that these things are the duty of the other; so they march us under guard from town to town. This has been going on now for more than six months, and in that time half of our party have died upon the road.”

He inclined his head.

“Now that our gunso is dead,”she said,“what shall we do? If we go on until we find a Japanese officer and report to him, he will not want us; nobody in all this country wants us They will not kill us quickly, as they might if we were men. They will get us out of the way by marching us on to some other place, perhaps into a country of swamps such as we have come through. So we shall grow ill again, and one by one we shall all die. That is what lies ahead of us, if we report now to the Japanese.”

He replied,“It is written that the angels said, ‘Every soul shall taste of death, and we will prove you with evil and with good for a trial of you, and unto us shall ye return.’”

She thought quickly; the words of the headman at Dilit came into her mind. She said,“It is also written, ‘If you be kind towards women and fear to wrong them, God is well acquainted with what ye do.’”

He eyed her steadily.“Where is that written?”

She said,“In the Fourth Surah.”

“Are you of the Faith?”he asked incredulously.

She shook her head.“I do not want to deceive you. I am a Christian; we are all Christians. The headman of a village on our road was kind to us, and when I thanked him he said that to me. I do not know the Koran.”

“You are a very clever woman,”he said.“Tell me what you want.”

“I want our party to stay here, in this village,”she said,“and go to work in the paddy fields, as your women do.”He stared at her, astonished.“This will be dangerous for you,”she said. We know that very well. If Japanese officers find us in this place before you have reported to them that we are here, they will be very angry. And so, I want you to do this. I want you to let us go to work at once with one or two of your women to show us what to do. We will work all day for our food alone and a place to sleep. When we have worked so for two weeks, I will go myself and find an officer and report to him, and tell him what we are doing. And you shall come with me, as headman of this village, and you shall tell the officer that more rice will be grown for the Japanese if we are allowed to continue working in the rice fields. These are the things I want.”

“I have never heard of white mems working in the paddy fields,”he said.

She asked,“Have you ever heard of white mems marching and dying as we have marched and died?”

He was silent.

“We are in your hands,”she said.“If you say, go upon your way and walk on to some other place, then we must go, and going we must die. That will then be a matter between you and God. If you allow us to stay and cultivate your fields and live with you in peace and safety, you will get great honour when the English Tuans return to this country after their victory. Because they will win this war in the end; these Short Ones are in power now, but they cannot win against the Americans and all the free peoples of the world. One day the English Tuans will come back.”

He said,“I shall be glad to see that day.”

They sat in silence for a time, sipping the glasses of coffee. Presently the headman said,“This is a matter not to be decided lightly, for it concerns the whole village. I will think about it and I will talk it over with my brothers.”

Jean went away, and that evening after the hour of evening prayer she saw a gathering of men squatting with the headman in front of his house; they were all old men, because there were very few young ones in Kuala Telang at that time, and young ones probably would not have been admitted to the conference in any case. Later that evening Mat Amin came to the godown and asked for Mem Paget; Jean came out to him, carrying the baby. She stood talking to him in the light of a small oil lamp.

“We have discussed this matter that we talked about,”he said.“It is a strange thing, that white mems should work in our rice fields, and some of my brothers are afraid that the white Tuans will not understand when they come back, and that they will be angry, saying we have made you work for us against your will.”

Jean said,“We will give you a letter now, that you can show them if they should say that.”

He shook his head.“It is not necessary. It is sufficient if you tell the Tuans when they come back that this thing was done because you wished it so.”

She said,“That we will do.”

They went to work next day. There were six married women in the party at that time, and Jean, and ten children including Jean's baby. The headman took them out to the fields with two Malay girls, Fatimah binti Darus and Raihana binti Hassan. He gave them seven small fields covered in weeds to start upon, an area that was easily within their power to manage. There was a roofed platform nearby in the fields for resting in the shade; they left the youngest children here and went to work.

The seven women were all fairly robust; the journey had eliminated the ones who would have been unable to stand agricultural work. Those who were left were women of determination and grit, with high morale and a good sense of humour. As soon as they became accustomed to the novelty of working ankle-deep in mud and water they did not find the work exacting, and presently as they became accustomed to it they were seized with an ambition to show the village that white mems could do as much work as Malay women, or more.

Paddy is grown in little fields surrounded by a low wall of earth, so that water from a stream can be led into the field at will to turn it into a shallow pool. When the water is let out again the earth bottom is soft mud, and weeds can be pulled out by hand and the ground hoed and prepared for the seedlings. The seedlings are raised by scattering the rice in a similar nursery field, and they are then transplanted in rows into the muddy field. The field is then flooded again for a few days while the seedlings stand with their heads above the water in the hot sun, and the water is let out again for a few days to let the sun get to the roots. With alternating flood and dry in that hot climate the plants grow very quickly to about the height of wheat, with feathery ears of rice on top of the stalks. The rice is harvested by cutting off the ears with a little knife, leaving the straw standing, and is taken in sacks to the village to be winnowed. Water buffaloes are then turned in to eat the straw and fertilize the ground and tramp it all about, and the ground is ready for sowing again to repeat the cycle. Two crops a year are normally got from the rice fields, and there is no rotation of crop.

Working in these fields is not unpleasant when you get accustomed to it. There are worse things to do in a very hot country than to put on a large conical sun-hat of plaited palm leaves and take off most of your clothes, and play about with mud and water, damming and diverting little trickling streams. By the end of the fortnight the women had settled down to it and quite liked the work, and all the children loved it from the first. No Japanese came near the village in that time.

On the sixteenth day Jean started out with the headman, Mat Amin, to go and look for the Japanese; they carried the sergeant's rifle and equipment, and his uniform, and his paybook. There was a place called Kuala Rakit twenty-seven miles away where a Japanese detachment was stationed, and they went there.

They took two days to walk this distance, staying overnight at a place called Bukit Perah. They stayed with the headman there, Jean sleeping in the back quarters with the women. They went on next day and came to Kuala Rakit in the evening; it was a very large village, or small town. Here Mat Amin took her to see an official of the Malay administration at his house, Tungku Bentara Raja. Tungku Bentara was a little thin Malay who spoke excellent English; he was genuinely concerned at the story that he heard from Mat Amin and from Jean.

“I am very, very sorry,”he said at last.“I cannot do much to help you directly, because the Japanese control everything we do. It is terrible that you should have to work in the rice fields.”

“That's not terrible at all,”Jean said.“As a matter of fact, we rather like it. We want to stay there, with Mat Amin here. If the Japanese have got a camp for women in this district I suppose they'll put us into that, but if they haven't, we don't want to go on marching all over Malaya. Half of us have died already doing that.”

“You must stay with us tonight,”he said.“Tomorrow I will have a talk with the Japanese Civil Administrator. There is no camp here for women, anyway.”

That night Jean slept in a bed for the first time in nearly seven months. She did not care for it much; having grown used to sleeping on the floor she found it cooler to sleep so than to sleep on a mattress. She did not actually get out of bed and sleep upon the floor, but she came very near to it. The bath and shower after the bath taken by holding a gourd full of water over her head, however, were a joy, and she spent a long time washing.

In the morning she went with Tungku Bentara and Mat Amin to the Japanese Civil Administrator, and told her tale again. The Civil Administrator had been to the State University of California and spoke first-class American English; he was sympathetic, but declared that prisoners were nothing to do with him, being the concern of the Army. He came with them, however, to see the military commanding officer, a Colonel Matisaka, and Jean told her tale once more.

It was quite clear that Colonel Matisaka considered women prisoners to be a nuisance, and he had no intention whatsoever of diverting any portion of his force to guarding them. Left to himself he would probably have sent them marching on, but with Tungku Bentara and the Civil Administrator in his office and acquainted with the facts he could hardly do that. In the end he washed his hands of the whole thing and told the Civil Administrator to make what arrangements he thought best. The Civil Administrator told Bentara that the women could stay where they were for the time being, and Jean started back for Kuala Telang with Mat Amin.

They lived there for three years.

“It was three years wasted, just chopped out of one's life,”she said. She raised her head and looked at me, hesitantly.“At least—I suppose it was. I know a lot about Malays, but that's not worth much here in England.”

“You won't know if it was wasted until you come to the end of your life,”I said.“Perhaps not then.”

She nodded.“I suppose that's right.”She took up the poker and began scraping the ash from the bars of the grate.“They were so very kind to us,”she said.“They couldn't have been nicer, within the limits of what they are and what they've got. Fatimah, the girl who showed us what to do in the rice fields in those first weeks—she was a perfect dear. I got to know her very well indeed.”

“Is that where you want to go back to?”I asked.

She nodded.“I would like to do something for them, now that I've got this money. We lived with them for three years, and they did everything for us. We'd have all died before the war was ended if they hadn't taken us in and let us stay with them. And now I've got so much, and they so very, very little...”

“Don't forget you haven't got as much as all that,”I said.“Travelling to Malaya is a very expensive journey.”

She smiled.“I know. What I want to do for them won't cost so very much—not more than fifty pounds, if that. We had to carry water in that village—that's the women's work—and it's a fearful job. You see, the river's tidal at the village so the water's brackish; you can use it for washing in or rinsing out your clothes, but drinking water has to be fetched from the spring, nearly a mile away. We used to go for it with gourds, two in each hand with a stick between them, morning and evening—a mile there and a mile back—four miles a day. Fatimah and the other girls didn't think about it; it's what the village has done always, generation after generation.”

“That's why you want to dig a well?”

She nodded.“It's something I could do for them, for the women—something that would make life easier for them, as they made life easier for us. A well right in the middle of the village, within a couple of hundred yards of every house. It's what they ought to have. I'm sure it wouldn't have to be more than about ten feet deep, because there's water all about. The water level can't be more than about ten feet down, or fifteen feet at the most. I thought if I went back there and offered to engage a gang of well-diggers to do this for them, it'ld sort of wind things up. And after that I could enjoy this money with a clear conscience.”She looked up at me again.“You don't think that's silly, do you?”

“No,”I said.“I don't think that. The only thing is, I wish it wasn't quite so far away. Travelling there and back will make a very big hole in a year's income.”

“I know that,”she said.“If I run out of money, I'll take a job in Singapore or somewhere for a few months and save up a bit.”

“As a matter of interest,”I said,“why didn't you stay out there and get a job? You know the country so well.”

She said,“I had a scunner of it, then—in 1945. We were all dying to get home. They sent three trucks for us from Kota Bahru, and we were taken to the airfield there and flown down to Singapore in a Dakota with an Australian crew. And there I met Bill Holland, and I had to tell him about Eileen, and Freddie and Jane.”Her voice dropped.“All the family, except Robin; he was four years old by that time, and quite a sturdy little chap. They let me travel home with Bill and Robin, to look after Robin. He looked on me as his mother, of course.”

She smiled a little.“Bill wanted to make it permanent,”she said.“I couldn't do that. I couldn't have been the sort of wife he wanted.”

I said nothing.

“When we landed, England was so green and beautiful,”she said.“I wanted to forget about the war, and forget about the East, and grow to be an ordinary person again. I got this job with Pack and Levy and I've been there two years now—ladies' handbags and attaché cases for the luxury trade, nothing to do with wars or sickness or death. I've had a happy time there, on the whole.”

She was very much alone when she got home. She had cabled to her mother directly she reached Singapore; there was a long delay, and then she got a cable in reply from her Aunt Agatha in Colwyn Bay, breaking to her the news that her mother was dead. Before she left Singapore she heard that her brother Donald had died upon the Burma-Siam railway. She must have felt very much alone in the world when she regained her freedom; it seemed to me that she had shown great strength of character in refusing an offer of marriage at that time. She landed at Liverpool, and went to stay for a few weeks with her Aunt Agatha at Colwyn Bay; then she went down to London to look for a job.

I asked her why she had not got in touch with her uncle, the old man at Ayr.“Quite honestly,”she said,“I forgot all about him, or if I thought of him at all I thought he was dead, too. I only saw him once, that time when I was eleven years old, and he looked about dead then. It never entered my head that he would still be alive. Mother's estate was all wound up, and there were very few of her personal papers left, because they were all in the Pagets' house in Southampton when that got blitzed. If I had thought about Uncle Douglas I wouldn't have known where he lived...”

It was still pouring with rain. We decided to give up the idea of going out that afternoon, and to have tea in my flat. She went out into my little kitchen and began getting it, and I busied myself with laying the tea table and cutting bread and butter. When she came in with the tray, I asked,“When do you think of going to Malaya, then?”

She said,“I thought I'd book my passage for the end of May, and go on working at Pack and Levy up till then,”she said.“That's about another six weeks. By then I'll have enough saved up to pay my passage out and home, and I'll still have about sixty pounds I saved out of my wages in this last two years.”She had been into the cost of her journey, and had found a line of intermediate class cargo ships that took about a dozen passengers for a relatively modest fare to Singapore.“I think I'll have to fly to Kota Bahru from Singapore,”she said.“Malayan Airways go to Kuantan and then to Kota Bahru. I don't know how I'll get from Kota Bahru to Kuala Telang, but I expect there'll be something.”

She was quite capable of walking it, I thought; a journey through the heart of Malaya could mean little to her now. I had had the atlas out while she had been telling me her story to see where the places were, and I looked at it again now.“You could get off the aeroplane at Kuantan,”I said.“It's shorter from there.”

“I know,”she said,“I know it's a bit shorter. But I couldn't bear to go back there again.”There was distress in her voice.

To ease the situation I said idly,“It would take me years to learn how to remember these Malay names.”

“It's all right when you know what they mean,”she said.“They're just like English names. Bahru means New, and Kota means a fort. It's only Newcastle, in Malay.”

She went on with her work at Perivale, and I went on with mine in Chancery Lane, but I was unable to get her story out of my mind. There is a man called Wright, a member of my club, who was in the Malayan Police and was a prisoner of the Japanese during their occupation of Malaya, I think in Changi gaol. I sat next to him at dinner one night, and I could not resist sounding him about it.“One of my clients told me an extraordinary story about Malaya the other day,”I said.“She was one of a party of women that the Japanese refused to put into a camp.”

He laid his knife down.“Not the party who were taken at Panong and marched across Malaya?”

“That was it,”I said.“You know about them, do you?”

“Oh yes,”he said.“It was a most extraordinary thing, as you say. The Japanese commanders marched them from place to place, till finally they were allowed to settle in a village on the east coast somewhere, and they lived there for the rest of the war. There was a very fine girl who was their leader; she spoke Malay fluently. She wasn't anybody notable; she'd been a shorthand typist in an office in Kuala Lumpur. A very fine type.”

I nodded.“She's my client.”

“Is she! I always wondered what had happened to her. What's she doing now?”

I said dryly,“She's a shorthand typist again, working in a handbag factory at Perivale.”

“Really!”He ate a mouthful or two, and then he said,“I always thought that girl ought to have got a decoration of some sort. Unfortunately, there's nothing you can give to people like that. But if she hadn't been with them, all those women and children would have died. There was no one else in the party of that calibre at all.”

“I understand that half of them did die,”I said.

He nodded.“I believe that's true. She got them settled down and working in the rice fields in the end, and after that they were all right.”

I saw Jean Paget from time to time in the six weeks before she left this country. She booked her passage to sail from London docks on June 2nd, and she gave notice to her firm to leave at the end of May. She told me that they were rather upset about it, and they offered her a ten shilling rise at once; in view of that she had told Mr Pack about her legacy, and he had accepted the inevitable.

I made arrangements for her income for the months of July and August and September to be available to her in Singapore, and I opened an account for her with the Chartered Bank for that purpose. As the time for her departure drew closer I became worried for her, not because I was afraid that she would overspend her income, but because I was afraid she would get into some difficulty due to her expenses being higher than she thought they would be. Nine hundred a year does not go very far in these days for a person travelling about the east.

I mentioned that to her about a week before she left.“Don't forget that you're a fairly wealthy woman now,”I said.“You're quite right to live within your income and, indeed, I have to see you do. But don't forget that I have fairly wide discretionary powers under your uncle's will. If you get into any difficulty, or if you really need money, let me have a cable at once. As, for example, if you should get ill.”

She smiled.“That's very sweet of you,”she said.“But honestly, I think I'll be all right. I'm counting upon taking a job if I find I'm running short. After all, I haven't got to get back here to England by a given date, or anything like that.”

I said,“Don't stay too long away.”

She smiled.“I shan't Mr Strachan,”she said.“There's nothing to keep me in Malaya once I've done this thing.”

She was giving up her room in Ealing, of course, and she asked if she might leave a trunk and a suitcase in the box-room of my flat till she came back to England. She brought them round the day before she sailed, and with them a pair of skating boots with skates attached, which wouldn't go into the trunk. She told me then that she was only taking one suitcase as her luggage.

“But what about your tropical kit?”I asked.“Have you had that sent on?”

She smiled.“I've got it with me in the suitcase,”she said.“Fifty Paludrine tablets and a hundred Sulphatriads, some repellent, and my old sarong. I'm not going out to be a lady in Malaya.”

She had nobody but me to go down to the docks with her to see her off; she was very much alone in the world, and friends she had who might have liked to come were all working in jobs, and couldn't get the time off. I drove her down in a taxi. She took her journey very much as a matter of course; she seemed to have made no more preparation for a voyage half way round the world than a girl of my generation would have made for a weekend at Chislehurst. The ship was a new one and everything was bright and clean. When the steward opened the door of her cabin she stood back amazed, because he had arranged the flowers all round the little room, and there were plenty of them.“Oh Noel, look!”she said.“Just look at all the flowers!”She turned to the steward.“Wherever did they come from? Not from the Company?”

“They come in three big boxes yesterday evening,”he replied.“Make a nice show, don't they, Miss?”

She swung round on me.“I believe you sent them.”And then she said,“Oh, how perfectly sweet of you!”

“English flowers,”I said.“Just to remind you to come back to England soon.”I must have had a premonition, even then, that she was never going to come back.

Before I could realize what she was doing, she had slipped an arm round my shoulders and kissed me on the lips.“That's for the flowers, Noel,”she said softly.“For the flowers, and for everything you've done for me.”And I was so dumbfounded and confused that all I could find to say to her was,“I'll have another of those when you come back.”

I didn't wait to see her ship go off, because partings are stupid things and best got over quickly. I went back in the taxi to my flat alone, and I remember that I stood for a long time at the window of my room watching the ornamented wall of the stables opposite and thinking of her fine new steamer going down the river past Gravesend and Tilbury, past Shoebury and the North Foreland, taking her away. And then I woke myself up and went and shifted her trunk and her suitcase to a corner of the box-room by themselves, and I stood for some time with her boots and skates in my hand, personal things of hers, wondering where they had better go. Finally I took them to my bedroom and put them in the bottom of my wardrobe, because I should never have forgiven myself if they had been stolen. She was just such a girl as one would have liked to have for a daughter, but we never had a daughter at all.

She travelled across half the world in her tramp steamer and she wrote to me from most of the ports she called at, from Marseilles and Naples, from Alexandria and Aden, from Colombo, from Rangoon, and from Penang. Wright was always very interested in her because he had known about her in Malaya, and I got into the habit of carrying her latest letter about with me and telling him about her voyage and how she was getting on. He knew the British Adviser to the Raja at Kota Bahru quite well, a Mr Wilson-Hays, and I got him to write out to Wilson-Hays by air mail telling him about Jean Paget and asking him to do what he could for her. He told me that that was rather necessary, because there was nowhere a lady could stay in Kota Bahru except with one of the British people who were living there. We got a very friendly letter back from Wilson-Hays saying that he was expecting her, and I was able to get a letter out to her by air mail to meet her at the Chartered Bank telling her what we had done.

She only stayed one night in Singapore, and took the morning plane to Kota Bahru; the Dakota wandered about all over Malaya calling at various places, and put her down upon the air-strip at Kota Bahru early in the afternoon. She got out of the Dakota wearing the same light grey coat and skirt in which she had left London, and Wilson-Hays was there himself to meet the aeroplane, with his wife.

I met Wilson-Hays at the United University Club a year later, when he was on leave. He was a tall, dark, quiet man with rather a long face. He said that she had been a little embarrassed to find that he had come to the airstrip to meet her personally; she did not seem to realize that she was quite a well-known person in that part of Malaya. Wilson-Hays knew all about her long before we wrote to him although, of course, he had heard nothing of her since the end of the war. He had sent word to Mat Amin when he got our letter to tell him that she was coming back to see them, and he had arranged to lend her his jeep with a driver to take her the hundred miles or so to Kuala Telang. I thought that very decent of him, and I told him so. He said that the prestige of the British was higher in the Kuala Telang district after the war was over than it was before, due solely to the presence of this girl and her party; he thought she'd earned the use of a jeep for a few days.

She stayed in the Residency two nights, and bought a few simple articles in the native shops. When she left in the jeep next morning she was wearing native clothes; she left her suitcase and most of her things with Mrs Wilson-Hays. She took with her only what a native woman of good class would take; she wore a faded old blue and white chequered sarong with a white coatee. She wore sandals as a concession to the softness of her feet, and she carried a plain tan Chinese type umbrella as a sunshade. She had done her hair up on top of her head in the native style with a large comb in the middle of it. She carried a small palm-leaf basket, but Mrs Wilson-Hays told her husband there was very little in it; she took a toothbrush but no toothpaste; she took a towel and a cake of antiseptic soap and a few drugs. She took one change of clothes, a new sarong and a flowered cotton top to match; she took three small Woolworth brooches and two rings as little presents for her friends, but she took no cosmetics. That was about all she had.

“I thought her very wise to go like that,”said Wilson-Hays.“If she had gone dressed as an Englishwoman she'd have made them embarrassed. Some of the English residents were quite upset when they heard she'd gone off in native dress—old school tie, and letting down the side, and all that sort of thing. I must say, when I saw her go I thought it was rather a good thing to do.”He paused.“After all, it's how she was dressed all through the war, and nobody talks about her letting down the side then.”

It is a long day in a jeep from Kota Bahru to Kuala Telang; the roads are very poor, and there are four main rivers to be crossed which necessitate ferrying the jeep over in a boat, apart from a large number of fords. It took her fourteen hours to cover the hundred miles, and it was dark when they drove into Kuala Telang. There was a buzz of excitement as the jeep drove through the shadowy village, and people came out of their houses doing up their sarongs; there was a full moon that night, so that there was light enough to see to drive. They stopped in front of the headman's house, and she got out of the jeep a little wearily, and went to him, and put her hands up in the praying gesture, and said in Malay,“I have come back, Mat Amin, lest you should think the white mems have forgotten all about you when their need is past.”

He said,“We have thought and talked about you ever since you went.”And then there were people thronging about them, and she saw Fatimah approaching with a baby in her arms and a toddler hanging on to her sarong, and she pushed through the crowd and took her by the hand, and said,“It is too long since we met.”And there was Raihana, and Safirah binti Yacob, and Safirah binti Taib, and little Ibrahim who squinted, now grown into a young man, and his brother Samat, and old Zubeidah, and Meriam, and many others, some of whom she did not know, because the men had come back from the labour gangs soon after she left Malaya, and there were a number of new faces.

Fatimah was married to a young man called Derahman bin Ismail, and she brought him forward and presented him to the white mem; Jean bowed before him and wished that she had brought a shawl to pull over her face, as would have been polite when being introduced to a strange man. She put her hand up to her face, and said,“Excuse me that I have no veil.”He bowed to her and said,“It is no matter,”and Fatimah broke in and said,“He knows and everybody knows that the white mems never veiled their faces when they lived with us, because different people have different ways. Oh Djeen, we are so happy that you have come back.”

She made arrangements with Mat Amin for the accommodation of the driver, and then went with Fatimah to her husband's house. They asked if she had eaten, and she said no, and they made her a supper of rice and blachan, the highly-spiced paste of ripe prawns and fish that the Malays preserve in an upended concrete drain pipe. And presently, tired out, she made a pillow of her palm-leaf bag and lay down on a mat as she had done a thousand times before, and loosened the sarong around her waist, and slept. It would not be entirely accurate to say that she slept well upon the floor after sleeping in a bed for three years. She woke many times throughout the night, and listened to the noises of the night, and watched the moonlight creep around the house, and she was happy.

She had a talk with Fatimah and Meriam and old Zubeidah next morning, squatting round the cooking-pots behind the house out of the way of the men.“Every day that I have been away I have thought of this place,”she said; it was not precisely true, but near enough.“I have thought of you all living and working as I lived and worked. I was working in England, in an office at books in the way that women have to work in my country, because, as you know, I am a poor woman and I have had to work all my life to earn my living till I find a husband who suits me, and I am very particular.”The women laughed, and old Zubeidah said,“It is very strange that a woman should earn her living in that way.”

Meriam said,“There is a woman of our people working in the bank at Kuala Rakit. I saw her through the window. She was doing something with her fingers on a machine, and it went clock-click-click.”

Jean nodded.“That is how I earn my living in my country, working a machine like that to make a printed letter for the Tuan. But recently my uncle died; he lived far away from me and I have only met him once, but he had no other relatives and I inherited his money, so that now I need not work unless I want to.”A murmur of appreciation went around the women. Two or three more had drifted up to enlarge the circle.“And now having money of my own for the first time in my life, I thought more of you here in Kuala Telang than ever before, and of your kindness to us when we lived with you as prisoners. And it came to me that I should give a thankoffering to this place, and that this thankoffering should be a present from a woman to the women of Kuala Telang, nothing to do with the men.”

There was a pleased and excited little buzz amongst the women who surrounded her. Old Zubeidah said,“It is true, the men get everything.”One or two of the women looked shocked at this heresy.

“I have thought many times,”Jean said,“that there should be a well in this place, so that you should not have to fetch fresh water from the spring morning and evening, but you could walk out of your houses only fifty paces at the most and there would be a well of fresh water with a bucket that you could go to and draw water at any time of the day whenever you had the need of cool, fresh water.”There was a little buzz of appreciation again.“There would be smooth stones around the well where you could sit and talk while the young men work the bucket for you. And close beside the well, I would have an atap house for washing clothes with long slabs of smooth stone or concrete arranged so that you could face each other while you wash, and talk, but all surrounded by an atap wall so that the men will not be able to see.”The buzz rose to an excited clamour.“This is what I want to do, as a thankoffering. I will engage a gang of well-diggers, and they shall dig the well, and I will pay masons for the stonework round the top, and I will pay carpenters to build the washing-house. But for the arrangement inside the house I shall want two or three women of experience to advise me how it should be devised, for the height of the slabs, for concrete pools or channels for the water, and so on. This is the gift of a woman for women, and in this thing the men shall do what women say.”

There was a long clamour of discussion. Some of the women were doubtful if the men would ever allow such a thing, and some were doubtful whether it was not impious to wish to alter the arrangements that had satisfied their mothers and their grandmothers before them. But most were avid for the innovation if it could be achieved; once they were used to the idea they savoured it and turned it over, examining it in every detail and discussing where the well should be and where the washhouse, and where the concrete pools should be, and where the drain. At the end of a couple of hours they had accepted the idea whole-heartedly, and Jean was satisfied that it would fill a real need, and that there was nothing that they would have preferred her to give.

That evening she sat opposite Mat Amin on the small veranda before his house, as she had sat so many times before when matters that concerned the women had to be discussed. She sipped her coffee.“I have come to talk with you,”she said,“because I want to give a thankoffering to this place, that people may remember when the white women came here, and you were kind to them.”

He said,“The wife has been talking of nothing else all day, with other women. They say you want to make a well.”

Jean said,“That is true. This is a thankoffering from all the English mems to Kuala Telang, but because we are women it is fitting that it should be a present for the women of this place. When we lived here it was a great labour, morning and evening, to fetch water from the spring and I was sorry for your women when I thought of them, in England, fetching water all that way. That is why I want my thankoffering to be a well in the middle of the village.”

He said,“The spring was good enough for their mothers and their grandmothers before them. They will get ideas above their station in life if they have a well.”

She said patiently,“They will have more energy to serve you faithfully and kindly if they have this well, Mat Amin. Do you remember Raihana binti Ismail who lost her baby when she was three months' pregnant, carrying this water?”He was shocked that she should speak of such a thing, but English mems would speak of anything.“She was ill for a year after that, and I don't think she was any good to her husband ever again. If the women had had this well I want to give you as a thankoffering, that accident would not have happened.”

He said,“God disposes of the lives of women as well as those of men.”

She smiled gently,“Do I have to remind you, Mat Amin, that it is written, ‘Men's souls are naturally inclined to covetousness; but if ye be kind towards women and fear to wrong them, God is well acquainted with what ye do.’”

He laughed and slapped his thigh.“You said that to me many times when you lived here, whenever you wanted anything, but I have not heard it since.”

“It would be kind to let the women have their well,”she said.

He replied, still laughing,“I say this to you, Si-Jean; that when women want a thing as badly as they want this well that you have promised them, they usually get it. But this is a matter which concerns the village as a whole, and I must consult my brothers.”

The men sat in conference next morning, squatting on their heels in the shade of the atap market house. Presently they sent for Jean and she squatted down with them a little to one side as is fitting for a woman, and they asked her where the well was to be put, and where the atap washhouse. She said that everything was in their hands, but it would be convenient for the women if it was on the patch of ground in front of Chai San's shop, with the atap washhouse west of it and pointing towards Ahmed's house. They all got up then and went to see the ground and discuss it from all angles, and all the women of the village stood around and watched their lords making this important decision, and Djeen talking with them almost as if she was an equal.

She did not hurry them; she had lived three years in this village and she knew the slowness of their mental processes, the caution with which all innovations were approached. It took them two days to make up their minds that the well would be a good thing to have, and that the Wrath of God would not descend upon them if they put the work in hand.

Well-digging is a skilled craft, and there was one family only on the coast who could be entrusted with the work; they lived about five miles from Kuantan. Mat Amin dictated a letter for the Imam to write in the Jawi script, and then they took it into Kuala Rakit and posted it. Jean sent for five sacks of cement from Kota Bahru, and settled down to wait for several weeks while the situation developed.

She spent much of the time with the fishermen on their boats, or sitting on the beach and playing with the children. She taught them to build sand castles and to play Noughts and Crosses on a chequer drawn with the finger in the sand; she bathed and swam a good deal, and worked for a week in the rice fields at the time of harvest. She had lived so long with these people that she was patient about the passage of time; moreover, she had a use for time to consider what she was going to do with her life now that she had no further need to work. She waited there for three weeks in idleness, and she did not find it tedious.

The well-diggers and the cement arrived about the same time, and work commenced. The diggers were a family of an old grey-bearded father, Suleiman, and his two sons, Yacob and Hussein. They spent a day surveying the land and all the arguments for the site chosen for the well had to be gone over once again to satisfy these experts; when work finally began it was done quickly and well. The diggers worked from dawn till dusk, with one at the bottom of the shaft and the other two disposing of the soil on top; they bricked it downwards from the top as they worked, supporting the brickwork upon stakes driven into the earth sides.

Old Suleiman, the father, was a mine of information to the village, for he travelled up and down the east coast of Malaya building and repairing wells, and so visited most villages from time to time. The men and women of Kuala Telang used to sit around watching the progress of the new well and gossiping with the old man, getting news of their acquaintances and relatives up and down the coast. Jean was sitting there one afternoon, and said to him,“You are from Kuantan?”

“From Batu Sawah,”said the old man.“That is two hours' walk from Kuantan. Our home is there, but we are great travellers.”

She was silent for a moment; then she said,“Do you remember the Japanese officer in charge at Kuantan in the first year of the war, Captain Sugamo?”

“Assuredly,”the old man replied.“He is a very bad man, and we were glad when he went away. Captain Ichino who came after him was better.”

Jean was surprised that he did not seem to know that Sugamo was dead; she had supposed that the War Crimes Commission would have taken evidence in Kuantan. She told him,“Captain Sugamo is dead now. He was sent to the Burma-Siam railway, and there he caused many atrocities, and many murders. But the Allies caught him when the war was over, and he was tried for murder, and executed in Penang.”

“I am glad to hear it,”the old man replied.“I will tell my sons.”He called down the well with the news; it was discussed a little, and then the men went on with their work.

Jean asked,“Did he do many evil things in Kuantan?”There was one still hideously fresh in her mind, but she could not bring herself to speak of it directly.

Suleiman said,“Many people were tortured.”

She nodded.“I saw one myself.”It had to come out, and it did not matter what she said to this old man.“When we were starving and ill, a soldier who was a prisoner helped us. The Japanese caught him, and they crucified him with nails through his hands, and they beat him to death.”

“I remember that,”the old man said.“He was in hospital at Kuantan.”

Jean stared at him.“Old man, when was he in hospital? He died.”

“Perhaps there were two.”He called down the well to Yacob.“The English soldier who was crucified and beaten at Kuantan in the first year of the war. The English mem knew him. Tell us, did that man die?”

Hussein broke in.“The one who was beaten was an Australian, not English. He was beaten because he stole chickens.”

“Assuredly,”the old man said.“It was for stealing the black chickens. But did he live or die?”

Yacob called up from the bottom of the well.“Captain Sugamo had him taken down that night; they pulled the nails out of his hands. He lived.”

Chapter 5

In Kuantan, in the evening of that day in July 1942, a sergeant had come to Captain Sugamo in the District Commissioner's house, and had reported that the Australian was still alive. Captain Sugamo found this curious and interesting, and as there was still half an hour before his evening rice, he strolled down to the recreation ground to have a look.

The body still hung by its hands, facing the tree. Blood had drained from the blackened mess that was its back and had run down the legs to form a black pool on the ground, now dried and oxidized by the hot sun. A great mass of flies covered the body and the blood. But the man undoubtedly was still alive; when Captain Sugamo approached the face the eyes opened, and looked at him with recognition.

It is doubtful if the West can ever fully understand the working of a Japanese mind. When Captain Sugamo saw that the Australian recognized him from the threshold of death, he bowed reverently to the torn body, and he said with complete sincerity,“Is there anything that I can get for you before you die?”

The ringer said distinctly,“You bloody bastard. I'll have one of your black chickens and a bottle of beer.”

Captain Sugamo stood looking at the wreck of the man nailed to the tree, and his face was completely expressionless. Presently he turned upon his heel and went back to his house. He called for his orderly as he went into the shade, and he told him to fetch a bottle of beer and a glass, but not to open the bottle.

The man protested that there was no beer. Captain Sugamo already knew that, but he sent his orderly to the town to visit all the Chinese eating-houses to see if he could find a bottle of beer anywhere in Kuantan. In an hour the man came back; Captain Sugamo was sitting in exactly the same attitude as when he had gone out to find the beer. With considerable apprehension he informed his officer that there was no beer in all Kuantan. He was dismissed, and went away gladly.

Death to Captain Sugamo was a ritual. There had been an element of holiness in his approach to the Australian, and having offered in the hearing of his men to implement the last wishes of his victim he was personally dedicated to see that those last wishes were provided. If a bottle of beer had been available he would have sacrificed one of his remaining black Leghorns and sent the cooked meat and the beer down to the dying body on the tree; he might even have carried the tray down himself. By doing so he would have set an example of chivalry and Bushido to the troops under his command. Unfortunately, it was impossible for him to provide the bottle of beer, and since the beer was missing and the soldier's dying wish could not be met in full, there was no point in sacrificing one of the remaining black Leghorns. He could not carry out his own part in the ritual; he could not show Bushido by granting the man's dying wish. Therefore, the Australian could not be allowed to die, or he himself would be disgraced.

He called for his sergeant. When the man came, he ordered him to take a party with a stretcher to the recreation ground. They were to pull the nails out and take the man down from the tree without injuring him any further, and put him face downwards on the stretcher, and take him to the hospital.

To Jean, the news that the Australian was still alive came like the opening of a door. She slipped away and went and sat in the shade of a casuarina tree at the head of the beach to consider this incredible fact. The sun glinted on the surf and the beach was so white, the sea so blue, that it was almost ecstasy to look at them. She felt as if she had suddenly come out of a dark tunnel that she had walked down for six years. She tried to pray, but she had never been religious and she didn't know how to put what she was feeling into a prayer. The best she could do was to recollect the words of a prayer that they had used at school sometimes.“Lighten our darkness, oh Lord, and of Thy great mercy...”That was all she could remember, and she repeated it over and over to herself that afternoon. Her darkness had been lightened by the well-diggers.

She went back that evening and spoke to Suleiman again about the matter, but neither he nor his sons could supply much further information. The Australian had been in the hospital at Kuantan for a long time, but how long they did not know. Yacob said that he had been there for a year, but she soon found that he only meant a very long time. Hussein said three months, and Suleiman did not know how long he had been there, but said that he was sent down on a ship to Singapore to a prison camp, and he was then walking with two sticks. She could not find out from them when that was.

So she had to leave it, and she stayed on in Kuala Telang till the well and washhouse were completed. She had already started the carpenters upon the washhouse after long consultations with the elder women, and the concrete work was now completed in the shuttering, and drying out. On the day that water was reached at the bottom of the well the carpenters began to erect the posts for the atap house, and the well and the house were finished about the same time. Two days were spent in baling out the muddy water from the well till it ran clean, and then they had an opening ceremony when Jean washed her own sarong and all the women crowded into the washhouse laughing, and the men stood round in a tolerant circle at a distance, wondering if they had been quite wise to allow anything that made the women laugh so much.

On the next day she sent a telegram by runner to Kuala Rakit to be dispatched to Wilson-Hays asking him to send the jeep for her, and a day or two later it arrived. She left in a flurry of shy good wishes with some moisture in her eyes; she was going back to her own place and her own people, but she was leaving three years of her life behind her, and that is never a very easy thing to do.

She got back to the Residency at Kota Bahru after dark that night, too tired to eat. Mrs Wilson-Hays sent her up a cup of tea and a little fruit to her bedroom, and she had a long, warm bath, putting off her native clothes for the last time. She lay on the bed in the cool, spacious room under the mosquito net, rested and growing sleepy, and what she thought about was Ringer Harman, and the red country he had told her of round Alice Springs, and euros, and wild horses.

She walked with Wilson-Hays in the garden of the Residency next morning after breakfast in the cool of the day. She told him what she had done in Kuala Telang; he asked her where she had got the idea of the washhouse from.“It's obvious that's what they need,”she said.“Women don't like washing their clothes in public, especially Moslem women.”

He thought about it for a minute.“You've probably started something,”he remarked at last.“Every village will want one now. Where did you get the plan of it—the arrangement of the sinks and all that sort of thing?”

“We worked it out ourselves,”she said.“They knew what they wanted all right.”

They strolled along by the river, brown and muddy and half a mile wide, running its way down to the sea. As they walked she told him about the Australian, because she could talk freely about that now. She told him what had happened.“His name was Joe Harman,”she said,“and he came from a place near Alice Springs. I would like to get in touch with him again. Do you think I could find out anything about him in Singapore?”

He shook his head.“I shouldn't think so, not now that SEAC is disbanded. I shouldn't think there's any record of prisoners of war in Singapore now.”

“How would one find out about him, then?”

“You say he was an Australian?”

She nodded.

“I think you'd have to write to Canberra,”he said.“They ought to have a record of all prisoners there. I suppose you don't happen to know his unit?”

She shook her head.“I'm afraid I don't.”

“That might make it difficult, of course—there may be several Joe Harmans. I should start off by writing to the Minister for the Army—that's what they call him, the head of the War Office. Just address your letter to the Minister for the Army, Canberra, Australia. Something might come of that. What you want is an address where you could write to him, I suppose?”

Jean stared across the river at the rubber trees and coconut palms.“I suppose so. As a matter of fact, I've got an address of a sort. He used to work before the war on a cattle station called Wollara, near a place called Alice Springs. He said that they were keeping his job open for him there.”

“If you've got that address,”he observed,“I should write there. You're much more likely to find him that way than by writing to Canberra.”

“I might do that,”she said slowly.“I would like to see him again. You see, it was because of us that it all happened...”

It had been her intention to go back to Singapore and wait there for a boat to England; if she had to wait long for a cheap passage she intended to try and find a job for a few weeks or months. Malayan Airways called at Koto Bahru next day, and the Dakota landed at Kuantan on the way down to Singapore. She spoke to Wilson-Hays again that evening after dinner.

“Do you think there would be a hotel or anything at Kuantan if I stopped there for a day?”she asked.

He looked at her kindly.“Do you want to go back there?”he asked.

“I think I do,”she said.“I'd like to go and see the people at the hospital and find out what I can.”

He said,“You'd better stay with David and Joyce Bowen. Bowen is the District Commissioner; he'd be glad to put you up.”

“I don't want to be a nuisance to people,”she said.“Isn't there a resthouse that I could stay in? After all, I know this country fairly well.”

“That's why Bowen would like to meet you,”he remarked.“You must realize that you're quite a well-known person in these parts. He would be very disappointed if you stayed at the resthouse.”

She looked at him in wonder.“Do people think of me like that? I only did what anybody could have done.”

“That's as it may be,”he replied.“The fact is, that you did it.”

She flew on down to Kuantan next day. Someone must have told the crew of the aircraft about her, because the Malay stewardess came to her after half an hour and said,“We're just coming up to Kuala Telang, Miss Paget. Captain Philby wants to know if you would care to come forward to the cockpit and see it.”So she went forward through the door and stood between the pilots; they brought the Dakota down to about seven hundred feet and circled the village; she could see the well and the new atap roof of the washhouse, and she could see people standing gazing up at the machine. Fatimah and Zubeidah and Mat Amin. Then they straightened up and flew on down the coast, and Kuala Telang was left behind.

The Bowens met her at the airstrip, which is ten miles from the town of Kuantan; Wilson-Hays had sent them a signal that morning. They were a friendly, unsophisticated couple, and she had no difficulty in telling them a little about the Australian soldier who had been tortured when they were sitting in the DC's house, where Captain Sugamo had sat so often, over a cup of tea. They said that Sister Frost was now in charge of the hospital, but it was doubtful if there was anybody now upon the staff who was there in 1942. They drove down after tea to see Sister Frost.

She received them in the matron's room, very hygienic and smelling strongly of disinfectant. She was an Englishwoman about forty years of age.“There's nobody here now who was on the staff then,”she said.“Nurses in a place like this—they're always leaving to get married. We never seem to keep them longer than about two years. I don't know what to suggest.”

Bowen said,“What about Phyllis Williams? She was a nurse here, wasn't she?”

“Oh, her,”the sister said disparagingly.“She was here for the first part of the war until she married that man. She might know something about it.”

They left the hospital, and as they drove to find Phyllis Williams Mrs Bowen enlightened Jean.“She's a Eurasian,”she said.“Very dark, almost as dark as a Malay. She married a Chinese, a man called Bun Tai Lin who runs the cinema. What you'd call a mixed marriage, but they seem to get along all right. She's a Roman Catholic, of course.”Jean never fathomed the“of course”.

The Bun Tai Lins lived in a rickety wooden house up the hill overlooking the harbour. They could not get the car to the house, but left it in the road and walked up a short lane littered with garbage. They found Phyllis Williams at home, a merry-faced, brown woman with four children around her and evidently about to produce a fifth. She was glad to see them and took them into a shabby room, the chief decorations of which were a set of pewter beer-mugs and a large oleograph of the King and Queen in coronation robes.

She spoke very good English.“Oh yes, I remember that poor boy,”she said.“Joe Harman, that was his name. I nursed him for three or four months—he was in a state when he came in. We none of us thought he'd live. But he got over it. He must have led a very healthy life, because his flesh healed wonderfully. He said that he was like a dog, he healed so well.”

She turned to Jean.“Are you the lady that was leading the party of women and children from Panong?”she asked.“I thought you must be. Fancy you coming here again! You know, he was always wanting to know about you and your party, if anybody knew the way you'd gone. And of course, we didn't know, and with that Captain Sugamo in the mood he was nobody was going to go round asking questions to find out.”

She turned to Jean.“I forget your name?”

“Paget. Jean Paget.”

The Eurasian looked puzzled.“That wasn't it. I wonder now, was he talking about someone different? I can't remember now what he called her, but it wasn't that. I thought it would have been you.”

“Mrs Frith?”

She shook her head.“I'll remember presently.”

She could not tell them very much more than Jean knew already. The Australian had been sent down to a prison camp in Singapore as soon as he was fit to travel; they heard no more of him. They thought that he would make a good recovery in the end, though it would be years before the muscles of his back got back their strength if, indeed, they ever would. She knew no more than that.

They left presently, and went down the garbage-strewn lane towards the car. When they were nearly at the bottom the woman called to them from the veranda.“I just remembered that name. Mrs Boong. That's who he was always talking about, Mrs Boong. Was that one of your party?”

Jean laughed, and called back to her,“That's what he used to call me!”

The woman was satisfied.“I thought it must have been you that he was always talking about.”

On the way back to the DC's house in the car, they passed the recreation ground. There were tennis nets rigged and one or two couples playing; there was a white young man playing a brown girl. The tree still stood overlooking the courts, and underneath it a couple of Malay women sat exactly where the feet of the tortured man had hung, on ground that had been soaked in blood, and gossiped while their children played around. It all looked very peaceful in the evening light.

Jean spent that night with the Bowens, and went on to Singapore next day in the Dakota. Wilson-Hays had advised her about hotels, and she stayed at the Adelphi opposite the Cathedral.

She wrote to me from there a couple of days later. It was a long letter, about eight pages long, written in ink smudged a little with the sweat that had formed on her hand as she wrote in that humid place. First she told me what had happened in Kuala Telang; she told me about the well-diggers and that Joe Harman was still alive. And then she went on,

I've been puzzling over what I could do to get in touch with him again. You see, it was all because of us that it happened. He stole the chickens for us, and he must have known the sort of man that Captain Sugamo was, and the risk that he was taking. I must find out where he is living now, and if he's all right; I can't believe that he can be able to work as a stockrider after having been so terribly injured. I think he was a man who'd always fall upon his feet somehow or other if he was well enough, but I can't bear the thought that he might be still in hospital, perhaps, and likely to stay there for ever with his injuries.

I did think of writing to him at this place Wollara that he

told me about, the cattle station that he worked on, somewhere near Alice Springs. But thinking it over, if he can't work he can't be there, and I don't suppose I'd ever get an answer to a letter from a place like that, or not for ages, anyway. I thought of writing to Canberra to try and find out something, but that's almost as bad. And this brings me to what I wanted to tell you when I started this letter, Noel, and I hope it won't be too much of a shock. I'm going on to Australia from here.

Don't think me absolutely crazy for doing this. The fare from here to Darwin costs sixty pounds by the Constellation, and you can get a bus from Darwin to Alice Springs; it takes two or three days but it ought to be much cheaper than flying. After paying the hotel bill here I shall still have about a hundred and seven pounds, not counting next month's money. I thought I'd go to Alice Springs and get to this place Wollara and find out about him there; someone in that district is bound to know what happened to him, and where he is now.

There are some merchant service officers staying here, very nice young men, and they tell me I can get a cabin on a merchant ship back to England probably from Townsville, that's on the east coast of Australia in Queensland, and if there isn't a ship there I'd certainly get one at Brisbane. I've been talking to a man in the Chartered Bank here in Raffles Place who is very helpful, and I've arranged with him to transfer my next month's money to the Bank of New South Wales in Alice Springs, and so I'll have money to get me across to Townsville or Brisbane. Write to me care of the Bank of New South Wales in Alice Springs, because I know I'm going to feel a long way from home when I get there.

I'm leaving here on Thursday by the Constellation, so I'll be in Australia somewhere by the time you get this letter. I have a feeling that I'm being a terrible nuisance to you, Noel, but I'll have an awful lot to tell you when I get back home. I don't think the trip home from Townsville or Brisbane can take longer than three months at the outside, so I shall be home in England in time for Christmas at the very latest.

I sat there reading and re-reading this, bitterly disappointed. I had been making plans for entertainments for her when she came back, I suppose—in fact, I know I had been. Old men who lead a somewhat empty life get rather stupid over things like that. Lester Robinson came into my office with a sheaf of papers in his hand as I was reading her letter for the third time; I laid the letter down.“My Paget girl,”I said.“You know—that Macfadden estate that we're trustees for. She's not coming home after all. She's gone on from Malaya to Australia.”

He glanced at me, and I suppose the disappointment that I felt showed in my face, because he said gently,“I told you she was old enough to make a packet of trouble for us.”I looked up at him quickly to see what he meant by that, but he began talking about an unadopted road in Colchester, and the moment passed.

I went on with my work, but the black mood persisted and it was with me when I reached the club that night. I settled down after dinner in the library with a volume of Horace because I thought the mental exercise required to read the Latin would take my mind off things and put me in a better frame of mind. But I had forgotten my Horace, I suppose, because a phrase I had not read or thought about for forty years suddenly stared up at me from the page and brought me up with a round turn,

—Dulce ridentem Lalagen amabo,
Dulce loquentem.

It had been a part of my youth, that phrase, as I suppose it is a part of the youth of many young men who have been in love. I could not bear to go on reading Horace after that, and I sat thinking of sweetly smiling, soft-spoken Lalage on her way to Alice Springs in a long-distance bus, until I broke away from morbid fancies and got up and put the book back on the shelf.

It must have been about a week after that that Derek Harris came into my room as the client went out. Derek is one of our two articled clerks, and one day I expect to make him a partner; a pleasant fresh-faced lad. He said,“Could you spare a few minutes for a stranger, sir?”

“What sort of stranger?”I inquired.

He said,“A man called Harman. He came about an hour ago without any appointment and asked to see you. Sergeant Gunning asked if I would see him as you were engaged, and I had a talk with him, but it's you that he wants to see. I understand that it's something to do with Miss Paget.”

I knew now where I had heard that name before, but it was quite incredible. I asked,“What sort of a man is he?”

He grinned broadly.“Some sort of a colonial, I should think. Probably Australian. He's an outdoor type, anyway.”

“Is he a reasonable person?”

“Oh, I think so, sir. He's some sort of a countryman, I should say.”

It was all beginning to fit in, and yet it was incredible that an Australian stockman should have found his way to my office in Chancery Lane.“Is his name Joseph, by any chance?”I asked.

“You know him, do you, sir? Joe Harman. Shall I ask him to come up?”

I nodded.“I'll see him now.”Harris went down to fetch him, and I stood by my window looking out into the grey street, wondering what this visit meant and how it had come about, and how much of my client's business could I tell this man.

Harris showed him in, and I turned from the window to meet him.

He was a fair-haired man, about five feet ten in height. He was thickset but not fat; I judged him to be between thirty and thirty-five years old. His face was deeply tanned but his skin was clear; he had very bright blue eyes. He was not a handsome man; his face was too square and positive for that, but it was a simple and good natured face. He walked towards me with a curious stiff gait.

I shook hands with him.“Mr Harman?”I said.“My name is Strachan. Do you want to see me?”And as I spoke I was unable to resist the temptation to look down at his hand. There was a huge scar on the back of it.

He said a little awkwardly,“I don't want to keep you long.”He was ill at ease and obviously embarrassed.

“Not at all,”I said.“Sit down, Mr Harman, and tell me what I can do for you.”I put him in the client's chair before my desk and gave him a cigarette. He pulled from his pocket a tin box of wax matches of a style that was strange to me, and cracked one expertly with his thumbnail without burning himself. He was wearing a very ready-made suit, quite new, and an unusually ornamental tie for London wear.

“I was wondering if you could tell me about Miss Jean Paget,”he said.“Where she lives, or anything like that.”

I smiled.“Miss Paget is a client of mine, Mr Harman,”I said.“You evidently know that. But a client's business is entirely confidential, you know. Are you a friend of hers?”

The question seemed to embarrass him still further.“Sort of,”he replied.“We met once in the war, in Malaya that was. I'll have to tell you who I am, of course. I'm a Queenslander. I run a station in the Gulf country, about twenty miles from Willstown.”He spoke very slowly and deliberately, not from embarrassment but because that seemed to be his way.“I mean the homestead is twenty miles from the town, but one limb of the land runs down the creek to within five miles. Midhurst, that's the name of my station. Midhurst, Willstown, is the address.”

I made a note upon my pad, and smiled at him again.“You're a long way from home, Mr Harman,”I said.

“Too right,”he replied.“I don't know nobody in England except Miss Paget and a cobber I met in the prison camp who lives at a place called Gateshead in the north of England. I came here for a holiday, you might say, and I thought perhaps Miss Paget might be glad to know that I'm in England, but I don't know her address.”

“Rather a long way to come for a holiday?”I observed.

He smiled a little sheepishly.“I struck it lucky. I won the Casket.”

“The Casket?”

“The Golden Casket. Don't you have that here?”

I shook my head.“I'm afraid I've never heard of it.”

“Oh my word,”he said.“We couldn't get along without the Casket in Queensland. It's the State lottery that gets the money to build hospitals.”

“I see,”I said.“Did you win a prize in the lottery?”

“Oh my word,”he repeated.“Did I win a prize. I won a thousand pounds—not English pounds, of course, Australian pounds, but it's a thousand pounds to us. I always take a ticket in every Casket like everybody else because if you don't get a prize you get a hospital and there's times when that's more useful. You ought to see the hospital the Casket built at Willstown. Three wards it's got, with two beds in each, and two rooms for the sisters, and a separate house for the doctor only we can't get a doctor to come yet because Willstown's a bit isolated, you see. We've got an X-ray apparatus there and a wireless so that the sister can call for the Cairns Ambulance—the aeroplane, you know. We couldn't do without the Casket.”

I must say I was a little bit interested.“Does the Casket pay for the aeroplane, too?”

He shook his head.“You pay seven pounds ten a year to the Cairns Ambulance, each family, that is. Then if you get sick and have to go to Cairns the sister calls Cairns on the wireless and the aeroplane comes out to take you into Cairns to hospital. That's free, provided that you pay the seven pounds ten each year.”

“How far are you from Cairns?”

“About three hundred miles.”

I reverted to the business in hand.“Tell me, Mr Harman,”I said,“how did you get to know that I was Miss Paget's solicitor?”

“She told me in Malaya when we met, she lived in Southampton,”he said.“I didn't know any address, so I went there and stayed in a hotel, because I thought maybe she'd like to know I was in England. I never saw a city that had been bombed before—oh my word. Well, then I looked in the telephone book and asked a lot of people but I couldn't find out nothing except she had an aunt that lived in Wales at a place called Colwyn Bay. So then I went to Colwyn Bay.”

“You went right up there, did you?”

He nodded.“I think her aunt thought I was up to some crook game or other,”he said simply.“She wouldn't tell me where she lived or anything. All she said was that you were her trustee, whatever that means. So I came here.”

“When did you arrive in England?”I asked.

“Last Thursday. Five days ago.”

“You landed at Southampton, did you?”

He shook his head.“I flew from Australia, by Qantas. You see, I got a good stockman looking after Midhurst for me, but I can't afford to be away so long. Jim Lennon's all right for a time, but I wouldn't want to be away from Midhurst more'n three months. You see, this is a slack time in the Gulf country. We mustered in March this year on account of the late season and drove the stock down Julia Creek in April—that's railhead, you know. I had about fourteen hundred stores I sold down to Rockhampton for fattening. Well, after getting them on rail I had to get back up to Midhurst on account of the bore crew. I got Mrs Spears—she's the owner of Midhurst—I got her to agree we sink a bore at Willow Creek, that's about twenty miles south-east of the homestead, to get water down at that end in the dry, and we got a bonza bore, we did. She's flowing over thirty thousand gallons a day; it's going to make a lot of difference down at that end. Well, that took up to about three weeks ago before I got that finished up, and I must be back at Midhurst by the end of October for getting in the stores and that before the wet begins at Christmas. So I thought that coming on this holiday I'd better fly.”

Flying to England, I thought, must have made a considerable hole in his thousand pounds.“You came to London, then, and went straight down to Southampton?”

“That's right,”he said.

“And from there you went up to North Wales. And from there you came here?”

“That's right.”

I looked him in the eyes, and smiled.“You must want to see Miss Paget very much.”

He met my gaze.“I do.”

I leaned back in my chair.“I've got a disappointment for you, I'm afraid, Mr Harman. Miss Paget is abroad.”

He stared down at his hat for a moment. Then he raised his head.“Is she far away?”he asked.“I mean, is it France or anything like that, where I could get to see her?”

I shook my head.“She's travelling in the East.”

He said quietly,“I see.”

I couldn't help liking and respecting this man. It was perfectly obvious that he had come twelve thousand miles or so to find Jean Paget, and now he wasn't going to find her. It was bad luck, to say the least of it, and he was taking it well. I felt that I wanted a little time to consider this affair.

“The most that I can do for you,”I said,“is to forward a letter. I can do that, if you care to write one, and I'll send it to her by air mail. But I'm afraid that you may have to wait a month or so before you get an answer.”

He brightened.“I'd like to do that. I never thought that after coming all this way I'd find that she'd gone walkabout.”

He thought for a minute.“What address should I put upon the letter?”

“I can't give you my client's address, Mr Harman,”I said.“What I suggest that you do is to write her a letter and bring it in to me here tomorrow morning. I will send it on with a short covering note explaining how it came into my hands. Then if she wants to see you she will get in touch with you herself.”

“You don't think she'll want to see me?”he said heavily.

I smiled.“I didn't say anything of the sort, Mr Harman. I'm quite sure that when she hears you've been in England looking for her she will write to you. What I'm saying is that I have her interests to consider, and I'm not going to give her address to anyone who comes into this office and cares to ask for it.”I paused.“There's one thing that you'd better know,”I said.“Miss Paget is a fairly wealthy woman. Women who have command of a good deal of money are apt to be troubled by touts. I'm not saying that you're a tout or that you're after her money. I am saying that you must write to her first of all, and then let her decide if she wants to meet you. If you're a friend of hers you'll see that that's reasonable.”

He stared at me.“I never knew that she had money. She told me she was just a typist in an office.”

“That's quite true,”I said.“She inherited some money recently.”

He was silent.

“Suppose you come back tomorrow morning, Mr Harman,”I said. I glanced at my engagement diary.“Say, twelve o'clock tomorrow morning. Write her a letter saying whatever it is you want to say, and bring it here then. I will forward it to her tomorrow evening.”

“All right,”he said. He got up and I got up with him.“Where are you staying, Mr Harman?”I asked.

“At the Kingsway Palace Hotel.”

“All right, Mr Harman,”I said.“I shall expect you tomorrow morning, at twelve o'clock.”

I spent most of that evening wondering if I had done the right thing in refusing Mr Harman the address. I thought ruefully that Jean would have been very angry if she had known I had done such a thing, especially when she was looking for him all over Australia. At the same time, what I had done would not delay a letter from him reaching her, and there was no sense in putting all her cards upon the table for him to see just at present. One thing that puzzled me a little was, why had he suddenly awoken to the fact that he wanted to meet Jean Paget again, after six years? A question or two upon that point seemed to be in order, and I prepared a small interrogation for him when he came to see me with his letter.

Twelve o'clock next morning came, and he didn't turn up for his appointment. I waited in for him till one o'clock, and then I went to lunch.

By three o'clock I was a little bit concerned. The initiative had passed into his hands. If he should vanish into thin air now and never come back to see me again, Jean Paget would be very cross with me, and rightly so. Between clients I put in a telephone call to the Kingsway Palace Hotel and asked to speak to Mr Joseph Harman. The answer was that Mr Harman had gone out after breakfast, and had left no message at the desk. I left one for him, asking him to ring me as soon as he came in.

He did not ring that day.

At half past ten that night I rang the hotel again, but I was told that Mr Harman was not in.

At eight o'clock next morning I rang again. They told me that Mr Harman had not checked out and his luggage was still in his room, but that he had not slept in the room that night.

As soon as I got into the office I sent for Derek Harris.“Harris,”I said.“I want you to try and find that man Harman. He's an Australian.”I told him briefly what had happened.“I should try the hotel again, and if you draw a blank, ring round the various police courts. I think I may have given him some rather unwelcome news, and it's quite possible he's been out on a blind.”

He came back in a quarter of an hour.“You must have second sight, sir,”he said.“He's coming up at Bow Street this morning, drunk and disorderly. They had him in the cooler for the night.”

“He's a friend of Miss Paget's,”I said.“Get along down to Bow Street, Harris, and make yourself known to him. Which court is he coming up in?”

“Mr Horler's.”

I glanced at my watch.“Get along down there right away. Stay with Harman and pay the fine if he hasn't got any money. Then give me a ring, and if it's all in order take him in a taxi to my flat. I'll meet you there.”

There was nothing on my desk that day that could not be postponed or handled by Lester. I got back to my flat in time to catch my charwoman at work and tell her to make up the spare room bed. I told her I should want food in the flat for three or four meals, and I gave her money and sent her out to buy whatever food she could get off the ration.

Harris arrived with Harman half an hour later, and the Australian looked a little bit the worse for wear. He was cheerful and sober after his night in the cells, but he had lost one shoe and he had lost his collar stud and his hat. I met him in the hall.“Morning, Mr Harman,”I said.“I thought perhaps you'd rather come round here and clean up. You'd better not go back to the hotel looking like that.”

He looked me in the eyes.“I've been on the grog,”he said.

“So I see. The water's hot for a bath if you want one, and there's a razor in the bathroom.”I took him and showed him the geography of the house.“You can use this room.”I looked him up and down, smiling.“I'll get you a clean shirt and collar. You can try a pair of my shoes; if they're too small I'll send out for a pair.”

He wagged his head.“I dunno why you want to do this for me. I'll be all right.”

“You'll be righter when you've had a bath and a shave,”I said.“Miss Paget would never forgive me if I let a friend of hers go wandering about the streets like that.”

He looked at me curiously, but I left him and went back to the sitting-room. Harris was waiting for me there.“Thanks, Derek,”I said.“There was a fine, I suppose?”

“Forty shillings,”he said.“I paid it.”

I gave him the money.“He was cleaned out?”

“He's got four and fourpence halfpenny,”he replied.“He thinks he had about seventy pounds, but he's not sure.”

“It doesn't seem to worry him,”I said.

He laughed.“I don't think it does. He seems quite cheerful over it.”

I sent Harris back to the office and settled down to write a few letters while Harman was in the bath. He came into the sitting-room presently looking a bit sheepish, and again I noticed the curious, stiff gait with which he walked.“I dunno what to say,”he said in his slow way.“Those jokers I was with got all the money I had on me so Mr Harris had to pay the fine. But I got some more. I got a thing called a letter of credit that the bank in Brisbane gave me. I can get some money on that and pay him back.”

“That's all right,”I said.“Have you had any breakfast?”

“No.”

“Want any?”

“Well, I dunno. Maybe I'll get something round at the hotel.”

“You don't have to do that,”I said.“My woman's here still; she'll get you some breakfast.”I went out and organized this, and then I came back and found him standing by the window.“You didn't come back with that letter,”I observed.

“I changed my mind,”he said.“I'm going to give it away.”

“Give it away?”

“That's right,”he said.“I won't be writing any letter.”

“That's seems rather a pity,”I said quietly.

“Maybe. I had a good long think about it, and I won't be writing any letter. I decided that. That's why 1 didn't come back at the time you said.”

“As you like,”I said.“Perhaps you'd like to tell me a bit more about it when you've had some breakfast.”

I left him to his breakfast and went on with my letters. My woman took it to the dining-room and he went in there to eat it; a quarter of an hour later he came back to me in the sitting-room.

“I'd better be getting along now,”he said awkwardly.“Will it be all right if I come round later in the day and leave these shoes with the woman?”

I got up and offered him a cigarette.“Will you tell me a bit more about yourself before you go?”I asked.“You see, I shall be writing to Miss Paget in a day or two, and she's sure to want to know all about you.”

He stared at me, cigarette in hand.“You're going to write and tell her I've been here?”

“Of course.”

He stood silent for a moment, and then said in his slow Queensland way,“It would be better to forget about it, Mr Strachan. Just don't say nothing at all.”

I struck a match and lit his cigarette for him.“Is this because I told you about her inheritance?”

“You mean, the money?”

“Yes.”

He grinned.“I wouldn't mind about her having money, same as any man. No, it's Willstown.”

That was rather less intelligible than Greek to me, of course. I said,“Look, Joe, it won't hurt you to sit down for a few minutes and tell me one or two things.”I called him Joe because I thought that it might make him loosen up.

“I dunno as there's much to tell,”he said sheepishly.

“Sit down, anyway.”I thought for a moment, and then I said,“I'm right in thinking that you met Miss Paget first in the war?”

“That's right,”he said.

“That was in Malaya, when you were both prisoners?”

“That's right.”

“Some time in 1942?”

“That's right.”

“And you've never met her since, nor written to her?”

“That's right.”

“Well, what I don't understand is this,”I said.“Why do you want to meet her now so very badly? After all, it's six years since you met her. Why the sudden urge to get in touch with her now?”It was still vaguely in my mind that he had somehow heard about her money.

He looked up at me, grinning.“I thought she was a married woman.”

I stared at him.“I see.... When did you find out that she wasn't married?”

“I only found out that this May. I met the pilot that had flown her out from a place in Malaya called Kota Bahru. At Julia Creek, that was.”

He had driven his fourteen hundred cattle down from Midhurst station to Julia Creek with Jim Lennon and two Abo stockriders to help. From Midhurst to Julia Creek is about three hundred miles by way of the Norman River, the Saxby River and the Flinders River. They left Midhurst at the end of March and got the herd to railhead at Julia Creek on the third of May, moving them at the rate of about ten miles a day. The beasts were corralled in the stockyards of the railway, and they set to work to load them into trains; this took about three days.

During this time Jim and Joe lived in the Post Office Hotel at Julia Creek. It was very hot and they were working fourteen hours a day to load the cattle into trucks; whenever they were not working they were standing in the bar of the hotel drinking hugely at the cold Australian light beer that does no harm to people sweating freely at hard manual work. One evening while they were standing so two dapper men in uniform came into the bar and shouted a couple of rounds; these were the pilots of a Trans-Australia Airline Dakota which had stopped there for the night with an oil leak in the starboard engine.

Harman found himself next to the chief pilot. Joe was wearing an old green linen sun hat that had once belonged to the American Army, a cotton singlet, a pair of dirty khaki shorts, and boots without socks; his appearance contrasted strangely with the neatness of the airman, but the pilot was accustomed to the outback. They fell into conversation about the war and soon discovered they had both served in Malaya. Joe showed the scars upon his hands and the pilots examined them with interest; he told them how he had been nailed up to be beaten, and they shouted another grog for him.

“The funniest do I ever struck,”said the chief pilot presently,“was a party of women and children that never got into a prison camp at all. They spent most of the war in a Malay village working in the paddy fields.”

Joe said quickly,“Where was that in Malaya? I met that party.”

The pilot said,“It was somewhere between Kuantan and Kota Bahru. When we got back they were taken in trucks to Kota Bahru, and I flew them down to Singapore. All English, they were, but they looked just like Malays. All the women were in native clothes, and brown as anything.”

Joe said,“Was there a Mrs Paget with them then?”It was vastly important to him to hear if Jean had survived the war.

The pilot said,“There was a Miss Paget. She was a hell of a fine girl; she was their leader.”

Joe said,“Mrs. A dark-haired girl, with a baby.”

The pilot said,“That's right—a dark-haired girl. She had a little boy about four years old that she was looking after, but it wasn't hers. It belonged to one of the other women, one who died. I know that, because she was the only unmarried girl among the lot of them, and she was their leader. Just a typist in Kuala Lumpur before the war. Miss Jean Paget.”

Joe stared at him.“I thought she was a married woman.”

“She wasn't married. I know she wasn't, because the Japs had taken all their wedding rings so they had to be sorted out and that was quite easy, because they were all Mrs So and So except this one girl, and she was Miss Jean Paget.”

“That's right,”the ringer said slowly.“Jean was her name.”

He left the bar presently, and went out to the veranda and stood looking up at the stars. Presently he left the pub and strolled towards the stockyards; he found a gate to lean upon and stood there for a long time in the night, thinking things over. He told me a little about what he had been thinking, that morning in my London flat.

“She was a bonza girl,”he said simply.“If ever I got married it would have to be with somebody like her.”

I smiled.“I see,”I said.“That's why you came to England?”

“That's right,”he said simply. He had ridden back with Jim Lennon and the Abo stockmen to Midhurst, a journey that took them about ten days, leading their string of fifteen packhorses; since they had started mustering on the station in February he had been in the saddle almost continuously for three months.“Then there was the bore to see to,”he said.“I'd made such a point of that with Mrs Spears that I couldn't hardly leave before that was finished, but then I got away and I went into Cairns one Wednesday with John Duffy on the Milk Run”—I found out later that he meant the weekly Dakota air mail service—“and so down to Brisbane. And from Brisbane I came here.”

“What about the Golden Casket?”I inquired.

He said a little awkwardly,“I didn't tell you right about that. I did win the Casket, but not this year. I won it in 1946, the year after I got back to Queensland. I won a thousand pounds then, like I said.”

“I see,”I observed.“You hadn't spent it?”

He shook his head.“I was saving it, in case some day I got to have a station of my own, or do a deal with cattle, or something.”

“How much do you think you've got left now?”

He said,“There's five hundred pounds of our money on the letter of credit, and I suppose that's all I've got. Four hundred pounds of yours. There's my pay as manager goes into the bank at Willstown each month, of course.”

I sat smoking for a time in silence, and I couldn't help being sorry for this man. Since he had met Jean Paget six years previously he had held the image of her in his mind hoping to find somebody a little like her. When he had heard that she was not a married woman he had drawn the whole of his small savings and hurried expensively half across the world to England, hoping to find her and to find that she was still unmarried. It was a gambler's action, but his whole life had probably been made up of gambles; it could hardly be otherwise in the outback. Clearly he thought little of his money if it could buy a chance for him of marrying Jean Paget.

It was ironical to think that she was at that moment busy looking for him in his own country. I did not feel that I was quite prepared to tell him that.

“I still don't understand why you've given up the idea of writing to Miss Paget,”I said at last.“You said something about Willstown.”

“Yes.”There was a pause, and then he said in his slow way,“I thought a lot about things after I left you, Mr Strachan. Maybe I'd have done better to have done some thinking before ever I left Midhurst. I told you, I got none of them high-falutin ideas about not marrying a girl with money. So long as she was the right girl, I'd be tickled to death if she had money, same as any man. But there's more to it than that.”

He paused again.“I come from the outback,”he said slowly.“Running a cattle station is the only work I know, and it's where I like to be. I couldn't make out in any of the big cities, Brisbane or Sydney. I couldn't make out even in Cairns for very long, and anyway, there'd be no work there I could do. I never got a lot of schooling, living on a station like we did. I don't say that I won't make money. I can run a station better'n most ringers, and I seem to do all right with selling the stock too. I'll hope to get a station of my own one day, and there's plenty of station owners finish up with fifty thousand pounds. But if I get that far, it'll be staying in the outback and doing what I'm cut out for. And I tell you, Mr Strachan, the outback is a crook place for a woman.”

“In what way?”I asked quietly. We were really getting down to something now.

He smiled a little wryly.“Take Willstown, as an example. There's no radio station to listen to, only the short wave stuff from Brisbane and that comes and goes with static. There's no shop where you can buy fruit or fresh vegetables. The sister says that it's because of that so many of the old folk get this pellagra. There's no fresh milk. There's no dress shop, only what a woman can get in Bill Duncan's Store along with the dried peas and Jeyes Fluid and that. There's no ice-cream in Willstown. There's nowhere that a woman can buy a paper or a magazine or a book, and there's no doctor because we can't get one to come to Willstown. There's no telephone. There's no swimming-pool where a girl could sit around in a pretty bathing dress, although it can be hot there, oh my word. There's no other young women. I don't believe there's more'n five women in the district between the age of seventeen and forty; as soon as they're old enough to leave home they're off out of it, and down to the city. To get to Cairns to do a bit of shopping you can either fly, which costs money, or you can drive for four days in a jeep, and after that you'll find the jeep needs a new set of tyres.”He paused.“It's a grand country for a man to live and work in, and good money, too. But it's a crook place for a woman.”

“I see,”I said.“Are all the outback towns like that?”

“Most of them,”he said.“You get the bigger ones, like the Curry, they're better, of course. But Camooweal and Normanton and Burketown and Croydon and Georgetown—they're all just the same as Willstown.”He paused for a moment in thought.“There's only one good one for a woman,”he said.“Alice Springs. Alice is a bonza place, oh my word. A girl's got everything in Alice—two picture houses, shops for everything, fruit, ice-cream, fresh milk, Eddie Maclean's swimming-pool, plenty of girls and young married women in the place, and nice houses to live in. Alice is a bonza town,”he said,“but that's the only one.”

“Why is that?”I asked.“What makes Alice different from the others?”

He scratched his head.“I dunno,”he said.“It's just that it's got bigger, I suppose.”

I left that one.“What you mean is that if you got Miss Paget to agree to marry you, she wouldn't have a very happy life in Willstown.”

He nodded.“That's right,”he said, and there was pain in his eyes.“It all seemed sort of different when I met her in Malaya. You see, she was a prisoner and she hadn't got nothing, and I hadn't got nothing either, so there was a pair of us. When I got to know there was a chance she wouldn't be married I was so much in a hurry to get over here I didn't stop to think about the outback, or if I did I thought of her as someone who'd got nothing so she'd be all right in Willstown. See what I mean?”He looked at me appealingly.“But then I come to England and I see Southampton and the sort of way people live there, bombed and muggered up although it is, and I been in London and I been in Colwyn Bay. Then when you told me she'd come into money I got thinking about how she would be living and the sort of things that she'd be used to and she wouldn't get in Willstown, and then I thought I'd acted a bit hasty. I never know it to work, for a girl to come straight out from England to the outback. And for a girl with money of her own, it'ld be worse still.”He paused, and grinned at me.“So I went out on the grog.”

In all the circumstances, it now seemed to me that he had taken a very reasonable line of action, but it was a pity it had cost him seventy pounds.“Look, Joe,”I said.“We want to think about this thing a bit. I think I'll have to write and tell Miss Paget that I've met you. You see, she thought you were dead.”

He stared at me.“You knew about me, then?”

“Not very much,”I said.“I know that you stole chickens for her, and the Japs nailed you up and beat you. She thought you died.”

“I bloody near did,”he said grinning.“She told you that, did she?”

I nodded.“It's been a very deep grief to her,”I said quietly.“You wouldn't want her to go on like that? You see, she thinks it was her fault.”

“It wasn't her fault at all,”he said in his slow way.“She told me not to stick my neck out, and I went and bought it. It wasn't her fault at all.”

“I think you ought to write to her,”I repeated.

There was a long pause.

“I dunno what in hell I'd say to her if I did,”he muttered.

There was no point in going on agonizing about it. I got up.“Look, Joe,”I said. Take a bit of time to think it over. When have you got to be back in Australia?”

“I wouldn't be doing right by Mrs Spears unless I get back on the station by the end of October,”he said.“I don't want to serve her a crook deal.”

“That gives you two and a half months,”I said.“How much did your airline ticket cost you when you came here?”

“Three hundred and twenty-five pounds,”he said.

“And you've got five hundred pounds left, on your letter of credit.”

“That's right.”

“Do you want to go back by air, or would you rather go by sea? I could find out about sea passages for you, if you like. I think it would cost about eighty pounds on a tramp steamer, but you'd have to leave pretty soon—within a fortnight, say.”

“There don't seem to be much point in staying here,”he said a little wearily.“There wouldn't be no chance that she'll be coming back to England?”

“Not in that time, I'm afraid.”

“I'd better go back by sea, and save what's left of the money.”

“I think that's wise,”I said.“I'll get my office on to finding out about the passage. In the meantime, why don't you move in here? You're welcome to use that spare room till you go, and it will be cheaper for you than living in the hotel.”

“Wouldn't I be in your way?”

“Not in the least,”I said.“I'm out most of the day, and I'd be very glad for you to stay here if you'd like to.”

He agreed to that, and I asked him what he wanted most to see in England in his brief visit. He wanted to see No. 19 Acacia Road, Hammersmith, where his father had been born. He wanted to see a live broadcast of“Much-Binding-in-the-Marsh”which he listened to on short wave from Brisbane when the static permitted. (“They've got a bonza radio at Alice,”he said wistfully.“A local station, right in the town.”) He wanted to see all he could of thoroughbred horses and thoroughbred cattle. He was interested in saddlery, but he didn't think that we had much to teach them about that.

There was no difficulty about Hammersmith, of course; I put him in a bus that afternoon, and went into my office to deal with my neglected work. Apart from the clients who came to see me, I had plenty to think about. Whether Jean Paget chose to marry this man when she met him was entirely her own affair, but it was quite a possibility that she would do so. Whatever one might think about the suitability of such a match, there was no denying that Joe Harman had some very solid virtues; he seemed to be hard-working, thrifty if one excepts the great extravagance of flying half across the world to look for the girl he loved, and likely to make a success of his life; quite certainly he was a kind man who would make a good husband.

There was another aspect of the matter which was worth investigation. Whether she knew it or not, Jean Paget had Australia in her ancestry. She had never mentioned her grandfather, James Macfadden, to me and it seemed quite possible that she had never thought about him much. And yet, he was the original source of her money, and apparently he had made it in Australia before coming home to England to break his neck while riding in a point-to-point in Yorkshire. It would be interesting, I thought, to find out a little more about James Macfadden. Had he made his money on an outback cattle station, too? Had he been just such another as Joe Harman?

I sent my girl that afternoon to bring me the Macfadden box, and I sat looking through the old deeds and wills after my last client had gone. The only clue I found was in the Will of James Macfadden dated September 18th, 1903, which began,“I, James Nelson Macfadden of Lowdale Manor, Kirkby Moorside, in the County of Yorkshire, and of Hall's Creek in Western Australia, do hereby revoke all former wills... etc.”I knew nothing of Hall's Creek at that time, but I noted the name for future investigation. That is all there was.

I got Marcus Fernie on the telephone that afternoon at his office at the BBC and asked if I could have a ticket for“Much-Binding-in-the-Marsh”. I had to tell him something about Joe Harman in order to get it because there seemed to be considerable competition, and he came back at once with a demand that Harman should be interviewed for the programme“In Town Tonight”. I said I'd see him about that, and he promised to send over the ticket. Then I got on to old Sir Dennis Frampton who has a herd of pedigree Herefords at his place down by Taunton and told him about Joe Harman, and he very kindly invited him down for a couple of nights.

I got back to my flat at about seven o'clock; I had arranged for dinner there. Joe Harman was there, and he had been to the Bank and the hotel, and he had brought his suitcase round to my spare room. I asked if he had found his father's house at Hammersmith.

“I found it,”he said.“Oh my word, I did.”

“Pretty bad?”

He grinned.“That's putting it mild. We got some slums in Australia, but nothing like that. Dad did all right for himself when he come away from that and out to Queensland.”

I offered him a glass of sherry, but he preferred a beer; I went and got him a bottle.“When did your father leave this country?”I inquired,

“1904,”he said.“He went out to the Curry, to Cobb and Co. They used to run the stage coaches, before motors came. He must have been about fifteen then. He fought in the first war with the Aussies at Gallipoli.”

“He's dead now, is he?”

“Aye,”he said.“He died in 1940, soon after I joined the army.”He paused.“Mother's still alive. She lives with my sister Amy at the Curry.”

“Tell me,”I said,“do you know a place called Hall's Creek?”

“Where the gold was? Over by Wyndham, in West Australia?”

“That will be the place,”I said.“There are gold mines there, are there?”

“I don't think they work it now,”he said.“There was a lot of gold there in the nineties, like in Queensland, in the Gulf country. I've never been to Hall's Creek, but I've always thought that it would be like Croydon. There was a lot of gold at Croydon, oh my word. It lasted for about ten years, and then they had to go so deep for it, it didn't pay any longer. Croydon had thirty thousand people one time, so they say. Now it's got two hundred. It's the same at Normanton and Burketown—Willstown's the same. All gold towns at one time, they were.”

“You never heard of anybody called Macfadden over at Hall's Creek, did you?”

He shook his head.“I never heard the name.”

I told him I was getting a ticket for“Much-Binding-in-the-Marsh”, and that they wanted him to broadcast on Saturday night. He agreed diffidently to do this; when the time came I listened in and thought he did it surprisingly well. The announcer shepherded him along quite skilfully, and Harman spoke for about six or seven minutes about the Midhurst cattle station and the country down below the Gulf of Carpentaria that he called the Gulf country. Marcus Fernie took the trouble to ring me up next day to tell me how well it had gone.“I only wish we could get more chaps like him now and then,”he said.“It makes a difference when you hear the real McCoy.”

I put him on the train on Sunday down to Taunton to see Sir Dennis Frampton's cows. He had not much time left, because a ship of the Shaw Savill line was leaving on the following Friday morning for New Zealand and Australia, and I had managed to get him a cheap berth on that. He came back on the Wednesday full of what he had seen.“He's got a bonza herd there, oh my word,”he said.“I learned more about raising up the quality of stock there in two days than I'd have learned in ten years in the Gulf country. Of course, you couldn't do the things that he does on a station like Midhurst, but I got plenty to think about.”

“You mean about breeding?”

“We don't breed for quality at all in the Gulf,”he said.“Not like you set about it here in England. All we do is go out and shoot the scrub bulls when you see them so you keep the best ones breeding. I'd like to see a herd of pedigree stock out there, like he's got. I never see such beasts outside a show.”

After dinner I had a word with him about Miss Paget.“I shall write to her in a day or two and give her your address,”I said.“I know that she'll be very sorry to have missed you, and I should think you'd find a letter from her waiting for you at Midhurst when you get there. In fact, I know you will, because I shall write air mail, and she's certain to write air mail to you.”

He brightened considerably at the thought.“I don't think I'll write to her from here,”he said.“If you're going to do that I'll wait and write when I hear from her. I'm glad I didn't meet her over here, in a way. It's probably all turning out for the best.”

It was on the tip of my tongue to tell him then that she was in Australia, but I refrained. I had written to her in Alice Springs the day before Joe Harman had come to me, and I was expecting a letter from her any day now, because she used to write once a week, very regularly. If necessary, I could cable her to tell her his address in order that she might not leave Australia without seeing him, but there was no reason to lay all her cards before him at this stage.

I saw him off at the docks two days later, as I had seen Jean Paget a few months before. As I turned to go down the gangway he said gruffly,“Thank you for doing so much for me, Mr Strachan. I'll be writing from Midhurst.”And he shook my hand with a grip that made me wince, for all the injury his hand had suffered.

I turned to go down the gangway.“That's all right, Joe. You'll find a letter from Miss Paget when you get back home. You might even find more than that.”

I had reason for that last remark, because I had a letter from her in my pocket that had come by that day's post, and it was postmarked Willstown.

Chapter 6

When Jean Paget stepped down the gangway from the Constellation on to Darwin airport she was wildly and unreasonably happy. It is a fact, I think, that till that time she had never really recovered from the war. She had come to England when she was repatriated and she had done her job efficiently and well with Pack and Levy for two years or so, but she had done it in the manner of a woman of fifty. She lived, but she had very little zest for life. Deep in the background of her mind remained the tragedy of Kuantan, killing her youth. She had only been speaking the truth when she had told me once that she felt about seventy years old.

She landed at about eight-fifteen at night, after dark; as she was getting off the plane at Darwin, Qantas had booked a room for her at the Darwin Hotel. She stepped on to the concrete and was marshalled to the Customs office in the hangar; at the foot of the gangway there were three young men who scrutinized her carefully. At the time she took them for officials of the airport. It was only later that she found out that they were reporters on the staff of various Australian newspapers engaged in what must surely be the worst assignment in all journalism, meeting every aeroplane that lands on Darwin airport in the hope of finding a Prime Minister on board, or a woman with two heads.

One of them came up to her as soon as she was through the Customs; there had been nothing to make a story in this load of passengers. A happy-looking girl was a small dividend, however. He said,“Miss Paget? The stewardess tells me that you're getting off here and you're staying at the Darwin Hotel. Can I give you a lift into town? My name is Stuart Hopkinson; I represent the Sydney Monitor up here.”

She said,“That's terribly kind of you, Mr Hopkinson. I don't want to take you out of your way, though.”

He said,“I'm staying there myself.”He had a small Vauxhall parked outside the hanger; he took her suitcase and put it in the back seat and they got in, chatting about the Constellation and the journey from Singapore. And presently, as they drove past the remains of Vestey's meatworks, he said,“You're English, aren't you, Miss Paget?”She agreed.“Would you like to tell me why you're visiting Australia?”

She laughed.“Not very much, Mr Hopkinson. It's only something personal—it wouldn't make a story. Is this where I get out and walk?”

“You don't have to do that,”he said.“It was just a thought. I haven't filed a story for a week.”

“Would it help if I said that I thought Darwin was just wonderful? ‘London Typist thinks Darwin wonderful’?”

“We can't go panning London, not in the Monitor. Is that what you are, a typist?”

She nodded.

“Come out to get married?”

“I don't think so.”

He sighed.“I'm afraid you're not much good to me for a story.”

“Tell me, Mr Hopkinson,”she said,“how do the buses go from here to Alice Springs? I want to go down there, and I haven't got much money, so I thought I'd go by bus. That's possible, isn't it?”

“Sure,”he said.“One went this morning. You'll have to wait till Monday now; they don't run over the weekend.”

“How long does it take?”

“Two days. You start on Monday, stop at Daly Waters Monday night, and get in late on Tuesday. It's not too bad a journey, but it can be hot, you know.”

He put her down at the hotel and carried her bag into the lobby for her. She was lucky in that overcrowded place to get a room to herself, a room with a balcony overlooking the harbour. It was hot in Darwin, with a damp enervating heat that brought her out in streams of perspiration at the slightest movement. This was no novelty to her because she was accustomed to the tropics; she bolted the door and took off her clothes and had a shower, and washed some things in the hand basin, and lay down to sleep with a bare minimum of covering.

She woke early next morning and lay for some time in the cool of the dawn considering her position. It was imperative to her that she should find Joe Harman and talk to him; at the same time the meeting with Mr Hopkinson had warned her that there were certain difficulties ahead. However pleasant these young men might be, their duty was to get a story for the paper, and she had no desire whatever to figure in the headlines, as she certainly would do if the truth of her intentions became known.“Girl flies from Britain to seek soldier crucified for her...”It would be far easier if she were a man.

However, she wasn't. She set to work to invent a story for herself, and finally decided that she was going out to Adelaide to stay with her sister who was married to a man called Holmes who worked in the Post Office; that seemed a fairly safe one. She was travelling by way of Darwin and Alice Springs because a second cousin called Joe Harman was supposed to be working there but hadn't written home for nine years, and her uncle wanted to know if he was still alive. From Alice she would take the train down to Adelaide.

It didn't quite explain why she had come to Darwin in a Constellation, except that there is no other way to get to Darwin. Lying on her bed and cogitating this it seemed a pretty waterproof tale; when she got up and went downstairs for breakfast she decided to try it out on Stuart Hopkinson. She got her chance that morning as he showed her the way to the bus booking-office; she let it out in little artistic snippets over half an hour of conversation, and the representative of the Sydney Monitor swallowed it without question so that she became a little ashamed of herself.

He took her into a milk bar and stood her a Coca-Cola.“Joe Harman...”he said.“What was he doing at Alice nine years ago?”

She sucked her straw.“He was a cowboy on a cattle farm,”she said innocently, and hoped she wasn't overdoing it.

“A stockman? Do you remember the name of the station?”

“Wollara,”she said.“That's the name, Wollara. That's near Alice Springs, isn't it?”

“I don't know,”he said.“I'll try and find out.”

He came back to her after lunch with Hal Porter of the Adelaide Herald.“Wollara's a good long way from Alice Springs,”said Mr Porter.“The homestead must be nearly a hundred and twenty miles away. You mean Tommy Duveen's place?”

“I think that's it,”she said.“Is there a bus there from Alice Springs?”

“There's no bus or any way of getting there except to drive there in a truck or a utility.”

Hopkinson said.“It's on one of Eddie Maclean's rounds, isn't it?”

“Now you mention it, I think it is.”Porter turned to Jean.“Maclean Airways run around most of those stations once a week, delivering the mail,”he said.“You may find that you could get there by plane. If so, that's much the easiest.”

Her ideas about reporters had been moulded by the cinema; it was a surprise to her to find that in real life they could be kind and helpful people with good manners. She thanked them with sincere gratitude, and they took her out for a run round Darwin in a car. She exclaimed at the marvellous, white sand beaches and the azure blue of the sea, and suggested that a bathing party might be a good thing.

“There's one or two objections,”Mr Porter said.“One is the sharks. They'll take you if you go out more than knee deep. Another is the alligators. Then there's the stone fish—he lies on the beach and looks just like a stone until you tread on him, and he squirts about a pint of poison into you. The Portuguese Men-o'-War aren't so good, either. But the thing that really puts me off is Coral Ear.”

“What's that?”

“A sort of growth inside your head that comes from getting this fine coral sand into your ear.”

Jean came to the conclusion that perhaps she wouldn't bathe in Darwin after all.

She got her bathe, however, because on Sunday they drove her forty miles or so southwards down the one road to a place called Berry Springs, a deep water hole in a river where the bathing was good. The reporters eyed her curiously when she appeared in her two-piece costume because the weeks that she had spent in native clothes in Kuala Telang had left her body tanned with sunburn in unusual places. It was the first mistake that she had made, and for the first time a dim suspicion crossed their minds that this girl held a story for them if they could only get it out of her.

“Joe Harman...”said Hal Porter thoughtfully to Stuart Hopkinson.“I'm sure I've heard that name before somewhere, but I can't place it.”

As they drove back from the bathe the reporters told her about Darwin, and the picture they painted was a gloomy one.“Everything that happens here goes crook,”Hal Porter said.“The meatworks has been closed for years because of labour troubles—they got so many strikes they had to close it down. The railway was intended to go south to Alice and join up with the one from Alice down to Adelaide—go from north to south of the continent. It might have been some good if it had done that, but it got as far as Birdum and then stopped. God knows what it does now. This road has just about put the railway out of business—what business it ever had. There used to be an ice factory, but that's closed down.”He paused.“Everywhere you go round here you'll see ruins of things that have been tried and failed.”

“Why is that?”Jean asked.“It's not a bad place, this. It's got a marvellous harbour.”

“Of course it has. It ought to be a great big port, this place—a port like Singapore. It's the only town of any size at all on the north coast. I don't know. I've been up here too long. It gives me the willies.”

Stuart Hopkinson said cynically,“It's got outbackitis.”He smiled at Jean.“You'll see a lot of this in Australia, specially in the north.”

She asked,“Is Alice Springs like this?”It was so very different from the glowing recollections of Alice that Joe Harman had poured out to her, six years before.

“Oh, well,”said Hopkinson,“Alice is different. Alice is all right.”

“Why is it different?”she asked.

“I don't really know. It's railhead, of course, for trucking cattle down to Adelaide—that's one thing. But it's a go-ahead place is Alice; all sorts of things go on there. I wish to God the Monitor'ld send me there instead of here.”

She said goodbye to her two friends that night, and started at dawn next morning in the bus for Alice Springs. The bus was a big, modern Bedford, heavily streamlined; it towed a trailer carrying goods and luggage. It was comfortable enough although not air-conditioned; it cruised down the wide, empty tarmac road at fifty miles an hour, hour after hour, manned by ex-naval crew.

As far as Katherine, where the bus stopped for lunch, the country was well wooded with rather stunted eucalyptus trees, which Jean discovered were called gums. Between these trees were open meadows of wild land, ungrazed, unused, and uninhabited. She discussed this country with a fellow traveller, a bank inspector on his way to Tennant Creek, and she was told that all this coastal belt was useless for farming for some reason that she could not understand. After Katherine the country gradually became more arid, the trees more scattered and desiccated, till by the evening they were running through a country that was near to desert.

At dusk they stopped for the night at a place called Daly Waters. Daly Waters, she discovered, was a hotel, a post office, a large aerodrome, and nothing else whatsoever. The hotel was a rambling collection of single-storey wooden huts or dormitories for men and for women, strange to Jean but comfortable enough. She strolled outside before tea, in the dusk, and looked around. In front of the hotel three young men were squatting on their heels with one leg extended in the peculiar attitude that Joe Harman had used; they wore a sort of jodhpur trouser and elastic-sided boots with a very thin sole, and they were playing cards upon the ground, intent upon their game. She realized that she was looking at her first ringers.

She studied them with interest; that was how Joe Harman would have looked before he joined the army. She resisted an absurd temptation to go up to one of them and ask if they knew anything about him.

The bus started at dawn next day, and drove on southwards down the tarmac road, past Milners Lagoon and Newcastle Waters and Muckety Bore to Tennant Creek. As they went the vegetation grew sparser and the sun grew hotter, till by the time they stopped at Tennant Creek for a meal and a rest the country had become pure sand desert. They went on after an hour, driving at fifty to fifty- five miles an hour down the scorching road past tiny places of two or three houses dignified with a name, Wauchope and Barrow Creek and Aileron. Toward evening they found themselves running towards the Macdonnell Ranges, lines of bare red hills against the pale blue sky, and at about dusk they ran slowly into Alice Springs and drew up at the Talbot Arms Hotel.

Jean went into the hotel and got a room opening on to a balcony, the hotel being a bungalow-type building with a single storey, like practically every other building in Alice Springs. Tea was served immediately after they arrived, and she had already learned that in Australian country hotels unless you are punctual for your meals you will get nothing. She changed her dress and strolled out in the town after tea, walking very slowly down the broad suburban roads, examining the town.

She found it as Joe Harman had described it to her, a pleasant place with plenty of young people in it. In spite of its tropical surroundings and the bungalow nature of the houses there was a faint suggestion of an English suburb in Alice Springs which made her feel at home. There were the houses standing each in a small garden fenced around or bordered by a hedge for privacy; the streets were laid out in the way of English streets with shade trees planted along the kerbs. Shutting her eyes to the Macdonnell Ranges, she could almost imagine she was back in Bassett as a child. She could now see well what everybody meant by saying Alice was a bonza place. She knew that she could build a happy life for herself in this town, living in one of these suburban houses, with two or three children, perhaps.

She found her way back to the main street and strolled up it looking at the shops. It was quite true; this town had everything a reasonable girl could want—a hairdressing saloon, a good dress shop or two, two picture houses.... She turned into the milk bar at about nine o'clock and bought herself an ice-cream soda. If this was the outback, she thought, there were a great many worse places.

Next morning, after breakfast, she went and found the manageress, a Mrs Driver, in the hotel office. She said,“I want to try and get in touch with a second cousin of mine, who hasn't written home for ten years.”She told her story about being on her way from London to Adelaide to stay with her sister.“I told my uncle that I'd come this way and stop in Alice Springs and try and find out something about Joe.”

Mrs Driver was interested.“What's his name?”

“Joe Harman.”

“Joe Harman! Worked out at Wollara?”

“That's right,”Jean said.“Do you know if he's there still?”

The woman shook her head.“He used to come in here a lot just after the war, but he was only here about six months. I only came here in the war; I don't know about before that. He was a prisoner of the Japs, he was. They treated him terribly. Came back with scars on his hands where they'd put nails right through, crucified him, or something.”

Jean expressed surprise and horror.“Do you know where he is now?”

“I don't know, I'm sure. Maybe one of the boys would know.”

Old Art Foster, the general handyman who had lived in Alice Springs for thirty years said,“Joe Harman? He went back to Queensland where he come from. He was at Wollara for about six months after the war, and then he got a job as station manager at some place up in the Gulf country.”

Jean asked,“You don't know his address?”

“I don't. Tommy Duveen would know it, out at Wollara.”

“Does he come into town much?”

“Aye, he was in town on Friday. He comes about once every three or four weeks.”

Jean asked innocently,“I suppose Joe Harman took his family with him when he went to Queensland. They aren't living here still, are they?”

The old man stared at her.“I never heard Joe Harman had a family. He wasn't married, not so far as I know.”

She said defensively,“My uncle back in England thinks he's married.”

“I never heard nothing of a wife,”the old man said.

Jean thought about this for a minute, and then said to Mrs Driver,“Is there a telephone at Wollara? I mean, if Mr Duveen knows his address, I'd like to ring him up and get it.”

“There isn't any telephone,”she said.“They'll be speaking on the radio schedule morning and evening from Wollara, of course.”There was an extensive radio network operated by the Flying Doctor service from the hospital; morning and evening an operator at the hospital sat down to call up forty or fifty stations on the radio telephone to transmit messages, pass news, and generally ascertain that all was well. The station housewife operated the other end.“Mrs Duveen is sure to be on the air tonight because her sister Amy is in hospital here for a baby and Edith'll want to know if it's come off yet. If you write out a telegram and take it down to Mr Taylor at the hospital, he'll pass it to them tonight.”

Jean went back to her room and wrote out a suitable cable and took it down to the hospital to Mr Taylor, who agreed to pass it to Wollara.“Come back at about eight o'clock, and I may have the answer if they know the address right off; if they've got to look it up they'll probably transmit it on the schedule tomorrow morning.”That freed her for the remainder of the day, and she went back to the milk bar for another ice-cream.

In the milk bar she made a friend, a girl called Rose Sawyer. Miss Sawyer was about eighteen and had an Aberdeen terrier on a lead; she worked in the dress shop in the afternoons. She was very interested to hear that Jean came from England, and they talked about England for a time.“How do you like Alice?”she asked presently, and there was a touch of conventional scorn in her tone.

“I like it,”Jean said candidly.“I've seen many worse places. I should think you could have a pretty good time here.”

The girl said,“Well, I like it all right. We were in Newcastle before, and then Daddy got the job of being bank manager here and we all thought it would be awful. All my friends said these outback places were just terrible. I thought I wouldn't be able to stick it, but I've been here fifteen months now and it's not so bad.”

“Alice is better than most, isn't it?”

“That's what they say—I haven't been in any of the others. Of course, all this has come quite recently. There weren't any of these shops before the war, they say.”

Jean learned a little of the history of the town and she was surprised at the rapidity of its growth. In 1928 it was about three houses and a pub; that was the year when the railway reached it from Oodnadatta. The Flying Doctor service started about 1930 and small hospitals were placed about in the surrounding districts. The sisters married furiously, and Jean learned that most of the older families were those of these sisters. By 1939 the population was about three hundred; when the war came the town became a military staging point. After the war the population had risen to about seven hundred and fifty in 1945, and when Jean was there it was about twelve hundred.“All these new houses and shops going up,”Miss Sawyer said.“People seem to be coming in here all the time now.”

She suggested that Jean should come swimming in the late afternoon.“Mrs Maclean's got a lovely swimming-pool, just out by the aerodrome,”she said.“I'll ring her up and ask if I can bring you.”

She called for Jean that afternoon at five o'clock and Jean joined the swimming party at the pool; sitting and basking in the evening sun and looking at the gaunt line of Mount Ertwa, she became absorbed into the social life of Alice Springs. Most of the girls and married women were under thirty; she found them kindly, hospitable people, well educated and avid for news of England. Some spoke quite naturally of England as“home”though none of them had ever been there; each of them cherished the ambition that one day she would be able to go“home”for a trip. By the end of the evening Jean was in a humble frame of mind; these pleasant people knew so much about her country, and she knew so very little about theirs.

She strolled down to the hospital in the cool night, after tea. Mrs Duveen had not been able to give Joe Harman's address offhand, but she confirmed that he was managing a station somewhere in the Gulf country. She would ask her husband and send a message on the morning schedule.

That night Jean thought a good deal about what she would do when she did get the address. It was clear now that her first apprehensions were unfounded; Joe Harman had made a good recovery from his injuries, and was able to carry on his work in the outback. She was amazed that this could be so, but the man was tough. Though there was no compelling need for her to find him now, she felt that it would be impossible to leave Australia without seeing him again; too much had passed between them. She did not fear embarrassment when she met him. She felt that she could tell him the truth frankly; that she had heard of his survival and had come to satisfy herself that he was quite all right. If anything should happen after that, well, that would be just one of those things.

She drifted into sleep, smiling a little.

She went down to the hospital in the morning after the radio schedule and learned that Joe Harman was the manager of Midhurst station, near Willstown. She had never heard of Willstown before; Mr Taylor obligingly got out a map of Australia designed to show the various radio facilities and frequencies of the outback stations, and showed her Willstown at the mouth of the Gilbert River on the Gulf of Carpentaria.

“What sort of a place is it?”she asked him.“Is it a place like this?”

He laughed.“It's a fair cow up there.”He studied the map.“It's got an air-strip, anyway. I don't suppose it's got much else. I've never been there, and I've never heard of anyone who had.”

“I'm going there,”she said.“I've got to see Joe Harman, after coming all this way.”

“It's likely to be rough living,”he said.“Oh my word.”

“Would there be a hotel?”

“Oh, there'll be a hotel. They've got to have their grog.”

She left the hospital and went thoughtfully to the milk bar; as she ordered her ice-cream soda, it occurred to her that it might be a long time before she had another. When she had finished her soda she walked up the street a little way and turned into the magazine and book shop, and bought a map of Australia and a bus timetable and an airline timetable. Then she went back to the milk bar and had another ice-cream soda while she studied this literature.

Presently Rose Sawyer came into the milk bar with her dog. Jean said,“I've found out where Joe Harman lives. Now I've got to find out how to get there. There doesn't seem to be a bus going that way at all.”

They studied the timetables together.“It's going to be much easiest to fly,”said Rose.“That's how everybody goes, these days. It's more expensive, but it may not be in the long run because you've got so many meals and hotels if you try and go by land. I should take the Maclean service to Cloncurry, next Monday.”

It meant staying a few days more in Alice Springs, but it seemed the best thing to do.“You could come and stay with us,”said Rose.“Daddy and Mummy would love to have somebody from England. It's not very nice in the hotel, is it? I've never been in there, of course.”

“It's a bit beery,”said Jean. She was already aware of the strict Australian code, that makes it impossible for a woman to go into a bar.“I would like to do that, if you're sure it wouldn't be a lot of trouble.”

“We'd love to have you. It's so seldom one can talk to anyone that comes from England.”They walked round to the Sawyers' house; on the way they met Mrs Maclean, fair-haired and youthful, pushing her pram. They stopped, and Jean said,“I've got to go to Willstown in the Gulf country to see Joe Harman. Can I get a seat on your plane on Monday as far as Cloncurry?”

“I should think you could. I'm just going to the office; I'll tell them to put you down for Monday. Shall I ask them to arrange the passage for you from Cloncurry on to Willstown? I think you can get there direct from the Curry, but they'll find out that and make the booking if you want.”

“That's awfully good of you,”said Jean.“I would like them to do that.”

“Okay. Coming down to the pool this evening?”

“Yes, please.”

They went on to the Sawyer house, a pleasant bungalow with a rambler rose climbing over it, standing in a small garden full of English flowers, with a sprinkler playing on the lawn. Mrs Sawyer was grey-haired and practical; she made Jean welcome.“Much better for you to be here with us than in that nasty place,”she said, with all of an Australian woman's aversion to hotels.“It'll be nice having you, Miss Paget. Rose was telling us about you yesterday. It's nice to meet somebody from home.”

She went back to the hotel to pack her suitcase, and on the way she stopped at the Post Office. She spent a quarter of an hour sucking the end of a pencil, trying to word a telegram to Joe Harman to tell him that she was coming to see him. Finally she said,

Heard of your recovery from Kuantan atrocity quite recently perfectly delighted stop I am in Australia now and coming up to Willstown to see you next week.

Jean Paget

She took her suitcase round to the Sawyers' house in a taxi, and settled in with them. She stayed with these kind people for four days. On the third day she could not bear to go on lying to them; she told Rose and her mother what had happened in Malaya, and why she was looking for Joe Harman. She begged them not to spread the story; she was terribly afraid that it would get into the papers. They agreed to this, but asked her to tell her story again to Mr Sawyer when he came back from the office.

Mr Sawyer had a lot to say that interested her that evening.“Joe Harman may be on to a good thing up there,”he said.“The Gulf country's not much just at present, but he's a young man, and things can happen very quickly in Australia. This town was nothing twenty years ago, and look at it now! The Gulf's got one thing in its favour, and that's rain. We get about six or seven inches a year up here—about a quarter of what London gets. Up where Joe Harman is they probably get thirty inches—more than England does. That's bound to tell in the long run, you know.”

He sucked at his pipe.“Mind you,”he said,“it's not much good to them, that rainfall, because it all comes in two months and runs off into the sea. It's not spread out all the year round, like yours is in England. But I met a chap from home last year, and he said most of your water would run off into the sea, in England, if you hadn't got a weir every three miles or so on every river. That's what Australia hasn't got around to yet—water conservation on the stations. They're doing a little at it, but not much.”

In the days she spent with the Sawyers, Jean inevitably heard about Rose Sawyer's love life, which was not so far very serious. It chiefly centred round a Mr Billy Wakeling, who built roads when he could get a road to build.“He did awfully well in the war,”she told Jean.“He was a captain when he was twenty-three. But he's nothing to compare with your Joe Harman. He hasn't been crucified for me yet...”

“I'm not in love with Joe Harman,”Jean said with some dignity.“I just want to know that he's all right.”

Rose was still looking round for work that would suit her.

“I like a shop,”she said.“I couldn't ever learn shorthand, like you do. I like a shop all right, but I don't know that the dress shop is much catch. I can never tell what suits a person till I see it on, so I don't think I'll ever be a dress designer. I'd like to run a milk bar, that's what I'd like to do. I think it must be ever such fun, running a milk bar...”

Jean visited Mr Sawyer at the back in his professional capacity, and arranged for him to transfer to Willstown any credits that might come for her account after she had gone. She left Alice Springs on Monday morning with regret, and the Sawyers and Macleans were sorry to see her go.

She flew all that day in a Dragonfly, and it was a very instructive day for her. The machine did not go directly to Cloncurry, but zigzagged to and fro across the wastes of Central Australia, depositing small bags of mail at cattle stations and picking up stockmen and travellers to drop them off after a hundred or a hundred and fifty miles. They landed eight or ten times in the course of the day, at Ammaroo and Hatches Creek and Kurundi and Rockhampton Downs and many other stations; at each place they would get out of the plane and drink a cup of tea and gossip with the station manager or owner, and get back into the plane and go on their way. By the end of the day Jean Paget knew exactly what the homestead of a cattle station looked like, and she was beginning to have a very good idea of what went on there.

They got to Cloncurry at dusk, a fairly extensive town on a railway that ran eastward to the sea at Townsville. Here she was in Queensland, and she heard for the first time the slow, deliberate speech of the Queenslander that reminded her of Joe Harman at once. She was driven into town in a very old open car and deposited at the Post Office Hotel; she got a bedroom but tea was over, and she had to go down the wide, dusty main street to a café for her evening meal. Cloncurry, she found, had none of the clean glamour of Alice Springs; it was a town redolent of cattle, with wide streets through which to drive the herds down to the stockyards, many hotels, and a few shops. All the houses were of wood with red-painted corrugated iron roofs; the hotels were of two storeys, but very few of the other houses were more than bungalows.

She had to spend a day here, because the air service to Normanton and Willstown ran weekly on a Wednesday. She went out after breakfast while the air was still cool and walked up the huge main street for half a mile till she came to the end of the town, and she walked down it a quarter of a mile till she came to the other end. Then she went and had a look at the railway station, and, having seen the aerodrome, with that she had exhausted the sights of Cloncurry. She looked in at a shop that sold toys and newspapers, but they were sold out of all reading matter except a few dressmaking journals; as the day was starting to warm up she went back to the hotel. She managed to borrow a copy of the Australian Women's Weekly from the manageress of the hotel and took it up to her room, and took off most of her clothes and lay down on her bed to sweat it out during the heat of the day. Most of the other citizens of Cloncurry seemed to be doing the same thing.

She revived shortly before tea and had a shower, and went out to the café for an ice-cream soda. Stupefied by the heavy meal of roast beef and plum pudding that the Queenslanders call“tea”she sat in a deckchair for a little in the dusk of the veranda, and went to bed again at about eight o'clock.

She was called before dawn, and was out at the aerodrome with the first light. The aircraft this time was a vintage Dragon, which wandered round the cattle stations as on the previous flight, Canobie and Wandoola and Milgarra. About midday, after four or five landings, they came to the sea, a desolate marshy coast, and shortly after that they put down at Normanton. Half an hour later they were in the air again for Constance Downs station; they had a cup of tea here and a chat with the manager's wife, and took off on the last leg to Willstown.

They got there about the middle of the afternoon, and Jean got a bird's-eye view of the place as they circled for a landing. The country was well wooded with gum trees and fairly green; the Gilbert River ran into the sea about three miles below the town. There was deep, permanent water in it as far up as Willstown and beyond, because she could see a wooden jetty, and the river ran inland out of sight into the heat haze with water in it as far as she could see. All the other watercourses, however, seemed to be dry.

The town itself consisted of about thirty buildings, very widely scattered on two enormous intersecting streets or areas of land, for the streets were not paved. Only one building, which she later learned to be the hotel, was of two storeys. From the town dirt tracks ran out into the country in various directions. That was all that one could see of Willstown, that and a magnificent aerodrome put there in the war for defence purposes, with three enormous tarmac runways each a mile long.

They landed upon one of these huge runways, and taxied towards a truck parked at the runway intersection; this truck was loaded with two barrels of petrol and a semi-rotary pump for refuelling. The pilot said to Jean as he came down the cabin,“You're getting off here, Miss Paget? Is anyone meeting you?”

She shook her head.“I want to see a man who's living in this district, on one of the stations. I'll have to go to the hotel, I think.”

“Who is it? Al Burns, the Shell agent out there on the truck, he knows everybody here.”

She said,“Oh, that's a good idea. I want to see Mr Joe Harman. He's manager of Midhurst station.”

They got out of the aeroplane together.“Morning, Al,”the pilot said.“She'll take about forty gallons. I'll have a look at the oil in a minute. Is Joe Harman in town?”

“Joe Harman?”said the man in the truck. He was a lean, dark-haired man of forty or so.“Joe Harman's in England. Went there for a holiday.”

Jean blinked, and tried to collect her thoughts. She had been prepared to hear that Harman was out on his property or even that he was away in Cairns or Townsville, but it was absurd to be told that he was in England. She was staggered for a moment, and then she wanted to laugh. She realized that the men were looking at her curiously.“I sent him a telegram to say that I was coming,”she said foolishly.“I suppose he didn't get that.”

“Couldn't have done,”said Al Burns slowly.“When did you send it?”

“About four or five days ago, from Alice Springs.”

“Oh no, he wouldn't have got that. Jim Lennon might have it, out at Midhurst station.”

“That's dinky-die is it?”the pilot asked.“He's gone to England?”

“Went about a month ago,”the man said.“Jim Lennon said the other night that he'd be back about the end of October.”

The pilot turned to Jean.“What will you do, Miss Paget? Do you want to stay here now? It's not much of a place, you know.”

She bit her lip in thought.“When will you be taking off?”she asked.“You're going back to Cloncurry?”

“That's right,”he replied.“We're going back to Normanton tonight and night-stopping there, and back to the Curry tomorrow morning. I'm going into town now while Al fills her up. Take off in about half an hour.”

Cloncurry was the last place that she wanted to go back to.“I'll have to think about this,”she said.“I'll have to stay in Australia, till I've seen Joe Harman. Cairns is a nice place to stay, isn't it?”

“Oh, Cairns is a bonza town,”he said.“Townsville, too. If you've got to wait six or eight weeks you don't want to wait here, Miss Paget.”

“How could I get to Cairns?”she asked.

“Well,”he said.“You could come back with me to Cloncurry and then go by train to Townsville and up to Cairns. I don't quite know how long that would take in the train—it must be between six and seven hundred miles. Or you could wait here till next Wednesday, today week, and go by the Dakota straight to Cairns in about two and a half hours.”

“How long would the train take, from Cloncurry to Cairns?”

“Oh, I don't know about that. I don't think they go every day from Townsville to Cairns, but I'm not really sure. I think you'd have to allow three days.”He paused.“Of course, the best way would be to fly from Cloncurry to Townsville and then fly up to Cairns.”

“I know.”She was getting very sensitive of the cost of flying these vast distances, but the alternative of three days in an outback train in sweltering heat was almost unbearable.“It'ld be much cheaper to stay here and go by the Dakota next week, wouldn't it?”

The pilot said,“Oh, much. From here to Cairns would cost you ten pounds fifteen shillings. Flying back to Cloncurry and then on to Townsville and Cairns would be about thirty pounds.”

“I suppose the hotel here is quite cheap?”

“About twelve and six a day, I should think.”He turned to the Shell agent, busy with the fuel.“Al, how much does Mrs Connor charge?”

“Ten and six.”

Jean did a rapid mental calculation; by staying in this place and waiting for the Dakota in a week's time she would save sixteen pounds.“I think I'll stay here,”she said.“It's much cheaper than going back with you. I'll stay here and see Jim Lennon and wait for the Dakota next week.”

“You know what it's going to be like, Miss Paget?”

“Like the Post Office Hotel at Cloncurry?”

“It's a bit more primitive than that. The whatnot's out in the back yard.”

She laughed.“Will I have to lock myself in my room and take a revolver to bed with me?”

He was a little shocked.“Oh, you'll find it quite respectable. But, well, you may find it a little primitive, you know.”

“I expect I'll survive.”

By that time another truck had appeared, a lorry with a couple of men in it; they stared at Jean curiously. The pilot took her suitcase and put it in the back; the driver helped her up into the cab beside him. It was a relief to get out of the blazing sunshine into the shade again.

The driver said,“Staying in Willstown?”

“I wanted to see Joe Harman, but they say he's away. I'm staying here till next week if Mrs Connor can have me, and going on to Cairns in the Dakota.”

He looked at her curiously.“Joe Harman's gone to England. You're English, aren't you?”

The truck moved off down the wide tarmac runway.“That's right,”she replied.

He beamed at her.“My mother and my dad, they both came from England. My dad, he was born in Lewisham, that's part of London, I think, and my mother, she came from Hull.”He paused.“My name's Small,”he said.“Sam Small, like the chap with the musket.”

The truck left the runway and began bumping and swaying over the earth track leading to the town. Dust rose into the cab, the engine roared, and blue fumes enveloped them; every item of the structure creaked and rattled.“Why did Joe Harman go to England?”she shouted above the din.“What did he go for?”

“Just took a fancy, I think,”Mr Small replied.“He won the Casket couple of years back.”This was Greek to her.“There's not a lot to do upon the stations, this time of the year.”

She shouted,“Do you know if there's a room vacant at the hotel?”

“Oh, aye, there'll be a room for you. You just out from England?”

“Yes.”

“What's the rationing like at home, now?”

She shouted her information to him as the truck bumped and swayed across the landscape to the town. A wooden shack appeared on one side of the track, and fifty yards on there was another on the left; there was another some distance ahead, and they were in the main street. They drew up in front of a two-storeyed building with a faded signboard on the first-floor veranda, AUSTRALIAN HOTEL.“This is it,”said Mr Small.“Come on in, and I'll find Mrs Connor.”

The Australian Hotel was a fair-sized building with about ten small bedrooms opening on to the top floor veranda. It had wooden floors and wooden doors; the whole of the rest of it was built of corrugated iron on a wood framework. Jean was accustomed by that time to the universal corrugated iron roofs, but a corrugated iron wall to her bedroom was a novelty.

She waited on the upstairs veranda while Mr Small went to find Mrs Connor; the veranda had one or two beds on it. When the landlady appeared she was evidently only just awake; she was a tall, grey-haired determined woman of about fifty.

Jean said,“Good afternoon. My name's Jean Paget, and I've got to stop here till next week. Have you got a room?”

The woman looked her up and down.“Well, I don't know, I'm sure. You travelling alone?”

“Yes. I really came to see Joe Harman, but they tell me he's away. I'm going on to Cairns.”

“You just missed the Cairns aeroplane.”

“I know. They say I'll have to wait a week for the next one.”

“That's right.”The woman looked around.“Well, I don't know. You see, the men sleep out on this balcony, often as not. That wouldn't be very nice for you.”

Sam Small said,“What about the two back rooms, Ma?”

“Aye, she could go there.”She turned to Jean.“It's on the back balcony, looks out over the yard. You'll see the boys all going to the gents, but I can't help that.”

Jean said,“I expect I'll survive that.”

“You been in outback towns before?”

She shook her head.“I've only just come out from England.”

“Is that so! What's it like in England now? Do you get enough to eat?”

Jean said her piece again.

“I got a sister married to an Englishman,”the woman said.“Living at a place called Goole. I send her home a parcel every month.”

She took Jean and showed her the room. It was clean and with a good mosquito net; it was small, but the passage door was opposite the double window opening on to the balcony, giving a clear draught through.“Nobody don't come along this balcony, except Anne—she's the maid. She sleeps in this other room, and if you hear any goings on at night I hope you'll let me know. I got my eye upon that girl.”She reverted to the ventilation.“You leave your door open a chink, prop your case against it so that no one can't come barging in by mistake, and have the windows open, and you'll get a nice draught through. I never had no difficulty sleeping in this place.”

She glanced down at Jean's hand.“You ain't married?”

“No.”

“Well, there'll be every ringer in this district coming into town to have a look at you. You better be prepared for that.”

Jean laughed.“I will.”

“You a friend of Joe Harman, then?”

“I met him in the war,”Jean said.“In Singapore, when we were both waiting for a passage home.”It was nearer to the truth than her last lie, anyway.“Then as I was in Australia I sent him a telegram to say I'd come and see him. I didn't get an answer so I came here anyway. But he's gone walkabout.”

The woman smiled.“You picked up some Aussie slang.”

“Joe Harman taught me that one, when I met him in the war.”

Sam Small brought up her suitcase; she thanked him, and he turned away, embarrassed. She went into her room and changed her damp clothes for dry ones, and went along to the bathroom and had a shower, and was ready for tea at half past six when the bell echoed through the corrugated iron building.

She found her way down to the dining-room. Three or four men were seated there already and they looked at her curiously; a well-developed girl of sixteen whom she came to know as Annie indicated a separate small table laid for one.“Roast beef, roast lamb, roast pork, roast turkey,”she said.“Tea or coffee?”

It was swelteringly hot still. Flies were everywhere in the dining-room; they lighted on Jean's face, her lips, her hands.“Roast turkey,”she said; time enough to try for a light meal tomorrow, when she knew the form.“Tea.”

A plate was brought to her heaped high with meat and vegetables, hot and greasy and already an attraction for the flies. Tea came, with milk out of a tin; the potatoes seemed to be fresh, but the carrots and the turnips were evidently tinned. She thought philosophically that the flies would probably result in dysentery but she knew what to do about that; she had plenty of sulphatriad to see her through the week. She ate about a quarter of the huge plate of food and drank two cups of tea; then she was defeated.

She got outside into the open air as soon as possible, escaping from the flies. On the downstairs veranda three feet above the level of the ground there were two or three deckchairs, a little distance from the entrance to the bar; She had seen nowhere else in the hotel where she could sit and she already knew enough about Australian conventions not to go near the bar; she went and sat down in one of these chairs wondering if by doing so she was offending against local manners.

She lit a cigarette and sat there smoking, looking at the scene. It was evening but the sun was still strong; the dusty great expanse that served as a street was flooded with a golden light. On the opposite side of the road, more than a hundred yards away, there was a fairly extensive single-storey building that had been built on to from time to time; this was labelled—Wm Duncan, General Merchant. There was no sign of any other shop in the town. Outside Mr Duncan's establishment three coloured Abo stockmen were gossiping together; one held the bridle of a horse. They were big, well-set-up young men, very like Negroes in appearance and, like Negroes, they seemed to have plenty to laugh about.

Further along the other side of the great street a six-inch pipe rose vertically from the ground to a height of about eight feet. A fountain of water gushed up from the top of this pipe and the water seemed to be boiling hot, because a cloud of steam surrounded the fountain, and the stream running away into the background was steaming along its length. A quarter of a mile away a small hut was built across the course of the stream so that the stream ran into the hut and out the other side, but Jean had yet to discover the purpose of this edifice.

A low murmur of voices reached her from the bar; from time to time a man passed her and went in through the open door. She saw no women in the place.

Presently a young man, passing by upon the road, smiled at her and said,“Good evening.”She smiled back at him, and said,“Good evening.”

He checked immediately, and she knew that she had started something. He said,“I saw you come in with Sam Small this afternoon. Came in the aeroplane, didn't you?”

He was a clean-looking young yokel; he walked with the typical swaying gait of the ringer, and he wore the green jodhpurs and the elastic-sided boots that marked his calling. It was no good trying to be standoffish.“That's right,”she said.“I came up from Cloncurry. Tell me, is that water natural?”

He looked where she was pointing.“Natural? That's a bore. Never seen one before?”

She shook her head.“I've only just come out from England.”

“From England? Oh my word.”He spoke in the slow manner of the outback.“What's it like in England? Do you get enough to eat?”

She said her piece again.“My Dad came from England,”he said.“From a place called Wolverhampton. Is that near where you live?”

“About two hundred miles,”she replied.

“Oh, quite close. You'll know the family then. Fletcher is the name. I'm Pete Fletcher.”

She explained to Pete that there were quite a lot of people in England, and reverted to the subject of the bore.“Does all the water that you get from bores come up hot like that?”

“Too right,”he said.“It's mineral, too—you couldn't drink that water. There's gas comes up with it as well. I'll light it for you if you'd like to see.”He explained that it would make a flame five or six feet high.“Wait till it gets a bit darker, and I'll light it for you then.”

She said that was terribly kind of him, and he looked embarrassed. Al Burn, the Shell agent and truck repairer came by and stopped to join them.“Got fixed up all right, Miss Paget?”

“Yes, thank you. I'm staying here till Wednesday and then going on to Cairns.”

“Good-oh. We don't see too many strange faces, here in Willstown.”

“I was asking Pete here about the bore. Pete, do the cattle drink that water?”

The boy laughed.“When they can't get nothing sweeter they'll drink that. You'll see that they won't touch it in the wet, but then in the dry you'll see them drinking it all right.”

“Some bores they won't touch,”said Al. He was rolling himself a cigarette.“They sunk a bore on Invergordon, that's a station between here and Normanton—over to the south a bit. They had to go down close on three thousand feet before they got the water and did it cost them something, oh my word. The bore crew, they were there close on three months. Then when they got the water it was stinking with the minerals and the cattle wouldn't touch it, not even in the dry. What's more, it wouldn't grow grass, either.”

Two more men had drifted up and joined the little gathering about her chair.“Tell me,”she said,“why is this town so spread out? Why aren't the houses closer together?”

One of the newcomers, a man of forty that she later learned to know as Tim Whelan, a carpenter, said,“There was houses all along here once. I got a photograph of this town took in 1905. I'll bring it and show you tomorrow.”

“Were there more people living here then?”

Al Burns said,“Oh my word. This was one of the gold towns, Miss Paget. Maybe you wouldn't know about that, but there was thirty thousand people living here one time.”

The other newcomer said,“Eight thousand. I saw that in a book.”

Al Burns said stubbornly,“My Dad always said there was thirty thousand when he come here first.”

It was evidently an old argument. Jean asked,“How many are there now?”

“Oh, I dunno.”Al turned to the others.“How many would you say now, Tim?”To Jean, aside, he said,“He builds the coffins so he ought to know.”

“A hundred and fifty,”said Mr Whelan.

Sam Small had joined them on the veranda.“There's not a hundred and fifty living in Willstown now. There's not more than a hundred and twenty.”He paused.“Living here in the town, not the stations, of course. Living right here in the town, not counting boongs.”

A slow wrangle developed, so they set to work to count them; Jean sat amused while the evening light faded and the census was taken. The result was a hundred and forty-six, and by the time that that had been determined she had heard the name and occupation of most people in the town.

“Were there goldmines here?”she asked.

“That's right,”said Mr Small.“They had claims by the hundred one time, all up and down these creeks, oh my word. There were seventeen hotels here, seventeen.”

Somebody else said,“Steamers used to come here from Brisbane in those days—all around Cape York and right up the river to the landing stage. I never see them myself, but that's what my old man told me.”

Jean asked,“What happened? Did the gold come to an end?”

“Aye. They got the stuff out of the creeks and the surface reefs, the stuff that was easy got. Then when they had to go deep and use a lot of machinery and that, it didn't pay. It's the same in all these towns. Croydon was the same, and Normanton.”

“They say they're going to start the mine in Croydon—open it again,”said somebody.

“They been talking like that ever since I can remember.”

Jean asked,“But what happened to the houses? Did the people go away?”

“The houses just fell down, or were pulled down to patch up others,”Al told her.“The people didn't stay here when the gold was done—they couldn't. There's only the cattle stations here now.”

The talk developed among the men, with Jean throwing in an occasional remark or question.“Ghost towns,”somebody said.“That's what they called the Gulf towns in a book that I read once. Ghost towns. That's because they're ghosts of what they were once, when the gold was on.”

“It didn't last for long,”somebody said.“1893 was the year that the first gold here was found, and there wasn't many people still living here in 1905.”

Jean sat while the men talked, trying to visualize this derelict little place as a town with eight thousand inhabitants, or thirty thousand; a place with seventeen hotels and houses thickly clustered in the angles of the streets. Whoever had planned the layout had dreamed a great dream; with people streaming in to take up claims and the population doubling itself every few days, the planner had had some excuse for dreaming of a New York of the Gulf of Carpentaria. Now all that remained was a network of rectangular tracks where once there had been streets of wooden houses; odd buildings alone remained among this network to show what had been the dream.

As the light faded Pete and Al went out and lit the bore for Jean. They struck half a dozen matches and got it to light; a flame shot upwards from it and lit up the whole town, playing and flickering amongst the water and the steam till finally it was extinguished by a vomit of water. They lit it again, and Jean admired it duly; it was clear that this was the one entertainment that the town provided, and they were doing their best to give her a good time.“It's wonderful,”she said.“I've never seen anything like that in England.”

They were duly modest.“Most towns around here have a bore like that, that you can light,”they said.

She was tired with her day of flying; at nine o'clock she excused herself from their company and they all wished her goodnight. She drew Al Burns a little to one side before she went.“Al,”she said.“I'd like to see Jim Lennon—he's the man at Midhurst, isn't he? I'd like to see him before I go on Wednesday. Will he be coming into town?”

“Saturday he might be in,”Al said.“I'd say that he'd be in here Saturday for his grog. If I hear of anybody going out that way I'll send him word and say that you're in town, and want to see him.”

“Do they work a radio schedule at Midhurst?”

He shook his head.“It's too close in town, it wouldn't be worth it. If anyone gets sick or has an accident they can get him into town here in an hour or so, and the sister has a radio at the hospital.”He paused.“There'll be someone going out that way in the next day or so. If not, and if Jim Lennon doesn't come in on Saturday, I'll run you out there in the truck on Sunday.”

“That's awfully kind of you,”she said.“I don't want to put you to that trouble.”

“It's no trouble,”he said.“Make a bit of a change.”

She went up to bed. The hotel was lit by electric light made in the backyard by an oil engine and generator set that thumped steadily outside her room till she heard the bar close at ten o'clock; at five past ten the engine stopped and all the lights went out. Willstown slept.

She was roused at five o'clock with the first light with the sounds of people getting up and washing; she lay dozing, listening to the early morning sounds. Breakfast was not till half past seven; she got up and had a shower and was punctual in the dining-room. She found that the standard breakfast in Willstown was half a pound of steak with two fried eggs on top of it; she surprised Annie very much by asking for one fried egg and no steak.“Breakfast is steak and eggs,”Annie explained patiently to this queer Englishwoman.

“I know it is,”said Jean.“But I don't want the steak.”

“Well, you don't have to eat it.”The girl was obviously puzzled.

“Could I have just one fried egg, and no steak?”asked Jean.

“You mean, just one fried egg on a plate by itself?”

“That's right.”

Food conversation in Willstown was evidently quite a new idea.“I'll ask Mrs Connor,”said Annie. She came back from the kitchen with a steak with two fried eggs on top.“We've only got the one breakfast,”she explained. Jean gave up the struggle.

She ventured out to the kitchen after breakfast and found Mrs Connor.“I've got a few things to wash,”she said.“Could I use your washtub, do you think? And—have you got an iron?”

“Annie'll do them for you,”Mrs Connor said.“Just give them to her.”

Jean had no intention of trusting her clothes to Annie.“She's got a lot of work to do,”she said,“and I've got nothing. I'll do them myself if I can borrow the tub.”

“Good-oh.”

Jean spent the morning washing and ironing in the back ground-floor veranda just outside the kitchen; in that dry, torrid place clothes hung out on a line were dry in ten minutes. In the kitchen the temperature must have been close on a hundred and twenty Fahrenheit; Jean made quick rushes in there to fetch her irons from the stove, and wondered at the fortitude of women who cooked three hot meals a day in such conditions. Annie came presently and stood around on the back veranda, furtively examining Jean's washing.

She picked up a carton of soap flakes.“How much of this do you put in the water?”

Jean said,“I think it's an ounce to a gallon of water, isn't it? I used to know. I put in just a bit. It tells you on the packet.”

The girl turned the packet over in her hands, scrutinizing it.“Where it says, DIRECTIONS FOR USE,”said Jean.

From the door behind her Mrs Connor said,“Annie don't read very well.”

The girl said,“I can read.”

“Oh, can you? Well then, read us out what's written on that packet.”

The girl put the carton down.“I ain't had much practice lately. I could read all right when I was at school.”

To ease the situation Jean said,“All you do is just go on putting in the soap flakes till the water lathers properly. It's different with different sorts of water, because of the hardness.”

“I use ordinary soap,”said Annie.“It don't come up so well as this.”

Presently the girl said,“Are you a nurse?”

Jean shook her head.“I'm a typist.”

“Oh, I thought you might be a nurse. Most women that come to Willstown are nurses. They don't stay here long. Six months, and then they've had enough.”

There was a pause.“If you'd been a nurse,”the girl said,“I'd have asked you for some medicine. I've been feeling ever so ill lately just after getting up. I was sick this morning.”

“That's bad,”said Jean cautiously. There did not seem to be much else to say.

“I think I'll go up to the hospital,”said Annie,“and ask Sister Douglas for some medicine.”

“I should do that,”said Jean.

In the course of the day she met most of the notable citizens of Willstown. She walked across to the store to try and buy some cigarettes, but only succeeded in buying a tin of tobacco and a packet of papers. While she was chatting to Mr Bill Duncan in the store and examining the piece of quartz with gold in it that he showed her, Miss Kenroy came in, the school teacher. Half an hour later, as Jean was walking back across the road to the hotel, Al Burns met her and wanted to introduce her to Mr Carter, the Shire Clerk.

She slept most of the afternoon upon her bed, in common with the rest of Willstown, when the day cooled off she came down to the lower veranda and sat there in a deckchair, as she had the previous evening. She had not long to wait before the ringers found her; they came one by one, diffidently, unsure of themselves before this English girl, and yet unable to keep away. She had a little circle of them squatting with her on the veranda presently.

She got them to talk about themselves; it seemed the best way to put them at their ease.“It's all right here,”said one.“It's good cattle country; more rain here than what you get down further south. But I'm off out of it next year. My brother, he's down at Rockhampton working on the railway. He said he'd get me in the gang if I went down and joined him.”

Jean asked,“Is it better pay down there?”

“Well, no. I don't think it's so good. We get five pounds seventeen and six here—that's all found, of course. That's for an ordinary stockrider.”

She was surprised.“That's not bad pay, is it? For a single man?”

Pete Fletcher said,“The pay's all right. Trouble is this place. There's nothing to do here.”

“Do you get a cinema here ever?”

“There's a chap supposed to come here every fortnight and show films in the Shire Hall—that building over there.”She saw a low, barnlike wooden structure.“He hasn't been for a month, but he's coming next week, Mr Carter says.”

“What about dances?”Jean asked.

There was a cynical laugh.“They try it sometimes, but it's a crook place for a dance. Not enough girls.”

Pete Fletcher said,“There's about fifty of us stockmen come into Willstown, Miss Paget, and there's two unmarried girls to dance with, Doris Nash and Susie Anderson. That's between the age of seventeen and twenty-two, say. Not counting the kids and the married women.”

One of the ringers laughed sourly.“Susie's more than twenty-two.”

Jean asked,“But what happens to all the girls? There must be more than that around here?”

“They all go to the cities for a job,”said somebody.“There's nothing for a girl to do in Willstown. They go to Townsville and Rockhampton—Brisbane, too.”

Pete Fletcher said,“That's where I'm going, Brisbane.”

Jean said,“Don't you like it on a cattle station, then?”She was thinking of Joe Harman and his love for the outback.

“Oh, the station's all right,”said Pete. He hesitated, uncertain how to put what he felt to this Englishwoman without incautiously using a rude word.“I mean,”he said,“a fellow's got a right to have a girl and marry, like anybody else.”

She stared at him.“It's really like that, is it?”

“It's a fair cow,”said somebody.“It's a fair cow up here. No kidding, lady. It's two unmarried girls for fifty men in Willstown. A fellow hasn't got a chance of marrying up here.”

Somebody else explained to her,“You see, Miss Paget, if a girl's a normal girl and got her head screwed on right—say, like it might be you—you wouldn't stay here. Soon as you were old enough to go away from home you'd be off to some place where you could get a job and make your own living, not have to depend on your folks all the time. My word, you would. The only girls that stay in Willstown are the ones who are a bit stupid and couldn't make out in any other place, or else ones who feel they've got to stay and look after the old folks.”

Somebody else said,“That kind take the old folks with them down to the city. Like Elsie Freeman.”

Jean laughed.“You mean, that if you stay in Willstown you'll finish up by marrying a girl who's not so hot.”

They looked over their shoulders, embarrassed.“Well, a fellow wants to look around a bit...”

“Who's going to run the stations if you all go down to the cities, looking round a bit?”Jean said.

“That's the manager's headache,”said Pete.“I've got headaches of my own.”

That evening shortly before tea a utility drove up, a battered old Chevrolet with a cab front and an open, truck-like body behind. It was driven by a man of about fifty with lean, sensitive features. Beside him sat a brown girl of twenty or twenty-five with a smooth skin and a serene face; she was not pure native, but probably a quarter white. She wore a bright red dress, and she carried a kitten, which was evidently a great amusement and interest to her. They passed into the hotel, the man carrying their bags; evidently they were staying for the night. At teatime Jean saw them in the dining-room sitting with the men at the other table, but they were keeping very much to themselves.

Jean asked Mrs Connor who they were, after tea.“That's Eddie Page,”she said.“He's manager of a station called Carlisle about a hundred miles out. The lubra's his wife; they've come in to buy stores.”

“Real wife?”asked Jean.

“Oh yes, he married her properly. One of the Bush Brothers was round that way last year, Brother Copeland, and he married them. They come in here from time to time. I must say, she never makes any trouble. She can't read or write, of course, and she doesn't speak much. Always got a kitten or a puppy along with her; that's what she likes.”

The picture of the man's sensitive, intelligent face came incongruously into Jean's mind.“I wonder what made him do that?”

Mrs Connor shrugged her shoulders.“Got lonely, I suppose.”

That night, when Jean went up to her bedroom, she saw a figure standing by the rail of the balcony that overlooked the backyard. There were two bedrooms only that opened on that balcony, her own and Annie's. In the dim light as she was going in at her window, she said,“Goodnight, Annie.”

The girl came towards her.“I been feeling awful bad,”she muttered.“Mind if I ask you something, Miss Paget?”

Jean stopped.“Of course, Annie. What's the matter?”

“Do you know how to get rid of a baby, Miss Paget?”

Jean had been prepared for that one by the morning's conversation; a deep pity for the child welled up in her.“I'm terribly sorry, Annie, but I don't. I don't think it's a very good thing to do, you know.”

“I went up to Sister Douglas and she said that's what's the matter with me. Pa'll beat the daylights out of me when he hears.”

Jean took her hand, and drew her into the bedroom.“Come in here and tell me about it.”

Annie said,“I know there's things you can do like eating something or riding on a horse or something like that. I thought perhaps you might have had to do it, and you'd know.”

“I've never had to do it, Annie. I don't know. Why don't you ask him to marry you and have it normally?”

The girl said,“I don't know how you'd tell which one it was. They'd all say it was one of the others, wouldn't they?”

It was a problem that Jean had never had to face.“I suppose they would.”

“I think I'll ask my sister Bessie. She might know. She had two kids afore getting married.”

It did not look as if Bessie's knowledge had been very useful to her. Jean asked,“Wouldn't the sister do anything to help you?”

“All she did was call me a wicked girl. That don't help much. Suppose I am a wicked girl. There's nothing else to do in a crook place like this.”

Jean did what she could to comfort her with words, but words were little good to Annie. Her interests were not moral, but practical.“Pa will be mad as anything when he gets to know about it,”she said apprehensively.“He'll beat the daylights out o'me.”

There was nothing Jean could do to help the girl, and presently they went to bed. Jean lay awake for a long time beset by human suffering.

She continued for the next two days in Willstown, sitting on the veranda and talking to the ringers, and visiting the various establishments in the town. Miss Kenroy took her and showed her the school. Sister Douglas showed her the hospital. Mr Carter showed her the Shire Hall with the pathetically few books that constituted the public library; Mr Watkins showed her the bank, which was full of flies, and Sergeant Haines showed her the Police Station. By the end of the week she was beginning to know a good deal about Willstown.

Jim Lennon came into town on Saturday, as predicted, for his grog. He came in an International utility that Jean learned was the property of Joe Harman, an outsize in motor cars with a truck body behind the front seat, furnished with tanks for seventy gallons of petrol and fifty gallons of water. Mr Lennon was a lean, bronzed, taciturn man.

“I got an air mail letter yesterday,”he said with the deliberation of the Queenslander.“Joe's starting on his way back from England in a ship. He said he'd be about the middle of October, so he thought.”

“I see,”said Jean.“I want to see him before I go back to England. I've arranged to fly to Cairns on Wednesday and wait there for him.”

“Aye. There's not much for you to do, I don't suppose, waiting round here. I'd say come out and live at Midhurst, but there's less to do there.”

“What's Joe been doing in England, Mr Lennon? Did he tell you what he was going for?”

The stockman laughed.“I didn't even know he was going. All I knew he was going down to Brisbane. Then I got a letter that he'd gone to England. I don't know why he went. He did say in this letter I got yesterday he'd seen a bonza herd of Herefords, belonging to a Sir Dennis Frampton. Maybe he's having bulls shipped out to raise the quality of the stock. He didn't tell me nothing.”

She gave him her address as the Strand Hotel in Cairns, and asked him to let her know when he got accurate news of Joe's arrival.

That evening as she was sitting in her deckchair on the veranda, Al Burns brought a bashful, bearded old man to her; he had disengaged the old man from the bar with some difficulty. He was carrying a sack.“Miss Paget,”he said,“want you to meet Jeff Pocock.”Jean got up and shook hands.“Thought you'd like to meet Jeff,”Al said cheerfully.“Jeff's the best alligator hunter in all Queensland. Aren't you, Jeff?”

The old man wagged his head.“I been huntin' 'gators since I was a boy,”he said.“I reckon I knows 'gators by this time.”

Al said,“He's got an alligator skin to show you, Miss Paget.”To the old man he said,“Show her your skin, Jeff. I bet she's never seen a skin like that in England.”

Jeff Pocock took the sack and opened it, and took out a small alligator skin rolled up.“'Course,”he said,“I cleaned and trimmed and tanned this one myself. Mostly we just salt them and sell 'em to the tannery like that.”He unrolled the skin before her on the floor of the veranda.“Pretty markings, ain't they? I bet you never seen a skin like that in England.”

The sight of it brought back nostalgic memories to Jean of red buses on the Great West Road at Perivale, and Pack and Levy Ltd, and rows of girls sitting at the work benches making up alligator-skin shoes and alligator-skin handbags and alligator-skin dressing-cases. She laughed.“I've seen hundreds of them in England,”she replied.“This is one thing I really know about. I used to work in a factory that made these skins up into handbags and dressing-cases.”She picked up the skin and handled it.“Ours were harder than this, I think. You've done the curing very well, Jeff.”

Two or three other men had drifted up; her story was repeated back and forth in other words, and she told them all about Pack and Levy Ltd. They were very interested; none of them knew much about the skins after they had left the Gulf country.“I know as they make shoes of them,”said Jeff.“I never see a pair.”

A vague idea was forming in Jean's mind.“How many of these do you get a year?”she asked.

“I turned in eighty-two last year,”the old man said.“'Course that's a little 'un. They mostly run about thirty to thirty-six inch—width of skin, that is. That's a 'gator about eleven foot long.”

Jean said,“Will you sell me this one, Jeff?”

“What do you want it for?”

She laughed.“I want to make myself a pair of shoes out of it.”She paused.“That's if Tim Whelan can make up a pair of lasts for me.”

He looked embarrassed.“I don't want nothing for it,”he said gruffly.“I'll give it to you.”

She argued with him for a little while, and then accepted gracefully.“We'll want a bit of calf skin for the soles,”she said,“and some thicker stuff for building up the heels.”

She fondled the skin in her hands.“It's beautifully soft,”she said,“I'll show you what to do with this.”

Chapter 7

Jean made that pair of shoes working upon the dressing-table of her bedroom; to be more exact, she made three pairs before she got a pair that she could wear.

She started off upon Tim Whelan. Tim had made lasts for shoes from time to time, working for various cobblers; the outback woodworker must turn his hand to anything. Jean lent him one of her shoes and lent him her foot to measure in his carpenter's shop, and he made a pair of lasts for her in mulga wood in a couple of days. She asked Pete Fletcher about leather for the soles and heels, and he produced some pieces of tanned cow-skin which were about the right thickness for the soles, and a piece of bull's skin for building up the heels. The lining was a major difficulty at first till somebody suggested a young wallaby skin. Pete Fletcher went out and shot the wallaby and skinned it, and the tanning was carried out by a committee of Pete Fletcher and Al Burns and Don Duncan, working in the back of Bill Duncan's store. The business of this pair of shoes assumed such an importance in the life of Willstown that Jean put off her trip to Cairns for a week, and then another week.

The wallaby skin for the lining was not ready, so Jean made up the first pair with a white satin lining that she bought in the store. She knew every process of shoe-making intimately from the point of view of an onlooker, and from the office end, but she had never done it herself before, and the first pair of shoes were terrible. They were shoes of a sort, but they pinched her toes and the heels were too large by a quarter of an inch, and they hurt her instep. The satin lining was not a success, and the whole job was messy with the streaming perspiration of her fingers. Still, they were shoes, and wearable by anyone whose feet happened to be that shape.

She could not show shoes like that to the men downstairs, and so she set to work to make another pair. She got Tim to alter the lasts for her, bought another knife and a small carborundum stone from the store, and started again. For fixative she was using small tubes of Durofix, also from the store.

In all this work Annie took a great interest. She used to come and sit and watch Jean working as she trimmed and filed the soles or stretched the wet alligator hides carefully upon the lasts.“I do think you're clever to be able to do that,”she said.“They're almost as good as you could buy in a shop.”

The second pair were better. They fitted Jean moderately well, but the wallaby-skin lining was uneven and lumpy, and the whole job was still messy and fingermarked with sweat. Undaunted, she began upon a third pair. This time she used portions of the wallaby skin that were of even thickness, having no means of trimming the skin down, and when it came to the final assembly of the shoes she worked in the early morning when the perspiration of her hands was least. The final result was quite a creditable shoe with rather an ugly coloured lining, but a shoe that she could have worn anywhere.

She took the three pairs downstairs and showed them to Al Burns on the veranda; Al fetched two or three of the other men, and Mrs Connor came to have a look at them.“That's what happens to the alligator skins in England,”Jean said.“They make them up into shoes like that. Pretty, aren't they?”

One of the men said,“You made them yourself, Miss Paget?”

She laughed.“Ask Mrs Connor. She knows the mess I've been making in the bedroom.”

The man turned the shoe over in his hand.“Oh my word,”he said slowly.“It's as good as you'd buy in a shop.”

Jean shook her head.“It's not,”she said.“It's not really.”She pointed out the defects to him.“I haven't got the proper brads or the proper fixative. And the whole thing's messy, too. I just made it up to show you what they do with all these skins that Jeff brings in.”

“I bet you could sell that in Cairns,”the man said, stubbornly.“Oh my word, you could.”

Sam Small said,“How much does a pair of shoes like that cost in England?”

“In a shop?”She thought for a minute.“About four pounds fifteen shillings, I should say. I know the manufacturer gets about forty-five bob, but then there's purchase tax and retailer's commission to go on.”She paused.“Of course, you can pay much more than that for a really good shoe. People pay up to ten pounds in some shops.”

“Ten pounds for a pair of shoes like that? Oh my word.”

Jeff was out of town up the river visiting his traps, so she could not show him the shoes that day. She left them with the men to take into the bar and talk over, and she went to have a bath. She had discovered how to have a bath in Willstown by that time; Annie had showed her. The Australian Hotel had a cold shower for ladies, which was usually a very hot shower because the tank stood in the sun. But if you wanted to wallow in hot water, there was another technique altogether.

Where the water from the bore ran off in a hot stream, a small wooden hut had been constructed spanning the stream, at such a distance from the bore that the temperature was just right for a bath. A rough concrete pool had been constructed here large enough for two bodies to lie in side by side; you took your towel and soap and went to the hut and locked yourself in and bathed in the warm, saline water flowing through the pool. The salts in the water made this bath unusually refreshing.

Jean lay in the warm water, locked in the little hut alone; the sunlight came in through little chinks in the woodwork and played on the water as she lay. Since she had seen Jeff Pocock's alligator skin the idea of making shoes had been in her mind. From the time that she had first met me and learned of her inheritance she had been puzzled, and at times distressed, by the problem of what she was going to do with her life. She had no background of education or environment that would have enabled her to take gracefully to a life of ease. She was a business girl, accustomed to industry. She had given up her work with Pack and Levy as was only natural when she inherited nine hundred a year, but she had found nothing yet to fill the gap left in her life. Subconsciously she had been searching, questing, for the last six months, seeking to find something that she could work at. The only work she really knew about was fancy leather goods, alligator shoes and handbags and attaché cases. She did know a little bit about the business of making and selling those.

She lay in the warm, medicated water, thinking deeply. Suppose a little workshop with about five girls in it, and a small tannery outside. Two handpresses and a rotary polisher; that meant a supply of electric current. A small motor generator set, unless perhaps she could buy current from the hotel. An air conditioner to keep the workshop cool and keep the girls' hands from sweating as they worked. It was imperative that the finished shoes should be virgin clean.

Could such a set-up pay? She lay calculating in her bath. She had discovered that Jeff Pocock got about seventy shillings for an average alligator skin, uncured. She knew that Pack and Levy paid about a hundred and eighty shillings for cured skins. It did not seem to her that it could cost more than twenty shillings to trim and tan an alligator skin, and her figures were in Australian money, too. The skins should be much cheaper than in England. Labour, too, would be cheaper; girl labour in Willstown would be cheaper than girl labour in Perivale. But then there would be the cost of shipping the shoes to England, and an agent's fees.

She wondered if Pack and Levy would sell for her. She knew that Mr Pack had been lukewarm for a long time about the manufacturing side of the business. They did sell other people's products, too —those handbags made by that French firm, Ducros Frères. Pack and Levy sold those, although they made handbags themselves...

The major problem was not the business, she thought. In Willstown both labour and materials were cheap; the business end of it might well be all right. But could she train the sort of girl that she could get in Willstown to turn out first-class quality work, capable of being sold in Bond Street shops? That was the real problem.

She lay for a long time in her warm, medicated bath, thinking very deeply.

That evening as she was sitting in her deckchair on the veranda, Sam Small came to her.“Miss Paget,”he said.“Mind if we have a talk?”

“Of course, Sam,”she said.

“I been thinking about that pair of shoes you made,”he said.“I been wondering if you could teach our Judy.”

“How old is Judy, Sam?”

“Fifteen,”he said.“Sixteen next November.”

“Do you want her to learn shoe-making?”

He said,“I been thinking that anyone who could make a dinkum pair of ladies' shoes like that, they could sell them in Cairns in the shops. You see, Judy's getting to an age when she's got to do some work, and there ain't nothing here a girl can do to make a living. She'll have to go into the cities, like the other girls. Well, that's a crook deal for her mother, Miss Paget. We've only got the one girl—three boys and one girl, that's our litter. It'll be a crook deal for her mother if Judy goes to Brisbane, like the other girls. And I thought this shoe-making, well, maybe it would be a thing that she could do at home. After all,”he said,“it looks like we've got everything you need to do it with, right here in Willstown.”

“Not buckles,”Jean said thoughtfully.“We'd have to do something about buckles.”She was speaking half to herself.

She thought for a minute.“It wouldn't work like that, Sam,”she said.“You think that pair of shoes are wonderful, but they aren't. They're a rotten pair of shoes. You couldn't sell a pair like that in England, not to the sort of people who buy shoes like that. I don't think you could sell them in any first-class shop, even in Cairns.”

“They look all right to me,”he said stubbornly.

She shook her head.“They aren't. I've been in this business, Sam—I know what a shoe ought to look like. I'm not saying that we can't turn out a decent shoe in Willstown; I'd rather like to try. But to get the job right I'll need machinery, and proper benches and hand tools, and proper materials. I see your point about Judy, and I'd like to see her with a job here in Willstown. But it's too big a thing for her to tackle on her own.”

He looked at her keenly.“Was you thinking of a factory or something?”

“I don't know. Suppose somebody started something of the sort here. How many girls would you get to work regular hours, morning and afternoon—say for five pounds a week?”

“Here in Willstown?”

“That's right.”

“How young would you let them start?”

She thought for a minute.“When they leave school, I suppose. That's fourteen, isn't it?”

“You wouldn't pay a girl of fourteen five pounds a week?”

“No. Work them up to that when they got skilled.”

He considered the matter.“I think you'd get six or seven round about sixteen or seventeen, Miss Paget. Then there'd be more coming on from school.”

She turned to another aspect of the matter.“Sam, what would it cost to put up a hut for a workshop?”

“How big?”

She looked around.“About as long as from here to the end of the veranda, and about half as wide.”

“That's thirty foot by fifteen wide. You mean a wooden hut, like it might be an army hut, with an iron roof, and windows all along?”

“That's the sort of thing.”

He calculated slowly in his head.“About two hundred pounds.”

“I think I'd want it to have a double roof and a veranda, like that house that Sergeant Haines lives in. It's got to be cool.”

“Ah, that puts up the cost. A house like that'ld cost you close upon four hundred, with a veranda all around.”

“How long would that take to build?”

“Oh, I dunno. Have to get the timber up from Normanton. Tim Whelan and his boys'ld put that up in a couple of months, I'd say.”

There would be extra buildings needed for the tanning and the dyeing of the hides.“Tell me, Sam,”she said.“Would people here like something of that sort started? Or would they think it just a bit of nonsense?”

“You mean, if it kept the girls here in the town, earning money?”

“That's right.”

“Oh my word,”he said.“Would they like it. They'd like anything that kept the girls at home, so long as they was happy and got work to do.”He paused thoughtfully.“It isn't natural the way the girls go off a thousand miles from home in this country,”he said slowly.“That's what Ma and I was saying the other night. It isn't natural.”

They sat in silence for a time.“Takes a bit of thinking about, Sam,”she said at last.

When the Dakota came next Wednesday she left Willstown for Cairns. She took two days to get there because that was the unhurried way of the Dakota; they left Willstown in the afternoon and called at various cattle stations with the mail and correspondence lessons for the children from the school at Cairns, at Dunbar and Miranda and Vanrook. With the last of the light they put down at Normanton for the night, and drove into the town in a truck.

The hotel at Normanton was similar to the hotel at Willstown, but rather larger. Jean had tea with the pilot, a man called Mackenzie; after tea she sat with him on the veranda. She asked him if anyone made shoes in Normanton.“I don't think so,”he said. He called out to an acquaintance.“Ted, does anyone make shoes round here?”

Ted shook his head.“Buy 'em from Burns Philp,”he said.“Want a pair of shoes mended?”

Jean said,“No—I was just curious. They all come from the cities, do they?”

“That's right.”Ted rolled himself a cigarette.“My wife's sister, she works in a shoe factory down at Rockhampton. That's where a lot of the shoes come from. Manning Cooper, at Rockhampton. That's where Burns Philp get 'em from.”

Jean asked,“Was your wife's sister born round here?”

“Croydon,”he said.“Their Dad used to keep a hotel at Croydon, but he give up; there wasn't work for two. Mrs Bridson's is the only one there now.”

“She's not married?”

“Who? Elsie Peters?”

“That's the one who works at Manning Cooper, is it?”

“No, she's not married. Got to be a charge hand now, with a lot of girls under her.”

When he had moved on Jean asked the pilot,“Who was that?”

“Him? Ted Horner. He runs the garage here.”She noted the name for future reference.

They flew on to Cairns early the next morning; she drove into the town and went to the Strand Hotel. Cairns, she found, was a prosperous town of about twenty thousand people, situated rather beautifully on an inlet of the sea. There were several streets of shops, wide avenues with flower beds down the middle of the road; the buildings were all wood and most had iron roofs. It looked rather like the cinema pictures she had seen of American towns in the deep south, with its wide broad sidewalks shaded by verandas to enable you to look into the shop windows in the shade, but it was almost aggressively English in its loyalties. She liked Cairns from the start.

She wrote to me from there. She had written to me twice from Willstown, and at the Strand Hotel she found a letter from me waiting for her that had been there for some days, on account of her delays. She wrote,

Strand Hotel,

Cairns,

North Queensland

My Dear Noel,

I got your letter of the 24th when I arrived here yesterday, and you will have got my two from Willstown by this time. I wish I had a typewriter because this is going to be a long letter. I think I'll have to get a portable soon in order to keep copies of my letters—not to you, but I'm getting involved a bit in business out here.

First of all, thank you so very much for telling me what you did about Joe Harman. You've evidently been very nice to him and, as you know, that's being nice to me. I can't get over what you say about him rushing off to England and spending all that money, just to see me again. But people out here are like that, I think. I could say an awful lot of rude things about Australians by this time, but I can say this, too. The people that I've met in the outback have all been like Joe Harman, very simple, very genuine, and very true.

And now, about Willstown. I don't know if Joe Harman will still be so keen on marrying me when he sees me; six years is a long time, and people change. I don't know if I'll be keen on marrying him. But if we were to want to marry, what he told you about Willstown is absolutely right.

It's just terrible there, Noel. There are some places in the outback where one could live a fully and happy life. Alice Springs is a grand little town. But Willstown's not one of them. Noel, it's absolutely the bottom. There's nothing for a woman there at all except the washtub. I know that one ought to be able to get along without such things as radio and lipstick and ice-cream and pretty clothes. I think I can get along all right without them—I did in Malaya. But when it comes to no fresh milk and no fresh vegetables or fruit, it's a bit thick. I think that what Joe told you was absolutely right. I don't think any girl could come straight out from England and live happily in Willstown. I don't think I could.

And yet, Noel, I wouldn't want to see Joe try and change his way of life. He's a first-class station manager, and he'll do very well. I asked all sorts of people about the way Midhurst is run, and it's good. I don't say it couldn't be better if he travelled a bit more widely and saw what other cattle breeders do, but relative to the other stations in the Gulf country, Midhurst is pretty good and getting better every year. The last manager let it run down, so they tell me, but Joe's done a good job in the two years that he's been there. I wouldn't want to see Joe try and make his life anywhere else, just because he'd married a rich wife who couldn't or wouldn't live in Willstown, where his work is.

Of course, you'll probably say that he could get another station near a better town, perhaps near Alice. I'm not sure that that would be very easy; I've thought a lot about that one. But if it was possible, I wouldn't like it much. Midhurst is in good country with more rainfall than in England; for a life's work it seems to me that the Gulf country is a far better prospect than anything round Alice. I wouldn't like to think that he'd left good land and gone to bad land, just because of me. That wouldn't be a very good start for a station manager's wife.

Noel, do you think I could have five thousand pounds of my capital? I'm going to take the advice you always shove at me, and not do anything in a hurry. If when I meet Joe Harman he still wants to marry me, and if I want to marry him, I'm going to wait a bit if I can get him to agree. I'd like to work in Willstown for a year or so myself before committing myself to live there for ever. I want to see if I could ever get to adapt myself to the place, or if it's hopeless. I don't want to think that. I would like to find it possible to live in the Gulf country even though I was brought up in England, because they are such very, very decent people living there.

I want to try and start a tiny workshop, making shoes and handbags out of alligator skins. I told you about that in my last letter. It's work I know about, and all the materials are there to hand in the Gulf country, except the metal parts. I've written a long letter this morning to Mr Pack to ask him if he would sell for me in England if the stuff is good enough, and to let me know the maximum price that he could give for shoes delivered at Perivale. And I've asked him to make me out a list of the things I'd want for a workshop employing up to ten girls and what they cost; things like a press and a polisher with the heads for it, and a Knighton No. 6 sewing machine.

The sewing-machine is a heavy duty one for leather and that's the most expensive single item. I should think the lot, including £400 for a building to work in, would cost about a thousand pounds. But I'm afraid that's not the whole story. If I'm going to start a workshop for girls, they've got to have something to spend their wages on. I want to start a shop to sell the sort of things that women want.

Not a big shop, just a little one. I want it to be a sort of ice-cream parlour with a few chromium-plated chairs and glass-topped tables. I want to sell fruit there and fresh vegetables; if I can't get them any other way I'll have them flown in from Cairns. There's plenty of money in the outback for that. I want to sell fresh milk there, too; Joe will have to play and keep a few milking cows. I want to sell sweets, and just a few little things like lipstick and powder and face cream and magazines.

The big expense here is the refrigerators and freezes, of course. I think we'd have to allow five hundred pounds for those, and then there's the building and the furniture—say £1200 the lot. That makes, say, £2500 for capital expenditure. If I have five thousand of my capital, I should be able to stock the shop and the workshop and employ five or six girls for a year without selling anything at all, and by that time the income should be coming in, I think. If it isn't, well that's just too bad and I shall have lost my money.

I want to do this, Noel. Apart from Joe Harman and me, they're decent people in Willstown, and they've got so very little. I'd like to work there for a year as a sort of self-discipline and to keep from running to seed now that I've got all this money. I think I'd want to do this even if there wasn't any Joe Harman in the background at all, but I shan't make up my mind or take any definite step until I've had a talk with him.

So what I want is five thousand pounds, please, Noel. May I have it if I want to go ahead with this?

Jean

I got this letter five days later by the air mail. I marked the passages about her money with a red pencil, and wrote a little note upon the top, and sent it into Lester for him to read. I went into his office later in the day.“You read that letter from the Paget girl?”I asked.

He took it up from his desk before him.“Yes. I've just been looking at the will. Did you draft that discretionary clause yourself?”

“I did.”

He smiled.“I think it's a masterpiece. It covers us all right, if you think she ought to have this money.”

“It's about nine per cent of her capital,”I said.“For a commercial venture that she intends to work at whole-time herself.”

“The testator didn't know her, did he?”

I shook my head.

“She's twenty-seven years old?”

“That is correct.”

“I think that we might let her have it,”he said.“It would be very extreme to do the other thing, to withhold it. We've got ample latitude under your discretionary clause to let her have it, and she seems to be a responsible person.”

“I'd like to think it over for a day or so,”I said.“It seems to me to be a very small amount of capital for what she wants to do.”

I put her letter on one side for a couple of days because I never like to take any action in a hurry. After a period of reflection it seemed to me that I would be carrying out the wishes of the late Mr Douglas Macfadden if I exerted myself to see that Jean Paget did not lose her money in this venture, and I picked up my telephone and rang up Mr Pack of Pack and Levy Ltd.

I said,“Mr Pack, this is Strachan, of Owen, Dalhousie, and Peters. I believe you've had a letter from a client of mine, Miss Jean Paget.”

“Aye, that's right,”he said.“You're her solicitor, are you? The one that's her trustee?”

“That is correct,”I said.“I've had a letter from her, too. I was thinking it might be a good thing if we got together, Mr Pack, and had a talk about it.”

“Well, that suits me,”he replied.“She asked for a list of what she'd want to start up in a small way. I got a list together, but I haven't got all the f.o.b. prices in yet.”

I made an appointment with him for the following Friday when he expected to be in London on other business. He came to see me then at my office. He was a small, fat, cheerful man, very much of a works manager. He brought with him a brown paper parcel.

“Afore we start,”he said,“these come in this morning.”He untied the parcel on my desk and produced a pair of alligator-skin shoes. I picked up one curiously.

“What are these?”I asked.

“They're what she made herself at this place Willstown,”he said.“Did she tell you about that?”

I shook my head, and examined them with fresh interest.“Did she make these herself, with her own hands?”

“Made 'em with her own hands in her hotel bedroom, so she said,”he replied.

I turned one over.“Are they any good?”

“Depends on how you look at it,”he observed.“For selling in the trade they're bloody awful. Look at this, and this, and this.”He pointed out the various irregularities and crudities.“They're not even the same. But she knows that. If you take them as a pair of shoes made by a typist that hadn't ever made a shoe before, working on her bed with no equipment, well, they're bloody marvellous.”

I laid down the shoe and offered him a cigarette.“She told you what she wants to do?”

He told me what he had heard from her, and I told him some of what she had written to me; we talked for a quarter of an hour. At the end of that time I asked him,“What do you really think about her proposition, Mr Pack?”

“I don't think she can do it,”he said flatly.“Not the way she's thinking of. I don't think she knows enough about the shoe business to make a go of it.”

I must say, I was disappointed, but it was as well to have the facts.“I see,”I said quietly.

“You see,”he explained,“she hasn't got the experience. She's a good girl, Mr Strachan, and she's got a good business head. But she's got no experience of making shoes to sell, and she's got no experience of keeping girls in order 'n making them bloody well work for their money. It's not even as if she was in her own country. These Australian country girls she writes about, they're just like so many foreigners to her. They may be willing, but they've never seen a factory before—they won't have the idea at all. She's got to learn her own job and teach them theirs at the same time. Well, she can't do it.”

“I see,”I said again.

“I'd like to help her,”said the little man,“but she'll have to change her ideas a bit. She's on to a good wheeze, if she can put it over. I must say, when I read her letter where it says that she's paying seventy shillings for an alligator skin uncured, you could have knocked me down with a feather. Australian shillings, too—fifty-six bob of our money. Here have I been paying a hundred and seventy, hundred and eighty shillings for a cured skin, all these years, and thinking I was getting 'em cheap at that! I said to Mr Levy, I said, couple of bloody mugs, we are.”

“What can you suggest to help her?”I asked.

“What I thought was this,”he said.“If she could pay the passage of a forewoman out and home, I'd let her have a girl out of my shop, say for the first year. I got a girl that's getting restless—well, a woman she is, thirty-five if she's a day. She's a married woman but she isn't living with her husband—hasn't been for a long time. She was a sergeant in the ATS in the war, out in Egypt some of the time, so she knows about a hot country. Aggie Topp, the name is. You wouldn't get girls playing up in any shop with Aggie Topp in charge.”

“Does Miss Paget know her?”I inquired.

“Oh, aye, Jean knows Aggie. And Aggie knows Jean. Matter of fact, Aggie came in yesterday and handed in her notice. I handed it back to her and jollied her along, you know. She does that every two or three months, getting restless, like I said. But I asked her then, how would she like to go out to Australia for a year to work with Miss Paget. She said she'd go anywhere to get away from standing in a queue for the bloody rations. She'd go out for a year, if Jean wants her. They all liked Jean.”

I said,“Can you spare her?”

“She won't stay long, anyway,”he said.“I don't want to lose her and perhaps I won't. If she gets a trip out to Australia and sees that other places aren't so good as England, then maybe she'll come back and settle down with us again. Get it out of her system.”

We talked about this for a time. The woman's passages and pay while travelling would tot up to about three hundred pounds, but it seemed cheap to me if it would help the venture through the early stages. For the rest of it, Mr Pack thought Jean's estimates of capital were on the low side, but not excessively so.“You can't afford much mechanization in the quality shoe trade,”he said.“You got to keep changing the style all the time.”

About the style, he suggested that they air-mailed a sample to Willstown from time to time for Jean's party to copy. He was quite willing to do the selling for her.“Mind, I don't know if she'll be able to make a go of it upon the prices we can sell at,”he said.“I'll tell her what we can buy at, and it's up to her. But I'd like to give this thing a spin, I must say. Manufacturing's getting so bloody difficult in this country with controls and that, one feels like trying something different.”

I thanked him very sincerely, and he went away. I wrote all this out to Jean Paget by air mail, and I believe Mr Pack wrote to her by the same mail. She did not get these letters for some days after their arrival, because she had gone down to Rockhampton to look for the girl Elsie Peters who worked in the shoe factory there. She went economically by train, a slow, hot journey of some seven hundred miles; till then she had not realized how vast and sparsely populated a state Queensland was. The aeroplanes had dwarfed it for her; fifty-one hours in the train to Rockhampton expanded it again.

She found Elsie Peters, and the meeting was a complete fiasco. It only lasted ten minutes. They met in a café close outside the works; as soon as Jean broached the subject of a job in the Gulf country, Elsie told her she could save her breath. It might be a good thing, she conceded, to start something in the Gulf country, but not for her. Wild horses would not drag her back again.

Jean came away from the café relieved in one way, and yet depressed. She would not have wanted anybody in that frame of mind, but she had been counting rather heavily on this unknown woman. She was very conscious of her own lack of managerial experience; as the venture became closer difficulties loomed up which had not been quite so obvious at the birth of the idea. She spent a depressed evening in the hotel, and flew back to Cairns next day in revolt at the long train journey; she found the air fare very little more expensive.

She found our letters waiting for her at the Strand Hotel when she got back there, and her spirits revived again. She remembered the gaunt, stern Aggie very well; if Aggie was prepared to come to Queensland for a year that really was something. I think she was beginning to feel very much alone and amongst strangers while she was waiting in Cairns for Joe Harman.

She wrote temporizing letters to us, for she would not make her mind up about anything until she had seen Harman. She told me later that the three weeks that she spent in Cairns living at the Strand Hotel after she came back from Rockhampton were the worst time of her life. Each morning she woke up in the cold light of dawn convinced that she was making a colossal fool of herself, that she could never settle down in this outlandish country, that she and Harman would have nothing in common and that it would be much better not to meet him at all. The wise course was to take the next plane down to Sydney and get a cheap passage to England, where she belonged. By noon some rough Australian kindness from a waitress or the manageress had sown a seed of doubt in the smooth bed of her resolution, that grew like a weed throughout the afternoon; by evening she knew that if she left that country and that place she would be running away from things that might be well worth having, things that she might never find again her whole life through. So she would go to bed resolved to be patient, and in the morning the whole cycle would start off again.

She knew the name of Harman's ship, of course, from my letters, and she had no difficulty in finding out when it docked at Brisbane. A few discreet inquiries showed her that he must pass through Cairns to get to Willstown, and convinced her that he would have to wait for several days in Cairns because his ship docked in Brisbane on a Monday and the weekly plane into the Gulf country left at dawn on Tuesday; he could never make that connection. She had found out in Willstown that he stayed at the Strand Hotel in Cairns, and so she waited there for him.

She wrote to him care of the shipping line at Brisbane, and she had some difficulty with that letter. Finally she said,

Dear Joe,

I got a letter from Mr Strachan telling me that you had been to see him while you were in England, and that you were sorry to have missed me. Funnily enough, I have been in Australia for some weeks, and I will wait at Cairns here so that we can have a talk before you go on to Willstown.

Don't let's talk too much about Malaya when we meet. We both know what happened; let's try and forget about it.

Will you let me know your movements—when you'll be coming up to Cairns? I do want to meet you again.

Yours sincerely,

Jean Paget

She got a telegram on Tuesday morning to tell her he was staying to see Mrs Spears, the owner of Midhurst, and he would be flying up to Cairns on Thursday. She went to meet him at the aerodrome, feeling absurdly like a girl of seventeen keeping her first date.

I think Joe Harman was in a position of some difficulty as the Dakota drew near to Cairns. For six years he had carried the image of this girl in his heart, but, in sober fact, he didn't in the least know what she looked like. The girl that he remembered had long black hair done in a pigtail down her back with the end tied up with a bit of string, like a Chinese woman. She was a very sunburnt girl, almost as brown as a Malay. She wore a tattered, faded, blouselike top part with a cheap cotton sarong underneath; she walked on bare feet which were very brown and usually dirty; and she habitually carried a baby on her hip. He did not really think that she would look like that at Cairns, and he was troubled and distressed by the fact that he probably wouldn't be able to recognize her again. It was unfortunate that the inner light in her, the quality that made her what he called a bonza girl, didn't show on the surface.

Something of his difficulty was apparent to Jean; she had wondered if he would know her while she was making herself pretty for him in her room, and had decided that he probably wouldn't. She had no such difficulty herself for he would have changed less than she, and anyway he carried stigmata upon his hands if there were any doubt. She stood waiting for him by the white rails bounding the tarmac as the Dakota taxied in in the hot sun.

She recognized him as he came out of the machine, fair-haired, blue-eyed, and broad-shouldered. He was looking anxiously about; his gaze fell on her, rested a minute, and passed on. She watched him, wondering if she was looking very old, and saw him start to walk towards the airline office with his curious, stiff gait. A little shaft of pain struck her; that was Kuantan, and it had left its mark on him. With her intellect she had known that this must be so, but seeing it for the first time was painful, all the same.

She left the rails, and walked quickly across the tarmac to him, and said,“Joe!”He stopped and stared at her incredulously. He had been looking for a stranger, but it was unbelievable to him that this smart, pretty girl in a light summer frock was the tragic, ragged figure that he had last seen on the road in Malaya, sunburnt, dirty, bullied by the Japanese soldiers, with blood upon her face where they had hit her, with blood upon her feet. Then he saw a characteristic turn of her head and memories came flooding back on him; it was Mrs Boong again, the Mrs Boong he had remembered all those years.

It was not in him to be able to express what he was feeling. He grinned a little sheepishly, and said,“Hullo, Miss Paget.”

She took his hand impulsively, and said,“Oh, Joe!”He pressed her hand and looked down into her eyes, and then he said,“Where are you staying? How long are you here for?”

She said,“I'm staying in the Strand Hotel.”

“Why, that's where I'm staying,”he said.“I always go there.”

“I know,”she said.“Mrs Smythe told me.”

There was much here that he did not understand, but first things came first.“Wait while I get my luggage,”he said.“We can drive in together.”

“I've got a taxi waiting,”she said.“Don't let's go in the bus.”

In the taxi as they drove into the town she asked him,“How was Mr Strachan, Joe?”

“He was fine,”he said.“I stayed with him quite a long time, in his flat.”

“Did you!”She had not known that part of it because I had not told her; I had told her the bare minimum about him since it was obvious that they were going to meet.“How long were you in England, Joe?”

“About three weeks.”

She did not ask him why he went because she knew that already, and it was hardly a matter to be entered on behind the taxi driver. He forestalled her, however, by asking,“What have you been doing in Australia, Miss Paget?”

She temporized.“Didn't you know I was here?”

He shook his head.“All I knew was what Mr Strachan said, that you were travelling in the East. You could have knocked me down with a feather when I got your letter at Brisbane. Oh my word, you could. Tell me, what are you doing in Cairns?”

A little smile played around her mouth.“What were you doing in England?”

He was silent, not knowing what to say to that. He had no lie ready. They were running through the outskirts of the town, past the churches.“We've got a good bit of explaining to do, Joe,”she said.“Let's leave it till you've got your room at the hotel, and then we'll find somewhere to talk.”

They sat in silence till they got to the hotel. Jean had a bedroom opening on to a veranda that looked out over the sea to the wild, jungle-covered hills behind Cape Grafton; they arranged to meet there when he had had a wash. She knew something of Australian habits by that time.“What about a beer or two?”she asked.

He grinned.“Good-oh.”

She asked Doris the waitress to get four beers, three for Joe and one for her; large quantities of cold liquid were necessary in that torrid place. It was symbolic of Australia, she felt, that they should hold their first sentimental conversation with the assistance of four bottles of beer.

She dragged two deckchairs into a patch of shade outside her room; the beer and Joe arrived about the same time. When the waitress had gone and they were alone, she said quietly,“Let me have a good look at you, Joe.”

He stood before her, examining her beauty; he had not dreamed when he had met her in Malaya that she was a girl like this.“You've not changed,”she said.“Does the back trouble you?”

“Not much,”he said.“It doesn't hinder me riding, thank the Lord, but I can't lift heavy weights. They told me in the hospital I won't ever be able to lift heavy weights again, and I'd better not try.”

She nodded, and took one of his hands in hers. He stood beside her while she turned it over in her own, and looked at the great scars upon the palm and on the back.“What about these, Joe?”

“They're all right,”he said.“I can grip anything—start up a truck, or anything.”

She turned to the table.“Have a beer.”She handed him a glass.“You must be thirsty. Three of these are for you.”

“Good-oh.”He took a glass and sank half of it. They sat down together in the deckchairs.“Tell me what happened to you,”he asked.“I know you said not to talk about Malaya. It was a fair cow, that place. I don't want to remember about it any more. But I do want to know what happened to you—after Kuantan.”

She sipped her beer.“We went on,”she said.“Captain Sugamo sent us on the same day, after— after that. We went on up the east coast with just the sergeant in charge of us. I was sorry for the sergeant, Joe, because he was very much in disgrace, because of what happened. He never got over it, and then he got fever and gave up. He died at a place called Kuala Telang, about half way between Kuantan and Kota Bahru. That was about a month later.”

“He was the only Nip guarding you?”he asked.

She nodded.

“Well, what did you do then?”

She raised her head.“They let us stay there all the war,”she said.“We just lived in the village, working in the paddy fields till the war was over.”

“You mean, paddling about in the water, planting the rice, like the Malays?”

“That's right,”she said.

“Oh my word,”he breathed.

She said,“It wasn't a bad life. I'd rather have been there than in a camp, I think—once we got settled down. We were all fairly healthy when the war ended, and we were able to make a little school and teach the children something. We taught some of the Malay children, too.”

“I did hear a bit about that,”he said thoughtfully.“I heard from a pilot on the airline, down at Julia Creek.”

She stared at him.“How did he know about us?”

“He was the pilot of the aeroplane that flew you out, in 1945,”he replied.“He said that you got taken in trucks to Kota Bahru. He flew you from Kota Bahru to Singapore. He's working for TAA now, on the route from Townsville to Mount Isa. That goes through Julia Creek. I met him there this last May, when I was down there putting stock onto the train.”

“I remember,”she said slowly.“It was an Australian Dakota that flew us out. Was he a thin, fair-haired boy?”

“That'ld be the one.”

She thought for a minute.“What did he tell you, Joe?”

“Just what I said. He said he'd flown you down to Singapore.”

“What did he tell you about me?”She looked at him, and there was laughter in her eyes.

He grinned sheepishly, and said nothing.

“Come on, Joe,”she said.“Have another beer, and let's get this straight.”

“All right,”he said. He took a glass and held it in his hand, but did not drink.“He said you were a single woman, Mrs Boong. I always thought the lot of you was married.”

“They all were, except me. Is that why you went rushing off to England?”

He met her eyes.“That's right.”

“Oh, Joe! What a waste of money, when here we are in Cairns!”

He laughed with her, and took a long drink of beer.“Well, how was I to know that you'd be turning up in Cairns?”He thought for a minute.“What are you doing here, anyway?”he asked.“You haven't told me that.”

She was embarrassed in her turn.“I came into some money,”she said.“I think Noel Strachan told you about that.”

“That's right,”he said kindly.

“I didn't know what to do with myself then,”she said.“I didn't want to go on working as a typist in a London suburb any more. And then I got the idea into my head that I wanted to do something for the village where we lived for those three years, Kuala Telang. I wanted to give them a well.”

“A well?”he asked.

Sitting there with a glass of beer in her hand she told him about Kuala Telang, and about her friends there, and the washhouse, and the well. Then she came to the difficult bit.“The well-diggers came from Kuantan,”she said.“I thought that you were dead, Joe. We all did.”

He grinned.“I bloody nearly was.”

“The well-diggers told me that you weren't,”she said.“They told me that you'd been put into the hospital, and you'd recovered.”

“That's right,”he said.“I tried to find out what had happened to you, but they didn't know, or if they knew they wouldn't say. I reckon they were all scared stiff of that Sugamo.”

She nodded.“I went to Kuantan. It's very peaceful there now. People playing tennis on the tennis courts, and sitting gossiping under that ghastly tree. They told me at the hospital that you'd asked about us.”She smiled.“Mrs Boong.”

He grinned.“But did you come on to Australia from there?”

She nodded.“Yes.”

“What for?”

“Well,”she said awkwardly,“I wanted to see if you were all right. I thought perhaps you might be still in hospital or something.”

“Is that dinky-die?”he asked.“You came on to Australia because of me?”

“In a way,”she said.“Don't let it put ideas into your head.”He grinned.“I'd have done the same if you'd have been an Abo.”

“Well, you're a fine one to talk about me wasting money,”he said.“We'd have met all right if you'd have stayed in England.”

She said indignantly,“Well, how was I to know that you'd be turning up in England, and as fit as a flea?”

They sat drinking their beer for some time.“How did you get here?”he asked.“Where did you come to first?”

She said,“I knew you used to work at Wollara and I thought they'd know about you there. So I flew from Singapore to Darwin, and went down to Alice on the bus.”

“Oh my word. You went to Alice Springs? Did you go out to Wollara and see Tommy Duveen?”

She shook her head.“I stayed about a week in Alice, and I got your address at Midhurst from Mr Duveen over the radio, from the hospital. So then I flew up to Willstown—I sent you a wire at Midhurst to say I was coming. But they told me there, of course, that you were in England.”

He stared at her.“Is that dinky-die? You've been to Willstown?”

She nodded.“I was there three weeks.”

“Three weeks!”He stared at her.“Where did you stay?”

“With Mrs Connor, in the hotel.”

“But why three weeks? Three hours would have been enough for most people.”

“I had to stay somewhere,”she said.“If you go running off to England, people who want to see you have to hang around. You'll probably find the Australian Hotel's full of them when you get back.”

He grinned,“My word, I will. What did you do all the time?”

“Sat around and talked to Al Burns and Pete Fletcher and Sam Small, and all the rest.”

“You must have created a riot.”He paused, thinking deeply about this new aspect of the matter.“Did you go out to Midhurst?”

She shook her head.“I stayed in Willstown all the time. I met Jim Lennon, though.”

The bell rang downstairs for tea.“We'd better go down, Joe,”she said.“They don't like it if you're late.”

“I know.”He picked up his glass to drain it, but sat with it in his hand, untouched. At last he said,“What did you think of Willstown, Miss Paget?”

She smiled.“Look, Joe, forget about Miss Paget. You can call me Mrs Boong or you can call me Jean, but if you go on with Miss Paget I'll go home tomorrow.”

He smiled slightly.“All right, Mrs Boong. What did you think of Willstown?”

“We'll be late for tea, Joe, if we start on that.”

“Tell me,”he said.

She smiled at him with her eyes.“I thought it was an awful place, Joe,”she said quietly.“I can't see how anyone can bear to live there.”She laid her hand upon his arm.“I want to talk to you about it, but we must go and have tea now.”

He got up from his chair, and set the glass down.“Too right,”he said heavily.“It's a crook kind of a place for a woman.”

They went down to tea and sat at a table together, Joe deep in gloom. When they had ordered, Jean said,“Joe, how long have you got? When have you got to be back at Midhurst?”

He raised his head and grinned.“When I'm ready to go back,”he said.“I been away so long a few days more won't make any difference.”He paused.“What about you?”

“I only came here to see if you were all right, Joe,”she said.“I suppose I'll go down to Brisbane and start looking for a boat home next week.”

Their food came, roast beef for Joe, cold ham and salad for Jean.“What have you been doing since you came to Cairns?”he asked presently.“Been out to the Reef?”

She shook her head.“I went down to Rockhampton once, and I went on one of the White Tours up to the Tableland, and stayed a night in Atherton. I've not been anywhere else.”

“Oh my word,”he said.“You can't go home without seeing the Great Barrier Reef.”He paused, and then he said,“Would you like to go to Green Island for the weekend?”

She cocked an eye at him.“What's Green Island like?”

“It's just a coral island on the reef,”he explained.“A little round one, about half a mile across. There's a restaurant on it and little sort of bedroom huts where you can stay, in among the trees. It's a bonza little place if you like bathing. Wear your bathers all the day.”

Jean thought the little bedroom huts among the trees wanted checking up on, but the suggestion certainly had its points. They knew so little about each other; they had so much to learn, so much to talk about. Whatever else might happen if she spent a weekend in her bathing dress with Joe Harman on a coral island, they would certainly come from it knowing more about each other than they would learn under the restraints of Cairns.

“I'd like to do that, Joe,”she said.“How would we get there?”

He beamed with pleasure, and she was glad for him.“I'll slip out after tea and find Ernie,”he said.“He's probably in the bar at Hides. He's got a boat, and he'll run us out there tomorrow; it'll take about three hours. We'd better start about eight o'clock, before the sun gets hot. Then I'd ask him to come out and fetch us on Monday, say.”

“All right,”she agreed.“But look, Joe—this is to be Dutch treat.”He did not understand that term.“I mean, you pay the boat one way and I'll pay it the other, and we both pay our own bills.”He objected strenuously.“If we don't do that, Joe, I won't come,”she said.“I'll think you're plotting to do me a bit of no good.”

He grinned.“Too right.”And then he said,“All right, Mrs Boong, we'll each pay our own whack.”

He went out after tea and came back to her on the veranda half an hour later; he had found Ernie and arranged the boat, and he had bought a large basket of fruit to take with them. In the quick dusk and the darkness they sat together for some hours, talking of everything but Willstown. She learned a lot about his early life on the various stations, and about his relations in and around Cloncurry, about his war service, and about Midhurst.“It's got a bonza rainfall, Midhurst has,”he said.“We got thirty-four inches in the last wet; down at Alice it's a good year if you get ten inches. I've been asking Mrs Spears if we couldn't build a couple of dams at the head of the creeks to hold back some of the water—one across the head of Kangaroo Creek and one on the Dry Gum.”

“Did she agree?”

“She'll pay for them,”he said.“Trouble is, of course, to get the labour. You can't get chaps to come and work in the outback. It's a fair cow.”

“Why is that?”she asked. She had a very good idea, herself, but she wanted to hear his views.

“I don't know,”he said.“They all want to go and work in the towns.”

She did not pursue the subject; there was time enough for that. They talked of pleasant, unimportant things; she found that he was very anxious to get back to Midhurst to see his horses and his dogs.“I got a bitch called Lily,”he said.“Her mother was a blue cattle dog and she got mated by a dingo, so Lily's half a dingo. She's a bonza dog. Well, I mated her with another blue cattle dog before I come away and she'll have had the litter now, so they'll be quarter dingo. A cross between a dingo and cattle dog makes a grand dog, but you've got to get the dingo strain weak or they aren't reliable. I had a quarter dingo dog before the war at Wollara, and he was grand.”

He told her that he had about sixty saddle and pack horses on the station, but they did not seem to be as close to his heart as his dogs.“A dog comes into the homestead and sits around with you in the evenings,”he said, and she could picture the long, lonely nights that were his normal life.“You couldn't get along in the outback without dogs.”

At ten o'clock they went to bed, prepared for an early start in the morning. They stood together in the darkness by the entrance to her room for a moment.“Have I changed much, Joe?”she asked.

He grinned.“I wouldn't have known you again.”

“I didn't think you would. Six years is a long time.”

“You haven't changed at all, really,”he said.“You're the same person underneath.”

“I think I am,”she said slowly.“After the war I felt like an old woman, Joe. After Kuantan, I didn't think I'd ever enjoy anything again.”She smiled.“Like a weekend at Green Island.”

“There's nothing to do there, you know,”he said.“You bathe and go out in a glass-bottomed boat to see the coral and the fishes.”

“I know. It's going to be such fun.”

They left next morning in Ernie's fishing boat, a motor launch with a canopy. For two hours they chugged out over a smooth sea, trolling a line behind and catching two large, brilliantly coloured horse-mackerel. Green Island appeared after an hour as the tops of coconut palms visible above the horizon; as they drew near the little circular island appeared, fringed round completely with a white coral beach. There was a long landing-stage built out over the shallow water of the reef; they landed and walked down this together, pausing to look at the scarlet and blue fishes playing round the coral heads below.

There were no other visitors staying on the island and they got two of the little bedroom huts in among the trees; these huts had open sides to let the breeze blow through, with an occasional curtain for privacy. They bathed at once and met upon the beach; Jean had a new white two-piece costume and was flattered at the reception that it got.“It's pretty as a picture,”he said.“Oh my word.”

She laughed.“There's not enough of it to fill a picture frame, Joe.”

“Too right,”he said.“But there aren't any wowsers here.”

“I'll have to look out I don't get burnt,”she said.“I bet I'm the whitest woman that ever bathed here.”

“You are in parts,”he observed. He stood looking at her, reluctant to take his eyes off her beauty.“You've been out in the sun up top, though.”

Her shoulders and her arms were tanned; there was a hard line above her breasts, brown above and white below.“That's where I was wearing a sarong in Malaya,”she said.“While they were building the well. In the village we used to wear the sarong up high, under the arms. It's beautifully cool like that, and yet it protects most of you from sunburn. And it's reasonably decent, too.”

“Have you got it here?”he asked.

She nodded.“I'm going to put it on presently.”

As they turned to go into the water she saw his back for the first time, lined and puckered and distorted with enormous scars. Deep pity for him welled up in her at the sight; this man had been hurt enough for her already. She must not hurt him any more. He glanced back at her and said,“We'd better not go in more than about knee-deep. There's plenty of sharks round here.”And then he looked at her more closely, and said,“What's the matter?”

She laughed quickly.“It's the sun,”she said.“It's making my eyes water. I ought to have brought my dark glasses.”

“I'll go and get them. Where are they?”

“I don't want them, really.”She threw herself forward in a shallow dive over the sand in about two feet of water and rolled over on her back, flirting the water from her face.“It's marvellous,”she said. He flung himself forward, wallowed for a little, and sat beside her on the coral sand in the warm sea.“Tell me, Joe,”she said.“Do sharks really come in close like this?”

“They'll take you in water that's only waist-deep,”he said.“Oh my word, they will. I don't know if there are any here just now. Trouble is, you never can tell. Didn't you have sharks in Malaya?”

“I think there were,”she said.“The villagers never went out more than about knee-deep, so we didn't. There were crocodiles in the river, too.”She laughed.“Taking it all in all, there's nothing to beat a good swimming-pool in a hot country.”

They rolled over in the blue, translucent water; the sun came shimmering through the ripples and made silvery lights upon the coral sand around them.“I've never bathed in a swimming-pool,”he said.“They make them with a shallow end, do they? Where you can sit, like this?”

“Of course. They have a shallow and a deep end, with diving-boards at the deep end. Don't they have swimming-pools here, in Australia?”

“Oh my word. They have them down in places like Sydney and Melbourne. I've heard of station owners having them upon their land, too. But places like Cairns and Townsville and Mackay, they're on the sea, so they don't need a pool.”

“Mrs Maclean's got a pool at Alice Springs,”she said.

“I know. They only made it a year or two ago. I've never seen it.”

She rolled over on her back, and watched a seagull soaring in the thermals from the island.“You could have a pool at Willstown,”she said.“You've got all the water in the world, from the bore, running to waste right in the middle of the town. You could make a lovely swimming-pool right opposite the hotel.”

“That water isn't running to waste,”he observed.“Oh my word. The cattle drink that, in the dry.”

“It wouldn't hurt the cattle if we borrowed it first and used it for a swimming-pool,”she said.“It'ld taste all the sweeter.”

“Might taste sweeter if you swam in it,”he concurred.“I don't know about me.”

He would not let her stay in the water more than a quarter of an hour.“You'll burn,”he said.“Midday, like this, you can burn just as easy in the sea as on the land. You want to be careful, with a skin as white as yours.”They went up from the beach into the shade of the trees and sat smoking for a time; then they went back to their huts to put on a little more covering for lunch. Australian hotels, she had discovered, are very particular about dress at mealtimes; in Cairns even on the hottest day of summer a man without a jacket and tie would not be served in the dining-room, nor would a woman in slacks.

Harman had arranged a light lunch for her, cold meat and fruit; she was touched by the care that he was taking to make her weekend a success. While struggling to eat a mango decently she asked,“Joe, why don't places like Willstown have more fresh fruit? Won't it grow?”

“Mangoes grow all right,”he said.“We've got three or four mango trees at Midhurst. Aren't there any in the town? I'd have thought there must be.”

“I don't believe there are. I never saw any fruit in the hotel, or anywhere on sale.”

“Oh well, maybe you wouldn't. People don't seem to bother much about it. Some places have every shade tree a mango tree. Cooktown, in the early summer you drive over them, all along the road.”

“Don't the people like fresh fruit and vegetables? I mean, they get all sorts of skin diseases through not having them.”

“It's too hot for the old folks to work in gardens, like in other places,”he said.“There aren't enough people in the country to grow things like that. We can't even get men to work as ringers on the stations—we have to use two-thirds boongs as stockmen, or more. There just aren't enough people. They won't come to the outback.”

She said thoughtfully,“There were plenty of fresh vegetables at Alice Springs.”

“Ah, yes,”he replied.“Alice is different. Alice is a bonza little town.”

They slept on their beds in the heat of the day after lunch and bathed again before tea; in the cool of the evening they went out to the end of the jetty and fished. They caught some sand snappers and three or four brilliant red and blue fish which were poisonous to eat and had to be handled with a glove because they stung; then tiring of this rather unprofitable sport they rolled up their lines and sat and watched the sunset over the heights of the Atherton Tableland on the horizon.“It's a funny thing,”Jean said.“You go to a new country, and you expect everything to be different, and then you find there's such a lot that stays the same. That sunset looks just like it does in England, on a fine summer evening.”

“Do you see much that's like England here?”he asked.

She smiled.“Not on Green Island, and not much in Willstown. But in Cairns—a lot. Vauxhall and Austin motor cars parked in the streets, and politicians telling people to buy British, and the North British Insurance Company, and Tattersalls, and bank clerks in the hotel listening to ‘Itma’. Even the newsboys selling papers in the street—‘Read all about it’. Listening to them with your eyes shut, they sound just the same. They used to shout exactly like that when I lived in Ealing.”

“Ealing's the place near London where you lived when you were working, isn't it?”

“That's right. It's a part of London, really—a suburb.”

“Are you going to live there again when you go home?”

“I don't know,”she said slowly.“I don't know what I'm going to do, Joe.”

In the evening light, sitting together on the jetty and watching the sunset over the calm water, she had expected him to follow up this opening, and she was disappointed that he did not do so. She had expected more than this of him, and that she didn't get it was beginning to distress her. She had expected to spend the whole weekend on the defensive, in repelling boarders, so to speak, but so far things had worked out very differently. Joe Harman's behaviour toward her had been above reproach; he had not tried to kiss her or even to make opportunities of touching her. But for the fact that he had been to England for no other purpose than to look for her, she might have thought he wasn't interested in her at all. By the end of the day she was becoming seriously worried about his restraint. She had caused him enough pain already.

It was no better when they went to bed. She would have liked to have been kissed, in the quiet darkness under the palm trees, but Joe didn't do it. They said goodnight in the most orderly way, not even shaking hands, and they retired to their own huts with perfect decorum. Jean lay awake for some time, restless and troubled. She had taken it for granted that they would arrive at some emotional conclusion at Green Island, but if things went on as they were going they would leave on Monday with nothing settled at all. If that happened, she would have to go down to Brisbane and go home; there would be no excuse for doing anything else. The thought was almost unbearable.

She knew that her English ways were strange to him; he could not know how very willing she was to adapt herself to his Queensland life. Perhaps, too, her money stood between them. She did not think that so sincere and genuine a man would have any scruples about marrying a girl with money, but it might well make him shy of her. She had a feeling that there was a difference between herself, a strange, wealthy, English girl, and an Australian girl from Cairns. If Joe Harman had been so much interested in a girl from Cairns, Jean thought, she would have been in bed with him by then; whereas she herself had not even been kissed.

She lay awake for a long time.

Things were no better the next day. They bathed in the cool of the morning in that marvellous translucent sea; they walked out upon the reef at low tide to see the coloured coral; they paddled about in a glass-bottomed boat to see the coloured fishes, and a good six inches separated them all the time. By teatime they were finding that they had exhausted their light conversation; the restraint was heavy upon both of them, and there were long awkward pauses when neither of them seemed to know what to say.

In the evening light they decided to walk round the island on the beach. She left him at the door of her hut, and said,“Give me a couple of minutes, Joe. I don't want to go around the beach in this frock.”She pulled one of the curtains for privacy; as she changed she thought that they had only one more day, and so much to settle that they had not started on. She would get nowhere without taking a bit of a risk, and it was worth it for Joe.

In the half light he turned as she came out of the hut, and he was back in the Malay scene of six years ago. She was wearing the same old faded cotton sarong or one very like it, held up in a roll under her arms; her brown shoulders and her brown arms were bare. She was barefooted, and her hair hung down in a long plait, tied at the end with a bit of string, as it had been in Malaya. She was no longer the strange English girl with money; she was Mrs Boong again, the Mrs Boong he had remembered all those years. She came to him rather shyly and put both hands on his shoulders, and said,“Is this better, Joe?”

She could never remember very clearly what happened in the next five minutes. She was standing locked in his arms as he kissed her face and her neck and her shoulders hungrily while his hands fondled her body; in the tumult of feelings that swept over her she knew that this man wanted her as nobody had ever wanted her before. She stood unresisting in his arms; it never entered her head to struggle or to try to get away. But presently, when she had breath to speak, she said,“Oh, Joe! They'll see us from the house!”

The next thing that she realized was that they were in her bedroom hut. She never knew how they got there, but thinking of it afterwards she came to the conclusion that he must have picked her up and carried her. And now a new confusion came to her. A sarong held up by a tight roll above the breasts will stay in place all day if given proper usage but it does not stand up very well to energetic man-handling; she could feel that it was getting loose and falling, and she had no other garment on at all.

Standing in his arms still unresisting, smothered by his kisses, she thought, this is It. And then she thought, It had to happen sometime, and I'm glad it's Joe. And then she thought, It's not his fault, I brought this on myself. And then she thought, I must sit down or something, or I'll be stark-naked, and at that she escaped backwards from his arms and sat down on the bed.

He followed her down, laughing, and her eyes laughed back at him as she tried to hold her sarong up with her hand to hide her bosom. Then she was in his arms again and he was hindering her. And then he said quite simply,“Do you mind?”

She reached her right arm round his shoulders, and said quietly,“Dear Joe. Not if you've got to. If you can wait till we're married, I'd much rather, but whatever you do now, I'll love you just the same.”

He looked down into her eyes.“Say that again.”

She drew his head down to her and kissed him.“Dear Joe. Of course I'm in love with you. What do you think I came to Australia for?”

“Will you marry me?”

“Of course I'll marry you.”She looked up at him with fondness and with laughter in her eyes.“Anyone looking at us now would say we were married already.”

He grinned; he was holding her more gently now.“I don't know what you must think of me.”

“Shall I tell you?”She took one of his wounded hands in hers and fondled the great scars.“I think you're the man I want to marry and have children by.”It did not seem to matter now that the sarong had fallen to her waist.“I'd rather wait a few months and get our lives arranged a little first, Joe. Marriage is a big thing, and there are things that ought to be done, first, before we marry. But if you say we can't wait, then I'll marry you tomorrow, or tonight.”

He drew her to him gently, and kissed her fingertips.“I can wait. I've waited six years for this, and I can wait a bit longer.”

She said softly,“Poor Joe. I'll try and make it easy, and not tantalize you. I oughtn't to have done this.”She freed herself from his arms and pulled up the sarong and rolled it round.“Just get outside a minute, and I'll put on some more clothes.”

He said,“You don't need to do that. I won't do anything, except kiss you now and then. Stay that way for tonight, as if it was Malaya.”

“Just for tonight,”she said. They went out presently and stood upon the beach in the bright moonlight, holding each other close.“I never knew a man could be so happy,”he said once.

Half an hour later she said,“Joe, we're both tired now, and it's time for bed. We've got an awful lot to talk about, but we'll talk better in the morning. There's just one thing I want to say tonight. If you ever feel you can't bear waiting any longer, you'll tell me, won't you? If you come to me like that, I promise we'll get married right away, or sooner than that.”

He said gently,“I can wait a long time for you, after this.”

“Dear Joe. I won't keep you waiting any more than I can help.”

She was so tired that when she got into her hut she did not light the candle, but fell upon her bed and loosened her sarong, Malay fashion, and slept almost at once. She woke with the first light of dawn and lay reflecting upon what had happened, absurdly happy; at last, she felt, things were going to go right, between them. She got up as the sun rose and peered cautiously over to Joe's hut and the restaurant building. There was no sign of any movement anywhere, so she put on her bathing dress and went down to the sea and had a bathe. Lying in the shallow water as the sun rose she discovered a number of bruises on her person, and reflected on the narrowness of her escape from a fate worse than death.

She went back very quietly to her hut and put on a frock. Then she went over to the restaurant. It stood open but there was nobody about; she put the kettle on the oil stove and made a pot of tea. Carrying a cup she went to Joe's hut and peered in cautiously.

He was lying on the bed asleep in a pair of shorts; she stood there for some minutes, watching him as he slept. The troubled lines had vanished from his face and he was sleeping easily and quietly, like a little boy; the scars upon his back stood out with an appalling and contrasting ferocity. She stood watching him for a time with fondness in her eyes, knowing that she would see him so most of the mornings of her life to come, and the thought pleased her.

She moved a little and put down the cup, and when she looked at him again he had opened his eyes, and he was looking at her.“Morning, Joe,”she said, wondering if she ought to be running like a rabbit.“I've made you a cup of tea.”

He leaned up on one arm.“Tell me,”he said.“Did what I think happened last night really happen?”

“I think so, Joe,”she said.“I think it must have done. I've got bruises all over me.”

He stretched out one hand.“Come here, and let me give you a kiss.”

She retreated.“Not on your life. I'll give you a kiss when you've got up and had a bathe and got some clothes on.”

He laughed.“Aren't you going to bathe?”

“I've bathed,”she said.“I've been up and pottering about for an hour, while you've been sleeping. I'll come down and watch you.”

He asked,“Did you sleep all right?”

She nodded.“Like a log.”

“So did I.”They smiled with mutual understanding.“Give me a minute, and I'll come down to the beach.”

She sat on the sand and chatted to him while he bathed. Then he came out and went to shave, and presently appeared in a clean shirt and a clean pair of khaki drill slacks, and she came into his arms and gave him his kiss. Then, as there was no sign yet of breakfast, they sat very close together on the beach in the cool morning breeze, talking and talking and talking. They had no difficulty in finding things to talk of now, and even their silences were intimate.

After breakfast, as they sat smoking cigarettes over a last cup of coffee, he said,“I've been thinking. I'm going to give up Midhurst, soon as Mrs Spears can find another manager.”She listened in consternation; what was coming now?“If we could get a grazing farm for fattening, in back of Adelaide, at Mallala or Hamley Bridge or Balaklava or some place like that, that's on the railway down from Alice Springs and not too far from the abattoir, that's what I'd like to do. I think we might be able to find a place like that only about fifty miles from the city, so as we could get in any time.”

She sat in silence for a minute; this needed careful handling.“Why do you want to do that, Joe? What's wrong with Midhurst?”

“It's too far from anywhere,”he said.“All right for a single man, perhaps, but not for a married couple. Now Adelaide's a bonza city. I'm a Queenslander, but I like Adelaide better than Brisbane. I haven't seen Sydney or Melbourne, but Adelaide's a bonza city, oh my word. It's got streets and streets of shops, and trams, and cinemas, and dance halls, and it's a pretty place, too, with hills behind and vineyards growing grapes to make the wine. We could have a bonza time if we got a farm near Adelaide.”

“But Joe,”she said,“is that the sort of work you want to do? Just buying store cattle from the outback and fattening them? It sounds awfully dull to me. Are you fed up with the outback?”

He ground his cigarette out on the floor beneath his heel.“There's places that suit single men and places that suit married people,”he said.“You've got to make a change or two when you get married.”

They had the breakfast table between them, separating them much too far for their newfound intimacy; she could not deal with so serious a matter as this without touching him.“Let's go outside,”she said. So they went out and found a patch of sandy grass at the head of the beach in the shade, and sat down there together.“I don't think that's right, Joe,”she said slowly.“I don't think you ought to leave the outback just because we're getting married.”

He smiled at her.“The Gulf country's no place for a woman,”he said.“Not unless she's been brought up and raised in the outback, and sometimes not then. I've seen some married people out from England try it, and I've never known it work. The life's too different, too hard.”

She said slowly,“I know it's very different, and very hard. I've lived in Willstown for three weeks, Joe, and so I know a bit about it.”She took his hand and fondled the great scars between her own two hands.“I know what you're afraid of. You're afraid that a girl straight out from England, a girl like me, will be unhappy in the outback, Joe. You're afraid that I'll get restless and start making excuses to go and stay in the city, for the dentist, or for shopping, and things like that. You're afraid that if we start at Midhurst you'll be trying me too hard, and that our marriage will go wrong.”

She raised her eyes and looked at him.“That's what you're afraid of, isn't it, Joe?”

He met her eyes.“Too right,”he said.“A man hasn't got a right to try and make an English girl live in a crook place like Willstown.”

She smiled.“It isn't only English girls, Joe. Australian girls, girls born in Willstown, they run a thousand miles to get away from it.”

He grinned.“That's right. If they can't stand it, how could you?”

“I don't know that I could,”she said thoughtfully. One had to be honest.“Are all the towns in the Gulf country the same?”

He nodded.“Normanton's a bit bigger; it's got three pubs instead of one, and it's got a church.”

There was a long silence.“I'm afraid of things, too,”she said at last.

He took her hand; he could not bear that she should be afraid of anything in the new life before them. She had been brave enough last night.“What's that?”he asked gently.

She said,“I'm afraid of changing your job.”She paused.“I can't believe that that would ever work out properly, that a man should change his work because his wife couldn't stand conditions that he could. You've been used to a property about two thousand square miles big, Joe, going off for three weeks at a time with packhorses and never going off your own land. What would a man like you do on a thousand acres?”

He grinned weakly; she had put her finger on the spot.“Get accustomed to it pretty soon, I should think.”

“I know you'd do it,”she said quietly.“You might even learn to do it reasonably well. But it could never satisfy you after the Gulf country, and cinemas won't fill the gap, or streets of shops, or dance halls. And sometimes when we squabble—we shall squabble, Joe—you'll think about your old life in the Gulf country, and how you had to give it up, because of me. And I shall know you're thinking that and blaming it on me, and that will be between us all the time. That's what I'm afraid of, Joe. I think we ought to stay up in the Gulf country, where your work is.”

“You just said you couldn't stand Willstown,”he objected.“Burketown and Croydon—well, they're just the same.”

“I know,”she said thoughtfully.“I'm not being very reasonable, am I? First I say I couldn't stand living in a place like that, and then I say that you oughtn't to think of living anywhere else.”

“That's right.”He was puzzled and distressed.“We've got to try and work it out some way to find what suits us both.”

“There's only one way to do that, Joe.”

“What's that?”

She smiled at him.“We'll have to do something about Willstown.”

Chapter 8

They spent that day in a curious mixture of love-making and economic discussion.“You can't tell me that a country with three times the rainfall of the Territory can't support a town as good as Alice,”she said once.“I know Alice has a railway. Willstown's got rain, and I know which I'd rather have for raising cattle. If you go on doing that, Joe, I'll go off and sit by myself. We aren't married yet.”She removed his hand and kissed it.

“Rain's not the only thing you want for raising cattle,”he said.“The better the feed, of course, the more calves live through the dry and the more you've got to sell. But there's a lot more to it than that, oh my word.”

“Tell me, Joe.”She had his hand in a firm grip.

“One thing,”he said,“you've got to keep that water when you've got it. It's true that Midhurst gets a lot of rainfall, but it's all gone in a flash. We get rain from the middle of December till the end of February, and you'll see the creeks all running full in flood. But three weeks later, by the end of March, they'll be all dry again, and the country as dry as ever.”

“Is that what you want to build the dams for, at Kangaroo Creek and Dry Gum Creek?”

“That's right,”he said.“I want to make a start with building little kind of barrages to hold back the water. Do a bit each year, starting at the head of each creek and working down. Get a little pool held back every two or three miles all down the creeks till they run out into the Gilbert. They wouldn't hold the water right through the dry, of course; the sun's too strong. But you could add a lot of feed to Midhurst if you had a lot of little dams like that. Oh my word, you could.”

She released his hand.“How big is Midhurst, Joe?”

“Eleven hundred square miles.”

“How many cattle does it carry?”

“About nine thousand. Ought to carry more than that, but it's dry up at the top end. Very dry.”

“Suppose you could get all the little dams that you're imagining. How many would it carry then?”

He thought for a minute.“I don't see why it shouldn't carry double what's on it now. That'ld be about sixteen to the mile. With a rainfall like we've got you should be able to do that.”

“You sold fourteen hundred head this year, didn't you?”

“That's right.”

“How much a head?”

“Four pound sixteen.”

She grabbed his hand again, and held it imprisoned.“I'm trying to think, Joe. If you doubled the stock on the station you'd have another fourteen hundred to sell each year. That's—that's between six and seven thousand pounds a year more to sell. You'd be selling twelve or thirteen thousand pounds worth every year then, Joe. It'ld be worth spending a bit of capital on dams to get that rise in turnover, wouldn't it?”

He looked at her with a new respect.“Well, that's the way I worked it out. I told Mrs Spears, I said, I want to keep a permanent gang of three men and a few Abos on this. Do a bit each year, working down from the top. Spend about fifteen hundred a year, you might say. There'd be less profit the first year, but after that it should rise steadily to nearly double. That's what I told her.”

“She agreed, did she?”

“She's agreed to spend the money. But that's only the start of it, the easy part. It may be years before I get the men.”

She looked at him incredulously.“Years?”

“Too right,”he said heavily.“It's all very well to think of things like that, but it's another thing to do them. Might be five years before I get the work in hand. You see, there's only three of us on Midhurst—whites, that is—me and Jim Lennon, and Dave Hope. We've got to find three more who'll work out all the week up-country, forty miles from the homestead, working with a pick and shovel mostly, and responsible enough to get on by themselves with only just a visit once a week or once a fortnight. Well, you can't get men like that. There are fewer people in the Gulf country every year. If it wasn't for the Abo stockmen, the boongs, I don't know what we'd do.”

“Are there really only three of you—whites—running Midhurst?”

He put his arm around her shoulders.“When you come it'll be four.”

She thought it would be five or six soon after that, but she refrained from saying so.“How many would you like to have?”

“You mean with eighteen thousand head of cattle, some time in the future?”She nodded.“I could use twenty on a station like that,”he said.“That wouldn't be too many, not if you were running tame bulls in a paddock, to improve the stock. There'd be fences and stockyards and all sorts of things to make. I could use twenty white ringers, and some other hands besides.”

She said slowly,“Pete Fletcher said that there were fifty ringers coming into Willstown, using it as their town.”

“That's about right,”he said.

“If all the stations developed like you say,”she observed,“that means seven times as many ringers, because there are only three of you now. Three or four hundred ringers in the district, all with wives and families, and shops for them, and pubs, and garages, and radio, and cinemas. There's room here for a town of two or three thousand people, Joe.”

He smiled.“You'll be making it as big as Brisbane next.”

She said severely,“Joe. There was an old girl in our party in Malaya called Mrs Frith. She thought you must be Jesus Christ, because you'd been crucified. I tried to tell her that you weren't. If she saw what you're doing now she'd probably believe me.”

They talked about Mrs Frith for a time, and then reverted to more mundane matters.“Joe,”she said,“listen to me. Would you think it very stupid if I said I wanted to start a business in Willstown?”

He stared at her.“A business? What sort of business could you do in Willstown?”

“Do you know what I was doing in England?”she inquired.

“Shorthand typing, wasn't it?”he asked.

She took his hand and smoothed it between her own.“There's such a lot that you don't know about me,”she said.“So much to tell you.”She started in to tell him about Pack and Levy, and Mr Pack, and about alligator-skin shoes, and Aggie Topp. Half an hour later she said,“That's what I want to do, Joe. Do you think it's crazy?”

“I don't know.”And then, quite unexpectedly, he said,“I took a walk down Bond Street, looking in the shops.”

She turned to him, surprised.“Did you, Joe?”

He nodded.“I asked Mr Strachan what I ought to see in London and he asked me how much history I knew and I told him that I never got much schooling. So then he said to go and see St Paul's and Westminster Abbey, and then he said to take the bus to Piccadilly Circus and walk up Regent Street and along Oxford Street and down Bond Street and back along Piccadilly; he said I'd see all the best shops that way.”

She nodded. It seemed very far away from Green Island, and the whisper of the coconut palms overhead in the sea breeze.

“I saw a lot of alligator-skin shoes,”he said.“Sort of dressing-cases, too.”He turned to her.“It was interesting seeing those, and wondering if they were skins that old Jeff Pocock trapped. Made me feel quite at home. Beautifully done up, they were. But the prices—oh my word. Most of them hadn't got no labels, but there was one, just a little alligator-skin case with silvery things in it, for a lady. A hundred guineas, that one was.”

She was excited.“Joe, I bet that was made by Pack and Levy. We did all that sort of work.”

“You weren't thinking you could make that sort of stuff in Willstown?”

“Not cases, Joe. Just shoes—shoes to start with, anyway. A little workshop with six or seven girls making alligator-skin shoes. It won't cost very much, Joe—not more than I can afford to lose if it goes wrong. But I don't know—perhaps it won't go wrong. If it worked out all right, and if it paid, it'ld be a good thing for the town.”

“Six or seven girls all earning money at a job in Willstown?”he said thoughtfully.“You wouldn't keep them six weeks. They'd all be married—oh my word, they would.”

She laughed.“Then I'd have to find six or seven more.”She got up.“Let's go and bathe. It'll be too hot if we don't bathe soon.”

They went and changed and lay in the clean, silvery water on the coral sand.“Look at those bruises,”she said.“You great bully. Hit somebody your own size.”And presently she said,“I've got another shock for you. You won't drown if I tell you now? I want to start an ice-cream parlour.”

“Oh my word.”

“I'm going to pay these girls a lot of money, Joe,”she said seriously.“I've got to get some of it back.”

He looked at her, uncertain if she were laughing or not.“An ice-cream parlour in Willstown?”he said.“It'll never pay.”

“You wait till you see what I charge for an ice-cream,”she said.“Not only ice-cream, Joe—fruit and vegetables, quick frozen stuff, and women's magazines, and cosmetics, and all the little bits of things that women want. I've got a very pretty girl who wants to come and run it for me, a girl called Rose Sawyer who lives in Alice Springs.”

He said slowly,“If you've got a girl like that to run it, the women won't be able to get in the shop. It'll be full of ringers.”

“That's all right,”she said,“so long as they buy ice-cream.”She turned to him.“Joe, did you ever spend a Sunday in Alice Springs?”

He shook his head.“I don't think I ever did. Not since before the war, anyway.”

“I know why that is, too,”she said.“The pubs are shut.”

He grinned.“Too right.”

“The pub's shut in Willstown, too, on Sundays.”

“The bar's shut,”he said.“You can usually get it out of Ma Connor, round the back.”

She rolled over in the water.“I'll have to tip off Sergeant Haines, Joe. Sunday's the best day of all for the ice-cream parlour at Alice. All the men who are in the bar all the week come along with their wives and kids on Sunday to the ice-cream parlour and put down ice-cream sodas and Coca-Cola. That place does a roaring trade on Sundays.”

“It would,”he said thoughtfully.“There'd be nothing else to do.”

They got out of the sea presently and went and sat in the shade; he would not let her stay in long for fear of sunburn. When they were smoking together under the trees, he said,“It's going to cost a hell of a lot of money, all this you want to do. Three or four thousand pounds, I'd say, or more than that.”

“I've got enough,”she said.

He turned to her.“Mr Strachan told me you were a wealthy woman,”he said quietly.“It worried me, that did, till I got used to the idea. How much have you got? Don't tell me if you'd rather not say, but if I knew about how much I'd be able to help you more.”

“Of course,”she said. Nothing would come between them now, after last night.“Mr Strachan says I've got about fifty-three thousand pounds. It's all in trust for me until I'm thirty-five, though. If I want to spend capital before then, I've got to ask him.”

“Oh my word.”

“It is a lot of money, isn't it?”she said.“I'm glad that it's in trust for me in a way, because I wouldn't in the least know what to do with it. And Noel has been such a dear.”She paused.“I want to do something useful with it,”she said.“I don't know anything about real business. The only thing I know about at all is what Pack and Levy made. I thought if we could start a little workshop of that sort, and a shop where women could get things they like—well, even if it didn't pay very well, it'll be using money the way money ought to be used, in places like Willstown.”

He bent and kissed her.“There's another thing, Joe,”she said.“I don't know, but I've got a sort of feeling that there's more to it than just employing a few girls. You say the ringers are all leaving the Gulf country, and men won't come to the outback. Well, of course they won't if they can't get a girl. And all the girls go because they can't get a job. For every girl I make a job for, I believe you'll get a man to work at Midhurst. Don't you think that's true?”

“I don't know.”He stared out over the sea to the dim blue line of the Tableland.“It'ld certainly help to have a flock of girls around. It can be lonely in the outback, oh my word.”

A poignant realization of the solitude struck her. The long nights alone in the homestead, when ‘you couldn't get along in the outback without dogs’. The sensitive, intelligent face of the manager of Carlisle, Eddie Page, who had married his illiterate, inarticulate lubra. She turned to him with quick understanding and sympathy.“I feel an awful pig asking you to wait,”she said. He took her hand and squeezed it.“I do want to try and start this business before we get married, Joe,”she said. She smiled at him.“You know, you're a pretty energetic lover. I don't believe you'll waste much time starting a family.”

He grinned,“I won't go quicker than you want to.”

“I want to have them, too.”She pulled his head down to her and kissed him.“But that means I'll only have six months for business after we get married, and then I'll have to begin thinking of other things. Joe, when do you start mustering?”

“After the wet,”he said.“It was March this year because of the late season, but normally we'd start mustering about the middle of February.”

“How long does the muster go on for?”

“About three weeks or a month. After that there's the branding of the calves, and driving the stock down to Julia Creek.”

“Could we get married after the mustering, Joe? Say early in April?”

“Of course.”

She said thoughtfully,“That would mean that I'd have nearly a year from now, to get it to the stage when I could leave the business for a month or two while we start your family. I think that's fair enough. If it couldn't run without me for a month by then the whole thing wouldn't be much good, and we'd better pack it up.”

He said,“I'll be around, of course.”

She laughed.“Handing out ice-creams and selling lipsticks to young girls. I won't ask you to do that, Joe.”

He thought about this programme.“Jim could drive the steers alone down to Julia Creek,”he said,“while we're getting married. I'd send Bourneville and some of the other boongs with him. Then we could drive down in the utility and catch him up about the time he got there, and put them on the train. Have it as a kind of honeymoon.”

She smiled.“I like your idea of a honeymoon.”He grinned.“Is there anything to do in Julia Creek, Joe, except drink beer?”

“Oh my word,”he said.“There's plenty to do in Julia Creek.”

“What is there to do there?”

“Put fifteen hundred cattle into railway trucks.”He grinned at her.“There's not many English girls get a chance of a honeymoon like that,”he said.

They went and changed for lunch, and over lunch he said,“About this tanning and dressing the alligator skins. I'd give that away.”He was very much against attempting to do that in Willstown; it was messy work, unsuitable for girls, and no men were available to do it. He told her that there was a tannery in Cairns who could dress any skins she sent them.“A joker called Gordon runs it,”he said.“He was over in the Gulf country last year. We could go and see him tomorrow afternoon if you like.”

“Would he have any white kid basils, do you think?”

“Might do. If not he'll probably get them.”

With his knowledge of station management he was a great help to her with suggestions for the workshop.“I'd make it good and big, while you're at it,”he said.“It's the transport of the wood to Willstown that's going to cost the money.”He thought for a minute.“There's three of you new girls coming in to live in Willstown, if all goes right,”he said.“You and this Rose Sawyer and this Aggie Topp. Why don't you make your workshop building a bit bigger and have three bed-sitting-rooms at the end, walled off from the rest of it and with a separate entrance? Then you wouldn't have to live in the hotel and you'd be all comfortable by yourselves. Then if the business grows up you can pull down the wall and throw it all into one.”This seemed to her to be a very good idea indeed.

They got a paper and pencil after lunch and jotted down a few essential things to do in Cairns when they got back there, and orders to be placed. Then they retired to their own huts and slept in the heat of the day. She was roused by Joe calling her outside her hut.“Come on and bathe,”he was saying.“It's nearly five o'clock.”

She pulled the sheet over quickly.“I won't be a minute. Have you been looking in?”

“I wouldn't do a thing like that.”

“I wish I could believe you.”She pulled the curtain across and put on her bathing dress, and joined him on the beach. And lying with him in the warm blue and silvery water on the sand, she said,“Joe, do you want us to be engaged, with a ring and everything?”

“You'd like that, wouldn't you?”

She shook her head.“Not unless it would prevent you worrying. I'll marry you early in April, Joe —that's dinkum.”He smiled.“But for the present, I believe we'd get on better if we weren't officially engaged.”She turned to him.“You see, when we get back to Willstown I'll be doing some pretty odd things, things that Willstown people will think crazy. Some of them may be, because there'll probably be some mistakes. I don't want you to have to be mixed up in it, just because we're engaged. You've got a position to keep up.”

“Wouldn't it help if people thought I was with you in whatever you're doing?”

She smiled, and rolled over and kissed him.“You're all salt. It wouldn't help if you get in a fight every Saturday night in the bar because somebody says something rude about your fiancée.”He grinned.“They will, you know. They're bound to think I'm crackers.”

They got out of the water presently and sat in the shade of the trees, talking and talking about the future.“Joe,”she said once,“what do I do if a boong comes into the ice-cream parlour and wants a soda? A boong stockrider? Do I serve him in the same place, or has he got to have a different shop?”

He scratched his head.“I dunno that it's ever happened in Willstown. They go into Bill Duncan's store. I don't think you could serve them in an ice-cream parlour, with a white girl behind the counter.”

She said firmly,“Then I'll have to have another parlour for them with a black girl in it. There's such a lot of them, Joe—we can't cut them out. We'll have two parlours, with the freezes and the kitchen between.”She drew a little diagram on the white sand with her forefinger.“Like this.”

“Oh my word,”he said.“You're going to start some talk in Willstown.”

She nodded.“I know. That's why I don't want us to be engaged till just before we're married.”

In the evening as they kissed goodnight between their bedroom huts, she said,“We won't be able to do this in Willstown. I'll remember this Green Island all my life, Joe.”

He grinned.“Come back here in April, if you like. Before Julia Creek.”

They left next morning, when Eddie came for them with his motorboat, and landed at Cairns early in the afternoon. They took their bags to the hotel, and then went straight to see Mr Gordon at the tannery, and spent an hour with him discussing alligator skins and other shoe materials. He advised them to dismiss the idea of kid for linings.“Anything that can be done with kid we'll do for you with wallaby,”he said.“You've got any amount of wallaby out there, and it's as good as kid— texture, appearance, bleaching, glazing—anything you like.”Harman arranged to send him half a dozen skins for sample treatment by the next lorry.“Be a good thing to keep down some of these wallabies,”he said.“They eat an awful lot of feed out on the station. Too many of them altogether.”

They spent the rest of the afternoon shopping and ordering, and got back to the hotel at dusk, tired out, having booked their passages to Willstown upon the morning plane. Jean said,“There's one thing I must do tonight, Joe, before leaving Cairns. I must write to Noel Strachan and tell him what's happened.”

In the warm scented night of early summer by the Queensland sea, she sat down on the veranda after tea and wrote me a long letter. Joe Harman sat beside her as she wrote, smoking quietly, at peace.

She was very good about writing, and she still is; she still writes every week. I got that letter early in November; I remember it so well. It was a foggy, dark morning with a light rain or drizzle falling. I had to have the electric light on for breakfast, and the Palace stables on the other side of the road were hardly visible. In the street below the taxis went past with a wet swish of mud and water on the wet wood blocks.

It was a long letter from a very happy girl, telling me about her love. I was delighted at the news, of course. I sat reading it with my breakfast before me, and then I read it through again, and then I read it a third time. When I woke up to realities my coffee was cold and the fried egg had frozen to the dish in front of me in cold, congealed fat, but I was too absorbed in her news to want it. I went into my bedroom to put my shoes and coat on for the office, and as I opened the wardrobe to get my coat I saw her boots and skates, that I had been keeping for her till she came back for them. Old men get rather silly, sometimes, and I must say that that rather dashed me for a moment, because she wouldn't be coming back for them. She wouldn't be coming back to England ever again.

I went to the front door, and my charwoman was in the flat, just coming out of the dining-room.“Such good news, Mrs Chambers,”I said.“Do you remember Miss Paget, who used to come here sometimes? She's got engaged to be married, to an Australian, out in Queensland.”

“Oh, I am glad,”she said.“Such a nice lady, she was.”

“Yes, wasn't she?”I repeated.“Such a nice lady.”

She said,“You didn't eat your breakfast, sir. Was everything all right?”

“Yes, quite all right, thanks, Mrs Chambers,”I said.“I didn't want anything this morning.”

It was cold and raw out in the street, one of those yellow foggy mornings with a reeking chill that makes you cough. I walked on towards the office in a dream, thinking about wallabies and laughing black stockmen, about blue water running over the white coral sands, about Jean Paget and the trouble she had had with her sarong in that hot country where all clothes are a burden. Then there was a fierce, rending squeal right on top of me, and a heavy blow on my right arm so that I staggered and nearly fell, and I was in the middle of Pall Mall with a taxi broadside on across the road beside me. I didn't know where I was for a moment, and then I heard the white-faced driver saying,“For Christ's sake. You can think yourself bloody lucky that you're still alive.”

“I'm sorry,”I said.“I wasn't looking where I was going.”

“Stepping out into the road like that,”he said angrily.“Ought to have more sense, at your age. Did I hit you?”

A little crowd was starting to collect.“Only my arm,”I said. I moved it, and it worked all right.“It's nothing.”

“Well, that's a bloody miracle,”he said.“Look out where you're going to next time.”He put his gear in, straightened up his taxi, and drove on; I walked on to the office.

The girl brought in the letters for me to go through, as usual, but I put them on one side in favour of another letter that I had in my breast pocket. I had a client or two that morning, I suppose; I usually have, and I suppose I gave them some advice, but my mind was twelve thousand miles away. Lester Robinson came in once with some business or other and I said to him,“You remember my Paget girl—the heir to that Macfadden estate? She's got herself engaged to be married to an Australian. He seems to be a very good chap.”

He grunted.“I forget. Does that terminate our trust?”

“No,”I said.“That goes on for some time to come. Till she's thirty-five.”

“Pity,”he said.“It's made a lot of work for you, that trust has. It'll be a good thing when it's all wound up.”

“It's been no trouble, really,”I said. By the end of the day I think I knew her letter by heart although it was eight quarto pages long, but I took it with me to the club. I had a glass of sherry in the bar and told Moore about her engagement because he knew something about her story, and after dinner we sat down to a couple of rubbers of bridge, Dennison and Strickland and Callaghan, the four of us who play together every evening, and I told them about her.

I got up from the table at about eleven o'clock, and went into the library for a final cigarette before going back across the park to my flat. The big room was empty but for Wright, who had been in the Malay Police and knew her story. I dropped down into a chair beside him, and remarked,“You know that girl, Jean Paget? I think I've spoken to you about her once or twice before.”

He smiled.“You have.”

“She's got herself engaged to be married,”I told him.“To the manager of a cattle station, in Northern Queensland.”

“Indeed?”he said.“What's he like?”

“I've met him,”I replied.“He's a very good chap. She's very much in love with him. I think they're going to be very happy.”

“Is she coming back to England before getting married?”he asked.

I sat staring at the rows of books upon the wall, the gold embossed carving at the corner of the ceiling.“No,”I said.“I don't think she's ever coming back to England, ever again.”

He was silent.

“It's too far,”I said.“I think she'll make her life in Queensland now.”

There was a long pause.“After all, there's no reason why she should come back to England,”I said at last.“There's nothing for her to come back for. She's got no ties in this country.”

And then he said a very foolish thing. He meant it well enough, but it was a stupid thing to say. I got up and left him and went home to my dark, empty flat, and I avoided meeting him for some time after that. I was seventy-three years old that autumn, old enough to be her grandfather. I couldn't possibly have been in love with her myself.

Chapter 9

In the months of November and December that year Jean Paget worked harder than she had ever worked before.

Rose Sawyer joined her in Willstown within a fortnight, and Aggie Topp sailed early in November. I got Mr Pack to send Aggie to see me before she left. She was a gaunt, rather prim woman, but I could see at once that Pack had been quite right; if anyone could make girls work this woman could. I gave her her ticket and a typed sheet of instructions telling her how she would get by air from Sydney to Willstown, and then I talked to her about the job.“You know, it's very, very rough,”I said.“It's rough, and it's hot, and Miss Paget is having to start absolutely from nothing. She's got plenty of money, but it's going to be hard, all the time. You understand that, Mrs Topp?”

She said,“I've had two letters from Miss Paget, and she sent a photograph of the place, the main street. It don't look up to much, I must say.”

“You're quite happy to go out there, are you?”

She said,“Oh well, I've been in rough places before. It's only for a year to start with, anyway.”And then she said,“I always liked Miss Paget.”

I had another matter to fix up with Aggie Topp. Jean was very anxious to get hold of an air-conditioning unit, a thing about the size of a small refrigerator which stood in the room and took hot air into itself and pumped it out cold into the room; it seemed to her important to have this to prevent the girls' hands from sweating as they worked and marking the delicate leathers of the shoes. She had not been able to get hold of one in Australia and had cabled me, and I had found a firm that made them and got hold of one with a good deal of difficulty and some small payments on the side. Derek Harris is rather good at that sort of negotiation. I had it in our office standing at the foot of the stairs and I showed it to Mrs Topp, and arranged for her to take it out with her to Sydney. From Sydney it would have to be flown up with her to Cairns and Willstown at some considerable expense, but it seemed to me to be worth it since it was then the hottest time of the year.

This was the biggest commission that I got from Jean and was my own main contribution to the venture; the remainder of her cables were concerned with little bits of things that were no trouble. Aggie Topp took out with her a good deal of stuff from Pack and Levy, too; three cases full of tools and lasts and formers and all sorts of things, the bill for which came to about a hundred and forty-six pounds, which I paid for Jean in England.

Joe Harman helped her to get the buildings started on the day that they arrived in Willstown. They had a meeting with Tim Whelan and his two sons, in the carpenter's shop amongst the coffins. They had already placed orders for two lorry loads of lumber in Cairns. The men stood or sat squatting, ringer fashion, on the floor with papers on the floor before them, planning the layout of the buildings; the workshop with its three-bedroom annexe was to be built first, and after that the ice-cream parlour next to it, leaving room for the expansion of the workshop one way and of the ice-cream parlour the other way. There were no great difficulties of expansion in the built-up area of Willstown.

They sent Tim Whelan presently to find Mr Carter, the Shire Clerk, to pass the plans of the new buildings and to grant a lease of the site in the main street.“It'll be all right there,”he said thoughtfully.“There was a whole row of houses there in 1905—I've got a photograph. But nobody ever paid rent for that land in my time.”Jean asked what rent would be required for the area she wanted, a difficult matter to decide in view of the fact that no plans existed and the area that she wanted was quite uncertain.“This is a town borough,”Mr Carter said.“You don't lease land upon an acreage basis in a town borough. If you're going to develop the land by building, then I'd say about a shilling a year for each hundred foot of frontage. It's in the main street, you see. If you wanted it for chickens or anything like that I'd have to charge five shillings.”

They adjourned to the bar of the hotel to seal the contracts; Jean sat on the steps outside with a lemonade, as was fitting for a lady with a reputation to preserve in Willstown.

She went to Brisbane a week later, flying to Cairns and flying on the same day down to Brisbane. She stayed there for three days and came back having ordered an electric generating set, a very large refrigerator, two deep freezes, a stainless steel counter, eight glass-topped tables, thirty-two chairs, two sink units, and a mass of minor shop fittings, glasses, plates, cutlery, and furnishings as well as a good deal of electrical fittings and cable. She made arrangements with the firms for all this stuff to be crated and consigned to Forsayth; in Cairns she made arrangements for the truck transport of these goods from Forsayth to Willstown. I had arranged the necessary credits for her and she was able to pay cash for everything.

She came back to Willstown a week later having made tentative arrangements for supplies of stock for her ice-cream parlour, and found the framework of the workshop already erected; a wooden building goes up very quickly. The matter was a nine days' wonder in Willstown and old men used to stand around wondering at this midsummer madness of an English girl, a stranger to the Gulf country, who proposed to make shoes there and send them all the way to England to be sold. They were too kindly to be rude to her or to laugh at such an eccentricity, but an aura of disbelief surrounded the whole venture and made her feel very much alone in those first weeks.

She visited Midhurst at a very early stage, one Sunday when no work was going on upon her building. Joe Harman drove in to fetch her in his big utility at dawn one day, and took her back to Midhurst in time for breakfast. As soon as they were out of sight of the town they stopped for five minutes to kiss and talk.

Presently they disentangled and went on. Jean was accustomed by this time to the idea that no road in this country had a metalled surface. She had not been beyond the town hitherto; very soon she discovered that a road was where the car drove across country. The land was parched and dry with the heat of summer, covered with thin tufts of scorched grass. It was a wooded land, covered thinly with spindly, distorted eucalyptus trees averaging twenty to thirty feet in height; these trees were fairly widely spaced so that it was possible for a car or truck driven across country to find a way between them. This was the road, and when the surface of the earth became too deeply pitted and potholed with traffic the cars and trucks would deviate and choose another course. These tracks followed the same general direction, coming together at the fords where creeks, now dry and stony, had to be crossed, and fanning out again upon the other side.

Once in the twenty miles she saw half a dozen cattle, that stampeded wildly at the noise of the utility as it bounced, and rocketed over the uneven ground. She asked Joe what on earth the cattle found to eat; the ground seemed to her to be completely barren.“They get along,”he said.“There's plenty here for them to eat, my word. This dry stuff in the tussocks, why, it's just the same as hay.”He told her that there was a waterhole a little way from their track.“They never go more than three or four miles from water,”he said.“Horses, now—you'll find them grazing up to twenty miles from a drink.”

Once she exclaimed at three brown, furry forms bounding away among the trees.“Oh, Joe— kangaroos!”

He corrected her.“Wallabies. We don't get any 'roos up in these parts.”

She stared after the flying forms, entranced.“What's the difference between a wallaby and a kangaroo, Joe?”

“A wallaby's smaller,”he said.“A big, buck kangaroo, he'll stand up to six feet high, but a wallaby's not more than four. A kangaroo, he's got a face like a deer. A wallaby, he's got a face like a rabbit, or a rat. I got a little wallaby to show you at the homestead.”

“A wild one?”

“He's a tame one now. He'll get wild as he grows older; then he'll go off to his own folks.”He told her that when they had shot the wallabies to send the sample skins to Cairns for her they had shot a doe with a joey, and rather than leave the small defenceless creature to die they had taken it home to rear.“I like a wallaby about the place,”he said.

They came to Midhurst presently. A fence of two wire strands tacked to the trees, with an occasional post in the wider gaps, crossed their path, with an iron gate; beyond the gate the track became the semblance of a road. She got out of the utility and opened the gate and he drove through.“This is the home paddock,”he said.“For horses, mostly.”She could see horses standing underneath the trees, lean riding horses, swishing long black tails.“I've got about three square miles fenced off like this around the house.”

The road swung round, and she saw Midhurst homestead. It was prettily situated on a low hill above the bend of a creek; this creek was not running, but there were still pools of water held along its length.“Of course, you're seeing it at the worst time of year,”he said, and she became aware of his anxiety.“It's a lovely little river in the winter, oh my word. But even in the worst part of the dry, like now, there's always water there.”

The homestead was a fairly large building that stood high off the ground on posts, so that you climbed eight feet up a flight of steps to reach the veranda and the one floor of the house. It was built of wood and had the inevitable corrugated iron roof. Four rooms, three bedrooms and one sitting-room, were surrounded on all four sides by a veranda twelve feet deep; masses of ferns and greenery of all sorts stood in pots and on stands on this veranda at the outer edge and killed most of the direct rays of the sun. There was a kitchen annexe at one end and a bathroom annexe at the other; the toilet was a little hut over a pit in the paddock, some distance from the house. Most of the life of the building evidently went on in the veranda and the rooms seemed to be little used; in the veranda was Joe's bed and his mosquito net, and several cane easy chairs, and the dining-room tables and chairs. Suspended from the rafters was a large canvas waterbag cooling in the draft, with an enamelled mug hung from it by a string.

Five or six dogs greeted them noisily as the utility came to a standstill before the steps. He brushed them aside, but pointed out a large blue and yellow bitch like no dog Jean had ever seen before.“That's Lily,”he said fondly.“She had a bonza litter, oh my word.”

He took her up into the coolness of the veranda; she turned to him.“Oh Joe, this is nice!”

“Like it?”Puppies were surging about them, grovelling and licking their hands; odd-shaped yellow and blue puppies. Along the veranda a small animal stood erect behind a chair, peering at them around the corner. Joe took the puppies one by one and dropped them into a wire-netting enclosure in one corner.“I let them out this morning before driving in,”he said.“They'll be big enough to go down in the yard pretty soon.”

“Joe, who fixed up these plants? Did you?”

He shook his head.“Mrs Spears did that, when she used to live here. I kept them going. The lubras water them, morning and evening.”He told her that he had three Abo women, wives of three of his stockriders, who shared the domestic duties of the homestead and cooked for him.

He looked around.“There's the joey somewhere.”They found the little wallaby lolloping about on the other side of the veranda; it stood like a little kangaroo about eighteen inches high, and had no fear of them. Jean stooped beside it and it nibbled at her fingers.“What do you feed it on, Joe?”

“Bread and milk. It's doing fine on that.”

“Don't the puppies hurt it?”

“They chase it now and then, but it can kick all right. A full-grown wallaby can kill a dog. Rip him right up.”He paused, watching her caress the little creature, thinking how lovely she was.“It's all in fun,”he said.“They get along all right. By and by when he gets bigger and the dogs are bigger he'll get angry with them, and then he'll go off into the bush.”

A fat, middle-aged lubra, a black golliwog of a woman, laid the table and presently appeared with two plates of the inevitable steak with two eggs on the top, and a pot of strong tea. Jean had become accustomed to the outback breakfast by this time but this steak was tougher than most; she made mental notes to look into the Midhurst cooking as she struggled with it. In the end she gave up and sat back laughing.“I'm sorry, Joe,”she said.“It's because I'm English, I suppose.”

He was very much concerned.“Have a couple more fried eggs. You haven't eaten anything.”

“I've eaten six times as much as I ever ate in England for breakfast, Joe. Who does the cooking?”

“Palmolive did this,”he said.“It's her day. Mary cooks much better, but it's her day off.”

“Who are they, Joe?”

“I've got a ringer called Moonshine,”he said.“Palmolive's his gin. My boss Abo, he's called Bourneville; he's a bonza boy. Mary's his gin. Mary cooks all right.”

“Tell me, Joe,”she said,“do you ever get any indigestion?”

He grinned.“Not very often. Just now and then.”

“You won't mind if I reorganize the cooking a bit when I come in?”

“Not so long as you don't do it all yourself,”he said.

“You wouldn't like me to do that?”

He shook his head.“I'd rather see you keep time for the things you want to do, the shoes, and the ice-cream parlour, and that.”

She touched his hand.“I want to keep time for you.”

He took her out before the heat of the day and showed her the establishment. Although the property covered over a thousand square miles, there were no more buildings round the homestead than she had seen on a four-hundred-acre farm in England. There were three or four cottages of two rooms at the most, for stockmen; there were two small bunkhouses for unmarried ringers, white and black. There was a shed housing the truck and the utility and a mass of oddments of machinery. There was a stable for about six horses, which was empty, and a saddle-room, and a butcher's room. There was a Diesel engine that drove an electric generator and pumped water from the creek. That was about all.

Once he said,“Can you ride a horse?”

She shook her head.“I'm afraid not, Joe. Ordinary people don't ride horses much in England.”

“Oh my word,”he said.“You should be able to do that.”

“Could I learn?”

“Too right.”

He put his fingers to his mouth like a schoolboy and blew a shrill whistle; a black head came poking out the window of a single-room cottage.“Bourneville,”he called.“Get out and bring in Auntie and Robin, 'n saddle up. I'll be down to help you in a minute.”

He turned to her, surveying her cotton frock.“I dunno about your things. Could you get into a pair of my strides, or would you rather not?”

She laughed.“Oh Joe, they'd go round me twice!”

“I wasn't always as fat as this,”he said.“I got a pair I used to wear before the war, I can't get into now. It doesn't matter if they don't fit right; we'll only be walking the horses so you'll see what it feels like.”

He took her up into the homestead and produced a clean man's shirt and a faded pair of jodhpurs and a belt for her; she took them from him laughing, and went into his spare room and put them on, with a pair of his elastic-sided, thin-soled riding boots that were far too big for her. It gave her a queer feeling of possession to be dressed all in his clothes. She walked gingerly down into the yard with the feeling that everything was likely to fall off her, as it had done on another memorable occasion.

He helped her up into the saddle; once astride the patient fourteen-year-old Auntie the feeling of insecurity left her. They adjusted her stirrups and showed her how to set her foot; once she was fairly settled she felt very safe. She knew little about horses or saddlery at that time, but this saddle was like no saddle she had ever seen in England, even in a picture. It rose up in an arch high behind her seat and high in front of her, so that she was seated as in a hammock. There was a great horn that projected above each of her thighs and another one under each thigh, so that she was as if clamped into place.“I don't believe that anyone could fall off from a saddle like this,”she said.

“You aren't meant to fall off,”he replied.

They walked the horses out of the yard and down the track to the creek; as they went he showed her how to hold the reins and how to use her heels. He took her up the creek for about a mile and then by a wide circuit through the bush, winding beneath the trees so far as possible to seek the shade. Once she saw four scurrying black forms vanishing among the trees and he told her that these were wild pig, and once in a wide stretch of water covered with water lilies there was a violent swirl of water as an alligator dived away from them. She saw several wallabies bounding away before their horses.

They returned to the homestead after an hour or so. Although they had walked the horses all the way Jean was drenched with sweat under the hot sun, and she had a raging thirst. In the veranda she drank several mugs of water, and then she went into the bathroom and had a shower, and changed back into her own cool clothes.

They lunched in the veranda on steak and bread and jam, a repeat of breakfast without the eggs.“Palmolive hasn't got much imagination in the matter of tucker,”he said apologetically.

“She's looking very tired,”Jean said.“Great black circles under her eyes. Give her the afternoon off, Joe. I'll make tea for you.”

He offered her the use of the spare room bed to sleep on after lunch, but they had seen so little of each other in the last fortnight that the time seemed too precious to waste in sleep.“Let's sit out here,”she said.“If I should go to sleep, Joe, it'll be just one of those things.”So they pulled two of the long cane chairs to the corner of the veranda where there might be a little breeze, and sat together close, so that they could touch hands.“It's not always as hot as this,”he said, still anxious for her approval of the place.“Just these two months are the bad ones. By January it'll be beginning to cool off, when the rain gets properly under way.”

“It's not too bad,”she said.“I remember times when it was quite as hot as this in Malaya.”

She led him on to tell her about his work on the station; having seen a little of the terrain that morning she felt she could appreciate what he told her better now.“There's not a lot to do this time of year,”he said.“I like to get up to the top end of the station once a fortnight, if I can, in case of duffers. Make a cache or two of tucker up there, top, this time of year, and shoot the worst of the scrub bulls you see around.”

“What's a duffer, Joe?”

“Why, cattle duffers—cattle thieves. We've not had much of it this year. Sometimes the drovers coming down to Julia Creek from the Cape stations—they pick up a few as they go through the property and put them with the herd. It means faking the brands, of course, and there's the police at Julia to keep an eye open for fresh-branded beasts as they go on the train. They caught a joker at it two years ago and he got six months. We've not had much since then. Poddy-dodging, now—well, that's another matter.”

“What's poddy-dodging, Joe?”She was beginning to grow sleepy, but she wanted to know all she could.

“Why, a poddy's a cleanskin, a calf born since the last muster that hasn't been branded. Some of these jokers, even your best friends, they'll come on to your station and round up the poddys and drive them off on to their own land, and then there's nothing to say they're yours. That's poddy-dodging, that is. It's a fair cow. Of course, there's always cattle crossing the boundaries because there aren't any fences, so it's a bit of a mix-up generally when you come to muster. But I've been on stations where there weren't hardly any poddys there at all when we come to muster. All the jokers on the other stations had got them.”

She said,“But do the poddys just stay on the new land? Don't they want to go back to mother?”

He glanced at her, appreciating the question.“That's right—they would if you let them. They'd go straight back to their own herd on their own land, even if it was fifty miles. But what these jokers do is this. They build a little corral on their land in some place where no one wouldn't ever think to look, and they drive your poddys into it. Then they leave them there for four or five days without food or water—don't give them nothing at all. Well, if you do that to a poddy he goes sort of silly and forgets about the herd, and mother. All he wants is a drink of water, same as you or I. Then you let him out and let him drink his fill at a waterhole. He's had such a thirst he won't leave that waterhole for months. He forgets all about his own place, and just stays in his new home.”

Her eyes closed, and she slept. When she woke up the sun was lower in the sky, and Joe had left her. She got up and sponged her face in the bathroom, and saw him outside working on the engine of the truck. She tidied herself up, looked at her watch, and went to investigate the kitchen.

Primitive was the word, she thought. There was a wood-burning hearth which mercifully was out, and a wick-burning oil stove; this was the cooking equipment. There was a small kerosene refrigerator. Masses of cooked meat were stored in a wire gauze meat safe with nearly as many flies inside it as there were outside. The utensils were old-fashioned and dirty and few in number; it was a nightmare of a kitchen. Jean felt that the right course would be to burn it down and start again, and she wondered if this could be done without burning down the house as well. There was little in the store cupboard but staple foods such as flour and salt and soap.

She put on the kettle to boil for tea and looked around for something to cook, other than meat. Eggs were plentiful at Midhurst and she found some stale cheese; she went and consulted Joe, and then came back and made him a cheese omelette with eight eggs. He cleaned his hands and came and watched her while she did it.“Oh my word,”he said.“Where did you learn cooking?”

“In Ealing,”she said, and it all seemed very far away: the grey skies, the big red buses, and the clamour of the Underground.“I had a sort of little kitchenette with an electric cooker. I always used to cook myself a two-course evening meal.”

He grinned awkwardly.“Afraid you won't find many electric cookers in the outback.”

She touched his hand.“I know that, Joe. But there are lots of things that could be done here to make it a bit easier.”As they ate their tea they talked about the kitchen and the house.“It's just the kitchen that needs altering,”she said.“The rest of it is lovely.”

“I'll get a toilet fixed up in the house before you come,”he promised her.“It's all right for me going out there, but it's not nice for you.”

She laughed.“I don't mind that, so long as you keep up the supplies of the Saturday Evening Post.”He grinned, but she found him set upon this alteration.“Some places have a septic tank and everything,”he said.“They put one in at Augustus when the Duke and Duchess stayed there. I reckon that we'll have to wait a while for that.”

They ate their tea out on the veranda as the sun went down, and sat looking out over the creek and the bush, smoking and talking quietly.“What are you doing next week?”she asked.“Will you be in town, Joe?”

He nodded.“I'll be in on Thursday, or Friday at the latest.“I'm going up to the top end tomorrow for a couple of days, just see what's going on.”

She smiled.“Looking after the poddys?”

He grinned.“That's right. It's a bit difficult this time of year, in the dry, because the tracks don't show so good. I got a boy called Nugget on the station now, and he's a bonza tracker, oh my word. I'm taking him up with me. I've got a kind of feeling that Don Curtis, up on Windermere station, he's been at my poddys.”

“What would you do if you found tracks, then, Joe? Tracks leading off your land and on to his?”

He grinned.“Go after 'em and find 'em and drive 'em back,”he said.“Hope Don doesn't come along while we're doing it.”

He drove her into Willstown at about nine o'clock that night; they halted for a while outside the town to say goodnight in proper style. She lay against his shoulder with his arm around her, listening to the noises of the bush, the croaking of the frogs, the sound of crickets, and the crying of a night bird.“It's a lovely place you live in, Joe,”she said.“It just wants a new kitchen, that's all. Don't ever worry about me not liking it.”

He kissed her.“It'll be all ready for you when you come.”

“April,”she said.“Early in April, Joe.”

She started up the shoe workshop in the first week of December, three or four days after Aggie Topp arrived. To start with she had five girls, Judy Small and her friend Lois Strang, and Annie, whose figure was beginning to deteriorate and who had been sacked from the hotel, and two fifteen-year-olds who had recently left school. For cleanliness and to mark the fact that they were working in a regular job she put everyone into a green overall coat in the workshop, and gave them a mirror on the wall so that they could see what they looked like.

From the first days she found that the fifteen-year-olds were the best employees. Girls straight from school were used to the discipline of regular hours of work; she seldom got the girls from outback homes to settle down to it so well as the younger ones. The monotony was irksome to the older girls who had left school for some years, or who had never been to school at all. She tried to help them by ordering an automatic changing gramophone from Cairns, with a supply of records; the music certainly intrigued and amused the whole of Willstown and may have helped the older girls a little, but not much. The big attraction of the workshop was the air-conditioner.

The air-conditioner was the best recruiting agent of the lot. In that torrid summer heat which ranged from between a hundred and a hundred and ten degrees at midday, she managed to keep the temperature of the workshop down to about seventy degrees, at which the girls could work without their hands sweating. For the girls it meant that they got respite from the heat of the day, and music to listen to, and the novelty of a clean green overall to wear, and money in their pockets at the end of the week. The workshop was popular from the first, and Jean never had any difficulty in getting as many recruits for it as she could handle. For the early months, however, she was content with five.

She spent a hectic fortnight after the workshop opened getting the ice-cream parlour furnished and stocked. She was resolved to have this open by Christmas Day, and she achieved her aim by opening on December 20th. On Joe's advice she only opened half of it at first, leaving the parlour for the Abos till it was established that they wanted ice-cream. This saved her the wages of a coloured girl and the expense of furnishing. In fact, it was not for nearly a year that the demand arose and Abo ringers started hanging round the kitchen door to buy an ice-cream soda. She opened the coloured annexe in the following September.

She stood with Joe outside in the blazing sunlit street on that first afternoon, looking at what she had done. The workshop and the ice-cream parlour stood more or less side by side on the main street. The windows of the workshop were closed to keep the cool air in, but they could hear the girls singing as they worked over the shoes. Christmas was near, and they were singing carols —“Holy Night”, and“Good King Wenceslas”, and“See Amid the Winter Snow”. The shirt was sticking to Jean's back and she shifted her shoulders to get a little air inside.“Well, there it all is,”she said.“Now we've got to see if we can make it pay.”

“Come on and I'll buy you a soda,”he said.“That'll help.”They went in and bought a soda from Rose Sawyer behind the counter.“This part of it'll pay,”he said.“I don't know about the shoes, but this should do all right. I was talking to George Connor up at the hotel. He's getting very worried about his bar, with you starting up.”

“I don't see why he's got anything to worry about,”she said.“I'm not going to sell beer.”

“You're going to sell drinks to ringers,”he remarked.“If you had a bar instead of this, wouldn't it rile you?”

She laughed.“I suppose it would. I can't see myself putting the bar out of business, Joe.”

“I can see you doing all right, all the same.”As they sat at the little chromium glass-topped table, Pete Fletcher came in shyly and sidled up to the bar and ordered an ice-cream, and began chatting with Rose Sawyer. Joe said,“Poor old George Connor.”They laughed together, and then he said,“I bet you don't keep Rose six months.”

Jean had seen a good deal of Rose Sawyer in the last month.“I'll take you,”she said.“Bet you a quid she's still there in a year from now, Joe.”They shook hands on it according to the custom of the place.“If she is,”he said,“it'll be a miracle.”

Now that the businesses were started, she was very tired; she felt slack and listless in the great heat, drained of all energy. She would have liked to go out with Joe to Midhurst that evening and live quietly there for a day or two, sleeping and riding and playing with the little wallaby. A cautionary instinct warned her not to offend against the rural code of morals by an indiscretion of that sort; if she was to make a success of what she had set out to do for women in that place her own behaviour would have to be above reproach. No mothers in the outback, she knew, would care to let their daughters work for her if it were known that she was spending nights alone at Midhurst with Joe Harman; no married man would care to bring his wife and daughters to an ice-cream parlour run by a loose woman of that sort.

It was a Wednesday, but Sunday was no longer an off day for Jean since it was likely to be the biggest day of all for the ice-cream and soft drinks. She arranged with Joe that he should call for her at the hotel soon after dawn and take her out to Midhurst for the day. She said goodbye to him and went to her room as soon as work stopped in the workshop, pausing only to see the girls from the workshop sampling the ice-cream parlour. She went and lay down on her bed, exhausted and too tired to eat that night; it was refreshingly cool in the workshop building, for the air-conditioner had been on all day. She took off her clothes and put on her pyjamas, and slept in the coolness; she slept so for twelve hours.

She had been out to Midhurst several times since that first visit and had fitted herself out with a small pair of ringer's trousers in Bill Duncan's store for riding, with a pair of elastic-sided ringer's riding boots to match. She met Joe in the early morning with a little bundle of riding things under her arm, and got into the utility with him. As usual they drove a little way out of town and stopped for an exchange of mutual esteem; as he held her he asked,“How are you feeling this morning?”

She smiled.“I'm better now, Joe. It was the reaction, I suppose—getting it finished and open. I went to bed just after leaving you and slept right through. Twelve solid hours. I'm feeling fine.”

“Take things very easy today,”he said.

She stroked his hair,“Dear Joe. It's going to be much easier from now on.”

“This bloody weather'll break soon,”he said.“We'll get rain starting within the week, and after that it'll begin to get cool.”

They drove on presently.“Joe,”she said,“I had an awful row this week with the bank manager— Mr Watkins. Did you hear about it?”

He grinned.“I did hear something,”he admitted.“What really happened?”

“It was the flies,”she said.“It was so hot on Friday, and I was so tired. I went into that miserable little bank to cash the wages cheque and you know how full of flies it always is. I had to wait a few minutes and the flies started crawling all over me, in my hair and in my mouth and in my eyes. I was sweating, I suppose. I lost my temper, Joe. I oughtn't to have done that.”

“It's a crook place, that bank is,”he observed.“There's no reason why it should have all those flies. What did you say?”

“Everything,”she said simply.“I told him I was closing my account because I couldn't stand his bloody flies. I said I was going to bank in Cairns and get the cash in by Dakota every week. I said I was going to write to his head office in Sydney and tell them why I'd done it, and I said I was going to write to the Bank of New South Wales and offer my account to them if they'd start up a branch here with no flies. I said I used a DDT spray and I didn't get flies in my workshop and I wasn't going to have them in my bank. I said he ought to be setting an example to Willstown instead of...”She stopped.

“Instead of what?”he asked.

She said weakly,“I forgot what I did say.”

He stared straight ahead at the track.“I did hear in the bar you told him he ought to set an example instead of sitting on his arse and scratching.”

“Oh, Joe, I couldn't have said that!”

He grinned.“That's what they're saying that you told him, in Willstown.”

“Oh...”They drove on in silence for a time.“I'll go in on Friday and apologize,”she said.“It's no good making quarrels in a place like this.”

“I don't see why you should apologize,”he objected.“It's up to him to apologize to you. After all, you're the customer.”He paused.“I'd go in there on Friday and see how he's getting on,”he advised.“I know he got ten gallons of DDT spray on Saturday, because Al Burns told me.”

When they got to Midhurst he made her go at once and sit in a long chair at the corner of the veranda with a glass of lemon squash made with cold water from the refrigerator. He would not let her move for breakfast, but brought her a cup of tea and a boiled egg and some bread and butter on a tray. She sat there, relaxed, with the fatigue soaking out of her, content to have him gently fussing over her. When the day grew hot he suggested that she took the spare bedroom and lay down upon the bed leaving the double doors open at each end of the room to get the draught through; he promised, grinning, not to look if he passed along the veranda. She took him at his word and took off most of her clothes in the spare room and lay down on the bed and slept through the midday heat.

When she woke up it was nearly four o'clock and she was cool and rested and at ease. She lay for a while wondering if he had looked; then she got up and slipped her frock on and went to the shower, and stood for a long time under the warm stream of water. She came to him presently on the veranda, fresh and rested and full of fondness for him in his generosity, and found him squatting on the floor mending a bridle with palm, needle, and waxed thread. She stooped and kissed him, and said,“Thanks for everything, Joe. I had a lovely sleep.”And then she said,“Can we go riding after tea?”

“Still a bit hot,”he said.“Think that's a good thing?”

“I'd like to,”she said.“I want to be able to sit on a horse properly.”

He said,“You did all right last time.”She had been promoted from the fourteen-year-old Auntie to the more energetic Sally and she was gradually learning how to trot. She found that trotting in that climate made her sweat more than the horse and made it difficult for her to sit down next day, but the exercise, she knew, was good for her. Starting at her age, she would never be a very good rider, but she was determined to achieve the ability to do it as a means of locomotion in that country.

They rode for an hour and a half that evening, coming back to Midhurst in the early dusk. He would not let her stay out longer than that, though she wanted to.“I'm not a bit tired now,”she said.“I believe I'm getting the hang of this, Joe. It's much easier on Sally than it was on Auntie.”

“Aye,”he said.“The better the horse the less tiring for the rider, long as you can manage him.”

“I'd like to come with you one day up to the top end,”she said.“I suppose it'll have to be after we're married.”

He grinned.“Plenty of wowsers back in Willstown to talk about it, if you came before.”

“Do I ride well enough for that?”

“Oh, aye,”he said.“Take it easy and you'ld get along all right on Sally. I never travel more than twenty miles in the day, not unless there's some special reason.”

He drove her into Willstown in the utility, and as they kissed goodnight he said that he would be in during the following week. She went to bed that night rested and content, refreshed by her quiet day.

She went to the bank on Friday and cashed the wages cheque as usual; she found that the walls were in the process of being distempered and there was not a fly in the place. Mr Watkins was distant in his manner and ignored her; Len James, the young bank clerk, gave her her money with a broad grin and a wink. She saw Len again on Saturday afternoon, when he brought in Doris Nash for an ice-cream soda. He grinned at her, and said,“You wouldn't know the bank, Miss Paget.”

“I was in there yesterday,”she said.“You're having it all distempered.”

“That's right,”he said.“You started something.”

“Is he very sore?”she asked.

“Not really,”the boy said.“He's been wanting to decorate for a long tune, but he's been scared of what the head office would say. There's not a lot of turnover in a place like this, you know. Well, now he's doing it.”

“I'm sorry I was rude,”she said.“If you get a chance, tell him I said that.”

“I will,”he promised her.“I'm glad you were. Haven't had such a laugh for years. I don't like flies, either.”

On the first Sunday she worked steadily in the ice-cream parlour with Rose Sawyer from nine in the morning till ten o'clock at night. They sold a hundred and eighty-two ice-creams at a shilling each and three hundred and forty-one soft drinks at sixpence. Dead tired, Jean counted the money in the till at the end of the day.“Seventeen pounds thirteen shillings,”she said. She stared at Rose in wonder.“That doesn't seem so bad for a town with a hundred and forty-six people, all told. How much is that a head?”

“About two and six, isn't it?”

“Do you think it's going to go on like this?”

“I don't see why not. Lots of people didn't come in today. Most of them come in two or three times. Judy must have had about ten bob's worth.”

“She can't keep that up,”Jean said.“She'll be sick, and we'll get a recession. Come on and let's go to bed.”

She opened the ice-cream parlour after lunch on Christmas Day and took twenty pounds in the afternoon and evening. She had the gramophone from the workshop in the parlour that evening playing dance music so that the little wooden shack that was her ice-cream parlour streamed out music and light into the dark wastes of the main street, and seemed to the inhabitants just like a bit of Manly Beach dropped down in Willstown. Old, withered women that Jean had never seen before came in that night with equally old men to have an ice-cream soda, drawn by the lights and by the music. Although the parlour was still full of people she closed punctually at ten o'clock, thinking it better as a start to stick to the bar closing time and not introduce the complication of late hours and night life into a rural community.

The workshop went fairly steadily under Aggie Topp and they despatched two packing-cases of shoes to Forsayth just after Christmas to be sent by rail to Brisbane and by ship to England. She had already sent a few early samples of their work to Pack and Levy by air mail.

On Boxing Day the rain came. They had had one or two short showers before, but that day the clouds massed high in great peaks of cumulonimbus that spread and covered the whole sky so that it grew dark. Then down it came, a steady, vertical torrent of rain that went on and on, unending. At first the conditions became worse, with no less heat and very high humidity; in the workshops the girls sweated freely even at seventy degrees, and Aggie Topp had to postpone the finishing operations and concentrate on the earlier, less delicate stages of the manufacture of shoes.

Jean went with Joe to Midhurst for a day soon after the New Year; as usual he called for her just after dawn. This time it was a grey dawn of hot, streaming rain; she scuttled quickly from the door of her room into the cab of the utility. By that time she was getting used to being wet through to the skin, and drying, and getting wet again; the water as it fell was nearly blood temperature and the chance of a chill was slight. She said as she got into the car,“What are the creeks like, Joe?”

“Coming up,”he said.“Nothing to worry over yet.”A time would come when for a few weeks he would be unable to reach Willstown from Midhurst in the utility, and would have to ride in if they were to meet at all. He had been stocking up with foodstuffs for the homestead in the last week or two.

There were two creeks between Willstown and Midhurst, wide bottoms of sand and boulders that she knew as hot, arid places in the dry. Now they were wide streams of yellow, muddy water, rather terrifying to her. At the first one she said,“Can we get through that, Joe?”

“That's all right,”he said.“It's only a foot deep. You see that tree there with the overhanging branch? When that branch gets covered, at the fork, it's a bit deep then.”

They drove the utility ploughing through the water and emerged the other side; they forded the second creek in the same way, leaping from boulder to boulder, and went on to Midhurst. They got there as usual in time for breakfast. It was still streaming rain down in a steady torrent, too wet for any outdoor activity. They set to work after breakfast to plan out the new kitchen and the toilet he had set his heart on.

In Cairns that morning, four hundred miles to the west of them, Miss Jacqueline Bacon tripped delicately down the pavement in the rain from her home to the Cairns Ambulance and Fire Station. She wore a blue raincoat and she carried an umbrella. She hurried in between the fire engines, and shook the rain from her umbrella. She said to one of the firemen on duty,“My, isn't it wet?”

He sucked his empty pipe and stared out at the rain.“Fine weather for ducks.”

She went into her little office off the main hall where the gleaming fire engines stood and glanced at the clock; she had still three minutes to go. The room was furnished with a table and with a microphone and a writing-pad, and two tall metal cabinets of wireless gear; a set stood on the table before her pad. She turned three switches for the apparatus to warm up and took off her wet coat and her hat. Then she found her pencil and drew the pad to her, and a card with a long list of call signs and stations on it. She sat down and began her daily work.

She turned a switch on the face of the cabinet before her and said,“Eight Baker Tare, Eight Baker Tare, this is Eight Queen Charlie calling Eight Baker Tare. Eight Baker Tare, Eight Baker Tare, this is Eight Queen Charlie calling Eight Baker Tare. Eight Baker Tare, if you are receiving Eight Queen Charlie will you please come in. Over to you. Over.”She turned the switch.

From the speaker in the set before her came a woman's voice.“Eight Queen Charlie, Eight Queen Charlie, this is Eight Baker Tare. Can you hear me, Jackie?”

Miss Bacon turned the switch and said,“Eight Baker Tare, this is Eight Queen Charlie. I'm receiving you quite well, about strength four. What's the weather like with you, Mrs Corbett? Over to you. Over.”

“Oh my dear,”the loudspeaker said,“it's coming down in torrents here. We're having a lovely rain; Jim says we've really got it at last. I do believe it's getting cooler already. Over to you.”

“Eight Baker Tare,”said Miss Bacon,“this is Eight Queen Charlie. We're having a lovely rain here, too. I have nothing for you, Mrs Corbett, but if you should have anybody going into Georgetown will you pass word to Mrs Cutter that her son Ronnie came up on the train from Mackay last night and he's coming on by train to Forsayth. He'll be there on Thursday morning, so he should be home on Thursday night. Is this Roger, Mrs Corbett? Over to you. Over.”

The loudspeaker said,“That's Roger, Jackie. One of the boys or Jim will be in Georgetown later on today, and I'll see Mrs Cutter gets that message. Over.”

“Eight Baker Tare,”said Miss Bacon,“this is Eight Queen Charlie. Roger, Mrs Corbett. I must sign off now. Listening out. Eight Easy Victor, Eight Easy Victor, this is Eight Queen Charlie calling Eight Easy Victor. Eight Easy Victor, this is Eight Queen Charlie calling Eight Easy Victor. If you are receiving me, Mrs Marshall, will you please come in. Over to you. Over.”

There was silence. Miss Bacon went on calling Eight Easy Victor for a minute, but Mrs Marshall, she knew, was in the habit of feeding the hens at the time of the morning schedule and more usually came in in the evening. She made her statutory number of calls and went on to the next.“Eight Nan How, this is Eight Queen Charlie,”and repeated herself.“If you are receiving me, Eight Nan How, will you please come in. Over to you. Over.”

A man's voice said,“Eight Queen Charlie, this is Eight Nan How. Over.”

Miss Bacon said,“Eight Nan How, this is Eight Queen Charlie. I have a telegram for you, Mr Gosling. Have you got a pencil and paper? I can wait just one minute. Only one minute, mind. Call me when you're ready. Over.”

She waited till he called her back, and then said,“Eight Nan How, this is Eight Queen Charlie. Your telegram is from Townsville and it reads Molly had son seven last night eight pounds four ounces both doing fine. And the signature is, Bert. Have you got that, Mr Gosling? Over to you. Over.”

The speaker said,“I got that. It's another boy. Over.”

Miss Bacon said,“I am so glad it's all gone off all right. Give Molly my love when you write, won't you, Mr Gosling? Have you got anything else for me? Over.”

The speaker said,“I'll think out a reply to this, Jackie, and give it to you on the evening schedule. Over to you. Over.”

She said,“Okay, Mr Gosling, I'll take it then. Now I must sign off from you. Eight Item Yoke, Eight Item Yoke, this is Eight Queen Charlie calling Eight Item Yoke.”She went on with her work.

Twenty minutes later she was still at it.“Eight Able George, Eight Able George, this is Eight Queen Charlie calling Eight Able George. Eight Able George, if you are receiving Eight Queen Charlie will you come in now. Over.”

The answer came in a sobbing torrent of words, rather impeded by the static of three hundred miles.“Oh, Jackie. I'm so glad you've come. We're in such trouble here. Don's horse came back last night. I heard the horse come in about two o'clock in the morning and I thought, that's funny, because Don never travels at night because of the trees, you know. And then I thought, that's funny, because there was only one horse and he had Samson with him so I got up to look and I couldn't see the horse, my dear, so I got a torch and put my coat on and went out in the rain and, my dear, there it was, Don's horse, Jubilee, saddled and everything and Don wasn't there, and I'm so frightened.”The voice dissolved into a torrent of sobs.

Miss Bacon sat motionless before the microphone, one hand on the transmitter switch, listening to the carrier wave and the low sobbing at the other end, clearly distinguishable through the static. There was nothing to be done until Helen Curtis recovered herself and remembered to switch over to Receive. She glanced quickly at the list before her; she hesitated, and then left her chair and opened the door and called to the fireman on duty,“Fred, ring up Mr Barnes and ask him to come down if he can. Something's happened at Windermere.”

She went back to her chair, and now a heterodyne squeal shrilled out, drowning the sobbing as some sympathetic, foolish woman came in on the same wave saying something unintelligible. She sat patiently waiting for the air to clear; until they remembered their routines she could do nothing for them. The heterodyne stopped and Helen Curtis was still sobbing at the microphone three hundred miles away, beneath the coloured picture of the King and Queen in coronation robes and the picture of their daughter's wedding group that stood upon the set. Then she said,“Jackie, Jackie, are you there? Oh, I forgot. Over.”

Miss Bacon turned her switch and said,“All right, Helen, this is Jackie here. Look, everybody, this is Eight Queen Charlie talking to Eight Able George. Will everybody please keep off the air and not transmit. You can stay listening in, but not transmit. I'll call you if you can do anything. Mrs Curtis, I've sent Fred to telephone to Mr Barnes to get him to come down. Now sit down quietly and tell me what happened and I'll take it down. Remember your routine and switch over when you want me to answer. It's going to be all right, Helen. Just tell me quietly what happened. Over to you. Over.”

The speaker said,“Oh, Jackie, it is good to hear you. I've got nobody here except the boongs. Dave's on holiday and Pete's in Normanton. What happened was this. Don went up to the Disappointment Creek part of the station three days ago and he took Samson with him and he said he'd be away two days. I wasn't worried when they didn't get back because of the rain, you know, and I thought they'd have to go around because the creeks would be up. And then last night Don's horse came back alone, and no sign of Samson. Samson's our new Abo stockrider. I've got a very good tracker here called Johnnie Walker, and Johnnie went out at dawn to track the horse back. But he came back an hour ago and it wasn't any good because the rain had washed the tracks out; he could only follow it about three miles and then he lost it, and now I don't know what to do.”There was a pause, and then she said,“Oh, over.”

Miss Bacon's pad was covered with rough notes. She turned her switch and said,“This is Jackie, Helen. Tell me, what stations are north and south of you? Over.”

“It's Carlisle, north of us, Jackie—that's Eddie Page. It's Midhurst to the south, and Pelican to the east. Midhurst is Joe Harman and Pelican Len Driver. I don't think Midhurst's got a radio, though. Over.”

Miss Bacon said,“All right Helen, I'll call some of them. Stay listening in, because Mr Barnes will want to speak to you when he comes. Now I'm going over to Carlisle. I have telegrams for Eight Dog Sugar and for Eight Jig William, and I will give them as soon as I'm free. Eight Charlie Peter, Eight Charlie Peter, this is Eight Queen Charlie. If you are receiving me, Eight Charlie Peter, will you come in. Over.”

She turned her switch and heard the measured tones of Eddie Page, and sighed with relief.“Eight Queen Charlie, this is Eight Charlie Peter. I heard all that Jackie. I've got Fred Dawson here, and we'll go down to Windermere soon as we can. Tell Helen we'll be with her in about four hours and see what we can do. Will you be keeping a listening watch? Over.”

She said,“That's fine, Mr Page. We shall be on watch here till this is squared up listening every hour, from the hour till ten minutes past the hour. Is this Roger? Over.”

He said,“Okay Jackie, that's Roger. I'll sign off now and go and saddle up. You won't be able to raise me any more; Olive can't work it. Out.”

She called Pelican next, but got no answer, so she called Eight Love Mike, the Willstown Mounted Police Station, and got Sergeant Haines at once. He said,“Okay Jackie, I've heard all of that. I'm sending Phil Duncan and one of my trackers, and we'll see if any of the boys can come along. I'll see that someone goes round by Midhurst and tells Joe Harman. Tell Mr Barnes that Constable Duncan will be at Windermere about three or four this afternoon. Your listening watch is Roger. Good girl, Jackie. Out.”

Drama or no drama, the day's work still remained to be done. Miss Bacon said,“Eight Dog Sugar, this is Eight Queen Charlie calling Eight Dog Sugar. I have a telegram for Eight Dog Sugar. If you are receiving Eight Queen Charlie will you please come in. Over.”She went on with her work.

At Midhurst Jean was measuring up the kitchen with Joe Harman and making a plan on a writing-pad, when they heard a horse approaching about noon. It was still raining, though less fiercely than before. They went to the other side of the house and saw Pete Fletcher handing his horse over to Moonshine; he came up to the veranda. He was wearing his broad ringer's hat and he was soaked to the skin; his boots squelched as he climbed the steps.

He said,“Did you hear the radio?”

“No. What's that?”

“Some kind of trouble up on Windermere,”the boy said.“Don Curtis went up with an Abo ringer to the top end of his station three days ago. Now the horse is back without him.”

“Tracked the horse back?”Joe asked at once.

“Tried that, but it didn't work. Tracks all washed out.”The boy sat down on the edge of the veranda and began taking off his boots to tip the water out of them; a little pool formed round him.“Jackie Bacon, the girl on the Cairns radio, she got the news on the morning schedule. She called Sergeant Haines, and he sent Phil Duncan to Windermere. Phil's on his way there now, with Al Burns. I said I'd come round this way and tell you. Eddie Page is on his way to Windermere from Carlisle, with Fred Dawson.”

Joe asked,“Who was the Abo ringer he had with him?”

“Chap called Samson from the Mitchell River. He's been with Don about a month.”

“Do they know where on the station he was going to?”

“Up by Disappointment Creek.”

“For Christ's sake,”Joe said.“Then I know what he's been up to.”Jean, looking at him, saw his mouth set in a hard line.

“What's that?”asked Pete.

“He's been at my poddys again,”said Joe.“The mugger's got a poddy corral up there.”

“How do you know that?”asked Pete.

“Found the sod,”said Joe.“I'll tell you where it is. You know where Disappointment Creek runs into the Fish River?”The boy nodded.“Well, from there you go up Disappointment Creek about four miles and you'll come to an island and a little bit of a creek running in from the north just by it. Well, go on past that about a mile and you'll see a lot of thick bush north of the creek with a little bare hill behind. You can't mistake it. The poddy corral's round the back of the thick bush, just under the bare hill. If you get up on that hill—it's only about fifty feet high—you'll see the poddy corral to the south of you.”He paused.“If you're going on a search party I'd start off with that.”

“Thanks, Joe,”Pete said.“I'll tell them at Windermere.”

“Aye, you'd better. I don't suppose Mrs Curtis knows anything about it.”

Jean had been hesitant to break in on a discussion about things that she knew nothing of, but now she said,“How did you get to know about it, Joe?”

He turned to her.“I was up at the top end just after Christmas with Bourneville, and I thought poddys were a bit scarcer than they ought to be. So then Bourneville got to tracking and the rain hadn't hardly begun then, so it was easy. The Cartwright River makes the station boundary just there, and we followed the tracks across and on to Windermere. Two horses there were, with a lot of poddys. We found the corral like I said, and there they were; been there two or three days. I let 'em out, of course, and drove them back. Had a cow of a job to get them past the first water, oh my word.”

Pete asked,“How many were there, Joe?”

“Forty-seven.”

“All cleanskins?”

“Oh yes.”Joe was rather shocked at the implied suggestion.

“Don wouldn't go and do a thing like that,”he said.

The boy put on his boots and got up.“What'll you do, Joe? Come along with me?”

“I don't think so,”Joe replied slowly.“I think I'll get up to the top end of my station, where he got those poddys from. Maybe he's been after some more, and had his accident up there. That's south of the Cartwright River, and east of the new bore we made. If I can't see any trace of him on my land, then I'll follow the way he drove those poddys to his corral. Maybe I'll meet you around there somewhere tomorrow or the next day.”

Pete nodded.“I'll tell Phil.”

“Tell him I'll be taking Bourneville with me, and I'll start as soon as I've run Miss Paget here back into town in the utility.”

Forty miles in the utility in those wet conditions would take the best part of three hours. Jean said,“Joe, don't bother about me. I'll stay here till you come back. You get off at once.”

He hesitated.“I may be away for days.”

“Well then, I'll ride into town on Sally. One of the boongs can come with me and bring Sally back.”

“You could do that,”he said slowly.“Moonshine will be here, and he could go with you. I'll be taking Bourneville along with me.”

“Well then,”she said,“that's perfectly all right. What time's Dave coming back?”

“Should be back this afternoon,”he said. He turned to Pete.“I've got Jim Lennon on holiday, and Dave's off visiting a girl, one of the nurses down at Normanton. But he'll be back today.”

Jean said,“I'll stay here till Dave comes, in case anything crops up, Joe.”

He smiled at her.“Well, that would be a help. I don't like leaving the place with just the boongs. I'll tell Moonshine he's to take you into town any time you want to go. He turned to Pete.“Want another horse?”

“I don't think so. 'Bout thirty miles to Windermere from here?”

“That's right. Cross over the river here, you know, and you'll find a track that leads there all the way. It's not been used much lately. If you miss it, go north to the Gilbert and follow up a mile or two and you'll find a little hut Jeff Pocock uses when he's hunting 'gators. There's a shallow about two miles up from that where you can get across. Go north from there about ten miles and you'll find their track from the homestead to Willstown. You can't mistake that.”

“Okay.”

“What about some tucker?”

The boy shook his head.“Think I'll get on my way.”

They went down into the yard and saw him saddle up and ride away. The rain had practically stopped, but the clouds were heavy and black overhead. Joe turned to her.“Sorry about this,”he said quietly.“It's spoilt our day. You're sure you don't mind riding in with Moonshine?”

“Of course not,”she said.“You must get away at once.”

She hurried in to galvanize Palmolive to prepare some lunch and food for them to take with them; down in the yard the men were saddling up. They took their riding horses and one packhorse with them, loaded with a tent and camping gear. She was distressed at the meagre quantity and poor quality of the food Joe seemed to think it necessary to take with them. He took a hunk of horrible black, overcooked meat out of the meat safe and dropped it into a sack with three loaves of bread; he took a couple of handfuls of tea in an old cocoa tin and a couple of handfuls of sugar in another. That was the whole of his provision for a journey of indefinite length. She did not interfere, seeing that he was absorbed in his preparations and not wanting to fuss him, but she stored up the knowledge for her future information.

He kissed her goodbye on the veranda and she went down with him to the yard.“Look after yourself, Joe,”she said.

He grinned.“See you in Willstown next week.”Then he was trotting out of the gate with Bourneville by his side and the packhorse behind on a lead, and she was left alone at Midhurst with the boongs.

It began to rain again, and she went up into the veranda. It was very quiet and empty now that Joe was gone, and Palmolive had retired to her own place. The rain made a steady drumming on the iron roof. It occurred to her that the whole business might be over. Don Curtis might have turned up at Windermere and Joe's journey might be so much wasted effort. It was absurd that Midhurst had not got a radio transmitter. It was true enough that they were only twenty miles from the hospital and so would hardly need it for their own accidents, but in a case like this it was both difficult and trying not to know what was going on. She made up her mind to have a transmitter at Midhurst when they were married. A cattle station without one in these days was a back number.

She had never been alone in Midhurst before. She wandered through from room to room, slowly, deep in thought, and the wallaby lolloped after her; from time to time she dropped her hand to caress it, and it nibbled her fingers. She spent a long time in his room, touching and fingering the rough gear and clothes that were essentially Joe. He had so few things. Yet it was in this room he had dreamed and planned that fantastic journey to England in search of her, that journey that had ended in Noel Strachan's office in Chancery Lane. Chancery Lane seemed very far away.

At about three o'clock Dave Hope arrived. He came riding from Willstown through the rain as Pete Fletcher had come in the morning; he had got a lift up on a truck from Normanton. He had heard all about the Windermere affair in Willstown, which he had left shortly before noon, and he could add further information from the radio. He told her that the Abo ringer, Samson, had returned to the homestead.

“Seems they were looking for some poddys,”he said,“somewhere up at the Disappointment Creek end of the station. They separated and one went one way, one the other, for some reason; they left the camp standing and were going to meet back in the evening. Don didn't turn up that evening and of course the Abo couldn't track him in the dark. When the morning came the whole place was swimming in water, and he couldn't track him at all. That's how it seems to be.”

They talked about it for some time on the veranda. Somewhere thirty or forty miles from them a man must be lying injured on the ground; he might be anywhere within a circle thirty miles in diameter. He might be lying under a bush and very probably by that time he would be unconscious; looking for him would be like looking for a needle in a bundle of hay.

“You'd better go and help, Dave,”Jean said at last.“There's nothing to do here. I'll stay here and look after things.”

He was a little doubtful.“What did Mr Harman say I was to do?”

“He didn't say anything. I said I'd stay here till you got back. He doesn't want the station left without anyone at all, except the boongs. I'll stay here Dave, till somebody else comes. You go and join them over at Windermere. That's the best thing you can do.”

“It certainly seems crook to stay here doing nothing,”he admitted.

She got him off in the late afternoon with about two hours of daylight left. He knew Windermere station well, and was quite happy about finishing his journey in the dark. Left to herself, Jean went on with the plan of the kitchen she would have liked to see built, with a view to getting Joe to pull the old one down completely and start again from scratch. Presently Palmolive came in and cooked eggs for her tea, and fed the various animals, and watered the veranda plants.

When Palmolive had gone away, she was alone in Midhurst for the night, with only the puppies and the wallaby for company. Somewhere out in the darkness and the rain Joe Harman would be pushing on towards the top end of the property, horses and men soaked through, picking their way cautiously through the darkness. She could do nothing to help them, nothing but sit and wait.

She learned a lot that evening. She learned a little of the fortitude that a wife on a cattle station must develop, even, she thought a little grimly, a wife with fifty-three thousand pounds. She learned that a radio transmitting and receiving set was almost indispensable to such a wife; even on that first evening she would have liked to exchange a word or two with Jackie Bacon in Cairns. She learned how much a lonely person turns to animals, and queerly the memory of Olive came into her mind, the brown Abo girl who could not bear to be separated from her kitten even on a visit to the Willstown hotel. By the time she went to bed she understood Olive a bit better.

She went to bed at about nine. There were one or two old British and American magazines about the place, tattered, much read stories about a different world. She took one of these and tried to read it in bed, but the fiction failed to satisfy her or to quell her anxieties. The rain stopped, and started, and then stopped again, and presently she slept.

She slept lightly and woke many times, and dozed again. She woke before dawn to the sound of a horse in the yard. She got up at once and put her frock on and went out on the veranda, and switched on the light, and called,“Who's that?”

A man came forward into the light at the foot of the steps, and said,“It's me, Missy, Bourneville. Missa Hope, him come back?”

He spoke with a thick accent; she could not understand what he was saying. She said,“Come up here, Bourneville. What is it?”

He came up to her in the veranda. He was a man of about fifty years of age, very black, with a seamed, wrinkled face and greying hair. He said again,“Missa Hope, him come back?”

She understood this time.“He's gone over to Windermere. He came back here, and went on to Windermere. What's happened to Mr Harman, Bourneville?”

He said,“Missa Harman, him up top end. Him find Missa Curtis, him leg broken. Missa Harman, him send me back fetch Missa Hope, him drive utility up top end, bring Missa Curtis down.”

She was angry with herself that she could not fully understand what he was saying. The fault lay within herself; a woman of the Gulf country would understand this man at once, and it was terribly important that she should understand. She said quietly,“I'm sorry, Bourneville. Say that again slowly.”

She got it at the second repetition.“Mr Hope's not here,”she said.“He's gone to Windermere.”

He was silent for a time. Then he said,“No white feller here, drive utility?”

She shook her head.“Can you drive the utility, Bourneville?”

“No, Missy.”

“Can any of the other Abos drive the utility?”

“No, Missy.”

The thought came to her that she could drive it up to them herself, with Bourneville as a guide, but it was not a thing to be undertaken lightly. She had never owned a car, and though she had driven cars belonging to various young men from time to time and knew the movements, her total driving experience did not exceed five hours. Again, she was angry and humiliated by her own incompetence.

She lit a cigarette and thought deeply. It would benefit nobody if she attempted to drive the utility and crashed it. It was a very big vehicle, larger than any ordinary car and much bigger than anything she had ever driven before. The alternative would be to send Bourneville riding on to Willstown, perhaps to the police station; they would send a truck or a utility out with a driver who would go on to the top end. The return journey to Willstown was forty miles. It would mean at least six hours delay before the truck could arrive at Midhurst ready to start for the top end.

She asked,“How far away is Mr Harman, Bourneville?”

He thought.“Four mile past bore.”

Joe had once told her that the new bore was twenty-two miles from the homestead; that made the scene of the accident twenty-six miles away. She said,“What's the track like? Can the utility get there?”

“Him bonza track in dry far as bore,”he said. She nodded; this was likely enough because the bore had only been made a few months and there must have been trucks going up to it. It would probably be possible to get along it even in this rain. Already the sky was getting grey; full daylight was not far away.

She asked,“Are there any creeks to cross?”

He held up three fingers.“Tree.”

“Are they deep? Can the utility go through?”

“Yes, Missy. Creeks not too deep.”

If Bourneville rode a horse beside the utility to guide her, she thought that she could make it. It was worth trying, anyway; the worst that could happen would be that she would get it stuck and have to send Bourneville back to Willstown with a note for them to send up somebody more competent. So long as he had his horse there was no risk of any great delay. She said,“All right, Bourneville, I'll drive the utility. You come up with me on your horse.”

“Get fresh horse, Missy. Him tired.”

“All right, get a fresh horse.”Bourneville must be tired too, but she was too unaccustomed to these seamed black faces to be able to detect fatigue.“You get some tucker,”she said.“I get tucker, too. We'll start in half an hour.”

He went off and she put the kettle on for a cup of tea and then went and changed into her riding shirt and breeches. There was an old tin truck in Joe's room which she had discovered the night before; it was half full of bandages and splints and various medicines. Being of tin, she thought, it would be waterproof, and she filled it up with blankets and some tins of food from the store cupboard, and a small sack of flour. That was all she could think of for provision in case she got stuck halfway and had to spend a night or two in the utility.

She had a cup of tea and a small meal of meat and bread and jam; then she went down to the yard and examined the utility. The huge petrol tank had twenty gallons in it, and the sump was full of oil. She filled the radiator from the water-butt and filled the waterbag suspended from the lamp bracket. Then she sat in it; to her relief the gears were clearly marked. She switched it on and pressed the starter and jiggeted the accelerator, and was both alarmed and pleased when the engine started. Very gingerly she put it in reverse and drove it out into the yard.

They put the trunk into the back and started off, Bourneville riding ahead of her to show her the way. Partly because of Bourneville on his horse and partly because she thoroughly distrusted her own competence, she never got it into top gear all the way, and never exceeded ten miles an hour. She drove through each of the three creeks along the line that Bourneville showed her, following the agitated, plunging horse as he forced through the yellow water swirling about its legs. Once the water rose above the floorboards of the cab and she was very frightened. But she kept the utility going and the designer had anticipated such usage and had placed the ignition system above the cylinders, and it came through bounding from rock to rock with water pouring out of every hole and cranny.

Four miles beyond the bore Joe Harman sat at the mouth of his small tent. It was pitched in a clearing in a thick patch of bush in the bottom of a little valley. A heavy log stockade or corral had been built in this clearing and stood immediately behind the tent; the movable logs that formed a gate had been pulled down and the corral was empty. Joe had built a fire before the tent, and he was boiling up in a billy over it.

A man lay inside upon a bed of brushwood covered with a waterproof sheet, with a blanket over him. Joe turned his head, and said,“What happened, Don? Did they rush you when you got the pole down?”

From the tent the man said,“My bloody oath. They pushed the pole back on to me and knocked me down. Then about six of them ran over me.”

Joe said,“Serve you bloody well right. Teach you to go muggering about on other people's land.”

There was a pause. Then he said,“How many of mine did you get last year, Don?”

“'Bout three hundred.”

Mr Harman laughed.“I got three hundred and fifty of yours.”

From the tent Mr Curtis said a very rude word.

Chapter 10

Jean drove the utility slowly up to the tent with Bourneville riding beside her; she took out the gear and stopped it with a sigh of relief. Joe came to her as she sat there.“What's happened to Dave?”he asked.“Didn't he come back?”

She told him what had happened.“I thought I'd better have a go at driving it up myself,”she said.“I've only driven a car about three times before. I don't think I've done it any good, Joe.”

He stepped back.“Looks all right,”he said.“Did you hit anything?”

“I didn't hit anything. I couldn't get the gears in sometimes and it made an awful noise.”

“Do they still work?”

“Oh, I think so.”

“That's all right, then. What were the creeks like?”

“Pretty high,”she said.“It came over the floor of the cab.”

He grunted.“Get along back as soon as we can. I wish this bloody rain 'ld stop.”

She asked,“Is Mr Curtis here, Joe?”

He nodded.“In the tent.”

“What's wrong?”

“Got his leg bust,”he said.“Compound fracture—that's what you call it when the bone's sticking out, isn't it? I think he's got a broken ankle, too.”

She pursed her lips.“I brought up that trunk with your splints and things.”

He asked,“Do you know about breaks? Ever been a nurse or anything like that?”

She shook her head.“I've not.”

“I've had a look at it and washed it,”he said.“I set it well as I could, but it's a mess. I made a sort of long splint this morning and tied it all down on that. We'll get him down to hospital, soon as we can. It's been done two days.”

They set to work to strike camp. They removed the tent from over the injured man and he saw Jean for the first time.“Hullo, Miss Paget,”he said.“You don't remember me. I saw you in Willstown, day you arrived.”

She smiled at him.“You'll be back there in a little while. In the hospital.”

Once as she worked she turned to Joe with a puzzled expression.“Whose land are we on, Joe?”

“Midhurst,”he said.“Why?”

She glanced at the corral.“What's that for?”

“That?”he said.“Oh, that's just a place we put the cattle in sometimes, for branding and that.”

She said no more, but went on with her work; once or twice a little smile played round her lips. They worked a blanket underneath the brushwood bed as the man lay upon the ground, and lowered the tailboard of the utility; then, with infinite care and great labour they lifted him on his bed into the body of the truck. The man was white and sweating when they had done and a little blood was showing on his lip where he had bitten it, but there was nothing else that they could do to ease his pain.

They started off at about nine o'clock, Joe driving the utility, Jean riding in the back with the injured man, and Bourneville following behind, riding and leading the two horses. They passed the bore and went on for about five miles till they came to the creeks. The water was considerably higher than when Jean had crossed a couple of hours earlier.

They crossed the first without difficulty, though the water was in the cab of the utility and only just below the floor of the truck body on which the sick man lay. They came through that one and went on. At the second creek the water was higher. Joe stopped on the edge and consulted with Jean and Bourneville about the crossing they had made before. It seemed shallower fifty yards above the point where Jean had crossed; Joe sent Bourneville into the water on his horse to sound the crossing. It looked good enough, so he drove the utility into the water.

It grew deep quickly, and he accelerated to keep her going. The bottom, under the swirling yellow flood, was very rough; the big car went forward leaping from boulder to boulder under the water. Then she came down heavily on something with a crunch of metal, and stopped dead.

Joe said,“Jesus,”and pressed the starter, but the engine was immovable. Oil began to appear on the eddying yellow surface of the water, and slide away downstream in black and yellow tails. He stared at it in consternation.

Jean said,“What's happened, Joe?”

“I've cracked the bloody sump,”he said shortly.

He got down into the water from the cab, feeling his way gingerly; it was well above his knees, close on waist deep. He called Bourneville and made Jean pass him a coil of rope from the back of the truck. The utility was only about ten yards from the bank. They made a sort of tandem harness for the three horses with lariats that they carried at the pommel of the riding saddles, and harnessed this team to the back axle of the utility, groping and spluttering under the water to do so. In ten minutes the vehicle was on dry land; a performance that left Jean awed by its efficiency.

She got down from the back and went to Joe, who was lying on his back under the front axle. She stooped down with him to look; the cast iron sump was crushed and splintered.“Say it, Joe,”she said quietly.

He grinned at her, and said,“It's a fair mugger.”He picked the broken pieces of cast iron from the hole, and got out from underneath. He went and got the starting-handle from the cab and turned the engine carefully. He sighed with relief.“Crank-shaft's all right,”he said.“It's only just the sump.”

He stood in deep thought for a minute, starting-handle in his hand; the rain poured down upon them steadily. She asked,“Where do we go from here, Joe?”

“I could patch that,”he said,“good enough to get her home. But then we haven't got any oil. It's no good going down to fetch the truck the way these creeks are rising.”He stood watching the water for a minute or two.“Never get the truck through by the time it got here,”he said finally.“There's only one thing for it now. He'll have to be flown out.”

The country round about was covered with rocks and trees.“Is there anywhere an aeroplane can land here?”she asked.

“I know one place it might,”he said.“Five hundred yards, they want, and then a good approach.”

He took his horse and went off to the south; by the river they unpacked the tent and arranged it over Don Curtis to keep the rain off him. The wounded man said faintly once,“Joe Harman's a clumsy mugger with a car. He's a good poddy dodger, though.”Jean laughed.“Pair of criminals, the two of you,”she said.“I'm going to have a word with Mrs Curtis.”

“Don't do it,”he said.“She don't know nothing about this.”

She said,“Lie still, and don't talk. Joe's gone off to find a place where the aeroplane can land to fly you out.”

“Hope he makes a better job of it than he did driving this bloody truck,”said Mr Curtis.

Joe came back in a quarter of an hour.“Think we can make something of it,”he said.“It's only about a mile away.”With Bourneville he harnessed up the tandem team of three horses to the front axle of the truck, and with Jean at the wheel they set off through the bush, steering and manoeuvring between the trees.

They came presently to an open space, a long grassy sward with low bushes dotted about on it. It was more than five hundred yards long, but there were trees at each end. It would be possible to make an airstrip there.“Clear off some of those bushes,”Joe said,“and fell some of those trees. I've seen them use a lot worse places than this.”

An axe and a spade were part of the equipment of the utility; they had tools enough. Their labour was quite inadequate for the work.“We'll have to get the boys up from Midhurst,”he said.“Everyone that's there. And get a message down to Willstown about the aeroplane.”

She said,“I'll ride down with Bourneville to the homestead, Joe. Then he can bring the boys back, and I'll go on to Willstown.”

He stared at her.“You can't ride that far.”

“How far is it?”

“Forty miles, to Willstown.”

“I can get to Midhurst, anyway,”she said.“If I can't go on I'll send Moonshine in with a note to Sergeant Haines. He's the best man to tell, isn't he?”

“That's right. If you do this, there's to be no riding alone. If you go on from Midhurst to town, you've got to take Moonshine or one of the other boys with you. I won't have you trying to cross them creeks alone, on a horse.”

She touched his arm.“All right, Joe. I'll take someone with me.”She paused.“We could get on the radio from Willstown,”she said.“We could get some people over from Windermere to help you then, couldn't we?”

“That's right,”he said.“It would be better if we had a radio at Midhurst.”He paused.“There's one thing that they'll all want to know,”he said,“and that's where this place is. We're about six miles west-south-west of the new bore. Can you remember that?”

“I've got that, Joe,”she said.“Six miles west-south-west of the new bore.”She paused.“What are you going to do?”she asked.

“I'll make a camp here.”He looked around.“I'll pitch the tent over the back of the utility,”he said.“We don't want to shift him again if we can help it, not until we get a stretcher. After that I'll start and fell some of those trees for the approach.”

“What about your back?”she asked.

“That'll be all right.”

She thought of swinging a two-handed axe to fell a tree.“Have you done that, Joe?”

“No, but it'll be all right.”

She said,“If you're going to cut down trees I'll take back what I said about not riding alone. I'll send Moonshine up with the other boongs to help you here.”

“You're not to do that,”he said.“It's not safe for you crossing them creeks.”

“It's not safe for you to swing an axe,”she said.“It won't help if you go and ruin your back up here, Joe.”She touched his arm again.“Let's both be sensible,”she said.“The work you'll do in cutting down those trees alone is only what the boongs will do in an hour when they get here. Don't take risks, Joe.”

He smiled at her.“All right. But you're not to ride alone.”

“I'll promise that,”she said.

It was about half past ten when they put her up on Joe's horse, Robin. Robin was a much bigger horse than she had ridden before, and she was rather afraid of him. He was little, if any, wider for her to straddle than the horses she was used to, and Joe's saddle was much better than the casual saddles she had been using up till then; it was soft and worn and supple with much use and yet efficient and in very good repair. When they got the stirrups adjusted for her legs she found herself fairly comfortable.

She started off with Bourneville at a slow trot through the trees, and so began a feat of endurance which she was to look back upon with awe for years to come. She found the horse docile, responsive, and energetic; moreover, he had a very easy gait when trotting. At the same time, the bald fact remained that she had only been on a horse six times before, and never for more than an hour and a half at a time.

The rain had stopped for the moment, and they came to the creek and waded through the tumbling yellow water, Bourneville beside her. They came through that one and went on, walking and trotting alternately. After an hour they came to the second creek and found it very deep; Bourneville made her take her feet out of the stirrups and be prepared to swim, holding to the horse's mane. That was not necessary and they came through to the other side in good order, and then the creeks were over.

“Too deep for the utility,”she said.

“Yes, Missy. Him too deep now.”

No creeks now lay between them and Midhurst; it remained only for them to ride. The rain began again and soaked her to the skin, mingling with the sweat streaming off her. Very soon the wet strides began to chafe her legs and thighs; she could feel the soreness growing, but there was nothing to be done about that. She had said that she would ride, and ride she would.

She found, on the good going that was before them now, that she could get along faster than Bourneville. She was on a much better horse, and a horse that was fresh whereas he had ridden his from Midhurst with the utility. Frequently she had to slow to a walk for him when Robin would have trotted on, and these walks helped her, easing her fatigue.

They came to Midhurst homestead at about half past two. By that time she had a raging thirst, and she was getting very tired. Moonshine and one or two of the other boys ran out and took her bridle and helped her down from Robin; she could not manage the stretch from the stirrup to the ground. She said,“Bourneville, tell Moonshine to saddle up and come with me to Willstown. I'm going to have a cup of tea and some tucker, and then we'll start. You take all the boys back to Mr Harman. That okay?”

He said,“Yes, Missy.”It struck her that if she was tired he must be exhausted; he had been in the saddle continuously for twenty-four hours. She looked at the seamed black face and said,“Can you make it, Bourneville? Are you very tired?”

He grinned.“Me not tired, Missy. Go back to Missa Harman with the boys after tucker.”He went away shouting,“Palmolive, Palmolive. You go longa kitchen, make tea and tucker for Missy. You go longa kitchen quick.”

She sat down wearily upon the chair in the veranda, and in a very short time Palmolive appeared with a pot of tea and two fried eggs upon a steak that was almost uneatable. She ate the eggs and a corner of the steak and drank six huge cups of tea. She did not dare to change her clothes or examine her sores; once started on that sort of thing, she knew, she would never get going again. She finished eating and called out for Moonshine and went down into the yard. The black stockmen, saddling their own horses and making up the bundles for the packhorses in the rain, put her up into the saddle and she was off again for Willstown with Moonshine by her side.

The short rest had stiffened her, and it needed all her courage to face the twenty miles that lay ahead. Every muscle in her body was stretched and aching. Her legs ceased to function much to hold her in the saddle, but the big horns above and below her thighs came into play and held her in place.

They crossed the creeks, now too deep for a car, and rode on. They were following the car track, and the going was good. She was the laggard now, because Moonshine's horse was fresh and Robin was tiring. She rode the last ten miles in a daze, walking and trotting wearily; for the last five miles the black stockman rode close by her side to try and catch her if she fell. But she didn't fall. She rode into Willstown in the darkness at about seven o'clock, a very tired girl on a very tired horse with a black ringer beside her. She rode past the hotel and past the ice-cream parlour with its lights streaming out into the street, and came to a stand outside Sergeant Haines' police station and house. She had been about eight hours in the saddle.

Moonshine dismounted and held Robin's head. She summoned a last effort and got her right leg back over the saddle, and slithered down to the ground. She could not stand at first without holding on to something, and she held on to Robin's saddle. Then Sergeant Haines was there.

“Why, Miss Paget,”he said in the slow Queensland way,“where have you come from?”

“From Joe Harman,”she said.“He's got Don Curtis up at the top end of Midhurst with a broken leg. Look, tell Moonshine what he can do with these horses, and then help me inside, and I'll tell you.”

He told Moonshine to take the horses round to the police corral and to bed down for the night with the police trackers in the bunkhouse; then he turned to Jean.“Come on in the house,”he said.“Here, take my arm. How far have you ridden?”

“Forty miles,”she said, and even in her fatigue there was a touch of pride in the achievement.“Joe Harman's up there now with Mr Curtis. All the Midhurst stockmen have gone up there to make an airstrip. It's the only way to get him out, Joe says. You can't get through the creeks with a utility.”

He took her in and sat her down in his mosquito-wired veranda, and Mrs Haines brought out a cup of tea. He glanced at the clock and settled down to listen to her in slow time; he had missed the listening watch of seven o'clock on the Cairns Ambulance radio, and now there was three quarters of an hour to wait before he could take any action.“Six miles west-south-west of the new bore,”he said thoughtfully.“I know, there's open country round about that part. I'll get on to the radio presently, and get the plane out in the morning.”

“Joe thought if you got on the radio some ringers might go out from Windermere and help him make the strip,”she said.“He's talking about cutting down some trees. I don't want him to do that, because of his back.”

He nodded.“I'll be getting Windermere at the same time.”And then he said,“I never knew you were a rider, Miss Paget.”

“I'm not,”she said.“I've been on a horse six times before.”

He smiled, and then said,“Oh my word. Are you sore?”

She got up wearily.“I'm going home to bed,”she said, and caught hold of the back of the chair.“If I stay here any longer I won't be able to walk at all.”

“Stay where you are,”he said.“I'll get out the utility and run you to the hospital.”

“I don't want to go to the hospital.”

“I don't care if you want to go or not,”he said,“but that's where you're going. You'll be better off there for tonight, and Sister Douglas, she's got everything you'll want.”

Half an hour later she was bathed and in a hospital bed with penicillin ointment on various parts of her anatomy, feeling like a very small child. Back in his office Sergeant Haines sat down before his transmitter.

“Eight Queen Charlie, Eight Queen Charlie,”he said,“this is Eight Love Mike calling Eight Queen Charlie. Eight Queen Charlie, if you are receiving Eight Love Mike will you please come in. Over to you. Over.”

He turned his switch, and the speaker on top of the set said in a girl's voice,“Eight Love Mike this is Eight Queen Charlie answering, receiving you strength three. Pass your message. Over.”

He said,“Eight Queen Charlie, we've got Don Curtis. Joe Harman found him at the top end of Midhurst. His injuries are compound fracture of the left leg two and a half days old, probably left ankle broken in addition. Position of the camp is six miles west-south-west of Harman's new bore. Tell me now if this is Roger. Over.”

The girl's voice from the speaker said,“Oh, I am glad—we've all been so worried this end. That is Roger, but I will repeat.”She repeated.“Over to you. Over.”

He said,“Okay, Jackie. Now take a message for Mr Barnes. Message reads. Request ambulance aircraft at Willstown soon as possible prepared for bush landing. Just read that back to me. Over.”

She read it back to him.

“Okay, Jackie,”he said.“Now call Windermere for me and let me speak to them. Over.”

She said,“Eight Able George, Eight Able George, this is Eight Queen Charlie calling Eight Able George. If you are receiving me, Eight Able George, please come in. Over to you. Over.”

A tremulous woman's voice said in thirty speakers in thirty homesteads,“Eight Queen Charlie, this is Eight Able George. I've heard all that, Jackie. Isn't it marvellous the way prayer gets answered? Oh my dear, I'm that relieved I don't know what to say. I'm sure we all ought to go down on our bended knees tonight and thank God for His mercy. I'm sure we all ought to do that. Oh—over.”

Miss Bacon turned her switch.“I'm sure we'll all thank God tonight, Helen. Now Sergeant Haines is waiting to speak to you. You stay listening with your switch on to Receive, Helen. Eight Love Mike, will you come in now? Over.”

In Willstown Sergeant Haines said,“Eight Love Mike calling Eight Able George. Mrs Curtis, you've heard Joe Harman's with your husband up at the top end of Midhurst. He's got to make an airstrip for the ambulance to land on, and he's taken all his stockmen up there. Will you send everyone you have upon your station to help make this airstrip? I'll give you the position. If you have a pencil and a bit of paper write this down.”He paused.“The place where Joe Harman is making the strip is six miles west-south-west of his new bore. Six miles west-south-west of his new bore. I want you to send every man you've got there to help him, and pass that message to Constable Duncan if he's with you. Is that Roger, Mrs Curtis? Over.”

The tremulous voice said,“That's Roger, Sergeant. Six miles west-south-west of Joe's new bore. I've got that written down. Eddie Page is here, and I'm expecting Phil Duncan to come back tonight. I'll send everybody up there. Isn't it marvellous what God can do for us? When I think of all His mercies to us suffering sinners I could go down on my bended knees and cry.”There was a pause, and then she said,“Oh, I keep on forgetting. Over.”

He turned his switch and said,“It's not only God you've got to thank, Mrs Curtis.”He was very well aware that most of the housewives in a hundred thousand square miles of the Gulf country would be listening in to this conversation, and one good turn deserves another.“Miss Paget rode forty miles down from the top end of Midhurst to bring this message about Don. You know Jean Paget, the English girl that's started the shoe workshop and the ice-cream shop? She was out at Midhurst spending the day when we heard Don was missing, and she rode forty miles to tell me where this airstrip was to be. She's only been astride a horse six times before, and the poor girl's so sore she can't stand. Sister Douglas has her in the hospital for a good rest. She'll be all right in a day or two. Over.”

She said,“Oh my word. I don't know what to say to thank her. Give her my very dearest love, and I do hope she'll be better soon.”There was a pause, and then she said,“I've been so troubled in my mind about that ice-cream parlour. It didn't seem right to have a thing like that in Willstown, and opening it on Sundays and Christmas Day and all. I couldn't find nothing in the Bible either for or against it, and I've been that perplexed. But now it seems God had that under His hand like everything else. I do think it's wonderful. Over.”

“That's right,”said Sergeant Haines non-committally. He had been uncertain about the shop closing hours himself and had written to his head office for guidance; it was a good long time since he had been in a district where there was a shop to close.“Now I must sign off, Mrs Curtis. Eight Queen Charlie, this is Eight Love Mike. It's okay here if you want to close down your listening watch for tonight, Jackie. I'd like to have a listening watch in daylight hours tomorrow, from seven o'clock on. Is this Roger? Over.”

Miss Bacon said,“That is Roger, sergeant. I'll tell Mr Barnes. If you have nothing more for me, I shall close down. Over.”

“Nothing more, Jackie. Goodnight. Out.”

“Goodnight, Sergeant. Out.”

Miss Bacon switched off her sets thankfully. There was no proper organization for a twenty-four hour listening watch at the Cairns Ambulance; in an emergency such as this everybody had to muscle in and lend a hand. She had been on duty the previous day from eight in the morning till midnight, and from eight o'clock that morning till then; Mr Barnes had taken the night watch and was preparing to do so again. She thought, ruefully, that she had missed Humphrey Bogart and Lauren Bacall; the show would be half over. But there was still one more night, and with any luck this flap would be over and she could see it tomorrow. She went to telephone to Mr Barnes.

Mr Barnes telephoned to Mr Smythe of Australian National Airways, and Mr Smythe telephoned to his reserve pilot, Captain Jimmie Cope. Mr Cope said,“Hell, I hope it's better in the morning than it was today. We'd never have got over the Tableland today. Better say take off at six, I suppose. I'll be along at the hangar then.”

When he got to the aerodrome at dawn the old Dragon, surely the best aircraft ever built for ambulance work in the outback, was running up both engines. The clouds hung low at about five hundred feet, shrouding the hill immediately behind the aerodrome; it was raining a little. Willstown lay about four hundred miles to the west-north-west; the first seventy miles of this course lay over the Atherton Tableland with mountains up to three thousand five hundred feet in height With no radio navigational aids he would have to fly visually all the way, scraping along between the clouds and the treetops as best he could.

He said a sour word or two to the control officer and took off down the runway with an ambulance orderly on board. Once in the air it was worse than ever. He flew at three hundred feet up the Barron River towards the mountains, hoping to find a break in the low cloud that would enable him to get up on to the Tableland through the Kuranda Gap. The grey vapour closed around him and the sides of the jungle-covered gorge drew very near his wings. There was no sign of a break ahead. He edged over to the starboard side and made a tight, dicey turn round in the gorge with about a hundred feet to spare, and headed back for the coast. He lifted his microphone and said,“Cairns Tower, this is Victor How Able Mike Baker. I can't make it by Kuranda. I'm going up to Cooktown by the coast, and try it from there. Tell Cooktown I'll be landing there in about an hour, and I'll want twenty gallons of seventy-three octane.”

He flew on up the tropical Queensland coast at about three hundred feet, and came to Cooktown an hour later. Cooktown is a pretty little town of about three hundred people, but it was grey and rainswept when he got there. He landed on the aerodrome and refuelled.“I'm going to try and make Willstown from here,”he said.“There's not much high stuff on the way. If it gets too bad I shall come back. I'll be on a direct course from here to Willstown.”He said that in case a search party should be necessary.

He took off again immediately the refuelling was finished and flew inland on a compass course. In the whole of that flight he was never more than two hundred feet above the treetops. He scraped over the Great Dividing Range, petering out up in this northern latitude, with about fifty feet to spare, always on the point of turning back, always seeing a faint break ahead that made it necessary to go on. Behind him the orderly sat gripping his seat, only too well aware of danger in the flight and impotent to do anything about it. For three hours they flew like that, and then as they neared the Gulf of Carpentaria the pilot started picking up the landmarks that he knew, a river bend, a burnt patch of the bush, a curving sandy waste like a banana. He came to Willstown and flew round the few houses at a hundred feet to tell them he was there, and landed on the airstrip. He taxied in to where the truck was standing waiting for him; he was strained and tired. It was still raining.

He held a little conference with Sergeant Haines and Sister Douglas and Al Burns beside the truck.“I'll have a crack at flying him back here,”he said.“If it's no better this afternoon he'll have to spend the night in hospital here. I can't fly him to Cairns in this weather. It'll probably be better by tomorrow.”They gave him a freehand pencil map which the sergeant had prepared for him, showing him the creeks and Midhurst homestead, and the new bore, and the probable position of the airstrip, and he took off again. That was at about eleven o'clock.

Following this map he found the place without much difficulty. It was clear where they meant him to land, because trees had been felled upon a line he was to come in on, and bushes had been cleared for a short distance on what seemed to be a grassy meadow. He could see about ten men working or standing looking up at him; he could see a utility parked with a tent over it. He circled round under the low cloud, considering the risks. The runway that they had prepared was pitifully short, even for a Dragon. Time was also short, however; the man had had his compound fracture three days now. Sepsis and gangrene and all sorts of things would be setting in; he must not delay. He bit his lip and lined the Dragon up with the runway for a trial approach.

He came in as slowly as he dared over the trees, missing them by no more than five feet, motoring in with careful graduations of the throttles. Over the cut trees he throttled back and stuffed her down towards the grass, hoping it was smooth. He could... he couldn't, he could never stop her in time. With wheels no more than two feet from the ground he jammed the throttles forward, held her level for a moment, and climbed away.

He turned to the orderly behind him as he circled low under the clouds, keeping the airstrip in sight.“Got a pencil and paper? Write this.”He thought for a moment.“Sorry I can't make it. Strip must be about a hundred yards longer, or a hundred and fifty if you can manage it. I will come back at four o'clock this afternoon.”They put this in a message bag with coloured streamers flying from it, and flew over, and dropped it on the middle of the strip.

Back at Willstown airfield he told them what had happened.“They've not had time to make it long enough,”the sergeant said.“You'll find it'll be all right this afternoon.”He drove the pilot in to the hotel and Al Burns took him to the bar, but the pilot would drink nothing but lemonade till the difficult flying of the afternoon was over.

He lunched at the hotel and strolled into the ice-cream parlour after lunch. It was new since he had last been in Willstown, and he stared around him with amused wonder. He ordered an ice; Rose Sawyer told him briskly to be quick and eat it, because she was shutting up. He asked if she closed every afternoon and was told that she was going up to see Miss Paget at the hospital. Then, of course, he heard all about her ride.

At four o'clock he was back over the airstrip at the top end of Midhurst; the rain had stopped and he was able to approach at about eight hundred feet. He circled once and had a good look; they had made the strip much longer and he would have no difficulty now. He came in and touched down at the near end; the Dragon bounced on the uneven ground and landed again, and rolled bumping and swaying to a standstill.

He stopped the engines and got out; they took a stretcher from the cabin and the orderly began the business of getting Don Curtis on to the stretcher and into the cabin, helped by the ringers. The pilot lit a cigarette and gave one to Joe Harman.

Joe asked,“Did you hear anything about Miss Paget, down in Willstown?”

The pilot said,“She's in the hospital. Nothing much wrong, they say, just tired and sore. She must be quite a girl.”

Joe said,“Too right. If you see anyone from the hospital, leave a message for Miss Paget, will you? Tell her I'll be in town tomorrow afternoon.”

“I'll do that,”said the pilot.“I'll be staying there tonight. It's too late now to get to Cairns; I can't do night flying in this weather, not in this thing.”

The loading was completed now. He got into his seat; the orderly swung the propellers and they taxied back to the far end of the track. It was short, but he could make it. He opened out and took off down the runway, and cleared the trees at the far end with about fifteen feet to spare. Half an hour later he was on the ground at Willstown, helping to transfer the stretcher to the truck that was to take Don Curtis to the hospital.

In hospital that afternoon Jean Paget showed Rose Sawyer the more accessible of her wounds, great chafed raw places six inches long.“Honourable scars,”Rose said.“Pity you can't show them.”

“It's because everything was so wet,”Jean said.“But I'm going to have a proper pair of riding breeches made, I think. Ringers' strides are for ringers' skins.”

“I'd never want to get up on a horse again if it'd done that to me.”

“It's going to be some time before I can,”said Jean.

Presently Rose said,“Tell me, Jean. Do you think there'd be any work up here for a contractor?”

Jean stared at her.“What sort of a contractor?”

“Making roads and things like that. Buildings, too.”

“Is this Billy Wakeling, from Alice?”

Rose nodded.“He wrote me,”she said carelessly. For the bunch of seven letters that arrived by the Dakota regularly every Wednesday, this seemed to Jean to be an understatement.“You know, his father's a contractor in Newcastle—he's got graders and bulldozers and steam shovels and all sorts of things like that. He started Billy off in Alice after the war because he said Alice was expanding and expanding places meant work for contractors. But Billy says he's fed up with Alice.

“He's coming up here for a visit as soon as the wet's over,”she added artlessly.

“He won't get any roads or buildings to contract for here,”Jean observed.“There's nobody to pay for them. I know what does want doing though. Joe Harman wants some little dams built up on Midhurst. I don't know if that's in his line.”

“I should think it might be,”said Rose slowly.“After all, it's shifting muck, and that's what Billy does. He'd do it with a bulldozer in the dry, wouldn't he?”

“I haven't the least idea,”said Jean.“Can he get hold of a bulldozer?”

“His old man's got about forty down at Newcastle,”Rose said.“I should think he could spare one for Billy.”

“They're only little dams,”said Jean.

“Well, everything's got to start. I don't think Billy expects a contract like the Sydney Harbour Bridge, not in the first year.”

Jean asked,“Could you scoop out a hole for a swimming-pool with a bulldozer?”

“I should think so. Yes, I'm sure you could. I went out with him once and watched one working. He let me drive it; it was awful fun. You'd scoop it out first with a bulldozer and then you'd put up wooden stuff that they call shuttering and make the concrete sides.”

“Could he do all that, too?”

“Oh, Billy can do that. Why, do you want a swimming-pool?”

Jean stared at the white painted wall.“It was just an idea. A nice, big pool just by the bore, with diving-boards and everything, big enough for everybody to get into and have fun. You see, you've got the water there, right in the main street. You'd have a wooden thing they call a cooling tower and run the water through that to cool it off before it went into the pool. Have a lawn of grass by it, where people could lie and sunbathe if they want to. An old man taking the cash at the gate, a bob a bathe...”

Rose stared at her.“You've got it all worked out. Are you thinking of doing that, Jean?”

“I don't know. It would be fun to have it, and I believe it'ld pay like anything. Mixed bathing, of course.”

Rose laughed.“Have all the wowsers in the place looking over the rails to see what was going on.”

“Charge them sixpence for that,”said Jean. She turned to Rose.“Ask Billy to get hold of plans and things,”she said,“and tell us what it would cost when he comes up after the wet. I don't believe that there's a swimming-pool in the whole Gulf country. It would be fun to have one.”

“I'll ask him. Anything else?”

Jean stretched in her bed.“A nice hairdressing saloon and beauty parlour,”she said,“with a pretty French brunette in it who really knew her stuff, and could make one look like Rita Hayworth. That's what I want, sometimes. But I don't think that's in Billy's line.”

“It had better not be,”said Rose.

Jean got up next day and left the hospital, and walked awkwardly to the workshop. There was an airmail letter from Mr Pack about the air freight consignment of shoes that he had received from them. His enthusiasm was temperate; he pointed out a number of defects and crudities which would require correction in production batches; most of these they were aware of and had attended to. He finished up by saying he would try and shift them, which, knowing Mr Pack, Jean and Aggie Topp interpreted as praise.

“He'll like the next lot better,”Aggie said. And then she said,“I had two girls come along for jobs while you were away. One was Fred Dawson's daughter; he's the chief stockman or something on a station called Carlisle. She's fifteen; her mother brought her in. She's a bit young, but she'd be all right. The other was a girl of nineteen who's been working in the store at Normanton. I didn't like her so much.”

“I don't want to take on anyone else until that first batch of shoes have been sold,”said Jean.“If Mrs Dawson comes in again, tell her that we'll let her know about the kid after the wet. I'd like to have her if I can. I don't think we want the other one, do we?”

“I don't think so. Bit of a slut, she was.”

They talked about the details of the business for an hour.“We haven't got the overalls back yet,”said Aggie.“I went and saw Mrs Harrison, but her back's bad again. We'll have to find someone else.”They issued the girls with a clean overall each week to work in, and the washing of these overalls was something of a problem to them.

“What we want,”said Jean,“is one of those Home Laundry things, and do them ourselves. We could run it off the generating set.... Of course, it needs hot water.”She thought for a minute.“Think about that one,”she said.“Hire it out, do people's washing for them. Anyway, see if you can find another Mrs Harrison for the time being.”

Aggie said,“Everybody's talking about your ride, Miss Paget.”

“Are they?”

She nodded.“Even that girl from Normanton, she knew about it, too.”

“How on earth did she get to hear?”

“It's these little wireless sets they have up on the cattle stations,”Aggie said.“The boys here were telling me, they all listen in to what everybody else is saying—telegrams and everything. They've got nothing else to do. You can't keep anything secret in this country.”And then she said,“I heard the aeroplane go off this morning. Was the man very bad?”

“Not too good,”said Jean.“Sister thinks they'll be able to save the leg. We ought to have a doctor here, of course.”

“There's not enough work to keep a doctor occupied in a place like this,”said Aggie.“Where did they fly him to?”

“Cairns. There's a good hospital in Cairns.”She turned to the door, and paused.“Aggie,”she said,“how do you think a swimming-pool would go in Willstown? Would people use it?”

Joe Harman rode into the town that afternoon with Pete Fletcher. He put his horse into the stable behind the Australian Hotel and came to find Jean; he was wet and dirty in his riding clothes because the creeks were up, and though he had started spick and span from Midhurst as befits a man going in to town to see his girl, he had had to swim one of the two creeks on the way holding to the mane and saddle of his horse, which had rather spoilt the sartorial effect. He was half dry when he got to Willstown; he combed his hair and emptied out his boots, and went to the ice-cream parlour to ask Rose where Jean was.

He found her in her bedroom, writing a long letter to me. He tapped on the door and she came out to him.“We can't talk here, Joe. I'll never hear the last of it if you come in. Let's go and have an ice-cream in the parlour.”It was borne in on her that this was literally the only place in Willstown where young men and young women could meet reputably to talk; the alternative, in the wet, would be to go into the stable or a barn. They picked a table by the wall; she looked around her at the rectangular walls and the adjacent tables with discontent.“This won't do at all,”she said.“I'll have some sort of booths made, little corners where people can talk privately.”

“What'll you have?”he asked.

“I'll have a banana split,”she said.“I want feeding up. I don't know if you know it, but I've been very ill. Don't pay, Joe—have it on the house.”

He grinned.“Think I'm the kind of man to take a girl out and let her shout?”

“If you're feeling like that, I'll have two. The bananas will be going bad by tomorrow.”She was getting fruit flown in by the Dakota every Wednesday, and she had little difficulty in selling the small quantities she got at prices that would pay for the air freight. Her trouble was that usually she could not keep it for a week.

He came back with the ices and sat down with her.“Now Joe,”she said,“what about that poddy corral?”

He grinned sheepishly, and looked over his shoulder.“That's crook,”he said.“There's no poddy corral on Midhurst.”

“There's something damn like one,”she said, laughing.“Come clean, Joe. What happened to Don Curtis, anyway?”

“He was moseying about on my land where he hadn't got no right to be,”Joe said carefully.“He found that corral where I'd got some poddys—my own poddys, mind you. I'd put 'em in there to consider things a bit, because they'd been wandering. Well, Don went to steal them off me, and he took down the top bar, but they were pretty wild, those poddys were; they hadn't had no water for about four days except the rain. Far as I can make out they pushed the second bar out on top of him when he went to loose it, and knocked him over on his back with the pole on top, and then they all ran over him and bust his leg. They ran out on the horse, too; Don had hitched his horse by the rein to something or other, and these poddys, they come charging down on to the horse and he bust the rein and he went too. So there Don was, and serve him bloody well right for going where he hadn't got no business to be.”

“Whose poddys were they, really, Joe?”

“Mine,”he replied firmly.

She smiled.“Where had they been wandering?”

He grinned.“Windermere. But they were my poddys. He pinched 'em off me. You heard me telling Pete he's got a poddy corral there.”

“Were these poddys that you had in your corral the same ones that you let out of his corral?”she asked. It seemed to be getting just a little bit involved.

“Most of 'em,”he said.“There might have been one or two with them that we picked up as damages, you might say.”He paused.“Things get a bit mixed up sometimes,”he observed.

“Where are the poddys now?”she asked.“The ones that Don let out?”

“They'll be on Midhurst,”he said.“They'll be somewhere round about the bore, I'd say. They won't stir from the first water that they find, not even in the wet.”

She ate a little of her banana split in silence. Then she said,“Well, anyway, you're not to go after any of his poddys while he's in hospital, Joe. That's not fair. He'll come out of hospital and find there's not a poddy left.”

“I wouldn't do a thing like that.”

“I bet you would. I don't know how this game is played, Joe, but I'm quite sure that's against the rules.”

He grinned.“All right. But he'll be after mine as soon as he gets back. That's sure as anything.”

“Why can't you let each other's poddys alone?”

“I'll let his alone, but he won't let mine alone. You see,”he said simply.“I got about fifty more of his last year than he got of mine.”

This conversation, Jean felt, was not getting them anywhere; where poddys were concerned Joe's moral standards seemed to be extremely low. She changed the subject, and said,“Joe, about those little dams you were talking about on Green Island. Have you got anyone to build them for you yet?”

He shook his head.“It's no good thinking about those until the dry.”

“Could a bulldozer build them?”

“Oh my word,”he said.“If anybody had a bulldozer he'd built the lot inside a month. But there's no bulldozer this side of the Curry.”

“There might be one,”she said. She told him about Rose Sawyer and Billy Wakeling.“He's coming up to see her anyway,”she said,“and she says he's looking for that sort of work to do up here. I suppose he's turning into Rose's steady. You'd better take him out to Midhurst when he comes, and have a talk to him.”

“My word,”he said.“If we had a joker with a bulldozer in Willstown it'ld make a lot of difference to the stations.”

“It'ld make a lot of difference here in Willstown,”she observed.“Joe, if we had a really decent swimming-pool just by the bore, with little cabins to change in and green lawns to sunbathe on, and diving-boards, and an old man in charge to mow the grass and keep it clean and nice—would people use it, Joe? If we charged, say, a bob a bathe?”

They discussed the swimming-pool for some time, and came to the conclusion that it could never pay upon the basis of a town with a hundred and fifty people.“It's just a question of how fast this town is going to grow,”he said.“A swimming-pool is just another thing to make it grow. There's not a town in the whole Gulf country that's got a pool.”

“The ice-cream parlour's paying, definitely,”Jean said.“If we can keep up the quality, I feel we're home on that one. I'd like to try the swimming-pool next, I think, if I can get the money for it out of Noel Strachan.”

He smiled in curious wonder.“What comes after the swimming-pool?”

She stared out at the wet, miry expanse of earth that was the street.“They'll get their hair wet in the swimming-pool, so we'll have to have a beauty parlour,”she said.“I think that's the next thing. And after that, an open-air cinema. And after that, a battery of Home Laundries for the wet wash, and after that a decent dress shop.”She turned to him.“Don't laugh, Joe. I know it sounds crackers, but just look at the results. I start an ice-cream parlour and put Rose in it, and young Wakeling comes after her with a bulldozer, so you get your dams built.”

“You're a bit ahead of the game,”he said.“They aren't built yet.”

“They will be soon.”

He glanced around the ice-cream parlour.“If everything you want to do works out like this,”he said slowly,“you'll have a town as good as Alice Springs in no time.”

“That's what I want to have,”she said.“A town like Alice.”

Chapter 11

All that happened nearly three years ago.

I cannot deny that in that time her letters have been a great interest to me, perhaps the greatest interest in my rather barren life. I think that after the affair of Mr Curtis and the poddy dodging she became more closely integrated into the life of the Gulf country than she had been before, because even before her marriage there was a subtle change in her letters. She ceased to write as an Englishwoman living in a strange, hard, foreign land; she gradually began to write about the people as if she was one of them, about the place as if it was her place. That may be merely my fancy, of course, or it may be that I made such a study of her letters, reading and re-reading them and filing them carefully away in a special set of folders that I keep in my flat, that I found subtleties of meaning in them that a more casual reader would not have noticed.

She married Joe Harman in April after the mustering, as she had promised him. They were married by a travelling Church of England priest, one of the Bush Brothers who had been, queerly enough, a curate at St John's in Kingston-on-Thames, not ten miles from where I used to live in Wimbledon. There was, of course, no church in Willstown at that time though one is to be built next year; they were married in the Shire Hall, and all the countryside came to the wedding. They had their honeymoon, or part of it, on Green Island, and I suppose she took her sarong with her, though she did not tell me that.

In the first two years of her married life she made considerable inroads into her capital. She was very good about it; she always started off one thing and got it trading smoothly before starting on another, after the first effort when she started both the ice-cream parlour and the workshop together. She used to send me accounts of her ventures, too, prepared for her by a young man called Len James who worked in the bank. But all the same, she asked me for three or four thousand pounds every six months or so, till by the time her second son was born, the one that she called Noel after me, she had had over eighteen thousand pounds for her various local businesses. Although they all seemed to be making profits Lester and I were growing, by that time, a little concerned about our duty as trustees, broad though our terms of reference under the Macfadden will might be. Our duty was to keep her capital intact and hand it over to her when she was thirty-five, and I began to worry sometimes about the chances of a slump or some unknown disaster in Australia which would extinguish the thirty per cent of her inheritance that we had let her have. Too many eggs seemed to be going into one basket, and her investments, laudable though they might be, could hardly be classed as trustee stocks.

The climax came in February, when she wrote me a long letter from the hospital at Willstown, soon after she had given birth to Noel. She asked me if I would be one of his godfathers, and of course that pleased me very much although there was very little prospect that I should live long enough to discharge my duties by him. Wakeling was to be the second godfather, and as he had married Rose Sawyer about six months previously and seemed to be settled in the district I felt that she would not be injuring her child by giving him an elderly godfather who lived on the other side of the world. I made a corresponding alteration to my will immediately, of course.

She went on in the same letter to discuss affairs at Midhurst.“You know, Joe's only manager at present,”she wrote.“He's done awfully well; there were about eight thousand head of cattle on the place when he went there, but now there are twelve or thirteen thousand. We shall be selling over two thousand head this year, too many to send down to Julia in one herd, so Joe's got to make two trips. It looks as if there'll be a steady increase for the next few years, because each year in the dry Bill Wakeling builds a couple more dams for us so we get more and more feed each year.”

She went on to tell me about Mrs Spears, the owner.“She left the Gulf country after her husband died about ten years ago,”she said,“and now she lives in Brisbane. Joe and I went down and stayed a couple of nights with her last October; I didn't tell you about it then because I wanted to think it over and we had to find out if we could get a loan, too.”

She told me that Mrs Spears was getting very old, and she wanted to realize a part of the considerable capital that she had locked up in Midhurst; probably she wanted to give it away during her lifetime to avoid death duties.“She asked if we could buy a half share in the station,”she said.“She would give us an option to buy the other half at a valuation at the time of her death, whenever that might be. It means finding about thirty thousand pounds; that's about the value of half the stock. The land is rented from the State, of course, and there's seventeen years to go upon the present lease; it means an alteration to the lease to put Joe's name into it jointly with hers.”

She told me that they had been to the bank. The bank would advance two-thirds of the thirty thousand pounds that they would have to find.“They sent an inspector up who knows the cattle business, and he came out to Midhurst,”she wrote.“Joe's got a good name in the Gulf country and I think he thought that we were doing all right with the property. That leaves us with ten thousand pounds to find in cash and that's what I wanted to ask you about.”

She digressed a little.“Midhurst's a good station,”she said,“and we're very happy here. If we can't take it over Mrs Spears will probably sell it, and we'd have to go somewhere else and start again. I'd hate to do that and it would be a great disappointment to Joe after all the work he's put into Midhurst. I'd be miserable leaving Willstown now, because it's turning into quite a fair-sized place, and it's a happy little town to live in, too. I do want to stay here if we can.”

She went on,“I know a cattle station isn't a trustee investment, Noel, any more than any of the other things you've let me put my money into. Will you think it over, and tell me if we can have it? If we can't, I'll have to think again; perhaps I could sell or mortgage some of the businesses I've started since I got here. I should hate to do that, because they might get into bad hands and go downhill. This town's like a young baby—I know something about those, Noel! It needs nursing all the time till it's a bit bigger.”

Another ten thousand pounds, of course, would mean that we should have allowed her to invest half of her inheritance in highly speculative businesses in one district, which was by no means the intention of Mr Macfadden when he made his will. Legally, of course, we were probably safe from any action for a breach of trust by reason of the broad wording of the discretionary clause that I had slipped into the will. I spent a day or two thinking about this before I showed her letter to Lester, and it came to me in the end that our duty was to do what Mr Macfadden would himself have done in similar circumstances.

What would that queer recluse in Ayr have done if he had had to settle this point? He was an invalid, of course, but I did not think he was an unkind or an unreasonable man. He had not made that long trust because he distrusted Jean Paget; he did not even know her. He had made it for her good, because he thought that an unmarried girl in her twenties who was mistress of a large sum of money would be liable to be imposed upon. In that he may well have been right. But Jean Paget was a married woman of thirty with two children now, and married to a sensible and steady sort of man, whatever his ideas on poddy-dodging might be. Would Mr Macfadden, in these circumstances, still have insisted on the trust being maintained in its original form?

I thought not. He was a kindly man—I felt sure of that—and he would have wanted her to have her Midhurst station, since that was where her home and all her present interests were. He was a careful, Scottish man, however; I thought he would have turned his mind more to the details of her investment in Midhurst to ensure that she got good value for this ten thousand pounds. Looking at it from this point of view I was disturbed at the short tenure of the lease. Seventeen years was a short time for Joe Harman to regain the value of the dams that he was building on the property and all the other improvements that he was making; he could not possibly go on with capital improvements until a very much longer lease had been negotiated.

I showed her letter to my partner then, and we had a long talk about it. He took the same view that I did, that the lease was the kernel of the matter.“I can't say that I take a very serious view of this trust, Noel,”he said.“I think your approach is the right one, to try and put yourself in the testator's shoes when looking at this thing. He was quite content to leave the money to his sister without any question of a trust, while her husband was alive to help her. It was only after the husband's death that he wanted the trust. Well, now the daughter's got a husband to help her. If he was disposing of his money now, presumably he wouldn't bother about any trust at all.”

“That's a point,”I said.“I hadn't thought of that one.”

“I don't suggest we disregard the trust,”he said.“I think we ought to use it as a lever to get this lease put right for her. Tell all and sundry that we won't release her money till the leasehold is adjusted to our satisfaction. Then, so far as I'm concerned, she can have all she wants.”

I smiled.“I wouldn't tell her that.”

I sat down next day and drafted a letter to her in reply.“I do not think it is impossible to release a further ten thousand pounds,”I wrote,“but I should be very sorry to do so until this matter of the lease had been adjusted to our satisfaction. As the thing stands at the moment, you could lose your home in seventeen years' time and lose with it all the money that you and Mrs Spears have expended on improvements such as dams and other water conservation schemes, which would pass to the State without any payment whatsoever, so far as my present information goes.”I learned later that that was incorrect.

I came to the main point of my letter next.“No doubt you have a solicitor that you can trust, but if it would assist you I would very gladly come and visit you in Queensland for a few weeks and see this matter of the lease put into satisfactory order before you invest this money in Midhurst. It is many years since I left England and I have regretted that; I cannot expect to have many more years left in which to travel and see the world. I would like to take a long holiday and travel a little before I get too feeble, and if I could help you in this matter of the lease I should be only too glad to come and do so.”I added,“I need hardly say that I should travel at my own expense.”

The answer came in a night letter telegram about ten days later. She urged me to come to them, and suggested that I should come out by air about the end of April, since their winter was approaching then and the weather would be just like an English summer. She said that she was writing with a list of clothes that I should have and medicines and things that I might need upon the journey. I was a little touched by that.

I saw Kennedy, my doctor, at his place in Wimpole Street next day.“Is there any particular reason why I shouldn't fly out to Queensland?”I asked.

He looked at me quizzically.“It's not exactly what I should advise for you, you know. Have you got to go to Queensland?”

“I want to go, very much,”I said.“I want to go and stay out there about a month. There's business I should like to see to personally.”

“How have you been walking recently?”

There was no point in lying to him.“I walk as far as Trafalgar Square most mornings,”I said.“I take a taxi from time.”

“You can't quite manage the whole distance to your office?”

“No,”I said.“I haven't done that for some time.”

“Can you walk upstairs in your club, to the first floor, without stopping?”

I shook my head.“I always go up in the lift. But anyway, there aren't any stairs in Queensland. All the houses are bungalows.”

He smiled.“Take off your coat and your shirt, and let me have a look at you.”

When he had finished his examination, he said,“Well. Are you proposing to go alone?”

I nodded.“I shall be staying with friends at the other end. They'll meet me when I get off the aeroplane.”

“And you really feel it's necessary that you should go?”

I met his eyes.“I want to go, very much indeed.”

“All right,”he said.“You know your condition as well as I do. There's nothing new—only the deterioration that you've got to expect. You put ten years on your age during the war. I think, on the whole, you're wise to travel by air. I think you'd find the Red Sea very trying.”He went on to tell me what I could do and what I mustn't attempt, all the old precautions that he had told me before.

I went back to my office and saw Lester, and told him what I was proposing to do.“I'm going to take about three months holiday,”I said,“starting at the end of April. I'm going out by air, and I don't know quite how long I shall stay for. If I find air travel too tiring on the way out, I may come home by sea.”I paused.“In any case, you'll have to work on the assumption that I shall be away for some considerable time. It's probably about time you started to do that, in any case.”

“You really feel that it is necessary for you to go personally, yourself?”he asked.

“I do.”

“All right, Noel. I only wish you hadn't got to put so much of your energy into this. After all, it's a fairly trivial affair.”

“I can't agree with that,”I said.“I'm beginning to think that this thing is the most important business that I ever handled in my life.”

I left London one Monday morning, and travelled through to Sydney on the same airliner, arriving late on Wednesday night. We stopped for an hour or so at Cairo and Karachi and Calcutta and Singapore and Darwin. I must say the aeroplane was very comfortable and the stewardess was most kind and attentive; it was fatiguing, of course, sleeping two nights in a reclining chair and I was glad when it was over. I stayed two nights in Sydney to rest, and took a little drive around in a hired car during the afternoon. Next day I took the aeroplane to Cairns. It was a lovely flight, especially along the coast of Queensland, after Brisbane. The very last part, up the Hinchinbrook Channel between Cairns and Townsville, must be one of the most beautiful coastlines in the world.

We landed at Cairns in the evening, and here I had a great surprise, because Joe Harman met me at the aerodrome. The Dakota, he told me, now ran twice a week to the Gulf country, partly on account of the growth of Willstown, and he had come in on the Friday plane to take me out on Monday.“I got one or two little bits of things to order and to see to,”he said.“My solicitor, Ben Hope, he's here in Cairns too. I thought that over the weekend you might like to hear the general set-up of Midhurst, 'n have a talk with him.”

I had not heard the slow Queensland speech since he had come to me in Chancery Lane, over three years before. He took me in a car to the hotel, a queer, rambling building rather beautifully situated, with a huge bar that seemed to be the focal point. We got there just before tea, the evening meal, and went in almost at once and sat down together. He asked me if I would drink tea or beer or plonk.

“Plonk?”I asked.

“Red wine,”he said.“I don't go much for it myself, but jokers who know about wine, they say it's all right.”

They had a wine list, and I chose a Hunter River wine which I must say I found to be quite palatable.“Jean was very sorry she couldn't come and meet you,”he said.“We could have parked Joe with someone, but she's feeding Noel, so that ties her. She's going to drive into Willstown and meet the Dakota on Monday.”

“How is she?”I asked.

“She's fine,”he said.“Having babies seems to suit her. She's looking prettier than ever.”

We settled down after tea on the veranda outside my bedroom, and began discussing the business of Midhurst. He had brought with him copies of the accounts for the station for the last three years, neatly typed and very easily intelligible. I commented upon their form, and he said,“I'm not much of a hand at this sort of thing. Jean did these before she went into the hospital. She does most of the accounts for me. I tell her what I want to do out on the station, and she tells me how much money I've got left to spend. She's got the schooling for the two of us.”

Nevertheless, I found him quite a shrewd man, very well able to appreciate the somewhat intricate points that came up about the lease and his capital improvements. We talked for a couple of hours that night about his station and about the various businesses that Jean had started in the town. He was very interesting about those.

“She's got twenty-two girls working in the workshop,”he said.“Shoes and attaché cases and ladies' bags. That's the one that isn't doing quite so well as the others.”He turned the pages of the accounts to show me.“It's making a profit now, but last year there was a loss of over two hundred pounds—two hundred and twenty-seven. But all the others—oh my word.”He showed me the figures for the ice-cream parlour, the beauty parlour, the swimming-pool, the cinema, the laundry, and the dress shop.“They're doing fine. The fruit and vegetable shop, that's all right, too.”We totted up the figures and found that the seven of them together had made a clear profit of two thousand six hundred and seventy-three pounds in the previous year.“It'ld pay her to run the workshop at a loss,”he said.“She gets it back out of what the girls spend to make themselves look pretty for the ringers, and what the ringers spend in taking out the girls.”

I was a little troubled about the workshop.“Can she expand it?”I asked.“Can she lower the overhead by doing a bigger business?”

He was doubtful about that.“She's using just about all the alligator skins Jeff Pocock and two others can bring in,”he said.“Wallabies, they're getting scarcer than they were, too. I don't think she can get much bigger in the workshop. She doesn't want to, either. She's got a kind of hunch that in a few years' time the workshop won't be necessary at all, that the town will be so big that a workshop employing twenty girls won't be neither here nor there.”

“I see,”I said thoughtfully.“How big is the town now?”

“There's about four hundred and fifty people living in Willstown,”he said.“That's not counting boongs, and not counting people living out upon the stations. The population's trebled in the last three years.”

“Is that just because of the workshop?”I asked.

He said slowly,“I think it must be—everything comes back to that, when you look at it. It's not only the workshop, you see. She's got two girls employed in the ice-cream parlour, and one lubra. Two in the beauty parlour, three in the dress shop, two in the fruit shop, three in the cinema. She employs quite a lot of people.”

I was puzzled.“But can twenty girls in the workshop provide work for all these other girls?”I asked.

“It doesn't seem to work that way,”he said.“We were totting it up the other day. She's never employed more than about thirty-five girls at any one time, but since she started there's been forty-two girls married out of her businesses. They mostly marry ringers. Well, that's forty-two families starting, forty-two women wanting cinema and beauty parlour and fresh vegetables and that, besides the thirty-five girls that she's still got employed. It kind of snowballs.”He paused.“Take the bank. There's two girl clerks there that there never were before, because of the bigger business. The AMP have started up an office, and there's a girl in that. Bill Wakeling's got a girl in his office.”He turned to me.“It's a fact, there's something like a hundred girls and married women under twenty-five in Willstown now,”he said.“When Jean came, there was two.”

“And the babies!”he said.“There's more babies than you could shake a stick at. They've had to send a special maternity nurse to the hospital. That's another girl. She got engaged to Phil Duncan, the copper, last month, so there'll be another one.”

I smiled.“Are there enough men to go round?”

“Oh my word,”he said.“There's no difficulty in getting men to work in Willstown. I've had ringers coming from all over Queensland, from the Northern Territory, too, wanting a job round about Willstown. There was one chap came all the way from Marble Bar in Western Australia, two thousand miles or so. The labour situation's very different now from what it was three years ago.”

I went to bed early that night with plenty to think about. We had a conference next morning with Mr Hope, the solicitor, in his office, and wrote a letter to the Queensland Land Administration Board suggesting a meeting to discuss the lease of Midhurst. That afternoon we spent in driving around Cairns to see the sights; it seemed to me to be a pleasant little tropical town, beautifully situated. On Sunday we drove up on to the Atherton Tableland, high rolling downs farmed somewhat on the English style.

We flew to Willstown on Monday morning, in a Dakota. We landed at places called Georgetown and Croydon on the way and stayed on each aerodrome for about twenty minutes, picking up and setting down passengers and freight, as we circled Georgetown for the landing I was able to study the place. It was pathetic in a way, for you could see from the air the rectangular pattern of wide streets that once had been busy and lined with houses, now rutted with the rain and grass-grown. A few scattered houses stood at the intersections of what had once been these streets, and they were clustered rather more thickly around the hotel, the only two-storeyed building in either place. Both of these were derelict gold towns.

The people who came to meet the aeroplane in trucks were bronzed, healthy, and humorous; the men were mostly great big tanned, competent people; the women candid, uncomplaining housewives.

I sat at the window studying Croydon as we took off, till it fell away from view behind us.“I'm kind of glad that you've seen those,”said Joe beside me.“Willstown was like that, only a bit worse. It's no great shakes yet, of course, but it's better than Croydon, oh my word it is.”

We circled Willstown as we came in to land. It stood by quite a large river, and it was queerly like the other two towns in its layout. There were the same wide streets arranged in rectangular pattern, but the pattern was filling up with houses here. From the air the glint of the sun upon new corrugated iron roofs was everywhere, so that at one point as we circled opposite the sun I had to shut my eyes against the dazzle. All these houses seemed to be new, and a considerable number were still in the process of building. In the main street opposite the two-storeyed building that I guessed to be the hotel, a line of shrubs had been planted in a formal garden down the middle of the road, transforming the wide cattle-rack into two carriageways, and tarmac pavements had been made in this part of the town. Opposite the hotel I could see the swimming-pool with diving- boards and cabins and a lawn beside it, just as Jean had described it to me in her letters. Then the town was lost to view, and we were landing, coming in over a brand-new racetrack.

She was there to meet me in her Ford utility, her own car that she had bought for running in and out of town to see to her businesses. She was more mature now than I had remembered her; she had grown into a very lovely woman. She said,“Oh Noel, it is nice to see you. Are you very tired?”

“I'm not tired,”I said.“Three or four years older, perhaps. You're looking very well.”

“I am well,”she said.“Disgustingly well. Noel, it was good of you to offer to come out like this. I wanted to ask you to, and then it seemed too much to ask. It's such a very long way. Come and sit in the utility. Joe's just getting your bags.”

They drove me out immediately to Midhurst. We passed through the main street of Willstown and I wanted to stop and see what she had done, but they would not let me.“Time enough for that tomorrow or the next day,”she said.“We'll go to Midhurst now, and you can rest a bit.”

I knew the sort of scenery that I should see upon the way to Midhurst from many readings of her letters, and it was just as I had expected it to be. There was no road in the usually accepted sense; she picked her way across country in the car following the general line of the tracks but avoiding the deep holes. When we came to the first creek, however, I was interested to see that they had made a sort of concrete bottom or causeway across the river bed, and this causeway was marked by two massive wooden posts upon the bank at either end.“We haven't got as far as having bridges yet,”she said.“But this thing is a god-send in the wet, to know that you won't hit a boulder under water.”

The homestead was very much as I had expected it to be, but there was a garden now in front of it, bright with flowers, and there were great ranges of log stockades or cattle pens that I had not heard about.“They've gone up in the last two years,”Joe said.“We've got three Zebu bulls now, and you want more stockyards when you start breeding.”His Zebu bulls were a cross between Indian cattle and English Herefords. He told me that he was keeping a small herd of dairy cows, too, and that meant more enclosures still.

“How many hands have you got now?”I asked.

“Eleven white stockmen,”he said,“and ten boongs. It's almost easier to get white than black in this part of the country.”

They would not let me walk that day, but put me in a long chair in the veranda with a cool drink, and I sat watching all the work of the station as it went on in the yard below. It was fascinating to sit there and watch it all, the white stockmen and the black stockmen, the cattle, the dogs, and the horses, and a half grown wallaby lolloping about with puppies teasing it by playing with its tail. I could have sat there indefinitely watching it all, and watching the grace of Jean moving round the house attending to her children and her Abo women. I did sit there for three days.

She took me into town one morning, and showed me everything that she had done. She took me to the workshop first, and she made me put a scarf on before we went in because it would be cold. It was not cold as we would know cold, but it struck chilly after the warm day outside, because she kept the air-conditioner going all the year round.“The girls do love it so,”she said.“There's always more of them wanting to work here than I can take on, just because of that.”They all looked very smart and pretty in their green smocks, working at the leather goods. There was a long mirror at the end of the shop, and a few pictures of hair styles and frocks cut out of illustrated magazines pinned up on the wall.“We change those every so often,”she said.“I like them to make the best of themselves.”

The workshop stood by itself, but she had arranged her other enterprises all in a row as a little street of shops. She had built a wooden veranda over the broad tarmac pavement to shade shopgazers from the sun or the rain. Here she had the beauty parlour with an Estonian in charge, a dark, handsome middle-aged woman, beautifully got up, with two Australian girls under her. There were four private little booths, and a glass counter and display-case full of women's things; it was all very clean and nice. Next in the row came a little shop with a battery of four Home Laundries, and three young married women sitting gossiping while they waited for their wash. Next was the greengrocer's shop, which sold seeds and garden implements as well as fruit and vegetables, and after that the dress shop. This was quite a big place, with counters and dummys clothed in summer frocks, and I was interested to see a small, secluded part served by a middle-aged woman where the elderly could buy the clothes they were accustomed to, black skirts and flannel petticoats and coarse kitchen aprons.

She took me across the road and showed me the cinema and the swimming-pool. It was quite a hot day and by that time I had had about enough, so she took me to the ice-cream parlour and we had a cool drink there. She had some business to attend to and she left me there for half an hour, and I sat watching the people as they came into the parlour, or as they passed on the sidewalk. There were far more women than men. All of them seemed to be pretty, and at least half of them seemed to be in the family way.

She came back presently, and sat with me in the parlour.“What comes next?”I asked.“Is there any end to this?”

She laughed and touched my hand.“No end,”she said.“I keep on badgering you for more money, don't I? As a matter of fact, I think I can start the next one out of the profits.”

“What's that one going to be?”

“A self-service grocer's shop,”she replied.“The demand's shifting, Noel. When we started, it was entertainment that was needed, because everyone was young and nobody was married then. The solid, sensible things weren't wanted. What they needed then was ice-cream, and the swimming-pool, and the beauty parlour, and the cinema. They'll still need those things, but they won't expand so much more. What the town needs now is things for the young family. A really good grocer's shop selling good, varied food as cheap as we can possibly get it. And then, as soon as I can start it, we must have a household store. Do you know, you can't even buy a baby's pot in Willstown?”

I nodded at the store opposite.“Doesn't Mr Duncan sell those?”

“He's got no imagination. He only sells big ones, that'ld hold the whole baby.”

I asked her presently,“How do all your goods get here? They aren't all flown, surely?”

She shook her head.“They come by train from Cairns to Forsayth, and by truck from there. There's no proper road, of course. It makes it terribly expensive, because a truck is worn out in about two years. Bill Wakeling says the Roads Commission are considering a road from here to Mareeba and Cairns—a proper tarmac road. Of course, he wants to build it. He thinks we'll get it inside two years, because the town's growing so fast. I must say, it'll be a god-send when we do. Fancy being able to drive to Cairns in a day!”

The Land Administration Board answered our letter later on that week and suggested a meeting on the following Tuesday or Wednesday, which suited our air services. I flew down to Brisbane with Joe Harman, picking up his solicitor in Cairns, and we had a conference with the Land Administration Board, which lasted most of one day, settling the Heads of Agreement. Then Harman went back to his station and Mr Hope and I stayed on in Brisbane passing the draft of the final agreement backwards and forwards to the Land Administration Board with amendments in red and green and blue and purple ink. On top of this, I was in communication with the solicitors for Mrs Spears over the option agreement for the final purchase of Midhurst; all this kept me busy in Brisbane for nearly a fortnight. Finally I was able to agree to them both, after an exchange of cables with Lester, and brought them back to Cairns. Joe Harman signed them, and we put them in the post, and my business in Queensland was done.

I went back to Willstown with Joe and stayed another week with them, not because there was any reason why I should do so, but for an old man's sentiment. I sat on the veranda with Jean, studying her drawing of the layout of the self-service grocery. We discussed whether it could not be combined with the hardware store. We went into Willstown and visited the site for it, and I spent some time with Mr Carter, the Shire Clerk, discussing with him the position in regard to the leases that she held for land. She showed me the swimming-pool and we talked about the cost of tiling over the rough concrete to make it look better, and I sat for hours in the ice-cream parlour watching those beautiful young women as they pushed their prams from shop to shop.

I asked her once if she would be coming back to England for a holiday. She hesitated, and then said gently,“Not for a bit, Noel. Joe and I want to take a holiday next year, but we've been planning to go to America. We thought we'd go to San Francisco and get an old car, and drive down the west coast into Arizona and Texas. I'm sure we'd learn an awful lot that would be useful here if we did that. Their problems must be just the same as ours, and they've been at it longer.”

Jean touched me very much one evening by suggesting that I stayed out there and made my home with them.“You've nothing to go back to England for, Noel,”she said.“You're practically retired now. Why not give up Chancery Lane, give up London, and stay here with us? You know we'd love to have you.”

It was impossible, of course; the old have their place and the young have theirs.“That's very kind of you,”I said.“I wish I could. But I've got sons, and grandchildren, you know. Harry will be coming home next year and we're all hoping that he'll get a shore appointment. He's due for a term of duty at the Admiralty, I think.”

She said,“I'm sorry, for our sake. Joe and I talked this over, and we hoped we'd be able to get you to stay with us for a long time. Make your home here with us.”

I said quietly,“That was a very kind thought, Jean, but I must go back.”

They drove me to the aeroplane, of course, to see me off. Leave-takings are stupid things, and best forgotten about as quickly as possible. I cannot even remember what she said, and it is not important anyway. I can only remember a great thankfulness that the Dakota on that service didn't carry a stewardess so that nobody could see my face as we circled after taking off to get on course, and I saw the new buildings and bright roofs of that Gulf town for the last time.

It is winter now, and it is nearly three months since I have been able to get out to the office or the club. My daughter-in-law Eve, Martin's wife, has been organizing me; it was she who insisted that I should engage this nurse to sleep in the flat. They wanted me to go into some sort of nursing- home, but I won't do that.

I have spent the winter writing down this story, I suppose because an old man loves to dwell upon the past and this is my own form of the foible. And having finished it, it seems to me that I have been mixed up in things far greater than I realized at the time. It is no small matter to assist in the birth of a new city, and as I sit here looking out into the London mists I sometimes wonder just what it is that Jean has done; if any of us realize, even yet, the importance of her achievement.

I wrote to her the other day and told her a queer thought that came into my head. Her money came originally from the goldfields of Hall's Creek in West Australia, where James Macfadden made it in the last years of the last century. I suppose Hall's Creek is derelict now, and like another Burketown or another Croydon. I think it is fitting that the gold that has been taken from those places should come back to them again in capital to make them prosperous. When I thought of that, it seemed to me that I had done the right thing with her money and that James Macfadden would have approved, although I had run contrary to the strict intentions of his son's will. After all, it was James who made the money and took it away to England from a place like Willstown. I think he would have liked it when his great-niece took it back again.

I suppose it is because I have lived rather a restricted life myself that I have found so much enjoyment in remembering what I have learned in these last years about brave people and strange scenes. I have sat here day after day this winter, sleeping a good deal in my chair, hardly knowing if I was in London or the Gulf country, dreaming of the blazing sunshine, of poddy-dodging and black stockmen, of Cairns and of Green Island. Of a girl that I met forty years too late, and of her life in that small town that I shall never see again, that holds so much of my affection.

Author's Note

On the publication of this book I expect to be accused of falsifying history, especially in regard to the march and death of the homeless women prisoners. I shall be told that nothing of the sort ever happened in Malaya, and this is true. It happened in Sumatra.

After the conquest of Malaya in 1942 the Japanese invaded Sumatra and quickly took the island. A party of about eighty Dutch women and children were collected in the vicinity of Padang. The local Japanese commander was reluctant to assume responsibility for these women and, to solve his problem, marched them out of his area; so began a trek all round Sumatra which lasted for two and a half years. At the end of this vast journey less than thirty of them were still alive.

In 1949 I stayed with Mr and Mrs J. G. Geysel-Vonck at Palembang in Sumatra. Mrs Geysel had been a member of that party. When she was taken prisoner she was a slight, pretty girl of twenty-one, recently married; she had a baby six months old, and a very robust sense of humour. In the years that followed Mrs Geysel marched over twelve hundred miles carrying her baby, in circumstances similar to those which I have described. She emerged from this fantastic ordeal undaunted, and with her son fit and well.

I do not think that I have ever before turned to real life for an incident in one of my novels. If I have done so now it is because I have been unable to resist the appeal of this true story, and because I want to pay what tribute is within my power to the most gallant lady I have ever met.

Nevil Shute

第二编

一七七一年十月二十日

我们昨天抵达此地。公使觉着身体不舒服，要在家里休息几天。他要是脾气随和些，就一切都好了。我发现，一再地发现，命运总是安排给我种种严峻的考验。可要鼓起勇气啊！心情一轻松，便什么都能忍受了。好个心情轻松，这话竟然出自我的笔下，简直令人好笑！唉，岂知我只需心情稍微轻松一点儿，就可以成为天底下最幸福的人。可不是么，别人有一点点能力，一点点才分，便到处夸夸其谈，沾沾自喜，我干吗还要悲观失望，怀疑自己的能力和天赋呢？仁慈的上帝，是你赐予了我这一切；可你为什么不少给我一半才能，多给我一丁点自信与自足哟！

别急！别急！情况会好起来的。告诉你，好朋友，你的意见完全对。自从我每天在人们中间忙忙碌碌，看见他们干什么和怎么干以来，我的心绪已经好多了。的确，我们生来就爱拿自己和其他人反反复复比较；所以，我们是幸福或是不幸，全取决于我们与之相比的是些什么人；所以，最大最大的危险，就莫过于孤身独处了。我们的脑子生就是朝上想的，加之受到诗里的幻境的激发，便常常臆造出一些地位无比优越于我们的人来，好像他们个个都比自己杰出，个个都比自己完美。而且这似乎理所当然。经常地，我们感到自己身上有这样那样的缺陷；在我们看来，我们所欠缺的，别人偏偏都有。不仅如此，我们还把自己所有的品质全加在他们身上，外搭着某种心满意足。这样，一个幸福的人就完成了，只不过是我们自己的创造而已。

反之，如果我们不顾自己的衰弱和吃力，只管一个劲儿往前赶，我们常常便会发现，我们虽然步履踉跄，不断迷路，却仍比其他又张帆又划桨的人走得远——而且，一当你与其他人并驾齐驱，或者甚至超越了他们，你就会真正感觉到自身的价值。

十一月二十六日

我开始勉勉强强适应了此地的生活。最使我高兴的，是这儿有足够的事干；此外，还有许许多多的人，百态千姿，形形色色，恰似在对着我的灵魂演出一场热闹的趣剧。我已经结识了C伯爵，一位令我日益尊敬的博学而杰出的男子，他见多识广，所以对人就不冷漠；从他的待人接物，可以明显看出是很重感情和友谊的。我有一次奉命去他府上公干，他便表现出对我有好感，一经交谈，他更发现我们相互理解，发现他可以同我像同他的少数知心朋友似的倾谈。还有他对人态度之坦率，我怎么称赞也不为过。世间最纯粹、最暖人胸怀的乐事，恐怕莫过于看见一颗伟大的心灵对自己开诚相见吧。

十二月二十四日

公使给了我许多烦恼，这是我预料到的。像他似的吹毛求疵的傻瓜，世上找不出第二个。一板一眼，啰里啰唆，活像个老太婆；他这人从来没有满意自己的时候，因此谁也甭想多会儿能称他的心。我喜欢的可是干事爽快麻利，是怎样就怎样；他呢，却有本事把文稿退还给我，说什么“文章嘛写得倒挺好，不过您不妨再看看，每看一遍总可以找到一个更漂亮的句子，一个更适合的小品词”。——这真叫我气得要死。任何一个“和”，任何一个连词，你都甭想省去；我偶尔不经意用了几个倒装句，他都拼命反对；要是你竟把他那些长套句换了调调，他更会摆出一副完全摸不着头脑的样子，和这样一个人打交道，真叫受罪啊。

只有C伯爵的信任，才给我以安慰。最近他开诚布公地告诉我，他对我这位公使的拖沓与多疑也很不满。“这种人不仅自讨苦吃，也给人家添麻烦。不过，”他说，“我们必须听天由命。这就像旅行者不得不翻一座山，这座山要是不存在，路走起来自然舒坦得多，也短得多；可它既然已经存在，那你就必须翻过去！”

我那老头子心里明白，比起他来伯爵更器重我。他对此十分生气，一抓住机会就当着我的面讲伯爵的坏话；我呢，自然便要为伯爵辩护，这一来事情只会更糟。昨天我简直叫他惹火了，因为他下面的一席话，捎带着把我也给骂了进去。他说，伯爵处理起事务来还算行，非常干练，笔头嘛也来得，可就是缺少渊博的学识，跟所有文人一样。讲这话时，他那副神气仿佛在问：“怎么样，刺痛你了吧？”我才不吃这一套哩；我鄙视一个像这样思想和行动的人，便与他针锋相对，毫不让步。我道，无论品性或是学识，伯爵都是位理应受到尊重的人。“在我所有相识者中，”我说，“没有谁像他那样心胸开阔，见多识广，同时又精于日常事务的。”——我这话在老头子无异于对牛弹琴；为了避免闲扯下去再找气怄，我就告辞了。

瞧，全都怪你们不是。是你们唠唠叨叨，劝我来戴上了这副重轭，成天价在我耳边念“要有所作为呀”，“要有所作为呀”。要有所作为！如果一个种出马铃薯来运进城去卖的农民，他不就已经比我更有作为的话，我也甘愿在眼下这条囚禁我的苦役船上再受十年罪。

还有那班麇集此间的小市民们的虚伪与无聊！他们是如此斤斤计较等级，无时无刻不在瞅着抢到别人前头去一步的机会，以致这种最可悲、最低下的欲望，竟表现得赤裸裸的。比如有一个女人，她逢人便讲她的贵族血统和领地，使每个不谙内情者都只能当她是白痴，要不怎么会神经失常，把自己那点儿贵族的血液和世袭的领地竟看得如此了不起。——更糟糕的是，这个女的偏偏只是本地一名书记官的千金。——是啊，我真不明白这类人，他们怎么竟如此没有廉耻。

不过，好朋友，我一天比一天看得更加清楚，以自己去衡量别人是很愚蠢的。何况我本身有的是伤脑筋的事儿，我这颗心真叫不平静呵——唉，我真乐于让人家走人家的路，只要他们也让我走自己的路就成。

最令我恼火的是市民阶层的可悲处境。尽管我和任何人一样，也清楚了解等级差别是必要的，它甚至还给我本人带来了不少好处，可是，它却偏偏又妨碍着我，使我不能享受这世界上仅存的一点点欢乐，一星星幸福。最近，我在散步时认识了封·B小姐；她是一位在眼前的迂腐环境中仍不失其自然天性的可爱姑娘。我和她谈得十分投机，临别时请她允许我上她家去看她。她大大方方地答应了，使我更加急不可耐地等着约定的时间到来。她并非本地人，住的是一位姑母家里。老太太的长相我一见就不喜欢，但仍然对她十分敬重，多数时间都在和她周旋。可是不到半小时，我便摸清了她的底细，而事后封·B小姐也向我承认了。原来亲爱的姑妈老来事事不如意，既无一笔符合身份的产业，也无智慧和可依靠的人，有的只是一串祖先的名字和可资凭借的贵族地位，而她唯一的消遣，就是从她的楼上俯视脚下的市民的脑袋。据说她年轻时倒是很俊俏的，只是由于行事太诡，才毁了自己的一生，开始一意孤行，把不少倒霉的小青年折磨得够呛；后来上了几分年纪，就只好屈就一位软耳根的军官啦。此人以这个代价和一笔勉强够用的生活费，和她一道度过了那些艰辛的岁月。随后他就一命呜呼，丢下了她孤零零一个人，眼下的日子同样艰辛。要不是她那外甥女如此可爱的话，谁还高兴来瞅她一瞅啊。

一七七二年一月八日

真不知这是些什么人，整个的心思都系挂在那种种繁文缛节上，成年累月盘算和希冀的只是怎样才能在宴席上把自己的座位往上挪一把椅子。并非他们除此别无事做；相反，事情多得成堆，恰恰是为忙那些无聊的琐事去了，才顾不上干重要的事。上星期，在乘雪橇出游时便发生了争吵，结果大为扫兴。

这班傻瓜哟，他们看不出位置先后本身毫无意义；看不出坐第一把交椅的，很少是第一号角色！古往今来，不知有多少君王受自己宰相的支配，有多少宰相又被他秘书所驾驭！在这种情况下，谁是第一号人物呢？我认为是那个眼光超过常人，有足够的魄力和心计把别人的力量与热情全动员起来实现自己计划的人。

一月二十日

亲爱的绿蒂，我刚才为避一场暴风雪逃进了一家乡村小客栈；只有到了这儿，我才能给你写信。多久我还困在D城那可悲的窠巢里，忙碌在那班对于我的心来说完全是陌生的人们中间，多久我的心就不会叫我写信给你。可眼下，在这所茅屋中是如此寂寞，如此湫隘，雪和冰雹正扑打着我的小窗，在这儿我的第一个思念却是你。我一踏进门，你的倩影便出现在我的眼前，唤起了我对你的回忆，绿蒂呵，那么神圣，那么温馨的回忆！仁慈的上帝，这是许久以来你赐予我的第一个幸福时刻啊！

亲爱的，你哪知道我已变得多么心神不定，知觉麻木！我的心没有一刻充实，没有一刻幸福！空虚呀！空虚呀！我好像站在一架西洋镜前，看见人儿马儿在我眼前转来转去，不禁经常问自己，这是不是光学把戏呢？其实，我自己也参加了玩这把戏，或者更正确地说，也像个木偶似的被人玩，偶尔触到旁边一个人的木手，便吓得战栗着缩了回来。晚上，我下决心要享受日出，到了早晨却起不来床；白天，我希望能欣赏月色，天黑了又待在房中出不去。我闹不明白，我干吗起身，干吗就寝。

我的生活缺少了酵母；使我深夜仍精神饱满，一大早就跳下床来的兴奋剂已不知抛到了何处。

在此地我只结识了一个女子，一位名叫封·B的小姐；她就像你啊，亲爱的绿蒂，如果说谁还能像你的话。“哎，”你会说，“瞧这人才会献殷勤哩！”——此话倒也并非完全不对；一些时候以来，我的确变得有礼貌多了，机灵多了——不如此不行呵——。所以女士们讲：谁也不如我会说奉承话。“还有骗人的话。”你会补充说。可是，不如此不行呵，你懂吗？——让我还是讲封·B小姐吧。她是一个重感情的姑娘，这从她那一双明亮的蓝眼睛里可以看出来。她的贵族身份只是她的负担，满足不了她的任何一个愿望。她渴望离开扰攘的人群，我不止一次陪着她幻想过田园生活的纯净的幸福，啊，还幻想过你！她是多么经常地不得不崇拜你呵。不，不是不得不，而是自愿；她非常愿意听我讲你的情况，并且爱你。

呵，我真愿能再坐在你脚边，坐在那间舒适可爱的小房间里，看着我们亲爱的孩子们在我的周围打闹嬉戏！要是你嫌他们吵得太厉害，我就可以让他们聚到我身边来，安安静静听我讲一个可怕的故事。

美丽的夕阳慢慢沉落在闪着雪光的原野上，暴风雪过去了，而我呢，又必须把自己关进我那笼子里去……

再见！阿尔伯特和你在一起吗？你究竟过得……上帝饶恕我提这个问题！

二月八日

八天来天气坏得不能再坏，但对于我却太好啦。须知，自从我到此地以后，还没有一个天气好的日子不是让人破坏了或者搞得不痛快的。“哈，这会儿你尽管下雨、飞雪、降霜、结冰好了，”我想，“我反正待在屋子里也不会比外面坏，或者恰恰相反，倒好一些。”每当早上太阳升起，预示着有一个好日子的时候，我便忍不住要嚷：“今儿个上帝又降了一个恩惠，好让他们去你抢我夺啦！”他们互相抢夺着健康、荣誉、欢乐和休息，而且这样做多半是出于愚昧无知和心胸狭隘；可你要听他们讲起来，存心却又像好得不能再好了。我有时真想跪下去求他们，别这么发疯似的大动肝火好不好。

二月十七日

我担心，我的公使与我共事不长了。这个简直叫你受不了。他办公和处理问题的方式十分可笑，我常常禁不住要讲出自己的看法来，或者干脆按照自己的想法和方式行事，结果自然从来不能令他满意。最近他到宫里去告了我，部长也就给了我一个申斥，虽说相当和缓，但申斥毕竟是申斥。我已准备提出辞呈，这当口却收到了他的一封亲笔信[1]；这是一封怎样的信呵！在它所包含的崇高、高尚和英明的思想面前，我不能不五体投地。他责备我有失偏激。他说，我对办事效率、对影响他人、对干预政务等等问题的想法，固然表现了年轻人的朝气，值得尊重，但是却操之过急；因此，他并不准备叫我打消这些想法，而只希望使它们和缓一点，只希望引导它们，让它们发挥好影响，产生积极切实的作用。真的，有八天之久，我感到深受鼓舞，心情格外舒畅。内心的平静确是一件珍宝，简直就是欢乐本身。亲爱的朋友，要是这珍宝既贵重美丽，又不易破碎就好喽！

二月二十日

上帝保佑你们，亲爱的朋友！愿他把他从我这儿夺去的好日子，统统赐予你们吧。

我感谢你，阿尔伯特，感谢你瞒着我。我一直等着你们结婚的消息；我已下定决心，一当这大喜的日子到来，就将郑重其事地从墙上把绿蒂那张剪影像取掉，藏到其他画片中间去。喏，眼下你们已经成为眷属，可她的像仍然挂在这里；…是的，还要让它一直挂下去！为什么不呢？我知道，我也仍然存在于你们那儿，存在于绿蒂心中，但并未妨碍你，是的，我在她心中占据着第二个位置，并且希望和必须把这个位置保持下去。呵，要是她把我忘了，我就会发疯的……这个想法太可怕，阿尔伯特。再见，阿尔伯特！再见，绿蒂，我的天使！

三月十五日

我触了一个霉头，看起来是非离开此地不可啦。我咬牙切齿！见鬼！事情绝无补救，而要怨就只能怨你们。是你们鼓动我，催促我，折磨我，使我接受了这份与我性情不合的差事。这下我可好了！这下你们可好了！为了不让你讲什么又是我思想偏激才把一切弄糟了的，现在我请你，亲爱的先生，听听下面这段简短有趣的故事，它将是原原本本的纪实。

C伯爵喜欢我，器重我，这你知道，我已经对你讲过上百遍了。就在昨天，我在他府上吃饭，可没想到正巧碰着个当地的贵族男女晚上要来他家聚会的日子；再说我也从来没留心，像我们这样的小人物是不容插足他们的集会的。好啦。我在伯爵府上吃饭，饭后我们在大厅中踱起步来，我和伯爵谈话，和一位后来的上校谈话，不知不觉间聚会的时候就到了。天晓得，我却压根儿没想到呵。这当口，最最高贵的封·S太太率领着自己的丈夫老爷以及她那只孵化得很好的小鹅——一位胸部扁平、纤腰迷人的千金走进来了，并且在经过我身边时高高扬着他们那世袭贵族的眼睛和鼻孔。我打心眼儿里讨厌这号人，因此打算一等伯爵与他们寒暄完就去向他告辞，谁知这时我那B小姐又进来了。我每次一见她总感几分欣喜，便留下来，站在她的椅子背后，过了好一会儿才发现她和我交谈不如平时随便，样子也颇尴尬。我觉得奇怪。“原来她也跟那班家伙一样哩。”我暗想，不禁生起气来，准备马上走；可我仍留下了，因为我很希望是错怪了她，不相信她真会如此，希望能从她口里听见一句好话，并且……谁知还希望什么。这其间，聚会的人已经到齐：有穿戴着参加弗朗茨一世[2]加冕时的全套盛装的F男爵，有带着自己的聋子老婆、在这种场合被郑重地称为封·R大人的宫廷顾问R等等，此外，还不应忘记提到捉襟见肘的J，他在自己满是窟窿的老古董礼服上，打着许多时新的补丁。聚到一块儿的就是这种人物。我与其中几个我认识的攀谈，他们全都爱理不理。我想……我只留心着我的B小姐，没注意到女人们都凑到大厅的头上，在那儿叽叽咕咕地咬耳朵；没注意到，后来男人们也受了传染；没注意到，封·S夫人一个劲地在对伯爵讲什么（这些情形全是事后B小姐告诉我的），直到伯爵终于向我走来，把我领到一扇窗户跟前。

“您了解我们的特殊处境，”他说，“我发现，参加聚会的各位对您在场感到不满。我本人可是说什么也不想……”

“阁下，”我抢过话头说，“千万请您原谅；我早该想到才是呵。不过我知道，您会恕我失礼的。我本早想告辞，却让一个恶灵给留住了。”我微笑着补充道，同时鞠了一躬。

伯爵含意深长地紧紧握着我的手。我不声不响地出了一帮贵族聚会的大厅，到得门外，坐上一辆轻便马车，向着M地驶去。在那儿，我一边从山上观赏落日，一边读着我的荷马，听他歌唱俄底修斯如何受着好客的牧猪人的款待。一切都是如此的美好啊。

傍晚回寓所吃饭，在客厅里只剩几个人。他们挤在一个角落里掷骰子，把桌布都翻了起去。这当儿为人诚恳的阿德林走进来，脱下帽子，一见我就靠拢来低声说：

“你碰钉子了？”

“我？”我问。

“可不是，伯爵把你从集会里赶出来啦。”

“见他们的鬼去！”我说，“我倒宁肯出来呼吸呼吸新鲜空气哪。”

“这样就好，你能不在乎。”他说，“可令我讨厌的是，眼下已经闹得满城风雨。”

到这时候，我才感觉不自在起来。所有来进餐的人都盯着我瞧，我想原因就在这里吧！这才叫恼人呵。

甚至在今天，我走到哪儿，哪儿的人都对我表示同情；我还听见一些本来嫉恨我的人洋洋得意地讲：“这下瞧见了，那种妄自尊大的家伙会有怎样的下场。他们凭着点小聪明就自以为了不起，把一切全不放在眼中……”诸如此类的混账话还有的是。我真恨不得抓起刀来，刺进自己的心窝里去；要知道你们尽可以说什么自行其是，不予理睬，可我倒想看看，有谁能忍受占了上风的无赖们对自己说东道西。他们的话要是凭空捏造，唉，那倒也罢了。

三月十六日

所有的事情都叫我生气。今天我在大街上碰见B小姐，忍不住招呼了她。一当我们离开人群远了点，我就向她发泄对她最近那次态度的不满。

“呵，维特，”她语气亲切地说，“既然你了解我的心，怎么还能这样解释我当时的狼狈不安呢？从跨进大厅的一刻起，我就多么为你难受啊！我已预见到后来发生的一切，话到舌头无数次，只差对你讲出来。我知道，封·S和封·T宁肯带着她们的男人退场，也不愿和你在一起。我知道，伯爵也不好得罪他们……眼下可热闹啦！”

“眼下怎样了，B小姐？”我问，同时掩饰着内心的恐惧；而前天阿德林给我讲的一切，此刻就像沸腾的开水似地在我血管里急速流动起来。

“你可害得我好苦呵！”说着说着，可爱的人儿眼里就噙满了泪水。

我再控制不住自己，已准备跪倒在她脚下。

“请你有话就说出来吧。”我嚷道。

泪珠顺着她的脸颊往下淌，我完全失去了自制。她擦着眼泪，一点没有掩饰的意思。

“你知道我姑妈，”她开始讲，“当时她也在场，并且以怎样的目光盯着你哟！维特，我昨天晚上好不容易才熬过来，今儿一天又为和你交往挨了一顿训。我还不得不听着她贬低你，辱骂你，一点不能为你辩解，不好为你辩解。”

B小姐说的每一句话，都像剑一样刺痛我的心。她体会不到，如果不提这一切对我来说是多么大的仁慈。现在她又告诉我人家还有哪些流言蜚语，以及谁谁谁将因此洋洋得意。她说，那些早就指责我傲气和目中无人的家伙，眼下对于我受的报应真是心花怒放，乐不可支。听着她，威廉，听着她以怀着真诚同情的声调讲这些……我当时气得肺都炸了，眼下也仍然怒火中烧。我那会儿真希望有谁站出来指责我，这样我便可以一刀戳穿他；也许见了血，我的心中会好受些。呵，我曾上百次地抓起刀来，想要刺破自己的胸膛，以舒心中的闷气。人说有一种宝马，当骑手驱赶过急，它便会本能地咬破自己的血管，使呼吸变得舒畅一些。我的情形经常也就如此，真巴不得切开自己的一条动脉，以便获得永远的自由。

三月二十四日

我已向宫里要求辞职，希望能得到批准；我没有事先征得你们同意，谅必你们不会怪罪我吧。我反正是非走不可了；而你们为劝我留下可能说的话，我也都知道……对了，请你把此事尽可能委婉地告诉我母亲，我自己已是无计可施，如果不能使她称心，那就只有求她原谅。自然，这必定会叫她难过：眼看自己儿子业已开始的做枢密顾问和公使的美好前程就此断送，前功尽弃！你们爱怎么想就怎么想好了，任随想出几多我可以留下和应该留下的理由，一句话，我反正得走。为了让你们知道我的去向，我就告诉你，这儿有一位侯爵，他很乐于和我结交。当他得知我辞职的打算以后，便邀我到他猎庄上去，和他共度明媚的春天。他答应到时候让我自便，加之我们在一起还相互有某种程度的理解，我就想碰碰运气，随他一块儿去。

[1] 由于对这位杰出人物的尊敬，编者从书里抽去了这封信以及后文提到的别一封信；因为编者认为，不这样未免冒失，就算能得到读者的热诚感谢吧，也仍然是不可原谅的。——作者注

[2] 弗朗茨一世（Franz der Erste，1708—1765），“德意志民族的神圣罗马帝国”的皇帝，1745年加冕。

补记

四月十九日

感谢你的两封来信。我迟迟未作回答，是因为我把这封信压下了，一直等到辞呈批下来；我担心母亲会去找部长，使我的打算难以实现。眼下可好了，辞呈已经摆在面前。我不想告诉你们，上边是多么不愿意批准它，以及部长在信中写了些什么话；否则，你们又该抱怨开来。亲王赠我二十五个杜卡盾，作为解职金，我感动得几乎掉下泪来。这就是说，我不需要母亲再寄给我最近信上要的那笔钱了。

五月五日

我明天就要离开这儿；因为我的故乡离途经的某地只有六英里，我于是打算再去看看它，回忆回忆那些业已逝去的充满幸福梦想的日子。想当年，父亲故去以后，母亲领着我离开可爱的家园，把自己关进了城里；如今我又要走进她曾领着我出来的同一道门里去。再见，威廉，我在途中会给你写信的。

五月九日

我怀着朝圣者的虔敬心情，完成了我的故乡之行；一些意想不到的情感曾在我心中油然而生。在出城向S地走一刻钟处的那株大菩提树旁，我叫车夫停了下来。我下了车，打发邮车继续往前走，自己准备步行，以便随心所欲地唤起对往事的回忆，尽情地加以重温。瞧我又站在这株菩提树下啦！儿时，我曾无数次地以它为散步的终点和目的。世事无常！当初，无知而幸福的我多么渴望到那陌生的世界里去，为我的心寻找丰富的营养，无尽的享受，使我郁闷焦躁的胸怀得以舒畅，得到满足；如今，我从广大的世界上归来，我的朋友呵，可希望已一个个破灭，理想也尽皆消亡！

我看见那些山峰仍兀立眼前，我曾多少次希望去攀登它们呵！我曾几小时几小时地坐在这菩提树下，心儿却已飞过山去，尽情地神游在山后的森林与峡谷中；在我眼里，它们显得如此亲切，如此神秘。每当到了回家的时刻，我又多么恋恋不舍，不愿离开这可爱的所在呵！

离城渐渐近了。所有古老的、熟悉的花园小屋都得到了我的问候，而新建的却令我反感，一如其他所有由人造成的变化。我穿过城门，一下子就感觉自己到了家。好朋友，我不想细谈；这些对我具有极大魅力的事物，讲出来却会十分单调乏味。我决定下榻在市集广场上，紧靠着我们家的老屋。我在散步时发现，我们被一位认真的老太太塞在里边度过了童年时代的教室，如今已变成一家杂货铺。我回味着在这间小屋里经历过的不安，悲伤，迷惘和恐惧。——几乎每跨一步，我都能遇上吸引我注意的事物；即使一个朝圣者到了圣城，也找不到如许多值得纪念的地方，他的心也很难充满如许多神圣的激情呵。——仅再举千百件经历中的一件为例。我沿河而下，走到了有一个农场的地方；从前我也常来这儿，我们男孩子们练习用扁平的石块在河面上打水漂儿。我还记忆犹新的是，我有时站在江边目送着江水，心中充满了奇妙的预感，脑子里想象着江水正要流去的不可思议的地域，但很快便发现自己的想象力到了尽头；尽管如此，我仍然努力想下去，直到终于忘情在一个看不见的远方。——你瞧，朋友，我们那些杰出的祖先尽管孤陋寡闻，却也非常幸福！他们的感情和诗是那么天真！当俄底修斯讲到无垠的大海和无边的大地时，他的话是那么真实、感人、诚挚、幼稚而又十分神秘。现在，我可以和每一个学童讲，地球是圆的，可这对我又有何用处呢？人只需要小小一块土地，便可以在上边安安乐乐；而为了得到安息，他所需的地方就更小了。

眼下我已住在侯爵的猎庄上。这位爵爷待人真诚随和，倒也十分好处。可在他周围，却有一些令我简直莫名其妙的怪人。他们似乎并非奸诈之徒，但又没有正派人的样子。有时候，我也觉得他们是诚实的，但仍不能予以信赖。最令我感觉不快的是，侯爵经常人云亦云，高谈阔论，讲一些听到和读到的东西。

再说，他之重视我的智慧和才气，也胜过重视我的心；殊不知我的心才是我唯一的骄傲，才是我的一切力量、一切幸福、一切痛苦以及一切一切的唯一源泉！唉，我知道的东西谁都可以知道；而我的心却为我所独有。

五月二十五日

我脑子里有过一个计划；但在它实现以前，我本不想告诉你。现在反正不会成功，说说也无妨。我曾经希望去从军！这个想法在我心中久已有之；我所以追随侯爵来到他庄上，主要目的也在于此，因为他是×××地方的现役将军。一次在散步时，我把自己的打算透露给他；他劝我打消这个念头，说除非我真的有此热情，而不是一时胡思乱想，否则我就必须听从他的规劝。

六月十一日

随你讲什么吧，反正我是待不下去了。你要我在这儿干吗呢？日子长得叫我难过。至于侯爵，他待我要说多好有多好，可我仍然感到不自在。归根到底，我们之间毫无共同之处。他是个有理解力的人，但也仅仅是平平庸庸的理解力罢了；与他交往带给我的愉快，不见得比读一本好书来得多。我打算再待八天，然后又四处漂泊去。我在此间干的最有意义的事是作画。侯爵颇具艺术感受力；他要不是受讨厌的科学概念和流行术语的局限，对艺术的理解就会更深刻一些。有不少次，正当我兴致勃勃地领着他在自然与艺术之宫中畅游，他却突然自作聪明，从嘴里冒出一句艺术行话来，把直我恨得牙痒痒的。

六月十六日

唉，我不过是个漂泊者，是个在地球上来去匆匆的过客！难道你们就不是么？

六月十八日

我打算去哪儿？让我对你说实话吧。我不得不在此地再逗留十四天，然后准备考虑去参观×地的一些矿井；但参观矿井压根儿不算回事，目的还是想借此离绿蒂近一些，如此而已。我自己也不禁笑起自己这颗心来；但笑尽管笑，却仍然迁就了它。

七月二十九日

不，这样很好！好得无以复加！……我……她的丈夫！呵，上帝，是你创造了我，要是你还给了我这么个福分，那我这一生除了向你祈祷以外，便什么也不再做。我不想反抗命运，饶恕我的这些眼泪，饶恕我的这些痴心妄想吧！——她做我的妻子！要是我能拥抱这个天底下最可爱的人儿，那我就……

每当阿尔伯特搂住她纤腰的时候，呵，威廉，我的全身便会不寒而栗。

然而，我可以道出真情吗，威廉？为什么不可以？她和我在一起会比和他在一起幸福啊！他不是那个能满足她心中所有愿望的人。他这人缺乏敏感，缺乏某种……随你怎么理解吧，总之，在读到一本好书的某个片断时，他的心不会产生强烈的共鸣，像我的心和绿蒂的心那样；还有，经常地，当我们发表对另外某个人的行为的感想时，情况同样如此。亲爱的威廉！他虽说也专心一意地爱着她，但这样的爱尽可以获得任何别的报偿啊！

一个讨厌的来访者打断了我。我的泪水已经擦干，心也乱了。再见，好朋友！

八月四日

不只我一个人的处境是这样。所有的人都失望了，所有的人都遭到了命运的欺骗！我去看望住在菩提树下那位贤惠的妇人。她的大儿子跑上来迎接我；听见他的欢叫声，母亲也走了出来，一副垂头丧气的模样。她第一句话就告诉我：“先生，我的汉斯已经死了”——汉斯是她最小的一个儿子。我无言以对。——“还有我的丈夫，”她继续说，“他也两手空空地从瑞士回家来，要不是遇着些好人，他不讨饭才怪哩。他在半道上得了寒热病。”——我不知对她说什么好，只送了一点儿钱给她的小孩；她请我收下几只苹果，我接过了，带着忧伤的回忆离开了那地方。

八月二十一日

一眨眼，我的境况完全变了。有几次，我眼前又闪现过生活的欢愉的光辉，可惜转瞬即逝！——每当我堕入忘我的梦幻中，我便禁不住产生一个想法：“要是阿尔伯特死了又将怎样呢？你会的！是的，她也会……”随后，我便跟着自己的胡思乱想追去，直至被领到悬崖边上，吓得浑身战栗着往后退。

我出得门来，循着当初去接绿蒂参加舞会的大路走啊走啊，可是已经面目全非！一切已如过眼云烟！没有留下昔日世界的一丝痕迹，半缕情绪。我的心境恰似一个回到自己宫堡中来的幽灵：想当初，他身为显赫的王侯，建造了这座宫堡，对它极尽豪华装饰之能事，后来临终时又满怀希望地把它遗留给自己的爱子；看眼前，昔日的辉煌建筑已烧成一片废墟。

九月三日

我有时真不能理解，怎么还有另一个人能够爱她，可以爱她；要知道我爱她爱得如此专一，如此深沉，如此毫无保留，除她以外，我就什么也不知道，什么也不了解，什么也没有了呵！

九月四日

是的，就是这样，正如自然界已转入秋天，我的心中和我的周围也已一派秋意。我的树叶即将枯黄，而邻近我的那些树木却在落叶了。我上次刚到此地，不是对你讲过一个青年农民么？这次在瓦尔海姆我又打听他的情况，人家告诉我，他已被解雇了；此外就谁也不肯再讲什么。昨天，在通往邻村的路上，我碰见他，与他打招呼，他于是给我讲了他的故事。要是我现在再讲给你听，你将很容易理解，这个故事为何令我感动不已。可是，我干吗要讲这一切，干吗不把所有令我担忧、令我难受的事情藏在自己心中，而要让你和我一样不痛快呢？干吗我要给你一次一次机会，让你来怜悯我，骂我呢？随它去吧，这也许是我命中注定了的！

经我问起，这青年农民才带着默默的哀愁——我看还有几分羞怯——讲起他自己的事。但一讲开，他就突然像重新认识了自己和我似的，态度变得坦率起来，向我承认了自己的错误，并开始抱怨他的不幸。我的朋友，我现在请你来判断他的每一句话吧！

他承认，不，他是带着一种回忆往事的甜蜜和幸福的神情在追述，他对自己女东家的感情如何与日俱增，弄到后来六神无主，不知道自己该做什么，该说什么。他吃不进，喝不下，睡不着，嗓子眼好似给堵住了一样。人家不让他做的事，他做了；人家吩咐他做的事，他又给忘了，恰像有个恶灵附了体。直到有一天，他知道她在阁楼上，便跟着追了去，或者更确切地说，被吸引了去。由于她怎么也不听他的请求，他自己也不知怎么搞的，竟想对她动起蛮来；不过上帝做证，他对她的存心始终是正大光明的，别无其他欲念，只是想娶她做老婆，让她和他一起过日子而已。因为已经讲了相当久，他开始结巴起来，就像一个还有话讲但又不好说出口的人似的。最后，他还是很难为情地向我坦白，她允许了他对自己作一些小小的亲热表示，让他成为她的知己。他曾两三次中断叙述，插进来反复申辩说，他讲这些不是想败坏她的名誉；他并且表示，他仍像过去一样地爱她，尊重她，要不是为了叫我相信他并非完全是个头脑发昏的家伙，他才不会把这些事泄露出来哪。

喏，好朋友，我又要重弹我永远弹不厌的老调了：要是我能让你想象出这当时站在我跟前、眼下也仍像站在我跟前的人是个啥样子，那该多好呵！要是我能正确地讲述一切，让你感觉出我是如何同情他的命运，不得不同情他的命运，那该多好呵！总之，由于你了解我的命运，也了解我本人，你就会十分清楚地知道，是什么使我的心向着一切不幸者，尤其是这个不幸的青年农民。

我在重读此信时，发现忘记了讲故事的结尾；而结尾如何，是很容易猜想的。女东家没有同意他，她的兄弟也插了手。此人早就恨他，早就巴不得把他撵走，生怕自己姐姐一改嫁，他的孩子们就会失去财产继承权；她本身没有子女，所以他们眼下是大有望头的。这位舅老爷不久便赶走了年轻人，并且大肆张扬，闹得女东家本人即便再想找他回去也不可能了。眼下她已另雇了一个长工；而为着这个长工，据说她又和自己的弟弟吵翻了，人家断定她会嫁给他，可她弟弟却死活不答应。

我对你讲的一切绝无夸大，绝无涂脂抹粉；相反，倒可以说讲得不好，不来劲儿，而且是用我们听惯了的无伤大雅的语言在讲，也就失去了原有的情致。

这样的爱情，这样的忠心，这样的热诚，才不是诗人杜撰得出来的哩！如此纯真的情感，只存在于那个被我们称为没教养的、粗鲁的阶级中。我们这些有教养的人，实际上是被教养成了一塌糊涂的人！毕恭毕敬地读读这个故事吧，我求你。今天我由于写下了它，心情格外平静；再说，你从我的字迹也看得出，我可不是像平时那样心慌意乱，信手涂鸦的呵。读吧，亲爱的威廉，并且在读的时候想着，这也是你的朋友的故事。可不是么，我过去的遭遇和他一样，将来也会一样；只是我不如这个穷苦的不幸者的一半勇敢，一半坚决，我几乎没有拿自己与他相比的勇气。

九月五日

她的丈夫在乡下办事，她写了一张便条给他，开头一句是：

“亲爱的，我的好人，你赶快回来吧，我怀着无比的喜悦期待着你。”

碰巧一位朋友带来消息，说他有些事务未了，不能马上回来。这样字条便一直摆到桌上，当晚落到了我的手里。我读着读着就微笑了。她问我笑什么。

“人的想象力真是神赐的礼物。”我脱口说出，“我有一会儿恍惚觉得，它就是写给我的。”

她听了不再言语，样子似乎不高兴；我也只好沉默下来。

九月六日

我好不容易才下定决心，脱掉我第一次带绿蒂跳舞时穿的那件青色燕尾服；它式样简朴，穿到最后简直看不得了。我又让裁缝完全照样做了一件，同样的领子，同样的袖头，再配上一式的黄背心和黄裤子。

可新做的总不能完全称我的心。我不知道……我想，过段时间也许会好一点吧。

九月十二日

为了接阿尔伯特，她出门去了几天，今天我一跨进她房间，她便迎面走来，我于是高高兴兴地吻了她的手。

从镜台旁飞来一只金丝雀，落在她的肩上。

“一个新朋友，”她一边说，一边把雀儿逗到她手上，“是送给小家伙们的。你瞧多可爱！你瞧！每次我喂它面包，它都扑打双翅，小喙儿啄起来可真灵巧。它还和我接吻哩，你瞧！”

她说着便把嘴唇伸给金丝雀，这鸟儿也将自己的小喙子凑到她的芳唇上，仿佛确曾感受到了自己所享受的幸福似的。

“让它也吻吻你吧。”绿蒂道，同时把金丝雀递过来。

这鸟喙儿在她的嘴唇和我的嘴唇之间起了沟通作用，和它轻轻一接触，我仿佛就吸到了她的芳泽，心中顿时充满甜美无比的预感。

“它和你接吻并非毫无贪求，”我说，“它是在寻找食粮，光亲热一下会令它失望而去的。”

“它也从我嘴里吃东西。”她说，——她真就用嘴唇衔着几片面包屑递给它；在她那嘴唇上，洋溢着最天真无邪和愉快幸福的笑意。

我转开了脸。她真不该这样做啊！不该用如此天真无邪而又令人销魂的场面，来刺激我的想象力，把我这颗有时已由对生活的淡漠摇得入睡了的心重又唤醒！——为什么不该呢？——她是如此信赖我！她知道，我是多么爱她！

九月十五日

我真给气疯了，威廉，世上还有点价值的东西本已不多，可是人们仍不懂得爱护珍惜。你知道那两株美丽的胡桃树，那两株我和绿蒂去拜访一位善良的老牧师时曾在它们底下坐过的胡桃树！一想到这两株树，上帝知道，我心中便会充满最大的快乐！它们把牧师家的院子变得多么幽静，多么阴凉呵！它们的枝干是那样挺拔！看着这两株树，自然便会怀念许多年前栽种它们的那两位可敬的牧师。乡村学校的一个教员向我们多次提到他俩中一位的名字，这名字还是他从自己祖父口里听来的。人都讲了，这位牧师是个很好的人；每当走到树下，你对他的怀念便会显得神圣起来。告诉你，威廉，当我们昨天谈到这两株树已给人砍了的时候，教员就已眼泪汪汪的。砍掉了！我气得几乎发疯，恨不得把那个砍第一斧头的狗东西给宰啦。说到我这个人，那真是只要看见自己院子里长的树中有一棵快老死了，心里也会难过得要命。可也有一件，亲爱的朋友，人们到底还是有感情的！全村老小都抱怨连天；我真希望牧师娘子能从奶油、鸡蛋以及其他东西上感觉出，她给村子造成了多大的伤害。因为这个新牧师的老婆（我们的老牧师已经去世），一个瘦削而多病的女人，她有一切理由不喜欢这个世界，世人中也没有一个喜欢她；而她正是砍树的罪魁。这个自命博学的蠢女人，她还混在研究《圣经》的行列里，起劲地要对基督教进行一次新式的、合乎道德的改革，对拉瓦特尔的狂热不以为然；她的健康状况糟透了，因此在人世上全无欢乐可言。也只有这样一个家伙，才可能干出砍树的勾当来。你瞧我这气真是平不了啦！试想一想，就因为什么树叶掉下来会弄脏弄臭她的院子，树顶会挡住她的阳光，还有胡桃熟了孩子们会扔石头去打等等，据说这些都有害于她的神经，妨碍她专心思考，妨碍她在肯尼柯特[1]、塞姆勒[2]和米夏厄里斯[3]之间进行比较权衡。我看见村民们特别是老人如此不满，便问：“你们当时怎么竟听任人家砍了呢？”

他们回答：“在我们这地方，只要村长想干什么，你就毫无办法。”

可有一点倒也公平：牧师从自己老婆的怪癖中从未得到过甜头，这次竟想捞点好处，打算与村长平分卖树的钱；谁知镇公所知道了说，请把树送到这儿来吧！因为镇公所对长着这两棵树的牧师宅院从来拥有产权，便将它们卖给了出价最高的人。树反正砍倒啦！呵，可惜我不是侯爵！否则我真想把牧师娘子、村长和镇公所统统给……侯爵！……可我要真是侯爵，哪儿还会关心自己领地内的那些树啊？

十月十日

每当我看见她那双黑眼睛，我心中便十分快乐！使我感到不安的是，阿尔伯特似乎并不那么幸福，不像他希望……不如我自以为会……要是我……

我本不爱用删节号，但在这儿没有其他办法表达自己的意思；即使如此，我想也说得够清楚了。

十月十二日

莪相已从我心中把荷马排挤出去。这位杰出的诗人领我走进了一个何等样的世界呵！我漂泊在荒野里，四周狂风呼啸，只见在朦胧的月光下，狂风吹开弥漫的浓雾，现出了先人的幽灵。我听见从山上送来的林涛声中，夹杂着洞穴里幽灵们的咽咽哭声，以及在她的爱人——那高贵的战死者长满青苔的坟茔上哭得死去活来的少女的泣诉。蓦然间，我瞅见了他，瞅见了在荒野里寻觅自己祖先的足迹的白发行吟诗人；可他找到的，唉，却只是他们的墓碑。随后，他叹息着仰望夜空中灿烂的金星，发现它正要沉入波涛汹涌的大海，而往昔的时光便活现在他英雄的心中；要知道这和蔼的星光也曾照临过勇士们的险途，这明月也曾辉耀过他们凯旋归来时扎着花环的战船啊。在白发诗人的额间，我发现了深深的苦闷；我看见这最后一位孤独的伟人，他正精疲力竭地向着自己的坟墓蹒跚行去，一边不断地从已故亲人的虚幻无力的存在中吸取令人感到灼痛的欢乐，俯视着冰冷的土地和在狂风中摇曳不定的深草，一边口里呼道：“有个漂泊者将会到来，他曾见过我的美好青春；他将会问：‘那位歌手在哪里？芬戈[4]杰出的儿子在哪里？’他的脚步将踏过我的坟头，他将在大地上四处将我寻索，但却找不着我。”

啊，朋友！我真愿像一位忠诚的卫士拔出剑来，一下子结果我这位君王的性命，以免除他慢慢死去的痉挛的痛苦，然后再让我的灵魂去追随这位获得解放的半神。

十月十九日

多么空虚啊！我的胸口里觉得可怕的空虚！——我常常想，哪怕你能把她拥抱在心口一次，仅仅一次，这整个的空虚就会填满了。

十月二十六日

是的，好朋友，我将会确信，越来越确信，一个人的生命的价值是很少的，非常非常少！一个女朋友来看绿蒂，我便退到隔壁房间，拿起一本书来读，却读不进去，随后又取过一支笔想写点什么。这当儿，我听见她们在低声交谈，相互报告一些不足道的事，无外乎谁谁结了婚，谁谁生了病、病得很重之类的本地要闻。

“她现在老是干咳，脸上颧骨这么高，还常常晕倒，我看是活不长喽。”客人说。

“那个N.N的情况也一样糟。”绿蒂应着。

“他已经浮肿了。”客人又讲。

听她俩这么聊着，我在想象中已去到那两个可怜人的病榻前，看见他们如何苦苦挣扎，留恋生命，如何……

可是，威廉呵，我这两位女士却满不在乎地谈着他们，就像谈一个素不相识者快死了似的！我环顾四周，打量着我所在的房间，打量着放在这儿那儿的绿蒂的衣物，阿尔伯特的文书，以及这些我现在已经十分熟悉的家具，乃至这个墨水池，心里不禁就想：“瞧，你现在对这个家庭有多么重要啊！太太重要了！你的朋友们敬重你。你常常带给他们快乐；而你的心里也觉得，似乎离了他们你就活不下去。可是——你要是这会儿走了，从他们的圈子里消失了，他们又将有多久会感到失去你给他们的生活造成了缺陷呢？多久？唉，人生才叫无常呵！他甚至在对自己的存在最有把握的地方，在留下了他存在的唯一真实印记的地方，在他的亲爱者的记忆中，在他们的心坎里，也注定了要熄灭，要消失，而且如此的快！

十月二十七日

人对人竟如此地缺少价值，一想起来我常常恨不得撕破自己的胸膛，砸碎自己的脑袋。唉，要是我不带来爱情、欢乐、温暖和幸福，人家就不会白白给我；另一方面，就算我心里充满了幸福，也不能使一个冷冰冰地、有气无力地站在我面前的人幸福啊。

同日晚

我具有再多精力，也会被对她的热情吞噬掉；我具有再多天赋，没有她一切都将化作乌有。

十月三十日

我已有上百次几乎就要拥抱她了！伟大的主知道，当一个人面前摆着那么可爱的东西而又不能伸出手去攫取时，他心头会多难受。攫取本是人类最自然的欲望。婴儿不总是伸出小手抓他们喜爱的一切么？——可我呢？

十一月三日

上帝知道，我在上床时常常怀着这样一种希冀，是的，有时甚至是渴望，不要再醒来了吧！因此，第二天，当我早上睁开眼睛又见到太阳时，心里便异常难受。唉，要是我在心绪不佳时能怪天气，怪第三者，怪一件没做成功的事情，那也倒好，我身上的难受劲儿定会减少一半。多可悲啊，我的感觉千真万确，一切的过错全在我自己！——不，不是过错。总之，正如一度一切幸福的根源全存在于我本身，现在一切痛苦的根源也在我自己身上。当初，我满心欢喜地到处游逛，走到哪儿，哪儿就变成了天国，心胸开阔得可以容下整个宇宙，难道这个我不是同一个人么？可如今，…这颗心已经死去，从中再也涌流不出欣喜之情；我的眼睛枯涩了，再也不能以莹洁的泪水滋润我的感官；我的额头更是可怕地皱了起来。我痛苦之极；我已失去自己生命中唯一的欢乐，唯一神圣的、令我振奋的力量，我用它来创造自己周围的世界的力量，这力量业已消逝！

我眺望窗外远处的山岗，只见日光刺破岗上的浓雾，洒布在下面静静的草地上；在已经落叶的柳丝间，一条蜿蜒曲折的小河缓缓向我流来……呵，要是这如此美好的景色已像一幅漆画似的在我眼前凝滞不动，不能再娱悦我心，使它产生出丝毫的幸福感觉，那我这整个人在上帝面前不就成了一口干涸的水井，一只破底儿的水桶么。我常常扑倒在地，祈求上苍赐给我眼泪，就像一个头顶上是铁青色的天，四周是干裂的土地的农夫在祈雨一样。

但是，唉，我感觉到，上帝绝不会因为我们拼命哀求就赐给我们雨水和阳光！可那些我一回首就心里难过的过去的时光，它们为何又如此幸福呢？是因为那时我十分耐心地期待着他的精神来感召我，满怀感激地、专心一意地接受着他倾注到我身上的欢愉。

十一月八日

她责备我不知节制！啊，态度是如此温柔，亲切！说我不该每次一端起酒杯来就非喝一瓶不可。

“别这样，”她说，“想想你的绿蒂吧！”

“想！”我反驳道，“还用得着你叫我想吗？我在想啊！——不只是在想！你时刻都在我的心中。今天，我就坐在你不久前从马车上下来的那个地方……”

她引开话题，不让我讲下去。好朋友，我算完了！她想怎样处置我，就可以怎样处置。

十一月十五日

我感谢你，威廉，感谢你对我真诚的同情，感谢你的忠告；我请你放心，让我忍受下去吧，我尽管疲惫不堪，仍然有足够的力量支撑到底。我尊重宗教信仰，这你知道；我觉得，它是某些虚弱者的拐杖，奄奄一息的振奋剂。不过，它难道能够对人人都起这个作用么？必须对人人都起这个作用么？要是你看一看这个广大的世界，你就会发现有成千上万的人，对于他们来说宗教信仰并非如此，而且将来也不会如此，无论是旧教还是新教。难道我就非有宗教帮助不可么？圣子耶稣自己不是说过，只有那些天父交给他的人，才能生活在他周围么？要是天父没有把我交给他怎么办？要是如我的心所告诉我，天父希望把我留给自己怎么办？——我请你别误解我，别把这些诚心诚意的话看成是讽刺。我是在对你披肝沥胆，否则我就宁可沉默；因为，对于这一切大家和我一样都不甚了然的事情，我是很不乐意开口的。人不是命中注定要受完他那份罪，喝完他那杯苦酒吗？既然天堂里的上帝呷一口都觉得这酒太苦，我为什么就得充好汉，硬装作喝起来甜呢？此刻，我的整个生命都战栗于存在与虚无之间，过去像闪电似的照亮了未来的黯间深渊，我周围的一切都在沉沦，世界也将随我走向毁灭；在这样可怕的时刻，我还有什么可害羞的呢？那个被人压迫、孤立无助、注定沦亡的可怜虫，他在最后一刻不也鼓足力气从内心深处发出呼喊：“上帝啊，上帝！你干吗抛弃我？”[5]那么，我为何就该羞于流露自己的情感，就该害怕这位把天空像手帕一样卷起的神之子尚且不免的一刻呢？

十一月二十一日

她看不出，她感觉不到，她正在酿造一种将把我和她自己都毁掉的毒酒；而我呢，也满怀欣喜地接过她递过来置我于死地的酒杯，一饮而尽。为什么她要常常——常常吗？不，也不常常，而是有时候——为什么有时候她要那么温柔地望着我，要欣然接受我下意识的情感流露，要在额头上表现出对我的痛苦的同情呢？

昨天，当我离开时，她握着我的手说：“再见，亲爱的维特！”

亲爱的维特！这是破天荒第一次她叫我做亲爱的，叫得我周身筋骨都酥软了。我把这句话重复了无数次，等到夜里要上床睡觉时，还自言自语叨咕了半天，最后竟冒出一句：“晚安，亲爱的维特！”说罢自己禁不住笑起自己来。

十一月二十二日

我不能向上帝祈祷：“让她成为我的吧！”尽管如此，我却常常觉得她就是我的。我不能祈祷：“把她给我吧！”因为她属于另外一个人。我常常拿理智来克制自己的痛苦；可是，一当我松懈下来，我就会没完没了地反驳自己的理智。

十一月二十四日

她感觉到了我是多么痛苦。今天她对我的一瞥，深深地打动了我的心。当时我发现只有她一个人在；我沉默无语，她也久久地望着我。如今，我在她身上已见不到动人的妩媚，见不到智慧的光辉；这一切在我眼前业已消失。她现在打动我的，是一种美好得多的目光，是一种饱含着无比亲切的同情、无比甜蜜的怜悯的目光。为什么我不可以跪倒在她脚下呢？为什么我不可以搂住她的脖子，以无数的亲吻来报答她呢？为了避开我的盯视，她坐到钢琴前，伴着琴声，用她那甜美、低婉的歌喉，轻轻唱起了一支和谐的歌。我从来还未看见她的嘴唇像这样迷人过；它们微微翕动着，恰似正在吸吮那清泉般从钢琴中涌流出来的一串串妙音；同时，从她的玉口内，也发现神奇的回响。——是的，要是我能用言语向你说清这情景就好了！我再也忍不住，便弯下腰去发誓说：可爱的嘴唇啊，我永远也不会冒昧地亲吻你们，因为你们是天界神灵浮泛的所在啊！——然而……我希望……哈，你瞧，这就像立在我灵魂前面的一道高墙……为了幸福我得翻过墙去……然后下地狱补赎罪过！——罪过？

十一月二十六日

我有时对自己讲：“你的命运反正就这样了；祝祷别人都幸福吧——还从来没谁像你这样受过苦哟。”随后，我便读一位古代诗人[6]的作品，读着读着，仿佛窥见了自己的心。我要受的罪真是太多了！唉，难道在我以前的人们都这样不幸过么？

十一月三十日

不，不，我注定振作不起来了！无论我走到哪里，都会碰见叫我心神不定的事情。比如今天吧！呵，命运！呵，人类！

正午时分，我沿着河边散步，没有心思回去吃饭。四野一片荒凉，山前刮来阵阵湿冷的西风，灰色的雨云已经窜进峡谷里边。远远地，我瞅见一个穿着件破旧的绿色外套的人，在岩石间爬来爬去，像是正在采摘野花似的。我走到近旁，他听见脚步声便转过头来，模样十分怪异。脸上最主要的神情是难言的悲哀，但也透露着诚实与善良。黑色的头发用簪子在脑顶别成了两个卷儿，其余部分则编成一条大辫子拖在背后，看衣着是个地位低微的人。我想，他对我去过问他的事是不会见怪的，因此便与他搭起话来，问他找什么。

“找花呗，”他深深地叹了一口气，回答道，“可一朵也找不着。”

“眼下可不是找得到花的季节啊。”我说着微笑了。

“花倒是多得很。”他边讲边向我走下来，“在我家的园子里，长着玫瑰和两种忍冬花，其中一种是我爹送我的，长起来就跟野草一般快；我已经找了它两天，就是找不着。这外边也总开着花，黄的，蓝的，红的，还有那矢车菊的小花儿才叫美呢。不知怎的我竟一朵也找不到……”

我感到有些蹊跷，便绕个弯儿问：“你要这些花干吗呢？”

他脸上一抽动，闪过一丝古怪的笑意。

“您可别讲出去啊，”说时他把食指搁在嘴唇上，“我答应了送给我那心上人儿一束花。”

“这很好嘛。”我说。

“嗬，”他道，“她有好多好多别的东西，可富着哪。”

“尽管这样，她还是一定喜欢您这束花。”我应着。

“嗬，”他接着讲，“她有许多宝石，还有一顶王冠。”

“她叫什么来着？”

“唉，要是联省共和国[7]雇了我，我就会是另一个人啦！”他说，“可不，有一阵子，我过得挺不错。现在不成了，现在我……”

他眼泪汪汪地抬起头来望着苍空，其他一切全明白了。

“这么说，您也曾经幸福过？”我问。

“唉，要能再像那时候一样就好喽！”他回答，“那时候，我舒服，愉快，自由自在，就跟水中的鱼儿似的！”

“亨利希！”这当儿一个老妇人喊着，循着大路走来，“亨利希，你在哪儿？我们到处找你，快回家吃饭吧！”

“他是您的儿子吗？”我走过去，问。

“可不，我的可怜的儿子！”她回答，“上帝罚我背了一个沉重的十字架啊。”

“他这样多久了？”我问。

“像这样安静才半年，”她说，“就这样还得感谢上帝。从前他一年到头都大吵大闹的，只好用链子锁在疯人院里。现在不招惹任何人了，只是还经常跟国王和皇帝们打交道。从前，他可是个又善良又沉静的人，能供养我，写得一手好字；后来突然沉思默想起来，接着又发高烧，高烧过后便疯了；现在便是您看见的这个样子。要是我把他的事讲给您听，先生……”

我打断她滔滔不绝的话，问：

“他说他曾经有一段时间很自在，很幸福，这指的是怎么一个时候呢？”

“这傻小子！”她怜悯地笑了笑，大声说，“他指的是他神志昏乱的那段时间，他常常夸耀它。当时，他关在疯人院里，精神完全失常了。”

这话于我犹如一声霹雳，我塞了一枚银币在老妇人手里，仓皇逃离了她的身边。

“你那时是幸福的呵！”我情不自禁地喊着，快步奔回城去，“那时候，你自在得如水中的游鱼！——天堂里的上帝，难道你注定人的命运就是如此：他只有在具有理智以前，或者重新丧失理智以后，才能是幸福的么？——可怜的人！但我又是多么羡慕你的精神失常，知觉紊乱呵！你满怀着希望到野外来，为你的女王采摘鲜花，在冬天里！你为采不到鲜花而难过，不理解为什么竟采不到。而我呢，从家里跑出来时既无目的，也无希望，眼下回家去时依然如此。你幻想着，要是联省共和国雇用你，你就将成为一个了不起的人。幸福啊，谁要能把自身的不幸归因于人世的障碍！你感觉不出，感觉不出，你的不幸原本存在于你破碎的心中，存在于你被搅乱了的头脑里；而这样的不幸，全世界所有的国王也帮你消除不了啊。”

谁要嘲笑一个病人到远方的圣水泉去求医，结果反倒加重自己的病痛，使余生变得更难忍受，谁就不得善终！谁要蔑视一个为摆脱良心的不安和灵魂的痛苦而去朝拜圣墓的人，谁同样不得善终！要知道这个朝圣者，他的脚掌在荆棘丛生的道路上踏下的每一步，对他充满恐惧的灵魂来说，都是一滴镇痛剂；他每坚持着朝前走一天，晚上躺下时心里都要轻松得多。——难道你们能把这称作是妄想么，你们这些舒舒服服坐在软垫子上的清谈家？——妄想！上帝呵，你看见我的眼泪了吧！你把人已经造的够可怜了，难道还一定得再给他一些兄弟，让他们来把他仅有的一点点东西，仅有的一点点对于你这博爱者的信任，也统统夺走么？要知道对于能治百病的仙草的信任，对于葡萄的眼泪[8]的信任，也就是对于你的信任，相信你能赋予我们周围的一切以治疗疾病和减轻痛苦的力量，而我无时无刻不需要这种力量。我所没有见过面的父亲呵，曾几何时，你使我的心灵那么充实，如今却又转过脸去不再理我！父亲呵，把我召唤到你身边去吧，别再沉默无语；你的沉默使我这颗焦渴的心再也受不了啦！难道一个人，一个父亲，在自己的儿子突然归来，搂住他的脖子喊叫“我回来了，父亲”的时候，他还能生气么？别生气，如果我中断了人生旅程，没有如你所希望的那样苦挨下去。举世无处不一个样：劳劳碌碌，辛辛苦苦，而后才是报酬和欢乐；可这于我有何意义？我只有在你所在之处才会得到安适，我愿意到你的面前来吃苦和享乐。——而你，仁慈的天父。难道会拒我于门外么？

十二月一日

威廉！我上次信中讲的那个人，那个幸福的不幸者，过去就是绿蒂的父亲的秘书。他对她起了恋慕之心，先是暗暗滋长着，隐藏着，后来终于表露出来，因此丢掉了差事，结果发了疯。这段话尽管是干巴巴的，但请你体会一下，这个故事是如何震动了我。我之所以写成像你读到的这个样子，因为阿尔伯特就是这样无动于衷地给我讲的。

十二月四日

我求求你……你听我说吧，我这个人完了，再也忍受不住了！今天我坐在她房里……我坐着，她弹着琴，弹了各式各样的曲子，可支支曲子全都触动了我的心事！全都！全都！……你看怎么办？……她的小妹妹在我怀里打扮布娃娃。热泪涌进我的眼眶。我低下头，目光落在她的结婚戒指上……我的泪水滚落下来……这当儿，她突然弹起那支熟悉而美妙的曲调，我的灵魂顿时感到极大的安慰，往事立刻一件件浮上心头，我回忆起了初次听见这支曲调的美好日子，想到了后来的暗淡时日，想起了最终的不快和失望，以及……我在房里来回急走。心儿紧迫得几至于窒息。

“看在上帝分上，”我嚷道，情绪激动地冲她跑去，“看在上帝分上，别弹啦！”

她停下来，怔怔地望着我！

“维特，”她笑吟吟地说，这笑一直刺进了我心里，“维特，你病得很厉害啊，连自己最喜爱的东西也讨厌起来了。回去吧，我求你安静安静！”

我一下从她身边跑开，并且……上帝呵，你看见了我的痛苦，请你快快结束它吧。

十二月六日

她的形象四处追逐着我！不论我醒着还是做梦，都充满我整个的心灵！现在，当我闭上眼睛，在这儿，在聚集着我的内视力的额头中，便显现出她那双黑色的眼眸来。就在这儿啊！我无法向你表达清楚。每当我一阖上眼，它们就出现在这里，在我面前，在我心中，静静地如一片海洋，一道深谷，填满了我额头里的所有感官。

人，这个受到赞美的半神，他究竟算什么！他不是在正好需要力量的当儿，却缺少力量么？当他在多些欢乐中向上飞升，或在痛苦中向下沉沦时，他都渴望自己能融进无穷的宇宙中去，可偏偏在这一刹那，他不是又会受到羁縻，重行恢复迟钝的、冰冷的意识么？

[1] 肯尼柯特（Benjamin Kennikot, 1718—1783），英国神学家。

[2] 塞姆勒（Johann Salomo Semler, 1725—1791），德国新教神学家。

[3] 米夏厄里斯（Johann David Michaelis, 1717—1791），德国神学家和东方学家。

[4] 芬戈（Fingoi）相传为三世纪时的苏格兰国王，据说莪相是他的儿子。

[5] 据基督教圣经载，这是耶稣被钉上十字架时讲的话。

[6] 指莪相。

[7] 联省共和国（die Ceneralstaaten），即十六世纪资产阶级革命成功后的尼德兰（今荷兰），当时在德国人心目中是最富有的国家。

[8] 指酒。

编者致读者

从我们的朋友值得注意的最后几天中，我本来非常希望有足够多的第一手资料留下来，这样，我就没必要在他遗留下来的书信中间，再插进自己的叙述了。

我竭尽全力从了解他经历的人们口中搜集确切的事实；他的故事很简单，人们讲的全都大同小异，不一样的只是对当事者们思想性格的说法和评议。

剩下来由我们做的，只是把经过反复努力才打听到的情况认真叙述出来，把死者留下的几封信插入其中，对找到的哪怕一张小纸片也不轻易放过；要知道事情是出在一些异乎寻常的人们中间，所以即使某个单独的行为的真正动机，要想揭示出来也极不容易。

愤懑与忧郁在维特心中越来越深地扎下了根，两者紧紧缠绕在一起，久而久之就控制了他的整个存在。他精神的和谐完全被摧毁了，内心烦躁得如烈火焚烧，把他各种天赋的力量统统搅乱，最后落得个心力交瘁。为了摆脱这苦境，他拼命挣扎，作出了比过去和种种灾祸作斗争时更大的努力。内心的忧惧消耗了余下的精神力量，他不再生气勃勃，聪敏机灵，变成了一个愁眉苦脸的客人，因此越发不幸，越不幸又变得越发任性起来。至少阿尔伯特的朋友们是这样讲的；他们认为，维特像个一天就要把全部财产花光、晚上只好吃苦挨饿的人，他对终于获得渴望已久的幸福的那个真诚稳重的丈夫，以及他力图在将来仍保持这个幸福的行为，都不能作出正确评价。他们说，阿尔伯特在这么短的一段时间里没有变，他仍然是维特一开始所认识、器重和尊敬的那样一个人。他爱绿蒂超过一切，他为她感到骄傲，希望别人承认她是最最可爱的女性。他不希望自己和她之间出现任何猜疑的阴影，他不乐意和任何人哪怕以最无邪的方式，仅仅在一瞬间共同占有这个宝贝，难道因此就能责怪他不成？他们承认，当有维特在他妻子房中的时候，阿尔伯特常常就走开了；但他这样做不是出于对朋友的敌视和反感，而只是因为他感觉到，他在跟前维特总是显得局促不安。

绿蒂的父亲染了病，只能躺在家里；他给她派来一辆马车，她便坐着出城去了。那是个美丽的冬日，刚下过一场大雪，田野全给盖上了白被。

维特次日一早就跟了去，以便在阿尔伯特不去接绿蒂的情况下，自己陪她回来。

晴朗的天气也很少改变他阴郁的情绪，他的心总感觉压抑难受，老有些可悲的景象萦绕在眼前，脑子里不断涌现出一个接一个的痛苦念头。

正如他始终对自己不满一样，别人的情况在他看来也就更加可虑，更加暧昧了。他确信，阿尔伯特夫妇之间的和谐关系已遭破坏，为此他不但自责，还暗暗地埋怨身为丈夫的阿尔伯特。

途中，他的思绪又回到了这个问题上。

“是啊，是啊，”他自言自语说，暗暗还在咬牙切齿，“这就叫亲切的、和蔼的、温柔的、富于同情心的态度！这就叫默默无言的、持久不变的忠诚！不，这是厌倦与冷漠！不是任何一件无聊的琐事，都比他忠实可爱的妻子更吸引他么？他知道珍惜自己的幸福吗？他知道给予她应得的尊重吗？可是，她好歹已是他的人，她好歹……我知道这个，我还知道别的事情；我已经惯于这样想，他将使我发疯，他还要结果了我。——他对我的友谊经得起考验吗？他不是已将我对绿蒂的眷恋视为对自己权利的侵犯么？将我对绿蒂的关心，视为对他的无声谴责么？我清楚知道，我感觉得出来，他不乐意看见我，他希望我走，我在这儿已成了他的累赘。”

维特一次次放慢脚步，一次次停下来，站着发呆，看样子已打算往回走了。然而，他终究还是继续往前走去，边走边思索，边走边唠叨，最后像是很不情愿地走到了猎庄门前。

他跨进大门，打听老人和绿蒂在哪里，发现屋子里的人都有些激动。最大的一个男孩告诉他，瓦尔海姆那边出了事，一个农民给人打死了！——这个新闻没有给维特留下多少印象。他走进里屋，发现绿蒂正在极力劝自己的父亲，叫老人不要拖着有病的身子去现场调查那件惨案。凶手是谁尚不得而知。有人早上在门口发现了受害者的尸体，估计就是那位寡妇后来的长工；她先前雇的那个是在心怀不满的情况下离开的。

维特一听马上跳了起来。

“完全可能！”他叫道，“我得去看看，一秒钟也不能等。”

他匆匆忙忙向瓦尔海姆奔去；途中，一桩桩往事又历历在目。他一刻也不怀疑，肇事者就是那个多次与他交谈、后来简直成了他知己的年轻人。

要走到停放尸体的那家小酒馆去，他必须从那几株菩提树下经过。一见这个曾经极为可爱的所在如今已面目全非，他心中不由一震。邻家的孩子们常常坐在上面游戏的那道门槛，眼下是一片血污。爱情与忠诚这些人类最美好的情操，已经蜕变成了暴力和仇杀。高大的菩提树没有叶，覆着霜；以前在公墓的矮墙上形成一片穹顶的美丽树篱如今光秃秃的，盖着雪的墓碑便从空隙中突露出来。

正当他走拢全村人都聚在跟前的小酒店的时候，突然腾起一阵喧闹。人们看见远远走来一队武装汉子，便异口同声喊着：“抓到啦！抓到啦！”——维特也朝那边望去，顿时便看得一清二楚：是他！是这个爱那位寡妇爱得发狂的青年长工；前不久，他带着一肚子气恼，垂头丧气地四处徘徊，维特还碰见过他。

“瞧你干的好事，不幸的人呵！”维特嚷叫着，向被捕者奔去。

这人呆呆地瞪着他，先不言语，临了却泰然自若地答道：“谁也别想娶她，她也别打算嫁给任何人。”

犯人被押进了酒店，维特仓皇离去。

这个可怕的、残酷的经历，猛地震动了他，使他的心完全乱了。霎时间，他像让人从自己悲哀、抑郁和冷漠的沉思中拖了出来，突然为一种不可抗拒的同情心所控制，因而产生了无论如何要挽救那个人的强烈欲望。他觉得他太不幸了，相信他即使成为罪人也仍然是无辜的。他把自己完全摆在他的地位上，确信能说服其他人同样相信他的无辜。他恨不能立刻为他辩护；他的脑子里已经装满有力的证词；他急匆匆向猎庄赶去，半道上就忍不住把准备向总管陈述的话低声讲了出来。

他一踏进房间，发现阿尔伯特也在场，情绪顿时就低落下来；但是他仍然打起精神，把自己的看法向总管讲了一遍，讲的时候情绪十分激昂。可总管却连连摇头；虽然维特把一个人替另一个人辩护所可能讲的全讲了，而且讲得如此情词恳切，娓娓动听，但结果显而易见，总管仍然无动于衷。他甚至不容我们的朋友把话讲完，就给以激烈的驳斥，责怪他不该袒护一个杀人犯！总管教训他说，依了他一切法律都得取消，国家的安全就得彻底完蛋。最后，总管还补充：在这样的事情上，自己除去负起最崇高的职责，一切按部就班、照章行事以外，便什么都不能干。

维特还是不甘心，不过只是再恳求老人说，希望他在有人出来帮助罪犯逃跑的情况下，能够睁一只眼闭一只眼！这个请求也遭到总管拒绝。这当儿，阿尔伯特终于插话了，他也站在老头子一边，叫维特再也开不得口。维特怀着难以忍受的痛苦走出房去；在此之前，总管一再告诉他：“不，他没有救了！”

这句话给了他多么沉重的打击，我们可以从一张显然是他当天写的字条看出来。我们在他的文书中找到了这张字条，上面写道：

你没有救了，不幸的朋友！我明白，咱们都没有救了！

至于阿尔伯特最后当着总管讲的关于罪犯的一席话，维特听了更是反感之极，甚至还以为发现了有几处影射自己的地方。因此，尽管他以自己的聪明，经过反复考虑，不至于看不出这两位的话可能有道理，他却不愿意承认这一点，似乎对他来说，一承认就意味着背弃自己的本性。

从他的文书中，我们还发现另一张字条，与这个问题有着关系，也许它能把维特对阿尔伯特的态度充分泄露给我们吧：

有什么用呢，尽管我反反复复地告诉自己，对自己讲：他是个好人，正派人！可是，我心乱如麻，叫我怎么公正得了呵。

在一个温暖的傍晚，雪已经开始消融，绿蒂随阿尔伯特步行回城去。途中，她东瞅瞅，西望望，像是少了维特的陪伴，心神不定似的。阿尔伯特开始谈他，在指责他的同时，仍不忘替他讲几句公道话。他谈到他那不幸的热情，希望能够想办法让他离开。

“为了我们自己，我也希望这样。”他说，“另外，我请求你，”他接着讲，“想法使他对你的态度改变一下，别让他这么老来看你。人家会注意的；再说据我了解，这儿那儿已有人在讲闲话啦。”

绿蒂默不作声；阿尔伯特似乎品出了她这沉默的味道，至少从此再没对她提到过维特，甚至当她自己再提到维特时，他也立刻中止谈话，要不就把话题引到一边去。

维特为救那个不幸者所作的无望的努力，是一股行将熄灭的火苗儿的最后一次闪动；自此，他便更深地沉浸在痛苦与无为中。特别是当他听说，法庭也许会传他去当证人，证明那个如今矢口否认自己罪行的青年确实有罪的时候，他更是气得快要疯了。

他在实际生活中遭遇的种种不快，在公使馆里的难堪，以及一切的失败，一切的屈辱，这时都统统在他心里上上下下翻腾开来。这一切的一切，都使他觉得自己的无所作为就是应该。他发现自己毫无出路，连赖以平平庸庸地生活下去的本领也没有。结果，他便一任自己古怪的感情、思想以及无休止的渴慕驱使，一个劲儿和那位温柔可爱的女子相周旋，毫无目的、毫无希望地耗费着自己的精力，既破坏了人家的安宁，又苦了自己，一天一天向着可悲的结局靠近。

下边我编进他遗留下来的几封信。他的迷惘，他的热情，他的无休止的向往与追求，以及他对人生的厌倦，统统将从这几封信得到有力的证明。

十二月十二日

亲爱的威廉，目前我处于一种坐卧不安的状态，就像人们说的那些被恶鬼驱赶着四处游荡的不幸者一样。有时，我心神不定；这既非恐惧，也非渴望，而是一种内心的莫名的狂躁，几乎像要撕裂我的胸脯，扼紧我的喉咙！难过哟，难过哟！于是，我只好奔出门来，在这严冬季节的可怕的夜里瞎跑一气。

昨天晚上，我又不得不出去。其时适逢突然到来的融雪天气，我听见河水在泛滥，一道道小溪在激涨，雪水从瓦尔海姆方向流来，窜进了我那可爱的峡谷里。夜里十一时我跑出家门。只见狂暴的山洪卷起旋涡，从悬崖顶上直冲下来，漫过田畴、草场、园篱和野地里的一切，把开阔的谷地变成了一片翻腾的海洋，狂风同时发出呼啸，那景象怕人极了！尤其是当月亮重新露出脸来，静静地枕在乌云上，我面前的激流在它可怖而迷人的清辉映照下，翻滚着，咆哮着，我更是不寒而栗，心中冷不防产生一个欲望！我面对深渊，张开双臂，心里想着：跳下去吧！跳下去吧！要是我能带着自己的不幸和痛苦，像奔腾的山洪似的冲下悬崖峭壁，这将是何等痛快哟！唉，我却抬不起腿来，没有把所有的苦难一举结束的勇气！——我的时辰还没有到，我觉着。威廉啊，我真恨不得跟狂风一块儿去驱散乌云，去遏止激流，哪怕为此得付出我的生命！唉，也许连这样的欢乐也不容一个遭受囚禁的人得到吧？

俯瞰着那株我俩曾在下边坐过的老柳树，我心里非常难过——草坪也被水淹了，老柳树也几乎认不出来了，威廉！“还有她家的那些草地，还有她家周围的整个地区！”我想，“我们的小亭子这会儿准让激流毁得面目全非了吧！”想到此，一线往昔的阳光射进了我的心田，宛如一个囚人梦见了羊群，梦见了草地，梦见了荣耀的升迁一般！——我挺立着，不再骂自己没有死的勇气。我本该……

唉，我现在又坐在这儿，恰似个从篱笆上拾取烂柴和沿门告化的穷老婆子，苟延残喘，得过且过，毫无乐趣。

十二月十四日

怎么回事，好朋友？我竟自己害怕起自己来了！难道我对她的爱，不是最神圣、最纯洁、最真挚的爱么？难道什么时候我心中怀有过该受惩罚的欲念么？——我不想起誓……可现在这些梦！呵，那班相信鬼神能跟我们捣乱的人，他们是太正确了！这一夜——讲起来我的嘴唇还在哆嗦——这一夜我把她搂在怀里，紧紧贴在自己心口，用千百次的亲吻堵住她那说着绵绵情话的嘴；我的目光完全沉溺在她那醉意朦胧的媚眼中！主啊，我在回忆这令人销魂的梦境时，心中仍感到幸福，这难道也该受罚么？绿蒂呵，绿蒂呵！——我已经完了！我神志昏乱，八天来一直糊里糊涂，眼睛里满是泪水。我到哪儿都不自在，又到哪儿都感到自在。我无所希望，无所欲求。看起来，我真该走了。

这期间，在上述的情况下，辞世的决心在维特的脑子里越来越坚定。自从回到绿蒂身边，他就一直把这看作最后的出路和希望；不过他对自己讲，不应操之过急，不应草率行事，必须怀着美好的信念，怀着尽可能宁静的决心，去走这一步。

下面这张在他的文稿中发现的纸条，看来是一封准备写给威廉的信，刚开了头，还不曾落日期。从这则残简中，可以窥见他的动摇和矛盾心情：

她的存在，她的命运以及她对我的命运的关切，从我业已干枯的眼里挤压出了最后的几滴泪水。

揭开帷幕，走到幕后去吧！一了百了，干吗还迟疑畏缩啊！因为不知道幕后是个什么情形么？因为这一去便回不来了么？也许还因为我们的灵智能预感到，那后边只有我们一无所知的黑暗和混沌吧。

维特终于和这个阴郁的念头一天天亲密起来，决心便更坚定、更不可改变了。下面这封他写给自己友人的意义双关的信，提供了一个证明。

十二月二十日

我感谢你的友情，威廉，感谢你对那句话作了这样的理解。是的，你说得对：我真该走了。只是你让我回到你们那儿来的建议，不完全合我的心意；无论如何我还想兜个圈子，尤其是天气还有希望冷一段时间，眼看路又会变得好走起来。你来接我我当然很感激；只是请你再推迟两个礼拜，等接到我的下一封信再说吧。千万别果子没熟就摘呵。而两个礼拜左右可以干很多事情。请告诉我母亲，希望她替自己的儿子祈祷；为了我带给她的所有不快，我求她原谅。我命中注定了，要使那些我本该使他们快乐的人难过。别了，我的好朋友！愿老天多多降福于你！别了！

这期间绿蒂的心绪如何，她对自己丈夫的感情怎样，对她不幸的朋友的感情怎样，我们都不便下断语；尽管凭着对她个性的了解，我们很可以在私下作出评判，尤其是一颗美丽的女性的心，更可以设身处地，体会出她的感情。

肯定的只是，她已下了决心，要想一切办法打发维特离开。如果说她还有所迟疑的话，那也是出于对朋友的一片好意和爱护；她了解，这将使维特多么难受，是的，在他几乎就不可能。然而在此期间，情况更加逼迫她认真采取行动；她的丈夫压根儿不肯再提这事，就像她也一直保持着沉默一样，而唯其如此，她便更有必要通过行动向他证明，她并未辜负他的感情。

上面引的那封维特致友人的信，写于圣诞节前的礼拜日。当晚，他去找绿蒂，碰巧只有她一个人在房中。绿蒂正忙着整理准备在圣诞节分送给小弟妹们的玩具。维特说小家伙们在收到以后一定会高兴得什么似的，并回忆了自己突然站在房门口，看见一棵挂满蜡烛、糖果和苹果的漂亮圣诞树时的惊喜心情。

“你也会得到礼物的，”绿蒂说，同时嫣然一笑，借以掩饰自己的困窘，“你也会得到礼物，条件是你要很听话；比如得到一支圣诞树上的蜡烛什么的。”

“你说的听话是什么意思？”维特嚷起来，“你要我怎么样？我能够怎么样？亲爱的绿蒂！”

“礼拜四晚上是圣诞夜，”她说，“到时候我的弟弟妹妹，我的父亲都要来这里，每人都会得到自己的礼品。你也来吧，可是在这之前别再来了。”

维特听了一怔。

“我求你。”她又说，“事已至此，我求你为了我的安宁，答应我吧；不能，再不能这样下去了啊。”

维特转过脸去不看她，自顾自地在房里来回疾走，透过牙齿缝喃喃道：“再不能这样下去了！再不能这样下去了！”

绿蒂感到自己的话把他推进了一个可怕的境界，便提出各式各样的问题来企图引开他的思路，但是不成功。

“不，绿蒂，”他嚷道，“我将再也不来见你了！”

“干吗呢？”她问，“维特，你可以来看我们，你必须来看我们，只是减少一些就行了。唉，你干吗非得生成这么个急性子，一喜欢什么就死心眼儿地迷下去！我求你，”她拉住维特的手继续说，“克制克制自己吧！你的天资，你的学识，你的才能，它们不是可以带给你各种各样的快乐么？拿出男子汉的气概来！别再苦苦恋着一个除去同情你就什么也不能帮的女孩子。”

维特把牙齿咬得咯吱咯吱响，目光阴郁地瞪着她。绿蒂握着他的手，说：

“快冷静冷静吧，维特！你难道感觉不出，你是在自己欺骗自己，存心把自己毁掉么！干吗定要爱我呢，维特？我可已是另有所属啊！干吗偏偏这样？我担心，我害怕，仅仅是因为不可能实现，才使这个占有我的欲望对你如此有诱惑力的。”

维特把自己的手从她手里抽回来，目光定定地、愤怒地瞪着她。

“高明！”他喝道，“太高明了！没准儿是阿尔伯特这么讲的吧？外交家！了不起的外交家！”

“谁都可能这样讲，”绿蒂回答，“难道世间就没有一个姑娘合你心意了么？打起精神去找吧，我发誓，你一定能找到的；要知道，一些时候以来你自寻烦恼，已经早叫我为你和我们担心了啊。打起精神来，去旅行一下，这将会、一定会使你心胸开阔起来。去找吧，找一个值得你爱的人，然后再回来和我们团聚，共享真正的友谊的幸福。”

“你这一套可以印成教科书，推荐给所有的家庭教师哩。”维特冷笑一声说，“亲爱的绿蒂！你让我稍稍安静一下，然后一切都会好了。”

“只是，维特，圣诞节前你千万别来啊！”

他正要回答，阿尔伯特进屋来了。两人只冷冷地道了一声“晚上好”，便并排在房间里踱起步来，气氛十分尴尬。维特开始讲了几句无足轻重的话，但很快又没词儿了。阿尔伯特也一样；随后，他问自己的妻子，是否已经把这样那样交给她办的事办妥；一听绿蒂回答还不曾办妥，便冲她讲了几句在维特听来不止冷淡，简直称得上是粗暴的话。维特想走又不能走，迟迟挨挨地一直到了八点钟，心里越来越烦躁，越来越不快。人家已开始摆晚饭，他才拿起自己的帽子和手杖。阿尔伯特邀他留下，他只看作是客套敷衍，冷冷道过一声谢，便离开了。

他回到家中，从为他照路的年轻佣人手里接过蜡烛，走到了卧室里，一进门便放声大哭，过不多会儿又激动地自言自语，绕室狂奔，临了和衣倒在床上，直到深夜十一点，佣人蹑手蹑脚地摸进来问少爷要不要脱靴子，才惊动了他。他让佣人替他把靴子脱了，告诉佣人明天早上不叫不要进房里来。

礼拜一一大早，他给绿蒂写了一封信。他死后，人们在他的书桌上发现了这封信，已经用火漆封好，便送给了绿蒂。从行文本身看出，信是断断续续写成的。我也就依其本来面目，分段摘引于后。

已经决定了，绿蒂，我要去死。我在给你写这句话时，并没有怀着浪漫的激情，相反，倒是心平气和，在将要最后一次见到你的今天的早上。当你捧读此信的时候，亲爱的，冰冷的黄土已经盖住了我这个不安和不幸的人的僵硬的躯体。他在自己生命的最后一刻所感到的快慰，就是能和你再谈一谈心。我熬过了一个多可怕的夜晚啊；可是，唉，这也是一个仁慈的夜晚！是它坚定了我的决心，使我最后决定去死！昨天，我忍痛离开你时，真是五内俱焚；往事一一涌上心头，一个冷酷的事实猛地摆在我面前：我生活在你身边是既无希望，也无欢乐啊……

我一回到自己房里，就疯了似的跪在地上！上帝呵，求你赐给我最后几滴苦涩的泪水，让我用它们来滋润一下自己的心田吧！在我脑海中翻腾着千百种计划，千百种前景，但最后剩下的只有一个念头，一个十分坚决、十分肯定的念头，这就是：我要去死！我躺下睡了，今儿一早醒来心情平静，可它却仍然在那里，这个存在于我心中十分强烈的念头：我要去死！——这并非绝望；这是信念，我确信自己苦已受够，是该为你而牺牲自己的时候了。是的，绿蒂，我为什么应该保持缄默呢？我们三人中的确有一个必须离开，而我，就自愿做这一个人！呵，亲爱的，在我这破碎的心灵里，确曾隐隐约约出现过一个狂暴的想法——杀死你的丈夫！——杀死你！——杀死我自己！

眼下的事就这么定了！可是将来，当你在一个美丽夏日的黄昏登上山岗，你可别忘了我啊，别忘了我也常常喜欢上这儿来；然后，你要眺望那边公墓里的我的坟茔，看我坟头的茂草如何在落日的余晖中让风吹得摇曳不定……

我开始写此信时心情是平静的；可眼下，眼下一切都生动实在地出现在我面前，我又忍不住哭了，像个孩子似的哭了。

将近十点钟，维特叫来他的佣人，一边穿外套一边对他讲，过几天他要出门去，让佣人把他的衣服刷干净，打点好全部行装。此外，又命令佣人去各处结清账目，收回几册借给人家的书，把他本来按月施舍给一些穷人的钱提前一次给两个月。

他吩咐把早饭送到他房里去。吃完饭，他骑着马去总管家；总管不在，他便一边沉思，一边在花园中踱来踱去，像是在对以往的种种伤心事作最后一次的重温。

可是，小家伙们却不让他长久地安静，他们追踪他，跳到他背上，告诉他：明天，明天的明天，喏，就是再过一天，他们就可以从绿蒂手里领到圣诞礼物了！他们向他描述自己的小脑瓜儿所能想象出来的种种奇迹。

“明天！”维特喊出来，“明天的明天！再过一天！”——随后，他挨个儿吻了孩子们，打算要走。这当儿，最小的一个男孩却要给他说悄悄话。他向维特透露，哥哥们都写了许多张美丽的贺年片，挺大挺大的，一张给爸爸，一张给阿尔伯特和绿蒂，也有一张给维特先生；只不过要到新年早上才给他们。维特深为感动，给了每个孩子一点什么，然后才上马，让孩子们代他问候他们的父亲，说完便含着热泪驰去。

将近五点，他回到住所，吩咐女仆去给卧室中的壁炉添足柴，以便火能一直维持到深夜。他还让佣人把书籍和内衣装进箱子，把外衣缝进护套。做完这些，他显然又写给了绿蒂的最后一封信的下面这个片断：

你想不到我会来吧！你以为我会听你的话，直到圣诞节晚上才来看你，是不是！呵，绿蒂！今日不见就永远不见了。到圣诞节晚上你手里捧着这封信，你的手将会颤抖，你莹洁的泪水将把信纸打湿。我愿意，我必须！我多快意呵，我决心已定！

绿蒂这段时间的心境也很特别，最后那次和维特谈话以后她就感到，要她和他分手会多么困难，而维特如果被迫离开了她，又会何等痛苦。

她像无意似的当着阿尔伯特讲了一句：“维特圣诞夜之前不会来了。”阿尔伯特于是便骑马去找住在邻近的一位官员，和他了结一些公事，不得不就在他家中过夜。

绿蒂独坐房中，身边一个弟妹也没有，便不禁集中心思考虑起自己眼前的处境来。她看出自己已终身和丈夫结合在一起；丈夫对她的爱和忠诚她是了解的，因此也打心眼里倾慕他；他的稳重可靠仿佛天生来作为一种基础，好让一位贤淑的女子在上面建立起幸福的生活似的；她感到，他对她和她的弟妹真是永远不可缺少的靠山啊。可另一方面，维特之于她又如此可贵，从相识的第一瞬间起，他俩就意气相投；后来，长时间的交往以及种种共同的经历，都在她心中留下了不可磨灭的印象，她不管感到或想到什么有趣儿的事，都已习惯于把自己的快乐和他一块儿分享；他这一走，必然给她的整个一生造成永远无法弥补的空虚。呵，要是她能马上把他变成自己的哥哥就好了！这样她会多么幸福啊！——她真希望能把自己的一个女友许配给他，真希望能恢复他和阿尔伯特的友好关系！她把自己的女友挨个儿想了一遍，发现她们身上都有这样那样的缺点，觉得没有一个配得上维特的。

这么考虑来考虑去，她才深深感觉到自己衷心地暗中希望着一件事，虽然她不肯向自己明白承认，这就是把维特留给她自己。与此同时，她又对自己讲，这是不可能的，不允许的。此刻，她纯洁、美丽、素来总是那么轻松、那么无忧无虑的心，也变得忧伤而沉重起来，失去了对于未来幸福的希望。她的胸部感到压抑，眼睛也让乌云给蒙住了。

她这么一直坐到六点半；突然，她听见维特上楼来了。她一下子便听出是他的脚步声和他打听她的声音。她的心怦怦狂跳起来；可以说，她在他到来时像这个样子还是第一次，她很想让人对他讲自己不在；当他跨进房来时，她心慌意乱得冲他叫了一声：

“你食言了！”

“我可没许任何诺言。”维特回答。

“就算这样，你也该满足我的请求呀，”她反驳说，“我求过你让我们两人都安静安静。”

她不清楚自己说些什么，也不清楚自己做些什么，糊里糊涂地就派人去请她的几个女友来，以免自己单独和维特待在一起。他呢，放下带来的几本书，又问起另外几本书。这时，绿蒂心里一会儿盼着她的女友快来，一会儿又希望她们可千万别来。使女进房回话，有两位没有来，请她原谅。

她想叫使女留在隔壁房里做针线活；但一转念又改变了主意。维特在房中踱着方步，她便坐到钢琴前，弹奏法国舞曲，但怎么也弹不流畅。维特已在他坐惯了的老式沙发上坐下；她定了定神，也不慌不忙地坐在他对面。

“你没有什么书好念念吗？”她问。

他没有。

“那边，在我的抽屉里，放着你译的几首莪相的诗，”她又说，“我还没有念它们，一直希望听你自己来念，谁知又老找不到机会。”

维特微微一笑，走过去取那几首诗；可一当把它们拿在手中，身上便不觉打了个寒颤，低头看着稿纸，眼里已噙满泪花。他坐下，念道：

朦胧夜空中的孤星呵，你在西天发出美丽的闪光，从云朵深处昂起你明亮的头，庄严地步向你的丘岗。你在这荒原上寻觅什么呢？那狂暴的风已经安静，从远方传来了溪流的絮语，喧闹的惊涛拍击岩岸，夜蛾儿成群飞过旷野，嗡嗡嘤嘤。你在这荒原上寻觅什么哟，美丽的星？瞧你微笑着冉冉行进，欢乐的浪涛簇拥着你，洗濯你的秀发。别了，安静的星。望你永照人间，你这莪相心灵中的光华！

在它的照耀下，我看见了逝去的友人，他们在罗拉平原聚会，像在过去的日子里一样。——芬戈来了，像一根潮湿的雾柱；瞧啊，在他周围他的勇士，那些古代的歌人：白发苍苍的乌林！身躯伟岸的利诺！歌喉迷人的阿尔品！还有你，自怨自艾的弥诺娜！——我的朋友呵，想当年，在塞尔玛山上，我们竞相歌唱，歌声如春风阵阵飘过山丘，窃窃私语的小草久久把头儿低昂；自那时以来，你们可真变了样！

这当儿，娇艳的弥诺娜低着头走出来，泪眼汪汪；从山岗那边不断刮来的风，吹得她浓密的头发轻扬。她放开了甜美的歌喉，勇士们的心里更加忧伤；要知道他们已一次次张望过萨格尔的坟头，一次次张望过白衣女可尔玛幽暗的住房。可尔玛形影孤单，柔声儿在山岗上唱着歌：萨格尔答应来却没来，四周已是夜色迷茫。听啊，这就是可尔玛独坐在山岗上唱的歌：

可尔玛

夜已来临！——我坐在狂风呼啸的岗头，独自一人。山中风声凄厉。山洪咆哮着跃下岩顶。可怜我这被遗弃在风雨中的女子，没有茅舍供我避雨栖身。

月儿呵，从云端里走出来吧！星星呵，在夜空中闪耀吧！请照亮我的道路，领我去我的爱人打猎后休息的地方，他身旁摆着松了弦的弓弩，他周围躺着喘吁吁的狗群。可我只得独坐杂树丛生的河畔，激流和风暴喧啸不已，我却听不见爱人一丝儿声音。

我的萨格尔为何迟疑不归？莫非他已把自己的诺言忘记？这儿就是那岩石，那树，那湍急的河流！唉，你答应天一黑就来到这里！我的萨格尔呵，你可是迷失了归途？我愿随你一起逃走，离开高傲的父亲和兄弟！我们两个家族世代为仇，萨格尔呵，我俩却不是仇敌！

风啊，你静一静吧！激流啊，你也请别出声息！让我的声音越过山谷，传到我那漂泊者的耳际。萨格尔！是我在唤你哟，萨格尔！这儿是那树，这儿是那岩石，萨格尔，我的亲爱的！我在这儿等了又等，你为何迟迟不来？

瞧，月亮发出银辉，溪流在峡谷中闪亮，丘岗上灰色的岩石突兀立起；可丘顶却不见他的身影，也没有狗群报告他的来归。我只得孤零零地坐在此地。

可躺在那下边荒野上的是谁啊，是我的爱人？是我的兄弟？——你们说话呀，我的朋友！呵，他们不回答，徒令我心增忧戚！——啊，他们死了！他们的剑上犹有斑斑血迹！我的兄弟呵，我的兄弟，你为何杀死了我的萨格尔？我的萨格尔呵，你为何杀死了我的兄弟？你们两个都是我的亲人哟！在丘岗旁安息着的万千战死者中，数你最最英俊！可是他在战斗里却可怕无敌。回答我，亲爱的人，你们可已听见我的呼唤！唉，他们永远沉默无言，胸膛已冰凉如泥！

亡灵们呵，你们从丘顶的巨岩石上讲话吧！从暴风雨中的山巅讲话吧！我绝不会毛骨悚然！告诉我，你们将去哪儿安息？我要到群山中的哪道岩穴里才能找到你们啊！——狂风中，我听不见一些儿回音；暴风雨里，我听不见微弱的叹息。

我坐在岗头大放悲声；我等待着黎明，泪雨淅沥。死者的友人们呵，你们掘好了坟墓，但在我到来之前，千万别把墓室关闭。我怎能留下呢，我的生命已消逝如梦？我愿和我的亲人同住在这岩石鸣响的溪畔；每当夜色爬上山岗，狂飙掠过旷野，我的灵魂都要立在风中，为我亲人的死哀泣。猎人在他的小屋中听见我的泣诉，既恐惧又欢喜；要知道我是在悼念自己亲爱的人，声音又怎能不甜蜜！

这就是你的歌啊，弥诺娜，托尔曼的红颜的闺女。我们的泪为可尔玛而流，我们的心为她忧戚。

乌林怀抱竖琴登场，为我们伴奏阿尔品的歌唱。——阿尔品嗓音悦耳，利诺有火一般的心肠。可眼下他们都已安息在陋室中，他们的歌声已在塞尔玛绝响。有一次乌林猎罢归来，还在英雄们未曾战死的时光。他听见他们在山上比赛唱歌，歌声悠扬，但却忧伤。他们悲叹领袖群伦的英雄穆拉尔的陨落，说他的宝剑厉害如奥斯卡，他的灵魂高尚如芬戈。——但他仍然倒下了，他的父亲悲痛失声，他的姐姐泪流成河，英俊的穆拉尔的姐姐弥诺娜泪流成河。她在乌林唱歌以前便下去了，恰似西天的月亮预见到暴风雨来临，将美丽的脸儿向云里躲藏。我和乌林一同拨响琴弦，伴着利诺悲哀地歌唱。

利诺

风雨已过，雾散云开，天气晴朗，匆匆去来的太阳又照着山岗。溪流红光闪闪，穿过峡谷，淙淙潺潺，笑语欢畅。可我聆听着一个更动人的声音，那是阿尔品的声音，他在痛苦地把死者歌唱。他哀老的头颅低垂，他带泪的眼睛红肿。阿尔品，杰出的歌手，你为何独自来到这无声的山上？为你何悲声不断，像穿越山林的风，像拍击洋岸的浪？

阿尔品

利诺呵，我的泪为死者而流，我的歌为墓中人而唱。在荒野的儿子们中间，在岗头，你是何等英俊魁梧。但你也像穆拉尔一样战死，你的坟上也会有痛哭悲伤。这些山岗将把你忘记，你的弓弩将存放在大厅，从此不把弦张。

穆拉尔呵，在这山岗上你曾飞奔如快鹿，狂暴如野火。你的愤怒如可怕的飓风，你的宝剑如荒野的闪电，你的声音如雨后的山洪，如远方山岗上的雷动！多少人曾被你愤怒的烈火吞噬，多少人曾死在你手中，可当你从战斗里归来，额头上又洋溢着宁静！你的容颜如雨后的丽日，如静夜的月亮：你的胸膛呼吸均匀，如风住浪息的海洋！

如今，你的居室湫隘、黑暗，你的墓穴长不过三步：而你当初却是多么伟大呵！四块顶上长满青苔的石板砌成你唯一的纪念碑，还有无叶的树一株。一茎长草在风中低语，告诉猎人，这儿就是伟大的穆拉尔的归宿！没有母亲来为你哭泣，没有情人来为你一洒青泪。生育你的莫格兰的女儿，她已经先你亡故。

那扶杖走来的是谁呢？他的头发已经老得雪白，他的双眼已经哭得红肿。呵，那是你的父亲，穆拉尔，你是他唯一的儿子！他曾听见你在战斗中高声呐喊，他曾听见你打得敌人四处逃窜；他只听见你如雷的声名，唉，全不知你身负重伤！痛哭吧，穆拉尔的父亲！痛哭吧，尽管你儿子已听不见你的声音！死者酣睡沉沉，头枕尘埃，充耳不闻你的呼唤，永远不会复生。呵，墓穴中何时才会有黎明，才会召唤酣睡者：醒一醒！

别了，人中的最高贵者，沙场上无敌的勇士！从此战斗中再见不到你的英姿，幽林间再不会闪过你雪亮的兵刃！你没有子嗣继承伟业，但歌声将使你不朽，后世将听到你，听到战死沙场的穆拉尔的英名。

英雄们个个放声啼哭，阿明更是撕心裂肺地号啕。他悼念他的亡儿，痛惜他青春年华即已早夭。辽阔的格马尔的君王卡莫尔坐在老英雄身边，问：“阿明呵，你为何在痛哭流涕？是什么叫你大放悲声？且听这声声弦歌，真个叫悦耳迷人！它好似湖上升起的薄雾，轻轻儿飘进幽谷，把盛开的花朵滋润；可一当烈日重新照临，这雾啊也就散尽。你为何悲恸伤心啊，阿明，你这岛国哥尔马的至尊？”

“悲恸伤心！可不是吗，我的悲痛真诉说不尽。卡莫尔呵，你没有失去儿子，没有失去如花的女儿；勇敢的哥尔格还健在，天下最美的姑娘安妮拉还侍奉着你。你的家族枝繁叶茂，卡莫尔；可我阿明家却断了后嗣。岛拉呵，你的床头如此昏暗，你已在发霉的墓穴中长眠。什么时候你才会唱着歌醒来呢，你的歌喉可还是那样美，那样甜？刮起来吧，秋风，刮过这黑暗的原野！怒吼吧，狂飙，在山顶的橡树林中掀起巨澜！明月呵，请你从破碎的云絮后走出来，让我看一看你苍白的脸！你们都来帮我回忆吧，回忆我失去儿女的恐怖的夜晚：那一夜，强壮的阿林达尔死了，岛拉，我亲爱的女儿，她也未得生还。

“岛拉，我的女儿，你曾多么美丽！你美丽如悬挂在弗拉山岗上的皓月，洁白如天空飘下来的雪花，甜蜜如芳馨的空气！阿林达尔，你的弓弩强劲，你的标枪快捷，你的眼光如浪尖上的迷雾，你的盾牌如暴雨里的彤云！

“战争中遐迩闻名的阿玛尔来向岛拉求爱；岛拉没有能长久拒绝。朋友们已期待着那美好的时辰。

“奥德戈的儿子埃拉德怒不可遏，他的弟弟曾死在阿尔玛剑下。他乔装成一名船夫，驾来一叶轻舟，他的鬈发已老得雪白，脸色也和悦敦厚。‘最最美丽的姑娘啊，’他说，‘阿明可爱的女儿！在离岸不远的海里，在鲜红的水果从树上向这儿窥视的山崖旁，阿玛尔在那里等待他的岛拉，我奉命来接他的爱人，带她越过波涛翻滚的海洋。’

“岛拉跟着埃拉德上了船，口里不断呼唤阿玛尔：可她除去山崖的鸣响，就再听不见任何回答。‘阿玛尔！我的爱人，我亲爱的！你干吗要这样把我恐吓？听一听啊，阿纳兹的儿子！听一听呵，是我在唤你，我是你的岛拉！’

“埃拉德这个骗子，他狂笑着逃上陆地。岛拉拼命地喊啊，喊她的父亲，喊她的兄长的名字：‘阿林达尔！阿明！难道你们谁也不来救救他的岛拉？’

“她的喊声从海上传来，阿林达尔，我的儿子立刻从山岗跃下。终日行猎使他性格剽悍，他身挎箭矢，手执强弓，五只黑灰色猎犬紧紧跟随身边，他在海岸上瞧见勇敢的埃拉德，一把捉住他，把他缚在橡树上，用绳子将他的腰身缠了又缠，缚得埃拉德在海风中叫苦连天。

“阿林达尔驾着自己的船破浪前进，一心要救岛拉生还。阿玛尔气急败坏赶来，射出了他的灰翎利箭，只听嗖的一声响，阿林达尔呵，我的儿，射进了你的心田！你代替埃拉德丧了命。船一到岸边，他就倒下了。岛拉呵，你脚边淌着你兄长的鲜血，你真是悲痛难言！

“这当儿巨浪击破了小船，阿玛尔奋身纵入大海，不知是为救他的岛拉，还是自寻短见。一霎时狂风大作，白浪滔天，阿玛尔沉入海底，一去不返。

“只剩我一人在海浪冲击的悬崖上，听着女儿的哭诉。她呼天抢地，我身为她的父亲，却无法救她脱险。我彻夜伫立在岸边，在淡淡的月光里看见她，听着她的呼喊。风呼呼地吼，雨刷刷地抽打山岩。不等黎明到来，她的喊声已经微弱；当夜色在草丛中消散，她已经气息奄奄。她在悲痛的重压下死去了，留下了我阿明孤苦一人！我的勇力已在战争里用光，我的骄傲已被姑娘们耗完。

“每当山头雷雨交加，北风掀起狂澜，我就坐在发出轰响的岸旁，遥望那可怕的岩石。在西沉的月影里，我常常看见我孩子们的幽魂，时隐时现，缥缥缈缈，哀伤而和睦地携手同行……”

两股热泪从绿蒂的眼中迸流出来，她心里感觉轻松了一些，维特却再也念不下去。他丢下诗稿，抓住绿蒂的一只手，失声痛哭，绿蒂的头俯在另一只手上，用手绢捂住了眼睛。他俩的情绪激动得真叫可怕，从那些高贵的人的遭遇中，他们都体会出了自身的不幸。这相同的感情和流在一起的泪水，使他俩靠得更紧了。维特灼热的嘴唇和眼睛，全靠在了绿蒂的手臂上。她猛然惊醒，心里想要站起来离开；可是，悲痛和怜悯却使她动弹不得，她的手跟脚如同铅块。她喘息着，哽咽着，请求他继续念下去；她这时的声音之动人，真只有天使可比！维特浑身哆嗦，心都要碎了。他拾起诗稿，断断续续地念道：

春风呵，你为何将我唤醒？你轻轻抚摩着我的身儿回答：“我要滋润你以天上的甘霖！”可是啊，我的衰时近了，风暴即将袭来，吹打得我枝叶飘零！明天，有位旅人将要到来，他见过我的美好青春，他的眼儿将在旷野里四处寻觅，却不见我的踪影……

这几句诗的魔力，一下子攫住了不幸的青年。他完全绝望了，一头扑在绿蒂脚下，抓住她的双手，把它们先按在自己的眼睛上，再按在自己的额头上。绿蒂呢，心里也一下子闪过维特会做出什么可怕的事情来的预感，神志顿时昏乱起来，抓住他的双手，把它们捺在自己的胸口上，激动而伤感地弯下身子，两人灼热的脸颊便依偎在一起了。世界对于他们已不复存在。他用胳膊搂住她的身子，把她紧紧抱在怀中，同时狂吻起她颤抖的、嗫嚅的嘴唇来。“维特！”她的声音窒息地喊着，极力把头扭开。“维特！”她用软弱无力的手去推开他和她紧贴在一起的胸。“维特！”她再喊，声音克制而庄重。

维特不再反抗，从怀里放开她，疯了似的跪倒在她脚下。她站起来，对他既恼又爱，身子不住哆嗦，心里更惊慌迷乱，只说：“这是最后一次，维特！你别想再见到我了！”说完，向这个可怜的人投了深情的一瞥，便逃进隔壁房中，把门锁上了。维特向她伸出手去，但却没敢抓住她。随后他仰卧地上，头枕沙发，一动不动地呆了半个多小时，直到一些响声使他如梦初醒。是使女来摆晚饭了。他在房中来回踱着，等发现又只有他一个人，才走到通向隔壁的房门前，轻声呼唤道：

“绿蒂！绿蒂！只要再说一句！一句告别的话！”

绿蒂不作声。他等待着，请求着，再等待着；最后才扭转身，同时喊出：

“别了，绿蒂！永别了！”

他来到城门口。守门人已经认熟了他，一句话没问便放他出了城。野地里雨雪交加；直到夜里十一点，他才回家敲门。年轻的佣人发现，主人进屋时头上的帽子已经不见了。他一声没敢吭，只侍候维特脱下已经湿透的衣服。事后，在临着深谷的悬崖上，人家捡到了他的帽子。叫人难以想象的是，他怎能在漆黑的雨夜登上高崖，竟没有失足摔下去。

他上了床，睡了很久很久。翌日清晨，佣人听他一唤便送咖啡进去，发现他正在写信。他在致绿蒂的信上又添了下面一段。

最后一次了，最后一次我睁开眼睛。唉，它们就要再也见不到太阳，永远被一个暗淡无光、雾霭迷蒙的长昼给遮住了！痛悼吧，自然！你的儿子，你的朋友，你的情人，他的生命就要结束了。绿蒂呵，当一个人不得不对自己说“这是我的最后一个早晨”时，他心中便会有一种无可比拟、然而却最最接近于朦胧的梦的感觉。最后一个！绿蒂呵，我真完全不理解这个什么“最后一个”！难道此刻，我不是还身强力壮地站在这儿；可明天就要倒卧尘埃，了无生气了啊。死！死意味着什么？你瞧，当我们谈到死时，我们就像在做梦。我曾目睹一些人怎样死；然而人类生来就有很大的局限，他们对自己生命的开始与结束，从来都是不能理解的。眼下还存在我的，你的！你的，呵，亲爱的！可再过片刻……分开，离别……说不定就是永别了啊！……不，绿蒂，不……我怎么能逝去呢？你怎么能逝去呢？我们不是存在着吗！……逝去……这又意味着什么？还不只是一个词儿！一个没有意义的声音！我才没心思管它哩……死，绿蒂，被埋在冰冷的黄土里，那么狭窄，那么黑暗！……我曾有一个女友，在我无以自立的少年时代，她乃是我的一切。她后来死了，我跟随她的遗体去到她的墓旁，亲眼看见人家把她的棺木放下坑去，抽出棺下的绳子并且扯上来，然后便开始填土。土块落在那可怕的匣子上，咚咚直响；响声越来越沉闷，到最后墓坑整个给填了起来！这当儿我忍不住一下子扑到墓前……心痛欲裂，号啕悲恸，震惊恐惧到了极点；尽管如此，却不明白究竟出了什么事，会出什么事……死亡！坟墓！这些词儿我真不理解啊！

呵，原谅我！原谅我！昨天的事！那会儿我真要死了才好哩。我的天使哟！第一次，破天荒第一次，在我内心深处确凿无疑地涌现了这个令我热血沸腾的幸福感觉：她爱我！她爱我！此刻，我的嘴唇上还燃烧着从你的嘴唇传过来的圣洁的烈火，使我心中不断生出新的温暖和喜悦。原谅我吧！原谅我！

唉，我早知道你是爱我的，从一开始你对我的几次热情顾盼中，在我俩第一次握手时，我便知道你爱我；可后来，当我离开了你，当我在你身边看见阿尔伯特，我又产生了怀疑，因而感到焦灼和痛苦。

你还记得你给我的那些花么？在那次令人心烦的聚会中，你不能和我交谈，不能和我握手，便送了这些花给我；我在它们面前跪了半夜，它们使我确信了你对我的爱啊。可是，唉，这些印象不久便淡漠了，正如一个在领了实实在在的圣体以后内心无比幸福的基督徒，他那蒙受上帝恩赐的幸福感也渐渐会从心中消失一般。

一切都须臾即逝啊，唯有昨天我从你嘴唇上啜饮的生命之火，眼下我感觉它们在我体内燃烧，而且时光尽管流逝，它却永远不会熄灭。她爱我！这条胳膊曾经搂抱过她，这嘴唇在她的嘴唇上颤抖过，这口曾在她的口边低语过。她是我的！——你是我的！对，绿蒂，你永远永远是我的！

阿尔伯特是你丈夫，这又怎么样呢？哼，丈夫！难道我爱你，想把你从他的怀抱中夺到我的怀抱中来，对于这个世界就是罪孽么？罪孽！好，为此我情愿受罚；但我已尝到了这个罪孽的全部甘美滋味，已把生命的琼浆和力量吸进了我心里。从这一刻起你便是我的了！我的了，呵，绿蒂！我要先去啦，去见我的天父，你的天父！我将向他诉说我的不幸，他定会安慰我，直到你到来；那时，我将奔向你，拥抱你，将当着无所不在的上帝的面，永远永远和你拥抱在一起。

我不是在做梦，不是在说胡话！在即将进入坟墓之时，我心中更豁亮了。我们会，我们会再见的！我们将见到你的母亲！我们会见着她，找到她，呵，在她面前倾吐我的衷诚！因为你的母亲，她和你本是一个人呀！

将近十一时，维特问他的佣人，阿尔伯特是否已回来了。佣人回答是的，他已看见阿尔伯特骑着马跑过去。随后，维特便递给他一张没有用信封装的便条，内容是：

我拟出外旅行，把你的手枪借我一用好吗？谨祝万事如意！

可爱的绿蒂昨晚上迟迟未能入睡；她所害怕的事情终于证实了，以她不曾预料、不曾担心过的方式证实了。她那一向流得平匀轻快的血液，这时激荡沸腾开来，千百种情感交集着，把她的芳心给搅得乱糟糟的。这是维特在拥抱她时传到她胸中的情火的余焰呢，还是她为维特的放肆失礼而生气的怒火呢？还是她把自己眼前的处境，和过去无忧无虑、天真无邪、充满自信的日子相比较，因此心中深感不快呢？叫她怎么去见自己的丈夫？叫她怎样向他说清楚那一幕啊？——她本来完全可以直言不讳地告诉他，可是到底没有勇气。他俩久久地相对无言；难道她应该首先打破沉默，向自己丈夫交代那一意外的事件，在这不是时候的时候？她担心，仅仅一提起维特来过，就会给丈夫造成不快，更何况那意想不到的灾难！她未必能指望，她丈夫会完全明智地看待这件事，在态度中一点不带成见吧？她能希望，丈夫愿意明辨她的心迹吗？然而，另一方面，她又怎么可以对自己丈夫装模作样呢？要知道，在他面前，她从来都像水晶般纯洁透明，从来未曾隐讳——也不可能隐讳自己的任何感情。这样做，她有顾虑；那样做，也有顾虑，处境十分尴尬。与此同时，她的思想还一再回到对于她来说已经失去了的维特身上；她丢不开他，又不得不丢开他；而维特没有了她，便没有了一切。

她当时还不完全清楚，那在她和阿尔伯特之间出现的隔膜，对她是个多么沉重的负担。两个本来都如此理智、如此善良的人，开始由于某些暗中存在的分歧而相对无言了，各人都在心头想着自己的是和对方的非，情况便会越弄越复杂，越弄越糟糕，以致到头来变成了一个压根儿再也解不开的死结。设若她俩能早一些讲清楚，设若他俩之间互爱互谅的关系能早一些恢复，心胸得以开阔起来，那么，在此千钧一发关头，我们的朋友也许还有救。

此外，还有一点特别值得提提。如我们从他的信中知道，维特是从来也不讳言自己渴望离开这个世界的。对这个问题，阿尔伯特常常和他争论，并在绿蒂夫妇之间也不时谈起。阿尔伯特对自杀行为一贯深恶痛绝，不止一次甚至一反常态地激烈表示，他很有理由怀疑维特的这个打算是当真的，并且因此取笑过他几次，也把自己的怀疑告诉过绿蒂。这一方面固然使绿蒂在想到那可能出现的悲剧时宽心了一点，另一方面却又叫她难于启齿，向丈夫诉说眼下苦恼着她的忧虑。

阿尔伯特回到家，绿蒂急忙迎着，神色颇有些窘；他呢，事情没有办好，碰上邻近的那个官员是个不通情理的小气鬼，心头也不痛快，加之道路很难走，更使他没有好气儿。

他问家中有没有什么事情；绿蒂慌慌张张地回答：“维特昨晚上来啦！”他问有无信件，绿蒂说一封信和一个包裹已放在他房中。他回自己房间去了，又剩下绿蒂一个人。她所爱的和尊敬的丈夫的归来，在她心中唤起一种新的情绪。回想到他的高尚、他的温柔和他的善良，绿蒂的心便平静多了。她感到有一股神秘的吸引力，使她身不由己地要跟着他走去，于是便拿起针线，像往常一样跨进了他的房间。她发现阿尔伯特正忙着开包裹和读信；信的内容看来颇不令人愉快。她问了丈夫几句话，他回答却很简单，随即就坐在书桌前写起信来。

夫妇俩这么在一起待了一个钟头，绿蒂的心中越来越阴郁。她这会儿才感到，她丈夫的情绪就算好极了，自己也很难把压在心上的事向他剖白。绿蒂堕入了深沉的悲哀之中。与此同时，她却力图将自己的悲哀隐藏起来，把眼泪吞回肚子里去，这更令她加倍难受。

维特的佣人一来，她简直狼狈到了极点。佣人把维特的便条交给阿尔伯特，他读了便漫不经心地转过头来对绿蒂道：

“把手枪给他，”随即对维特的仆人说，“我祝他旅途愉快。”

这话在绿蒂耳里犹如一声响雷。她摇摇晃晃站起来，不知自己在干什么。她一步步挨到墙边，哆哆嗦嗦地取下枪，擦去枪上的灰尘，迟疑了半晌没有交出去；要不是阿尔伯特的询问的目光逼着她，她必定还会拖很久很久。她把那不祥之物递给仆人，一句话也讲不出来。佣人出门去了，她便收拾起自己的活计，返回自己房中，心里却七上八下，说不出有多么忧虑。她预感到种种可怕的事情。因此，一会儿，她决心去跪在丈夫脚下，向他承认一切，承认昨天晚上发生的事，承认她的过错以及她的预感；一会儿，她又觉得这样做不会有好结果，她能说服丈夫去维特那儿的希望微乎其微。这时，晚饭已经摆好；她的一个好朋友来问点什么事情，原打算马上走的，结果却留了下来，使席间的气氛变得轻松了一些。绿蒂控制住自己，大伙儿谈谈讲讲，不知不觉时间就过去了。

佣人拿着枪走进维特的房间；一听说枪是绿蒂亲手交给他的，维特便怀着狂喜一把夺了过去。他吩咐给他送来了面包和酒，让他的佣人去吃饭，自己却坐下写起信来：

它们经过了你的手，你还擦去了上面的灰尘；我把它们吻了一遍又一遍，因为你曾接触过它们。绿蒂呵，我的天使，是你成全我实现自己的决心！是你，绿蒂，是你把枪交给了我；我曾经渴望从你手中接受死亡，如今我的心愿得以满足了！唔，我盘问过我那小伙子；当你递枪给他时，你的手在颤抖，你连一句“再见”也没有讲！——可悲，可悲！连一句“再见”也没有！难道为了那把我和你永远联结起来的一瞬，你就把我从心中放逐出去了么？绿蒂啊，哪怕再过一千年，也不会把我对那一瞬的印象磨灭！我感觉到，你是不可能恨一个如此热恋你的人的。

饭后，维特叫佣人把行李全部捆好，自己撕毁了许多信函，随后再出去清理了几桩债务。事毕回到家来，可过不多会儿又冒雨跑出门去，走进已故的伯爵的花园里，在这废园中转来转去，一直流连到了夜幕降临，才回家来写信：

威廉，我已最后一次去看了田野，看了森林，还有天空。你也多珍重吧！亲爱的母亲，请原谅我！威廉，为我安慰安慰她啊！愿上帝保佑你们！我的事情全都已料理好。别了！我们会再见的，到那时将比现在多些欢乐。

我对不起你，阿尔伯特，请原谅我吧。我破坏了你家庭的和睦，造成了你俩之间的猜忌。别了！我自愿结束这一切。哦，但愿我的死能带给你们幸福！阿尔伯特，阿尔伯特，使我们的天使幸福吧！你要是做到了，上帝就会保佑你啊！

晚上，他又在自己的文书中翻了很久，撕碎和烧毁了其中的许多。然后，他在几个写着威廉的地址的包裹上打好漆封。包内是些记载着他的零星杂感的短文，我过去也曾见过几篇。十点钟，他叫佣人给壁炉添了柴，送来一瓶酒，随即便打发小伙子去睡觉。佣人和房东的卧室都在离得很远的后院，小伙子一回去便和衣倒上床睡了，以便第二天一大早就去伺候主人；他的主人讲过，明天六点以前邮车就要到门口来。

夜里十一点过

周围万籁无声，我心里也同样宁静。我感谢你，上帝，感谢你赐给我最后的时刻以如此多的温暖和力量。

我走到窗前，仰望夜空。我亲爱的人呵，透过汹涌的、急飞过我头顶的乌云，我仍看见在茫茫的空际有一颗颗明星！不，你们不会陨落！永恒的主宰在他的心中托负着你们，托负着我。我看见了群星中最美丽的北斗星。每当我晚上离开了你，每当我跨出你家大门，它就总挂在我的头上。望着它，我常常真是如醉如痴啊！我常常向它举起双手，把它看成是我眼前幸福的神圣象征和吉兆！还有那……哦，绿蒂，什么东西不会叫我想起你呢？在我周围无处没有你！不是么，我不是像个小孩子似的，把你神圣的手指碰过的一切小玩意儿，都贪得无厌地强占为己有么？

这张可爱的剪影画，我把它遗赠给你，绿蒂！请你珍惜它吧，我在它上面何止吻过千次。每逢出门或回家来。我都要向它挥手告别或者致意。

我给你父亲留了一张字条，请他保护我的遗体。在公墓后面朝向田野的一角，长着两株菩提树，我希望安息在那里。你父亲能够，也必定会为他的朋友帮这个忙的。希望你也替我求他一下。我不想勉强虔诚的基督徒把自己的躯体安放在一个可怜的不幸者旁边[1]。唉，我希望你们把我葬在路旁，或者幽寂的山谷中，好让过往的祭师和辅祭能在我的墓碑前祝福，撒马利亚人[2]能洒下泪水几滴。

时候到了，绿蒂！我捏住这冰冷的、可怕的枪柄，心中毫无畏惧，恰似端起一个酒杯，从这杯中，我将把死亡的香醪痛饮！是你把它递给了我，我还有什么可犹豫。一切一切，我生活中的一切希望和梦想，都由此得到了满足！此刻，我就可以冷静地，无动于衷地，去敲死亡的铁门了。

绿蒂啊，只要能为你死，为你献身，我就是幸福的！我愿勇敢地死，高高兴兴地死，只要我的死能给你的生活重新带来宁静，带来快乐。可是，唉，人世间只有很少高尚的人肯为自己的亲眷抛洒热血，以自己的死在他们的友朋中鼓动起新的、百倍的生之勇气。

我希望就穿着身上这些衣服下葬，因为绿蒂你曾经接触过它们，使它们变得神圣了。就这一点，我也在信上请求了你父亲。我的灵魂将飘浮在灵柩上。别让人翻我的衣袋。这个淡红色的蝴蝶结儿，是我第一次在你弟妹中间见到你时，你戴在胸前的……哦，为我多多地吻孩子们，给他们讲他们不幸的朋友的故事。可爱的孩子们啊！他们眼下好像还围在我身边哩！唉，我是多么依恋你呀！自从与你相见，我就再离不开你！……这个蝴蝶结儿，我希望把它和我葬在一起。还是在我过生日那天，你把它送给了我的哟！我真是如饥似渴地接受了你的一切！没想到，唉，我的结局竟是这样！……镇静一点！我求你，镇静点吧！……

子弹已经装好……钟正敲十二点！就这样吧！……绿蒂，绿蒂！别了啊，别了！

有位邻居看见火光闪了一下，接着听见一声枪响，但是随后一切复归于寂静，便没有再留意。

第二天早上六点，佣人端着灯走进房来，发现维特躺在地上，身旁是手枪和血。他唤他，扶他坐起来；维特一声不答，只是还在喘气。仆人跑去请大夫，通知阿尔伯特。绿蒂听见门铃响，浑身顿时战栗开了。她叫醒丈夫，两人一同起来；维特的年轻仆人哭喊着，结巴着，报告了凶信。绿蒂一听便昏倒在阿尔伯特跟前。

等大夫赶到出事地点，发现躺在地上的维特已经没救，脉搏倒还在跳，可四肢已经僵硬。维特对准右眼上方的额头开了一枪，脑浆都迸出来了。大夫不必要地割开他胳膊上的一条动脉，血流出来，可他仍有喘息。

从靠椅扶手上的血迹断定，他是坐在书桌前完成此举的，随后却摔到地上，痛得围着椅子打滚。最后，他仰卧着，面对窗户，再也没有动弹的力气。此刻，他仍穿的是那套他心爱的服装：长筒皮靴，青色燕尾服，再配上黄色的背心。

房东一家、左邻右舍以及全城居民都惊动了。阿尔伯特走进房来，维特已被众人放到床上，额头扎着绷带，脸色已成死灰，四肢一动不动。只有肺部还在可怕地喘哮着，一会儿轻，一会儿重，大伙儿都盼着他快点断气。

昨夜要的酒他只喝了一杯。书桌上摊开着一本《艾米莉亚·迦洛蒂》[3]。

关于阿尔伯特的震惊和绿蒂的悲恸，我就不用讲了。

老总管闻讯匆匆赶来，泪流满面地亲吻垂死的维特。他的几个大一点的儿子也接踵而至，一齐跪倒床前，放声大哭，吻了他的手，吻了他的嘴。尤其是平日最得维特喜欢的老大，更是一直吻着他，直至他断气，人家才把这孩子给强行拖开。维特断气的时间是正午十二点。由于总管亲临现场并作过布置，才防止了市民蜂拥而至。当晚十一点不到，他便吩咐大伙儿把维特葬在他自行选定的墓地里。老人领着儿子们走在维特的遗体后面；阿尔伯特没能来，绿蒂的生命叫他担忧。几名手工匠人抬着维特，没有任何教士来给他送葬。

[1] 按基督教教规，自杀乃是叛教行为，自杀者不能葬入公墓。

[2] 撒马利亚人指救死扶伤者，典出《新约·路加福音》第十章。

[3] 《艾米莉亚·迦洛蒂》（1772）是德国伟大作家莱辛（Gotthold Ephraim Lessing, 1729—1831）的著名抗暴悲剧。女主人公的父亲是一位军官，他为了不让女儿被暴君玷污，亲手杀死了女儿。

译后记

漫话《维特》

约翰·沃尔夫冈·歌德（1749—1832），德国十八世纪下半叶和十九世纪初最杰出的诗人、作家、学者和思想家。他以自己毕生的辛勤劳作，给德国和人类留下一笔光辉巨大、丰富多彩的精神财富。

1774年，歌德出版了他早年最重要的一部作品……——《少年维特的烦恼》（简称《维特》）。这在德国文学史上，是一件具有划时代意义的大事，不仅使年仅二十五岁的歌德因而成为德国乃至欧洲最享盛誉的作家，一向被人轻视的德国文学也被提高到了与欧洲先进国家并驾齐驱的地位。在1832年《浮士德》第二部问世前，歌德这位“最伟大的德国人”便一直作为《维特》的作者闻名于世。

影响如此巨大的《维特》是部怎样的书？这部书有何价值与意义？

《维特》是一部规模不大的长篇小说，特点是采用了第一人称的书信体。全书共分三个部分：第一、二部分纯粹由主人公维特致友人威廉和女友绿蒂的书简构成；第三部分则是本书“编者”威廉写的后记，中间也穿插着维特临死前写的四封信和几则残简。此外，书前尚有一段“编者”的小引，说明编成此书的“由来”和“用意”。

小说的情节可谓简单，贯穿全书的主线为主人公不幸的恋爱与社会遭遇。根据笔者个人的理解与体会，也不妨称这部书为“青年维特碰壁逃亡记”——

第一次出逃。为摆脱旧日生活中的烦恼，维特来到一个陌生的小城。其时正是春光明媚的五月，他立即投身在美丽大自然的怀抱中，终日读着庄严宁静的荷马古诗，与天真的儿童和纯朴的村民接近，于是感到有一种奇妙的欢愉充溢着整个的灵魂。稍后，他又在舞会上认识了一位聪明俏丽的绿蒂姑娘。他明知绿蒂已经订婚，却仍对她一见钟情，并很快搬到她家附近去居住，觉得自己好像进了“天国”，而绿蒂就是这个“天国”中的“天使”。可叹好景不长，绿蒂的未婚夫阿尔伯特从外地一回来，维特便从他这幻想的“天国”中摔到了地上，处于十分尴尬的境地。于是烦恼又代替了宁静，失望又代替了欢欣，就连美丽的大自然也变成了折磨他的“鬼魅”了。维特只好逃出这个已经失去欢乐的“乐园”。

第二次出逃。维特到了一个公使馆里当秘书，一开始总算从实际工作中得到了一些慰藉，谁知上司是个偏狭迂阔的官僚，对他的工作和交往多所挑剔，使维特在他手下当差如在“苦役船”上一般难受。维特好不容易忍耐到第二年春天，却又碰见了一件更难堪的事：维特应邀在某伯爵家做客，一班傲慢顽固的贵族对于这个市民阶级的青年在场大为不满，伯爵只好催请他离去。此事立即成了全城尽人皆知的“丑闻”。羞愤之下，维特“真恨不得抓起刀来，刺进自己的心窝里去”。

第三次出逃。一年之后，在落木萧萧的初秋，因在社会上四处碰壁而心灰意懒的维特又逃回到了绿蒂身边。可这时绿蒂已经结婚，他的“乐园”也不复存在：大自然秋风萧瑟，最小最可爱的一个村童已经死去，纯朴善良的村民一个个身遭不幸，就连两株维特与全村老小十分珍爱的胡桃树，也被贪财的村长伙同其新主人砍掉了………

维特终于从一个精神病患者的话里悟出，所谓幸福只存在于疯子的头脑里。

第四次出逃。维特对现实生活已经绝望，唯有逃到爱情中去寻找寄托，便更狂热地恋慕着有夫之妇绿蒂。可这无异于饮鸩止渴，既招来他人物议，又引起阿尔伯特疑忌，绿蒂不得不赶走他。

第五次出逃。残冬到了，维特深感自己成了世界上多余的人，便怀着痛苦与愤懑的心情最后一次出逃，逃向了“混沌与黑暗”，逃向了死亡，因为……——“别无他途”！

以上便是《维特》的主要故事，但他并非出自作者的虚构；而是歌德根据1772年自杀身死的青年耶路撒冷的不幸遭遇，并糅合进自己两年来的痛苦经历、思想和感情写成的。女主人公绿蒂就是他一位朋友的未婚妻夏绿蒂·布甫的化身，年轻的诗人确曾热恋过她；别的重要人物同样在现实生活中有不止一个原型。所以歌德自己说，《维特》这部作品是他“用自己的心血哺育出来的。其中有大量出自我心胸中的东西，有大量的情感和思想足够写一部比此书长十倍的长篇小说”。

然而，不能因此说，《维特》只是一部个人的恋爱与社会遭遇的悲剧。因为，正如十九世纪的丹麦大批评家勃兰兑斯等早就指出的，它还表现了一个时代的烦恼、憧憬以及苦闷。

《维特》出现在欧洲从封建主义向资本主义过渡的历史转折时期。经过了文艺复兴和启蒙运动，市民阶级的阶级意识已经觉醒，年轻的一代更是感情激荡，强烈要求改变自己在政治上的无权地位，打破社会上严格的等级界线，建立“自然的”、“平等的”人与人关系。他们以“个性解放”、“感情自由”等口号来反对封建束缚。但与此同时，封建贵族阶级仍牢牢掌握着政权，在其军队和国家机器面前，年轻的资产阶级感到自己十分软弱无力，因而普遍滋生了悲观失望、愤懑伤感的情绪。在一段时间里，伤感多愁成了一种时髦。1772年在故乡法兰克福养病期间，歌德就参加过一个由见花落泪、对月伤情的时髦男女组成的团体。而在文学中，感伤主义的小说以及市民悲剧也应运而生。《维特》便是在这种时代气氛和文学潮流中出现的。它那位耽于幻想，多愁善感、愤世嫉俗的主人公，便是当时一代青年的代表。他代表他们，述说了自己的理想与憧憬，并以其一次次碰壁失望后的悲伤哭泣，“对横跨在市民的现实和自己对这个现实所抱的同样是市民的幻想之间的鸿沟”（恩格斯语），发出凄惨的哀号。从这个意义上讲，《维特》反映了十八世纪这个历史转折时期资产阶级所感到的狼狈和痛苦。

而在欧洲大陆各国中，情况最糟糕的又数仍处于封建小诸侯统治下的德国。在这里，“一切都烂透了，动摇了，眼看就要坍塌了，简直没有一线好转的希望”（见恩格斯《德国现状》）。另一方面，德国的资产阶级由于历史和经济原因却最软弱，根本没有力量与勇气像在英、法等国那样去作改变现状的实际尝试。他们中最先进的人物也只能在文学与哲学中去寻求自由，幻想未来，一般平庸之辈就更是向封建势力妥协投降了。所以，我们在《维特》这部作品中看见的德国社会，城市里充满了迂腐的贵族和庸俗的小市民，乡村中到处是不幸者。所以，维特只能一次次逃走以至最后自杀，因为——…“别无他途”！

对于这个使卓有才智、心地高尚的青年无以存身的社会，歌德通过主人公维特之口进行了多方面的抨击和诅咒；维特恰恰自杀于圣诞节前一天，临死还读了莱辛的抗暴悲剧《艾米莉亚·迦洛蒂》，就更清楚地表示了他对社会的愤懑和抗议。但也仅仅如此而已，软弱的性格注定了他不可能有更勇敢的行动，虽然这已比恩格斯说的“处在（德国）这粪堆中却很舒服”的平庸资产者要高尚一些。

能不能说，维特的悲剧是性格的悲剧呢？诚然，他的性格是病态的；但这病态的性格一如上述乃是时代和阶级的产物，维特即是十八世纪欧洲流行的那种“时代病”的一名重症患者。

能不能说，维特的悲剧仅仅产生于他不幸的爱情和生活际遇呢？也不完全，我们知道，爱情是一个社会问题，历来都反映着时代与社会的风貌。而在《维特》这部小说中，仅仅因婚姻恋爱问题而死、而疯、而犯罪的不幸者还有好几个，并且几乎都是由礼法、财产、等级悬殊社会限制造成的。

综上所述，《维特》应该说是欧洲十八世纪这个过渡历史时期的悲剧，软弱无力的德国资产阶级的悲剧，落后腐朽的德国社会的悲剧。而这，便是《维特》这部作品的价值和意义。

不过，以上所述，仍然不能讲已经穷尽歌德这部杰作极其丰富的思想内涵。年轻主人公对大自然的热情讴歌，对天真无邪的儿童的热爱，对淳朴的古代社会的向往，还有他视死亡为回返自然父亲的怀抱，所有这些，统统都表现了作者返归自然的启蒙思想和哲学观。

《维特》一问世，当即风靡了德国和整个西欧。广大青年不仅读它，而且纷纷模仿主人公的穿戴打扮、风度举止，更有少数人学他而自杀了的。大诗人如克罗卜斯托克也为《维特》所倾倒，拿破仑读它甚至达七遍之多。与此同时，《维特》却遭到形形色色卫道士的诟骂，被斥为“淫书”，“不道德的该遭天谴的书”等等，因此译本一出现在米兰，就被教会搜去全部销毁，在丹麦和德国的一些邦，也被宣布为禁书。但尽管如此，仍阻止不了《维特》的流传。它很快译成了各种语言文字，在英、法两国译本分别多达十数种，仿效之作也大量出现。

德国人模仿我，法国人读我入迷，
英国啊，你殷勤接待我这个
憔悴的客人；
可于我又有何益哟，中国人
也用颤抖的手，把维特和绿蒂
画上了镜屏！

歌德这节诗，说的就是他对《维特》的广为流传所感到的矛盾心情。关于中国古瓷上出现维特与绿蒂画像的说法有好几起，较为可信的要数德国汉学家卫礼贤（Richard Wilhelm）在《歌德与中国文化》一文中所提到的。他写道：“………在广州地方，特别为外国人预备瓷器，所谓客货的那类东西，上面的画图是照欧洲人的嗜好绘的，所以画上维特与绿蒂等人的像。”但不管这类传说是否可信，千真万确的却是在《维特》问世后一个半世纪的1922年，我国出版了郭沫若译的《少年维特之烦恼》，同样引起了巨大的反响。当时正处于反封建斗争中的一代中国青年，在《维特》中找到了知音。仅据1932年的一个不完全统计，十年间郭译《维特》已由不同书店重印了三十版之多。最近一些年，各种新译也层出不穷，包括1981年率先推出的拙译在内，各个时期的译本加在一起，数量更多达30种左右。以一部外国文学作品在中国产生影响之大和重译、重版次数之多论，《维特》恐怕是无与伦比的。

《维特》为什么能产生如此巨大的影响？

起决定作用的，首先应该是《维特》所具有的反封建的时代精神，也即上文已经指出过的，它表现了一个时代的烦恼、憧憬以及苦闷。关于这一点，歌德在其自传《诗与真》中说得十分明白：“这本小册子的影响很大，甚至可以说轰动一时，主要就因为它恰在适当的时候出版的缘故。正如只需一点火药线就可引起一个地雷爆炸似的，当时青年的身上已埋藏有厌世的炸药，所以这本小册子在读者群众中引起的爆炸分外猛烈………”。

等到欧洲进入十九世纪四十年代的革命高潮时期，《维特》便不再时兴了。于是海涅在 1842年写的《倾向》一诗中劝诗人“别再像维特那样呻吟，因为他的心只为绿蒂燃烧”。匈牙利革命诗人裴多菲更把《维特》贬得无以复加，干脆称维特是一个“没有骨气的傻瓜”。因为当时的青年不再是哭哭啼啼的厌世者，他们已成了举起剑与火焰来进行斗争的战士。

同样，《维特》在我国广为流传，也主要因为我国“五四”运动时期，与一个半世纪前的德国“狂飙突进”时期有不少类似之处。反对封建压迫、追求个性解放乃是不可阻遏的时代潮流。

其次，必须强调，艺术上的成功也是使《维特》产生巨大影响的重要原因。

歌德恰当地使用了第一人称的书信体，取得了突出的艺术效果。近百封长短书简组成了一个有机整体，前后加上“编者”的引言和按语，读起来使人感到真切可信。信里时而写景，时而抒情，时而叙事，时而议论，读着读着，我们仿佛就变成了收信人，听见了主人公的言谈笑语，啼泣悲叹。

郭沫若在《维特》译本序引中赞它是一篇散文诗。《维特》的确像抒情诗一样以情动人。小说情节并不复杂，但却扣人心弦，引人入胜。作者常常让主人公直抒胸臆，如维特那封在生命的最后两天断断续续写成的绝命书，真是有声有泪，哀婉凄绝。此外他还巧妙地用自然景物烘托情感，用荷马和莪相的诗句或诗中的意境渲染气氛。

“春风呵，你为何将我唤醒？………可是啊，我的衰时近了，风暴即将袭来，吹打得我枝叶飘零！明天，有位旅人将要到来，他见过我的美好青春；他的眼儿将在旷野里四处寻觅，却不见我的踪影……”莪相的这几句哀歌，由即将离开人世的维特念出来，不正成了他自己的凄凉心境与悲惨命运的真切写照了吗？在《维特》中，类似这样能给人以诗的回味的段落，不胜枚举。

再有，小说的人物塑造也很出色。特别是青衣黄裤的翩翩少年维特，已成了世界文学中的著名典型，即那么一种“伟大而又渺小，可爱而又可鄙的怪人”（莱辛语）。

总的来说，强烈的时代精神加上卓越的艺术手法，赋予《维特》以爆炸似的震撼人心的力量，使它在世界各国千千万万的青年读者心中，引起了强烈的共鸣与回响。

从1772年《维特》问世到今天已经过去近两个半世纪。时代完全变了，世界完全变了，今天我们再来阅读、欣赏经典名著，当然也会以完全不同于一百年前的先辈的态度和眼光。作为本书的译者，我希望今日的读者特别是年轻的朋友们，不但能从中了解、认识主人公维特生活的十八世纪的德国社会，也能受到文学的陶冶，获得阅读杰作的巨大愉悦。

2012年10月于德国北威州小城缪尔斯　远望楼

爱的生命

春

亲爱的，让我们一起到丘山中走一走！冰雪已消融，生命已从沉睡中苏醒，正在山谷里和坡地上信步蹒跚。快和我一道走吧！让我们跟上春姑娘的脚步，走向遥远的田野。来吧，让我们登上山顶，尽情观赏四周平原上那起伏连绵的绿色波浪。

看，春的黎明已舒展开寒冬之夜折叠起来的衣裳，桃树、苹果树将之穿在身上，艳美绝伦，颇似“吉庆之夜”(1)的新娘；葡萄园醒来了，葡萄藤相互拥抱，就像互相依偎的情侣；溪水流淌，在岩石间翩翩起舞，唱着欢乐的歌；百花在大自然心上绽放，就像海浪涌起的泡沫。

来吧，让我们饮下水仙花神杯中剩余的泪雨；让我们用鸟雀的欢歌充满我们的心灵；让我们尽情饱闻惠风送来的馨香。

让我们坐在紫罗兰藏身的那块岩石后相亲互吻。

夏

亲爱的，我们一起到田间去吧！收获的日子已经到来，太阳对大自然的炽烈之爱已使五谷成熟。快走吧，我们要赶在前头，以免鸟雀和群蚁趁我们疲惫之时，将我们田地里的成熟谷物夺走。快快采摘大地上的果实，那是心灵采摘爱情，播在我们心灵深处的种子所结出的幸福籽粒。让我们用收获的粮食堆满粮库，就像生活充满我们的情感谷仓。

快快走，我的侣伴！让我们铺青草，盖蓝天，枕上一捆柔软禾秆，消除一日疲劳，静静听赏山涧溪水夜下的低声细语畅谈。

秋

亲爱的，让我们一同走进葡萄园，榨葡萄汁，将之储入池里，就像心灵记取世代先人智慧。让我们采集干果，提取百花香精；果与花之名虽亡，种子与花香之实犹存。

让我们回住处，因为树叶已黄，随风飘飞，仿佛风神想用黄叶为夏天告别时满腹怨言而离去的花儿来做敛衣。百鸟已飞向海岸，带走了花园的生气，把寂寞孤独留给了茉莉和野菊，花园只有将剩余的泪水洒在大地。

让我们打道回府！溪水已停止流淌，泉眼已揩干欢乐的泪痕，丘山也已脱掉艳丽衣裳。亲爱的，快来看，大自然已被困神纠缠，行将用奈哈温德歌声告别人间。

冬

我的生活伴侣，靠近我些，再靠近我一些，莫让冰雪的寒气把我俩的肉体分开。火炉前，你坐在我的身边吧！火炉是冬令最可口的果实，它会给我们讲述来者的前途，因为我的双耳已听厌了风神的呻吟和人类的哭声。关好门和窗户，因为苍天的怒容会使我的精神感到痛苦，看到像失子母亲似的坐在冰层下的城市会使我的心淌血……我的终生伴侣，给灯添些油，因为它快要灭了；把灯放得靠近你一些，以便让我看到夜色写在你脸上的字迹……拿来酒壶，让我们一起畅饮，一道回忆往昔岁月。

靠近我些！心爱的，再靠近我一些！炉火已熄灭，灰烬将火遮掩……紧紧抱住我吧！油灯已熄灭，黑暗笼罩了一切……啊，陈年佳酿已使我们的眼皮沉重不堪……困倦抹过眼睑的眼睛在盯着我……趁困神还未拥抱我，你要紧紧搂住我……亲亲我！冰雪已经征服了一切，只剩下你的热吻……啊，亲爱的，沉睡的大海多么痴呆！啊，在这个世界上，清晨又是何其遥远……

————————————————————

(1) “吉庆之夜”，伊斯兰教对《古兰经》始降之夜的敬称。“盖德尔”系阿拉伯语音译，意为“前定”“定命”“高贵”，译作“高贵的夜晚”“珍贵之夜”“高贵之夜”，又称“前定之夜”或“权力之夜”。关于“盖德尔之夜”的具体日期，教法学家说法不一。以布哈里、穆斯林所辑圣训为根据的3种说法是：⑴在莱麦丹月下旬的单日之中；⑵在该月的后七天之内；⑶该月的第29夜。另外还有4种说法，其中最后一种说法是：“盖德尔之夜”一词由9个阿拉伯文字母组成，在《古兰经》第97章共出现3次，合起来为27个字母，故应为莱麦丹月的第27夜。因这一说法符合圣训精神，故被世界穆斯林所公认。伊斯兰历以日落为一天之始，而中国穆斯林习惯上沿用公历或中国的农历计日法，故常把莱麦丹月的第28夜误认为“盖德尔之夜”。

死人城里

昨天，我摆脱城市的喧嚣，出门漫步在静悄悄的原野，终于登上一座山丘，但见大自然为它穿上了至华至美的盛装。我站在丘山上，极目望去，工厂排出的烟雾凝聚而成的浓密云彩下，整座城市连同高大建筑和宏伟宫殿一览无余，尽收眼底。

我坐在那里，远远地观看人们劳作，发现他们大多是辛苦的。我试图不用心去思考人的作为，而将目光转向主的光荣宝座——原野，看见当中有一墓地，那里排列着许多大理石坟墓，周围满是苍松翠柏。

在那里，我坐在活人城与死人城之间沉思，思考着在这里进行的持续不断的斗争和永不休止的活动，而那里却是无限的沉寂与永恒的安静。这一面，充满希望与失望，而且有爱有憎，有富有穷，有信神的有不信神的；另一面，却是除了土，还是土，大自然将之翻过来，再埋下去，从中创造出植物、动物，一切都是在寂静的夜里完成的。

当我正沉湎于冥想遐思之时，忽见一群人缓步走来，走在前面的是乐队，哀乐响彻天空。那支队伍规模宏大，富贵威严，队伍里什么样的人都有，气势雄壮，浩浩荡荡。原来那是一支为一位富豪送葬的队伍。一口棺木后面跟着大队活人，哭声惊天动地，直上云霄。

队伍到达墓地，祭司们聚在一起，祈祷焚香，乐师们吹起喇叭。片刻后，演说家们争相显示口才，用最精美的言辞为死者歌功颂德。接着是诗人们朗诵诗歌，用最华丽的诗句悼念死者。所有这些仪式都在令人厌烦的冗长过程中完成。过了一会儿，众人散去，那里留下一座新墓，乃是雕刻工匠和工程师们的精心之作，四周摆放着工艺匠人们用巧手扎成的花圈。

队伍返回城里，我远远望着，依旧沉思。

夕阳西下，山岩、树木的影子渐渐变长，大自然开始脱下用光编织、剪裁的衣衫。

那时，我又看见两个男子抬着一口木棺，后面跟着一个衣衫褴褛的女人，怀里还抱着一个吃奶的婴儿，身边跟着一条狗。那条狗时而望望女人，时而瞧瞧棺材。这是一个贫苦人的葬礼：跟在后面的妻子淌着悲泪，婴儿随着母亲哭泣不止，忠实的狗紧紧跟着，与孤儿寡母一样悲伤痛苦。

这些人来到墓地，将棺材埋在墓地的一个角落里，远远离开那座大理石墓，然后带着伤心的肃静返回。那条狗却不住回头望望主人的下葬之处。我一直望着那条狗，直到人们的身影消失在树林之后。

此时，我回头朝活人城望去，心想：“那座城市属于富贵豪强。”而后又朝死人城望了望，说道：“这座城市也属于富贵豪强！主啊，穷贫弱者的安身之地又在何方？”

我说着，朝镶着金色夕阳光边的浓密彩霞望去，只听我的内心发出一种声音，说：“就在那里！”

诗人之死是生

夜幕笼罩城市上空，冰雪为城市穿上冬装，严寒迫使人们退出市场，躲藏在自己的安乐巢窝里。狂风在房舍之间呼啸悲叹，就像吊丧者站在大理石墓间哀悼死神的猎物。

在城边上，有一座简陋茅舍，柱斜梁倾，在厚厚的冰雪重压下，行将坍塌。小屋的一角，放着一张破床，床上躺着一个奄奄一息、行将就木之人。他望着那微弱的灯光，那灯头似在竭尽全力挣扎，试图征服黑暗，但终于被黑暗压倒。那还是一个正值青春妙龄的少年郎，却知道自己大限即至，就要永远地摆脱生活桎梏，等待着死神降临。他那蜡黄色的脸上闪烁着求生渴望之光，而双唇上溢出的仍是凄楚的微笑。那是一位诗人：来到世上，以用纯美言辞给人送去欢乐为本；如今，就要饿死在这富贵活人城中了。那是一个高尚的灵魂：蒙主之恩而降生，以便使生活变得更甜美；如今，人类还未报之以微笑，它就要告别我们这个世界了。他已进入人生的弥留之际，行将断气，身旁只有油灯一盏，那是他孤独寂寞之中的伙伴；还有一页页诗稿，满载着他那颗高尚灵魂的梦幻。

那位生命垂危的青年，竭尽余力，把双手举上空中，睁开疲倦的眼皮，仿佛想用最后一丝目光穿透那破烂茅舍的屋顶，观看隐藏在乌云之后的繁星，然后说：

“美丽的死神，你来吧！我的神魂想念你呀！走近我，解去我身上的物质枷锁吧！因为我拖着它已感疲惫不堪。来吧，美妙的死神，快把我从人群中解救出来吧！只因我把从天使那里听来的话翻译成了人的语言，他们便说我是异己分子。快朝我走来吧！人已经抛弃了我，把我丢入被遗忘的角落，只因为我不像人一样贪图钱财，也不使用不如我的人。甜美的死神，快到我这里来，带我走吧！我的同胞们已不需要我。让我投入你那充满爱的怀抱吧！求你吻吻我的双唇。我这双唇既未尝过母亲亲吻的滋味，也没有接触过姐妹的前额，更未亲过意中情人的嘴。亲爱的死神，快来拥抱我吧！”

这时，诗人的病榻旁边突然闪出一位女子的身影，其美远非凡人所具有，只见她身穿雪白晶莹的衣裙，手持采自天园的百合花环。她走近诗人，热情拥抱他，伸手合上他的眼帘，以便让他借灵魂的目光看着她。她吻了吻他的双唇，那充满深爱的一吻留给诗人双唇的是心满意足的微笑。

刹那之间，茅屋变得空余尘土，只有一些诗稿散落在黑暗角落。

岁月不居，时节如流，数世代飞闪而过。那座城中的居民一直沉湎于昏睡之中。当他们苏醒过来，眼睛看到知识的曙光时，他们在公共广场的中心为那位诗人建造了一座巨大塑像，并为他确定了每年的纪念日……啊，人是多么愚昧！

笑与泪

夕阳从花木繁茂的花园收起金黄色的长尾，明月升起在遥远天际，将柔和的月华洒在花园里。我坐在树下，静静观赏着天色的变化，透过树木枝条间仰望挂在瓦蓝色的天毯上的银圆似的星斗，耳里聆听着从远处山谷传来的溪水的淙淙流淌声。

鸟儿藏身在叶子浓密的树枝间，花儿合上了眼，大自然一片寂静。这时，忽然听到踏着青草的沙沙脚步声，我调转视线望去，只见一对少年男女正朝我走来。片刻后，二人坐在一棵枝繁叶茂的树下；我能看见他俩，而他俩看不见我。

那小伙子朝四周环视了一下，我听他说：“亲爱的，你就坐在我的身边，听我说吧！你微笑吧！因为你的微笑是我们未来的标志。你欢乐吧！因为岁月已在为我们而欢乐。我的心灵告诉我，你的心中有疑虑；亲爱的，对爱情心怀疑虑是一种罪过。这大片银白色月光映照下的地产很快就要归你所有，你也将成为这足以与王宫媲美宫殿的女主人。我的宝马将供你四处游览时乘骑，我的花车将载着你出入舞场、筵席。亲爱的，你就像我的宝库中的黄金那样笑吧！亲爱的，你就像我父亲的珠宝那样望着我吧！亲爱的，你听，我的心只会在你的面前倾诉衷情。等待我们的是甜蜜华年。我们将带着大量金钱，到瑞士湖畔、意大利旅游胜地、尼罗河上的宫殿附近和黎巴嫩的雪杉下，度过我们的甜蜜华年。你将见到公主和贵妇人，她们也会嫉妒你的周身华丽服饰、珠光宝气。那一切都由我提供给你，难道你不喜欢？你的微笑多么甜美！你的微笑与我命运的微笑是何其相似！”

过了一会儿，我看见他俩缓步走去，脚下踏着鲜花，就像富人的脚踏着穷人的心。

二人消失在我的视野里，而我还在思考着金钱在爱情中的地位。我想：金钱乃人为恶之本，而爱情则是幸福与光明源泉。

我一直沉浸于这种思考之中，直至看见两个人影从我面前走过，然后坐在草地上。一个是小伙子，另一个是姑娘，都来自田间农家茅舍。一阵发人沉思的寂静过后，我听到那个患肺病小伙子的谈话中夹带着沉重叹息声。他说：“亲爱的，擦擦泪！爱神想打开我们的眼界，使我们成为她的崇拜者。爱神赋予我们以忍耐品性和吃苦精神。亲爱的，擦擦眼泪！你要忍耐，因为我们早已结成崇拜爱神的同盟。为了甜蜜生活，我们宁可忍受穷困折磨、不幸苦涩和分离熬煎。我一定要与岁月搏斗，以便挣到一笔堪放你手中的金钱，足以帮助我们度过此生各个阶段。亲爱的，爱就是我们的主，会像笑纳香火那样接受我们这叹息泪水，同样也把我们应得的奖赏赠予我们。亲爱的，我要和你告别，月落乌啼之前我将离去。”

继之，我听到一种低微柔和的声音，且不住被炽热的长吁短叹声打断。那是一位温柔少女的声音，其中饱含发自少女周身的爱情之火热、分离之痛苦和忍耐之甘甜。她说：“亲爱的，再见！”

二人分手，我仍坐在那棵树下，只觉得无数只怜悯之手争相拉我，这奇妙宇宙的种种奥秘争相涌入我的脑海。

那时，我朝着沉睡的大自然望去，久久凝视，发现那里有一种横无际涯的东西：那种东西，用金钱买不到；那种东西，秋天的眼泪抹不去，冬季的痛苦折磨不死；那种东西，在瑞士的湖泊、意大利的旅游胜地找不到；那种东西，忍耐到春天复生，夏令结果。

我在那里所发现的原本就是爱情。

昔与今

一位富翁漫步在自己公馆的花园里，愁闷一直紧跟着他的脚步，忧虑在他的头上打转，就像苍鹰在死神击中的死尸上空盘旋。富翁终于走到了湖边，那是一个人工湖，周边有用大理石雕成的围栏。他坐在那里，时而望望从禽兽雕像口中喷涌出来的水，那水酷似从情人脑海里涌出的思潮；时而瞧瞧他那坐落在山丘上的宫殿，那宫殿很像美人痣镶在少女的腮边。

富翁坐着，思绪联翩，往昔写下的关于他的生活的故事，一页一页地展现在他的眼前。他开始读着，禁不住泪水簌簌下落，模糊了双眼，看不到那人工湖水面；悲伤之情将神编织的往日画面重现于他的心间，止不住怨言脱口而出。他说：

“往昔，我曾在葱绿的山冈间牧羊，高高兴兴地生活，吹起我的芦笛，表达我的由衷欢乐。如今，我竟成了贪欲的俘虏，钱财把我引向钱财，钱财又把我引入醉生梦死，醉生梦死将把我带入不幸境地。往昔，我像鸟儿一样鸣啭歌唱，像蝴蝶一样款款飞舞。微风踏草头的脚步并不比我踏田野的脚步更轻。看哪，如今我却成了社会习俗的囚徒：靠穿着矫揉造作，不时出入筵宴；一切工作全为了讨好人类及其法规。我本期望我为享受人间快乐而生，然而今天，我发现自己为金钱所累，步上了一条痛苦之路，就像背驮黄金的骆驼，黄金将要置骆驼于死地。宽广的平原在哪里？唱歌的小溪何在？清新的空气在哪里？大自然的高贵何在？我的心神又在何方？我已失去了这一切，留给我的只有黄金；我喜欢黄金，而黄金却嘲笑、蔑视我。我的奴仆多了，而我的欢悦少了；我的宫殿高耸，却毁灭了我的快乐。往昔，我与游牧民的女儿同行，纯美忠贞伴着我们，纯真爱情是我们的挚友，皎洁月光为我们照明；如今，我却身陷在那么一帮女人当中：一个个伸长脖子，挤眉弄眼，借金链、饰带换取艳美，见镯子、戒指便出让皮肉。往昔，我与青年们像一群羚羊活跃在林间，一道歌唱，共享田野之乐；如今，我在众人之间，就像猛禽爪中的羔羊，走在大街被人们用讨厌的眼光盯视，被人们嫉妒的手指指点，到游览地看见的尽是高昂的头和冷酷的脸。往昔，天赋予我以勃勃生气，饱尝大自然之美；如今，这两项天福在我已完全被剥夺。往昔，我是个饱享幸福的富翁；如今，我变成了一贫如洗的穷光蛋。往昔，我与我的羊，就像仁慈的国王与其臣民；如今，我与我的金山，就像低贱的奴隶站在主人面前……我没有想到金钱会遮蔽我的心眼，将我的心灵引向愚昧深渊；我也不知道被人们视为荣誉的东西，却像地狱之火一样灼烧人心……”

富翁原地站起身来，缓步向自己的宫殿走去，不住地叹息道：“莫非这就是钱财？难道这就是神，我已成了它的祭司？莫非它就是我们用生命买来的，却不能用它换回一丝生命？我付出一堪他尔(1)黄金，谁能卖给我一个美好想法？谁能用一把珠宝换得一分钟爱情？谁能拿走我的金库，仅仅给我一只能看到美的眼睛？”

富翁来到殿门前，就像耶利米(2)望耶路撒冷城那样，朝城市望了一眼，并用手向城市指了一下，仿佛在向城市表示哀悼之意，并高声说道：“人们啊，你们走在黑暗中，坐在死神阴影下，紧追困苦，胡乱断案，倾吐蠢言，只吃芒刺，却把果和花丢进深渊……如此行动，会延续到何年何月？你们走崎岖小道，栖身废墟之间，抛弃生命乐园，如此生活将继续到何日何年？绫罗绸缎锦衣已为你们做好，你们为什么却要穿破衣烂衫？人们啊，智慧之灯行将熄灭，快给它添些油吧！流浪汉要破坏你们的葡萄园，快起来保卫它吧！盗贼偷了你们的舒适库房，你们要当心呀！”

就在那时，一个穷人站在了富翁的面前，伸手向他讨钱。富翁望着穷人，颤抖的双唇合起，紧皱的面容舒展开来，双目间闪出温和的光芒。他在湖边痛惜的往昔已经走来向他问安。于是，他走近乞丐，亲切、平等地吻了吻他，并将一把黄金递到穷人手里，怜悯之情充满话语间，说：“兄弟，你现在拿着这些金子，明天和你的伙伴一道来，把你们的钱财都拿回去吧！”穷人就像凋零的花儿雨后重新鲜灵起来，微微一笑，快步离去。

富翁进到殿堂，说道：“生活中的一切都是美的，钱财也不例外，因为它能教人警句格言：钱财如同风琴，不善弹奏者只能听到不悦耳的噪音；钱财又像爱情，令吝啬鬼死亡，让慷慨者永生。”

————————————————————

(1) 堪他尔，重量单位，等于45公斤。

(2) 耶利米，犹太人，大祭司希勒家的儿子。他原为便雅悯地区拿突城的祭司，奉上帝召见之后，成为列国先知。在约雅敬、约雅斤、西底家三个犹大王朝时期，耶利米一直四处传道，说了很多预言。因他所说的预言触怒当局，一再受到迫害。犹大国王西底家第十年，因他说了西底家必被巴比伦王打败的预言，就被西底家囚禁起来。巴比伦王攻破耶路撒冷城后，却把耶利米放了出来，并送给他粮食和礼物，让他自由选择去向。相传，《圣经》中的《耶利米书》和《耶利米哀歌》为耶利米所作。

孤儿寡母

夜迅速朝黎巴嫩北部袭来，彻底征服了白昼。在过去的白天里，卡迪沙山谷周围的村子下了一场大雪，使得田野、高原变成了一张大白纸，风神在上面不住地画线条，复又不停地抹去；暴风雪向大自然发怒的天气配合，肆意嬉戏、拨弄那张白纸。

人们躲藏在自己的家里，动物隐身于自己的窝穴，一切有生息的都停止了活动，只剩下严寒、阴冷、可怕的黑暗和令人恐怖的死亡。

在那片农村中的一座孤零零的房子里，有一妇人，坐在火炉前，正在织毛衣。待在妇人身边的是她的独生子。孩子时而望望火炉，时而瞧瞧母亲那平静的面孔。那时，阴风怒号，整座房子被刮得飘摇欲坠。孩子一惊，急忙靠近母亲，以求母亲慈爱的护佑，用来抗拒天怒。母亲忙把孩子搂在怀里，连连亲吻，然后让孩子坐在自己的双膝上，并且说：“孩子，不要怕！大自然有意教训人类：面对渺小的人类，展示自己的巨大；面对人类的脆弱，表现自己的强劲。孩子，不要害怕！在漫天飘雪、密布阴云和疯狂暴风后面，还有一个圣灵，全然知道田野和丘山需要什么。在这一切后面，还有一种目光，在用同情、怜悯的眼睛望着可怜的人。不要怕，我的心肝宝贝！春天微笑、夏季大笑、秋令叹息的大自然，现在想哭，伏在土层下的生命还等着吮吸它那冷冰的眼泪。睡吧，孩子！明天醒来，你会看到天空晴朗，田野穿着雪白的外衣，就像灵魂与死神搏斗之后换上了圣洁服装。孩子，睡吧！你父亲正在永恒平台上望着我们。多好的暴风雪，正是它使我们更加思念那些不朽的灵魂。亲爱的孩子，睡吧！四月来临时，美丽的鲜花就将从这些相互剧烈搏斗的各种因素里采摘。孩子，人也如此，只有经历了痛苦的疏远、苦涩的忍耐和致命的失望之后，才能采摘到至爱的果实。我的小宝贝呀，睡觉吧！甜蜜的梦必将来到你的心灵，既不怕黑夜的阴森，亦不惧严寒的侵袭。”

孩子望着母亲，困神已经驾临他的双眼。他说：“妈妈，我的眼皮直打架，恐怕念不上祈祷词，就睡着了。”慈祥的母亲紧紧搂住他，用泪眼望着他那天使般的面容，然后说：“孩子，跟妈一道说：主，求你怜悯穷苦人！保护穷苦人免受严寒折磨，用你的手遮住穷苦人的赤身！主，请瞧瞧睡在茅屋中的孤儿们！冰雪的寒气正在损伤着他们的身体。主，听听站在大街上、正在死神和寒冷魔爪中苦苦挣扎的寡母们的呼号！主，把你的手伸进富人的心中，打开富人的眼界，让他们看看受压迫的弱者是怎样忍受着贫困与饥馑！主，怜悯在这漆黑夜下站在门外的饥饿者，把沦落异乡的流浪汉带往温暖安身处，体谅他们背井离乡之苦！主，请你顾看一下小鸟儿们，用你的右手保护惧怕肆虐狂风的树木……主，请让这一切化为现实！”

当困意拥抱孩子的心灵时，母亲将他平放在床上，用颤抖的双唇吻了吻孩子的前额，然后回到火炉旁，继续为儿子织毛衣。

美神宝座前

我从社会逃离出来，徘徊在宽广的山谷中，时而沿溪水前往，时而静听鸟儿鸣唱，终于来到一个枝叶遮天蔽日的地方，于是坐下来，开始独自沉思，自言自语。一颗干渴的心灵，认为一切可见的都是海市蜃楼，而一切不可见的却全是陈酿美酒。

当我的头脑挣脱了物质的监牢，跃入幻梦天际时，无意中回头一望，忽见一位姑娘站在我的附近。那是一位仙女，不见珠光宝气，没有华衣锦饰，只有一条葡萄藤遮盖着部分肢体，还有一个花环束着金黄色的秀发……她从我的眼神里知道我一时惊愕不已，不知如何是好。她说：“我是林地之女。你不要害怕！”她那甜美声音恢复了我部分气息。我说：“像你这样的美女，怎么住在这野兽出没的凄清山野？凭你的生命起誓，告诉我，你究竟是何许人？又从何地而来？”她坐在草地上，说道：“我是大自然的象征。我就是你的祖辈崇拜，并在巴勒贝克、艾弗加和朱拜勒为之建祭坛、神庙的那位神女。”我说：“那些神庙已经倒塌，我的祖辈尸骨也已化为净土，他们崇拜的神和宗教的遗迹仅仅留在几页书中。”她说：“有的神伴随着崇拜者的生而生存，伴随着崇拜者的死而死亡，而有的神则依靠永恒的神性长生不老。至于我的神性，则源于你无论怎样都能看到的美。美就是整个大自然。美本是山冈间牧羊人、田间农夫和漂泊在山与海之间人们幸福的起点。美是智者登上颠覆不破真理宝座的阶梯。”我的心怦怦直跳，在说着口舌不会说的话。我说：“美是一种可怕的力量。”她的双唇间绽现出鲜花般的微笑，目光中蕴含着生命的秘密。她说：“你们人类什么都怕，甚至怕你们自身。你们怕天，而天本是安全之源；你们怕大自然，而大自然本是供休息的床榻；你们惧怕众神之主，并将仇恨和愤怒全归罪于它。其实，它既不是什么仁慈怜悯，也不是别的什么。”

一阵夹带着美梦的沉寂过后，我问她：“美究竟是何物？就像人们对它的赞美和热爱各不相同一样，人们对它的解释和理会千差万别。”她说：“它对于你的心灵有一种吸引力；当你遇到它时，你会感到数双手从你的内心深处伸出，以便将之拢到你的内心深处；肉体将之视为一种考验，灵魂把它看作一种馈赠；它可使悲欢者们之间亲近、融洽、友爱；它隐藏着，你能看到它；它不为人知，你却知道它；它沉默无声，你能听到它；它是一种力量，起自你的圣洁心灵，终结在你的想象之外……”

林地之女走近我，伸出她的酥手捂住我的眼睛。当她把手移开时，我发现我独自站在山谷中。我起身回返，心灵一遍又一遍地重复着：“美，是你所看到的；你甘愿奉献，无意索取。”

茅屋与宫殿

一

夜幕垂降，富翁的公馆里灯火辉煌，仆人们站在大门口，个个身着锦衣华饰，人人胸前纽扣闪光，等待宾临客至。

乐队高奏着欢乐的迎宾曲，众贵族男女乘坐香车宝马陆续来到公馆前，男的绣金锦袍加身，女的拖着显示富贵的长裙，一个个高视阔步，洋洋得意地步入大门。

男人们站起邀女子跳舞，女人们选定舞伴，刹那之间，大厅变成了舞曲惠风拂面的乐园，百花随风起舞，翩跹摇曳，春意盎然。

夜半时分，筵席摆就，种种美味俱全，色色水果新鲜。宾主举杯把盏，畅饮玉液琼浆，直喝得个个酩酊大醉，头昏目眩，东倒西歪。

晨光初照，熬了一整夜的贵族男女，酒喝得醉意朦胧，舞跳得精疲力竭，人人无精打采，方才散伙，各自爬上软床睡去。

二

日落之后，一个身穿劳动服的男子站在一座茅屋门前。敲过门，门开启了，他走了进去。他微笑着向家人问安之后，和孩子们一起坐在火堆旁取暖。片刻后，妻子备好了晚饭，一家人围木桌而坐，大口大口吃得又香又甜。饭后，他们走去，坐在一盏油灯旁，那灯头发出的黄色微弱光箭直扫黑暗。

一更天过去，他们不声不响地站起，然后躺下，酣然进入梦乡。

黎明时分，那男子起床后，与妻儿一起吃过些许面饼和牛奶，一一亲吻家人，继之肩扛大锄走向田地。他要用自己额头上的汗水浇灌土地，收获食粮，以供养昨夜纵酒狂舞作乐的富人。

太阳升上东山，炎热之神的脚重重地踏在耕夫的头上，而那些富人仍在他们巍峨宫殿里安睡梦中。

这是人类舞台上常演不衰的悲剧；为之叫好的观众大有人在，而静心沉思者却寥若晨星。

两个婴儿

国王站在宫殿阳台上，呼唤聚集在御花园的人们，说道：“我向你们报喜，我向国家道贺！王后生下一个王子，他将传承皇家光荣门第的尊严，同时也是你们的荣耀，还将成为列祖列宗留下基业的继承人。你们欢呼吧！你们的未来就寄托在王家子孙身上。”

众人齐声欢呼，欢声直上云天，热烈庆贺王子降生，衷心祝贺他在富贵摇篮里发育，在慈爱花台上长大，日后成为掌握奴隶生杀大权的绝对统治者，以自己的力量控制弱者的命运，随便使用他们的肉体，任意毁灭他们的灵魂。因此，他们兴高采烈，喜唱欢歌，沉湎于醉态之中。

就在那座城中，当居民盛赞强者，蔑视自己，欢歌专横者的大名，而天使却为他们的渺小泣哭之时，在一个被废弃的简陋茅舍里，有一妇人躺在病榻上，火热的怀里抱着一个用破烂襁褓包裹着的婴儿。

那是一位年轻女子，岁月注定她贫困不堪；贫困便是不幸，人们置之不理。她是一位妻子，国王的暴虐夺去了她丈夫的生命。她孤身一人，那天夜里，神给她派来了一个小伙伴，缠住了她的双手，使她无暇劳作谋生。

街上人们的喧闹声静息下来，那个可怜的女人将婴儿抱在怀里，望着孩子那闪亮的双眸，痛哭不止，仿佛她想用热泪为孩子施洗。她用足以令顽石破裂的声音说：“我的心肝宝贝儿，你为什么要从灵魂世界来到人间呀？你想分担我的痛苦生活呢，还是想怜悯我的虚弱？你为什么要离开天使和广袤天园，来到这个充满不幸和屈辱的狭窄人间？我的独生儿，我只有泪水；泪水能替代奶汁将你喂饱吗？你能拿我这赤裸的双臂当衣穿吗？牲口幼崽儿能吃青草，然后在窝棚里放心过夜；小鸟儿能啄食籽粒，然后安栖枝间巢中；你呢，我的孩子，除了我的叹息和虚弱，一无所有！”

妇人将孩子紧紧搂在自己的胸口，仿佛想使二体合一。她抬眼望着上方，大声喊道：“主啊，怜悯怜悯我们吧！”

乌云散去，月亮高悬，柔和的月光透过窗子，映入茅屋，洒在两具冰冷的尸体上……

致非难者

非难我的人，不要打搅我，让我独自待上一会儿！情侣的俊美使你爱在心中，母亲的慈爱在你心里无比可靠，儿女的情感将你的神魂打动。我求你凭这一切起誓，不要管我，让我自主行事！

请让我独自行事，自由做梦。请你忍耐到明天，任凭明天对我裁决。

你曾对我提出忠告，而忠告不过是幻影，只能把心灵带往彷徨天地，引导心灵走到生命僵死如土的地方。

我有一颗微小的心，我想把它从胸中掏出来，托在掌上，仔细探究它深处的秘密。非难我的人，请你不要用你那信念的利箭伏候着它，致使它因为害怕中箭而躲进胸腔，既无暇倾出心血，也不能尽情用美和爱尽时光赋予它的义务。

太阳已经升起，夜莺、篙雀唱个不停，桃金娘、紫罗兰花香四溢。我想挣脱卧榻粘缠，随着雪白羊群前进。

非难我的人，不要对我那样严厉，不要用林中猛狮、山谷毒蛇恫吓我！因为我的神魂不知何为恐惧，不善警戒厄运来临。

非难我的人，不要管我，也不要告诫我！因为灾难打开了我的眼界，泪水洗刷了我的眼帘，痛苦教会了我用心语。

请不要提那些禁令！我的良知里就有一个法庭，会对我做出公正判决：假若我确乎无辜，它会保护我免受惩罚；如我真是罪犯，它定会让我得到报应。

看，爱的队伍已经启程，美举着爱的旗帜紧跟，青年们边走边吹奏着欢乐乐曲。

非难我的人，不要阻拦我，让我跟着他们前进！看，眼前的道路上铺满玫瑰花和香草，空气中充满着麝香的芬芳。

请把我从利禄功名的说教中解放出来！因为我的心灵不再需要那些，只是沉醉在上帝的荣光之中。

请让我免受政治、权势的纠缠！因为整个大地是我的故乡，所有人都是我的同胞。

爱情秘语

我的美人儿，你现在哪里？你在小花园里浇灌那些爱你如同婴孩恋母的花儿？还是在自己的闺房，那个你为圣洁建造了祭坛，我誓愿以灵魂和生命献祭的地方？或者你在书海徜徉，虽然你已满腹经纶，还想更多地汲取人类的智慧？

我心灵的伴侣，你在何方？你在庙堂为我祈祷，还是在田野与你钦敬和梦想的大自然亲切交谈？或者在受苦人的茅舍里，用你那甜润的心灵安慰苦心欲碎的女人，并且慷慨施予她们以思想？

你无处不在，因为你是上帝灵魂的一部分；你无时不有，因为你强健胜过光明。

你可记得我们相聚的夜晚？你的心灵之光在我们周围形成光环，爱的天使围绕着我们，我们尽情歌颂圣灵的伟业。你可记得我们同坐在树荫下的白天？浓荫遮蔽着我们，仿佛有意挡住人们的视线，就像肋骨将心的神圣秘密遮掩。你可记得我们走过的小径、斜坡？你我的手指，就像你的辫子一样，发束相互编在一起；你我头依着头，酷似你保护着我，我保护着你。你可记得你来告别的时刻？你拥抱我，亲吻我。你给我的是圣母马利亚式的一吻，我从中知道，唇与唇一旦相吻，便带来了语言难以表述的天上秘密。那一吻是双双合叹一口气的前奏；那一口气就像上帝吹入泥中的那口气，泥顿时变成了人。那一口气，先于我们到达灵魂世界，宣布你我两颗心灵的高贵，在那里一直待到我们与之相会，永不分离……之后，你亲吻我，再亲吻我，流着泪说：“肉体有说不清、道不明的志趣，往往因为世间琐事和微小目的而分别远离；灵魂则不同，总是安居爱神掌中，直至死神降临，将之带往上帝那里。亲爱的，你去吧！生活既然委派你完成什么使命，你就乖乖服从她吧！生活是位美女，她会让服从者饱饮满杯的甘甜多福河(1)水。至于我嘛，你的爱就是与我朝夕相伴的新郎；思念你，那便是经久不散的吉庆婚礼。”

我的情侣，你现在哪里？每当微风吹向你那边时，我总是让它带去我的心脏搏动声和周身的隐秘。莫非你静夜里没有入睡？或者在静观意中情郎的肖像？那肖像已不似今日的他：往昔他因在你的身旁而眉头舒展，如今痛苦已在他的额上投下了阴影；往昔他的眼睑因用你的美搽涂而神采飞扬，如今已因哭泣而枯皱不堪；往昔他的双唇因你亲吻而富有润泽，如今已因干裂而失颜。

亲爱的，你在何方？你在大海后可能听到我的呼喊和哭声，看得见我的虚弱和低贱，晓知我的耐心和坚忍？莫非天空中没有能传达一个痛苦临终人声息的灵魂？难道心灵之间没有报送一位弥留中情人苦衷的无形连线？

我的生命，你在哪里？黑暗已将我扼住，悲伤已将我压倒。只要你在空中微笑，我就能恢复精神；只要你在苍穹呼吸，我就能重得生机。

亲爱的，你在何方？你在哪里？

啊，爱情多么伟大，而我又何其渺小！

————————————————————

(1) 多福河，神话传说中天堂里的一条河。

两种死

夜阑更深，死神从上帝那里降向熟睡的城市，落在一座宣礼塔顶。它用它那明亮的目光穿透住宅墙壁，看到乘坐在幻梦翅膀上的灵魂和受困神意志制约的躯体。

月亮沉没在曦微晨光之后，城市披上一层梦幻似的薄纱，死神迈着轻轻的脚步穿行在住宅之间，终于来到一个富豪的公馆。死神抬脚进门，没有遇到任何障碍。它站在富豪床边，伸手触摸富豪的前额，富豪惊醒过来。他一看见死神的影子站在面前，惶恐万状，失声喊道：“可怕的梦魔，离我远点！凶恶的幻影，你快走开！你这个盗贼，你是怎么进来的？你这个强盗，你来干什么？我是这家主人，你给我走开！快滚开！不然，我就要喊来奴仆和守卫，将你碎尸万段！”

死神走近富豪，用惊雷似的声音说道：“我就是死神！你要注意，放尊重一些！”富豪回答道：“你现在要我怎么样？你有什么要求？我还没有结束自己的工作，你为什么就来了？你对像我这样的富豪大亨有何要求？你还是到久病的人那里去吧！你快离开我，不要让我看见你那伤人的利爪和你那毒蛇似的长发。你走吧！我讨厌看你那两个巨大的翅膀和破烂的体躯。”一阵令人烦恼的沉寂之后，富豪又说：“不，不！仁慈的死神啊，我刚才说的那些话，请你不要在意！我因害怕，一时心惶，才那样说的。你拿一斗黄金走，或者带走几个家仆的灵魂，放我一马吧……死神，我还想活下去，因为我还有没结清的账，人们欠我的钱还没有还清；海上还有我的船，尚未靠岸；地里的庄稼也还没有长成。我这里的东西随你拿，只要放过我就行。我有婢女若干，个个像晨光那样美丽，任你挑，任你选。死神呀，你听我说，我有一个独生子，我喜欢他，我的希望全寄托在他的身上，你把他带走吧！只要能把我留下，你愿意拿什么就拿什么，你可以把一切都拿走，只求你放开我！”

富翁话音未落，死神伸手堵住那个凡奴的嘴，摄取了他的灵魂，并将之交给风神带走了。

旋即，死神又走进柔弱穷苦人们居住的区域，来到一座简陋茅舍。进了门，靠近一张床，那张床上躺着一个青春少年。死神观察一番少年的文静面孔，然后伸手触摸少年的眼睛，少年醒了过来。少年见死神站在自己的身边，急忙双膝下跪，伸出胳膊，用充满钟爱和思念的声音说：“死神，美丽的死神，我就在这里。你是我梦中的真实，你是我的希望所在，请接受我的灵魂吧！我心爱的死神，把我带走吧！你是仁慈的，不要把我丢在这里。你是神的使者，你是真理的右手，不要把我丢下。我曾多少次找你而见不到你，我曾多少次呼唤你而你没听到。你现在听到我的声音了，请不要拒绝我的愿望。亲爱的死神，拥抱我吧！”

这时，死神用柔软的手指捂住少年的双唇，摄取了他的灵魂，放在自己的双翼之下。

死神在空中盘旋，望着这个世界，对着风说：“只有来自永恒世界的人，才能回到永恒世界去。”

岁月游戏场

在美的效用与爱的幻梦之间徜徉的一分钟，要比可怜弱者在把光荣献给贪婪强者中所度过的一生都要高贵。

那一分钟里，人的神格得以生发；而那一生里，人的神格总在沉睡，蒙盖着噩梦的面纱。那一分钟里，心灵得以从人的种种法规重负下解放出来；而那一生里，心灵总是被囚禁在被人冷落的高墙之后，身上戴着沉重的镣铐。那一分钟，是所罗门诗篇(1)、山中训诫(2)和法里德塔韵长诗(3)的摇篮；而那一生，则是一种捣毁巴勒贝克神庙、台德木尔王宫和巴比伦城堡的盲目力量。

心灵在为穷人权利被剥夺、为公正丧失而遗憾，在叹息中度过的一天，要比富翁在纵欲、自私中度过的一生高贵、圣洁。那一天，可以借火纯洁心灵，用光明将心照亮；而这一生，全是在黑暗中挣扎，最后被埋在土层之下。那一天，是得启悟道(4)日，是髑髅地之日，是迁徙(5)日；而这一生，则是尼禄(6)自己的生命耗在暴虐市场上的一生，是可拉(7)身在贪欲祭坛上的一生，是唐璜(8)埋在坟墓中的一生。

这就是生活：黑暗在岁月的游戏场上将之演得类似悲剧，而白昼则将之当歌唱，最后永恒世界将之作为珍宝保存起来……

————————————————————

(1) 指《圣经·旧约》中的一部多人诗歌创作合集《诗篇》，属《圣录》。所罗门为其中的作者之一，还有大卫、可拉后裔、亚萨、以探、摩西等人。主要内容包括歌咏犹太教的真、善、美，颂扬圣境、圣物、圣徒，赞美上帝耶和华。

(2) 指穆罕默德四十岁那年，斋月的“珍贵之夜”，在希拉山洞里所得到的“训诫”，即第一次降临世上的《古兰经》。

(3) 法里德，即伊本·法里德，其作品《塔韵长诗》达760行，描写精神恋爱。

(4) 当指摩西一天到何烈山为岳父放羊，见到耶和华上帝，上帝命令他带领以色列人离开埃及返回迦南。

(5) 指穆罕默德迁都至麦地那，即公元622年7月16日，这是回历元年1月1日。

(6) 尼禄，古罗马暴君，以暴虐、放荡而闻名。

(7) 可拉，《圣经》人物，以色列利米族人，可拉党的领袖。他出生在埃及，在出埃及前往迦南途中，带头结党反对摩西和亚伦，受到上帝的惩罚，死于大地崩裂之中。

(8) 唐璜，拜伦著名长诗《唐璜》中的主人公，一生玩世不恭，几经情场艳遇的花花公子。

和平

将树枝吹弯，把庄稼刮倒的暴风平息下来了，繁星出现，像是电闪留在天幕上的剩余碎片。田野也平静下来了，仿佛那里不曾发生过两军激战。

这时，一位娘子走进自己的卧室，跪在床上，痛哭起来。旋即，她长吁短叹，声音阵高，呼出的热气凝成了这些话语：

“主啊，把他还给我吧！我的泪已哭干，我的肝胆俱裂。圣灵啊，你让他回来吧！因为你的英明裁决远比人的禁令有力。我的忍耐力已枯竭，我已完全被悲伤压倒。求你让他摆脱残酷的战争魔爪吧！求你把他从死神的手中拯救出来吧！主啊，求你怜悯他这么一个羸弱青年，正是强者的暴力从我的手中将他夺去的。爱神啊，你战胜你的劲敌——战神吧！求你将我的爱人拯救出来，因为他也是你的儿女。死神呀，你离他远一点！让他看看我，或者把我带到他的身边去吧！”

就在这时，一个青年走进房间，但见他头裹白色绷带，上有战神书写的腥红色字样。青年走近娘子，用泪和笑向她问安，然后拉住她的手，放在自己那火热的嘴唇上，继之用饱含炽热情感和久别重逢欢乐的声音说：

“你莫惊惶！你为之泣哭落泪的人回来了！你高兴吧！和平将战争夺去的人送回到了你的身旁，也把野心家抢去的善良青年还给了你。亲爱的，擦干眼泪，尽情地欢笑吧！因为暴君压迫人民之时，就是英明领袖引导人民抗暴之时。我能活着回来，你不要觉得奇怪！因为爱神身有印记，死神见之，必迅速逃离；敌人一经识别出来，也会踏步后退。我就是爱神。你不要以为我是来自沙场的鬼魂，只是为了欣赏你的俊美和这方的安静。你不要害怕，我是真理，安然摆脱了刀山火海，以便告诉人们：爱情必定压倒战争。我是语词，由和平之人讲出，以便为你的幸福故事作序言。”

讲到这里，青年语塞，泪水簌簌下落，取代了话语。欢乐天使在简陋茅屋四周盘旋，两颗心开始重温离别时失去的幸福。

晨光初照，二人站在田间静赏大自然秀美。充满甜言蜜语的一阵寂静之后，战士望着极远的东方，对他的爱人说：“你看哪，太阳已从黑暗中升起。”

死之美献给M.E.H.

死亡

让我安睡吧！我的心已沉醉于爱情。

让我长眠吧！我的魂已享尽日夜照应。

请在我的灵床周围点起蜡烛，燃起香，将玫瑰花和水仙花瓣儿撒在我的身上！把麝香粉撒在我的头上，把香水洒在我的脚下，然后仔细观看死神之手在我的前额上留下了什么字样。

让我深深睡在困神的怀抱！因为久醒，我的眼帘痛感疲劳。

请弹起琴弦！让银丝弦声响在我的耳边。

请吹起芦笛！用那甜润的笛声，在我那行将跳动的心脏周围织上一层薄纱。

请唱起轻歌！用那神妙的词句为我的情感铺床，然后仔细观察我的两眼里闪出的希望之光。

伙伴们，擦去眼泪，抬起头来！就像黎明到来之时，鲜花昂起花冠，向着太阳开放。你们看，死神的新娘像光柱一样站在我的灵床与天空之间……请你们屏着呼吸，留心细听，片刻之后，便能和我一道听到她那雪白翅膀的沙沙扇动声。

同胞们，你们来同我告别吧！用微微笑唇将我的前额亲吻。用你们的眼睑亲吻我的双唇，再用你们双唇将我的眼睑亲吻。

让儿童们靠近我的灵床，请他们用那柔嫩的玫瑰色手指摸一摸我的脖颈。让老年人靠近我的灵床为我祝福，用他们那枯萎、僵硬的手将我的前额抚摩。让本地的姑娘们靠近我，看看我眼中的上帝影像，听听永恒世界的歌声回音与我的呼吸声共鸣同响。

永别

呵！我的身已到山顶，我的魂已遨游在自由无束的太空。

同胞们，我已走得老远老远。我的视线被遮挡，丘山壮景已荫翳在雾霭后面。千道峡谷被寂静汪洋淹没，万条蹊径已被遗忘之掌尽抹。草原、森林、道路笑隐在无数幻影之后；那幻影，白的像春云，黄的似阳光，红的如晚霞。

大海波涛的歌声变得微弱，溪水的吟唱消失在田间，人间的喧嚣哑然静止。此时此刻，我的耳际中只有与灵魂嗜好相协调的永恒之歌。

安息

请取下我身上的麻织殓衣，用茉莉、百合花瓣为我裹体。

请从象牙棺材里抬出我的遗骸，让之平躺在柑橘、柠檬花枕上。同胞们，不要哭我，而要高唱青春欢乐之歌。田家女啊，请不要流泪，而要吟诵收获、榨汁季节的二重韵诗。

请你们不要用呻吟、叹息掩盖我的胸膛，而要用你们的手指画上友情与欢乐的符号和标记。

请你们不要用念咒和占卦打扰太空的休息，而要让你们的心与我一道盛赞永恒的真谛。

你们不要穿黑衣哀悼我，而要披白纱与我同乐。

你们不要伤心地谈论我一去不复返，而要闭上眼睛，就会看见我今天、明天和以后都在你们中间。

请你们让我躺在青枝绿叶上，肩抬着我，缓步把我送到空旷荒野那没有人烟的地方。

请你们不要把我抬到墓地，因为大理石会干扰我安息，尸骨、骷髅的咯咯碰撞声也会夺走我长眠的静谧。

请把我送到松柏林里，找块地方，为我掘个坟坑；在那里，紫罗兰与白头翁同长共生。

请把我的坟坑挖得深一些，以免洪水将我的尸骨卷入山谷。

请把我的坟坑挖得宽一点，好让夜的幻影来访时坐在我的身边。

请脱去这些衣服，让我赤身裸体入土。请你们将我放下，要慢要轻，让我安睡在母亲的怀中。

请你们用松软的土将我掩埋，每把土里都要掺入百合、茉莉和长寿花种，让群芳吸收我遗体的养分，在我的墓上生长；开出的花儿，在空气里散发我心底的馨香；高高扬起头，将我灵魂里的秘密诉与太阳；随微风摇曳，让过路人记起我过去的爱好和梦想。

同胞们，现在请离开我，让我独自留在这里！你们走吧，迈步要轻，就像寂静行走在空谷之中。

让我独自留在这里，请你们静静地散去，就像巴旦杏、苹果树花飘飞散落在四月的春风中。

请你们回家去吧！在那里，你们会发现死神也不能够从我和你们身上取走的东西。

离开这个地方吧！你们所要的东西已经远远地远远地离开了这个世界……

组歌

一支歌

我的心灵深处有一支歌，不喜以语词为衣；那支歌居于我的心坎，不愿随墨水注入笔端；那支歌像透明的封皮，包着我的情感，不肯像口水涌上舌尖。

我怕能媒细尘将之玷污，怎可将它吟唱？因它习惯于安居我心灵中，担忧它难耐人耳粗糙，我又能唱给谁听？

假如你看看我的眼睛，便会看到那支歌幻影的幻影；倘若你触摸我的手指，就能感到那支歌在抖动。

我的作品能显示那支歌，就像湖面能够倒影星斗之光；我的泪水能揭示那支歌，如同气温将露珠挥洒之时，露珠便将玫瑰花的秘密揭露。

寂静将那支歌张扬，喧嚣又将之掩盖；幻梦令其复出，苏醒又将之隐藏。

众人哪，那是一支爱之歌，哪位以撒(1)能唱？哪位大卫能歌？

它比茉莉花的气味芳香，哪个喉咙能将之抵抗？它比童贞女的秘密严实，哪根琴弦敢将之揭示？

谁能把大海咆哮与夜莺啼鸣结合在一起？谁能将暴风与孩子叹息合二而一？哪个人会唱神的歌曲？

浪之歌

我与海岸是一对情侣，爱情使我俩接近，风又把我俩分离。我来自蓝色晚霞之后，以便让我的银沫与它那金沙结合，用我的唾液把我的心冷却。

黎明时分，我对着情人的耳朵将爱法朗诵，情人把我紧紧搂在怀中；夜幕降临，我把思恋祷词对他唱吟，他便与我热烈亲吻。

我执拗、急躁；我的情侣却既有耐心，且又坚韧。

涨潮时，我拥抱情人；落潮时，我拜倒在情人脚下。

多少次，当美人鱼游出深水，坐在岩石山观赏繁星，我围着她们跳舞；多少次，我听情人与美女们诉说爱情之苦时，我与之一道叹息；多少次，岩石悔恨自己僵死不能动，我与它逗笑，而它从无笑意；多少次，我从海底窃得珍珠，将之赠送给天下美女！

夜阑更深，人们与困神拥抱进入梦乡，而我却不眠，时而歌唱，时而叹息。我多可怜！

熬夜使我精疲力竭，容颜憔悴。但是，我是热恋者；爱情的真谛是长醒不睡。

雨之歌

我是银线，上帝将我从高空抛下。大自然将我笑纳，并用我去装点千谷万壑。

我是美丽的珍珠，散落在阿施塔特女神的王冠上；晨光的女儿将我偷去，用我将田野镶嵌。

我哭，而山川在微笑；我谦恭下士，而花儿却高昂起头。云彩与田地本是一对情侣，我是二者之间的救急使者；我自天而降，医好那位的病疾，解除这位的干渴。

雷声和闪剑是我到来的先兆，七色彩虹宣布我的行程终结。世间生活亦如此：始终盛怒的物质脚下，终于平静的死神手上。

我从湖心升腾，在能媒的翅膀上行走。当我看见美丽的园林时，便立即降下，亲吻白花芳唇，拥抱绿叶青枝。

寂静之时，我便用自己纤细柔软的手指敲击窗玻璃；那敲击声构成乐曲，敏感的心灵方能通晓领会。

空气的高温将我生下，我则解除空气的高温。正如女子，她从男子那里汲取力量，又用这力量去征服男子。

我是大海的叹息，我是天空的泪水，我是田野的微笑。爱情亦如此：它是情感大海的一声叹息，思想天空的一滴泪水，心灵田野的一丝微笑。

美之歌

我是爱情的向导，我是精神的醇酒，我是心灵的美食。我是一朵玫瑰花，日出东方，我开启心扉，少女将我摘下，又把我亲吻，然后把我挂在她的胸前。

我是幸福之家，我是欢乐源泉，我是宽舒起点。我是窈窕淑女粉唇上的轻柔微笑，小伙子看见我会忘怀疲劳，他的生活会变成美梦的舞台。

我能启迪诗人的心灵，我能给画家引路，我能给音乐家当导师。

我是婴儿眼中的亮光，慈母见之，急忙跪拜、祈祷，把上帝赞扬。

我将夏娃的胴体展示在亚当面前，致使亚当对之顶礼膜拜；我在所罗门面前饰作他那意中人的苗条身段，致使所罗门变成了哲学家和诗人。

我向海伦(2)微微一笑，特洛伊(3)化为一片废墟；我为克娄巴特拉(4)戴上王冠，尼罗河谷充满温馨和睦。

我像世代，今天建设，明日毁坏；我是上帝，使万物生，亦令之死。

我比紫罗兰花的感叹轻柔，我比暴风强烈。

众人们，我就是真理。我是真理，这一点你们最该知晓。

幸福之歌

人是我的情郎，我是人的情伴。我思慕他，他迷恋我。可是，呜呼！我和他之间冒出了个第三者，和我一道爱上了他，使我面临不幸，也给他造成了痛苦和折磨。那暴虐的第三者名叫“物欲”：我们走到哪里，它跟我们到哪里；它像毒蛇一样，分开了情郎和我。

我去旷野寻情郎，在树下，到湖旁，不见他的身影；因为物欲引诱他，将他带往城市，去会狐朋狗友，搞腐化堕落，终于自投不幸之中。

我去知识学院、智慧殿堂，不见他的身影；因为那以尘土为衣的物欲把他带到自私自利堡垒中去了。那是醉生梦死居住之地。

我去知足之地寻情郎，不见他的身影；因为我的情敌把他禁锢在贪得无厌的洞穴里。

黎明时分，东方欲晓，我呼唤情郎，他听不到我的喊声；因为留恋过去的困意使他的眼皮感到沉重。夜深人静，百花入眠，我与他嬉戏，而他却不理睬我；因为向往未来的迷恋占据了他的心。情郎爱我，他在自己的作品中寻觅我；其实，他只能在上帝的作品里找到我。他想到用弱者的骷髅建在金银中的荣誉宫殿去与我相会，而我只在情感溪畔那神灵建造的朴素茅舍里才与他见面。他想在暴君、杀人犯面前和我亲吻，而我只有在纯洁花丛间幽会时，才准许他吻我的双唇。他希望计谋为我俩做媒，而我只求纯洁、美好的工作当我们之间的媒婆。

我的情郎从我的情敌——物质——那里学会了呐喊和喧嚣，而我将教他自己的眼里流出求怜的泪水，发出要求充足东西的叹息。我的情郎属于我，我也属于他。

————————————————————

(1) 以撒，《圣经》人物。亚伯拉罕的嫡子，撒拉所生。意为“欢乐”。撒拉一直到九十岁还未生育，因为上帝赐福，第二年，亚伯拉罕一百岁时，她生下了一个儿子。晚年得子，全家欢乐，故名之。上帝为了考验亚伯拉罕，要他将爱子以撒献为燔祭。亚伯拉罕捆了以撒摆好干柴，正要举刀杀儿子献祭时，上帝派天使拦住了他，让他用一只公羊代替儿子献为燔祭。

(2) 海伦，希腊传说中最美丽的美人，特洛伊战争的间接起因。

(3) 特洛伊，小亚西亚西北部的古城遗址。位于土耳其达达尼尔海峡主要港口查纳卡累以南40公里处，即今土耳其的希沙立克。此处山峦青翠，流水潺潺，一派典型的土耳其爱琴地区的乡村风光。

(4) 克娄巴特拉（前69-前30），埃及托勒密王朝著名女王。

人之歌

你们原是死的，而他以生命赋予你们，然后使你们死亡，然后使你们复活；然后你们要被召归于他。

——《古兰经》(1)

我自古存在，依然故我，我将存在到永久，我的存在无终结。

我曾在无穷太空遨游；我曾在幻想世界翱翔；我接近过最高光明圈；看哪，如今却成了物质的囚徒。

我听过孔夫子的教诲；我聆听过婆罗门的哲理；我曾在菩提树下坐在达摩的身旁；呵，我现在正与愚昧和不信神搏斗。耶和华面谕摩西时，我在何烈山上；在约旦河旁，我亲眼目睹过拿撒勒人耶稣显示奇迹；在麦地那城，我听过阿拉伯人的先知训教；呵，我现在却成了迷惑、彷徨的俘虏。我看到过巴比伦的强盛；我见识过埃及的辉煌；我领略过希腊的壮丽；但我仍看到柔弱、屈辱和卑微显现在那所有功业里。我曾与艾尼·杜尔的妖术师、亚述的祭司、巴勒斯坦的先知们坐在一起，但我仍然歌颂真理。我背诵过来自印度的格言；我熟读过源自阿拉伯半岛居民心中的诗歌；我领略过由马格里布人情感凝结而成的音乐；但我是视而不见的瞎子，听而不闻的聋子。我承受过贪婪征服者的残暴；我遭受过专制统治者的欺凌和暴虐之徒的奴役；但我仍然有力量与日月抗争。

我看到和听到所有这些时，我还是个孩童；我将要看到和听到青年时代及其未来的功业；我将要步入老年，臻于完美，归于上帝。我自古存在，依然故我，我将存在到永久，我的存在无终结。

————————————————————

(1) 引自马坚译《古兰经》第2章28节。

诗人之声

一

力量能够把种子播在我的心田，我来收割，集起谷穗，将之一捆一抱地送给饥馑者。

灵魂使这微小的葡萄树成活，我则把它结出的葡萄榨成汁，送给干渴人喝。苍天给这盏灯添满了油，我则将之点上，放在我家窗口，为夜下行人把路照亮。我之所以做这些事情是因为我依靠此而活着。假若白昼禁止我的行动，黑夜又将我的双手捆起，我则求一死。因为这最适合于一个被其民族抛弃的先知和在乡亲中被视为异乡人的诗人。

人们像暴风一样喧嚣，我则静静地叹息。因为我发现暴风的怒吼会消失，会被世代的汪洋大海吞噬，而叹息则与上帝一起永存。

人们贪恋冰雪一样寒冷的物质，我则追求爱的火焰，将之抱在怀里，让其吞食我的肋骨，销蚀我的五脏六腑。因为我熟知物质能使人毫无痛苦地死去，而爱情则用痛苦使人复活。

人类分种族、群体，分属国家、地域。我视自我在某一地区为异乡人，独立于任何一个民族。整个地球都是我的祖国，所有人类家庭都是我的亲戚。因为我发现人已十分弱小，还要自我分割，岂不是自视卑贱！地球本来就很狭窄，还要分成若干王国，岂不是过分愚昧！

人类竞相捣毁灵魂殿堂，合力建造肉体学院，我却独自站在痛惜的立场上。但是，我留心聆听，听到我的内心里有一种希望声音在说：“就像爱情用痛苦使人复活那样，愚昧能教人认识知识之路。痛苦和愚昧能化为巨大快乐和完整知识。因为永恒的智慧在太阳上没有创造任何虚假东西。”

二

我思恋我的祖国，因为她美丽无比；我热爱我的国民，因为他们无比不幸。但是，如果我的民族在被他们称为“爱国主义”的策动下，起来向临国发动进攻，掠夺人家的财产，残杀他们的男子，使儿童变为孤儿，令女子变成寡妇，使土地饮其男儿的血，令野兽食其青年的肉，那时，我便会厌恶我的祖国和国民。

我赞美我的故乡，我思念我在那里成长起来的国家。但是，如果有路人经过那里，要求在那家园投宿，向乡亲们要口面饼，竟会遭到拒绝，并被驱赶而去，那么，我的赞美就将为哀叹所代替，我的思念也将被遗忘淹没，我会自言自语：“连一块面饼都舍不得给饥馑者，连一张床都不肯给投宿者的家园，应该就地捣毁，夷为废墟！”

我爱故乡，更爱祖国，尤爱祖国的大地。我全身心热爱大地，因为大地是人性的摇篮，而人性则是大地上的神性灵魂。神圣的人性正是大地上的神性灵魂。那人性站在废墟之间，赤条条的身上只盖着破布片，凹陷的两腮挂着热泪，高声呼唤着自己的儿女们，使整个广宇充满了呻吟声和哭叫声，而她的儿女们根本不去理她的喊声，只顾唱着宗派主义的歌，更无视她的簌簌泪流，只顾磨自己的利剑。那人性独自坐着，向民众大声求救，而民众听不见。假如有人能听到她的喊声，定会回应，继而走近她，为她擦拭眼泪，安慰她惨遭不幸。这时，民众会说：“不要管她！眼泪只能打动弱者。”

人性是大地上的神性灵魂。那神性行走在各国之间，畅谈博爱，指出人生之路，而人们却嘲弄神性的言论和教诲。往昔，那里虽然耶稣听了神性，人们却把他钉在十字架上；苏格拉底(1)听了神性，人们让他服毒杀身；如今，许多人听了神性，而且当着众人大谈耶稣、苏格拉底和神性，人们再没有能力杀死他们，但却讥笑他们说：“讥笑比杀人更厉害、更苦涩。”

耶路撒冷未能杀死耶稣，耶稣活到永远；雅典未能处死苏格拉底，苏格拉底得到永生。

讥笑也不能征服听从人性呼唤、紧跟神性脚步的人们，他们也将活到永远，得到永生。

三

你是我的兄弟，我俩都是至尊圣灵之子。你像我一样，因为我俩同是肉体的囚徒，而上帝铸造两个肉体时用的是同一块泥。你是我生活道理上的伙伴，正是你帮助我认识隐藏在乌云之后的真理的本体。

你是人，我的兄弟，我爱你！你可以随意对我加以评说。因为明天将为你做裁判，你的话语将在公正裁决面前成为明显而确凿的证据。

你可以随意从我这里拿东西，因为我所占据的钱财，其中一部分属于你；我所占有的房地产，是我为我的贪心占有的，你可以享用其中一部分，如果一部分能让你满意。

你可以随意处置我，但是，你却没有能力触犯我的真理；你可以放我的血，焚烧我的肉体，但你不能使我的心灵痛苦，更不能使之死去；你只管给我的手脚戴上镣铐，将我下到黑暗的牢狱，但你却不能俘虏我的思想，因为它自由得像微风，徜徉、遨游在无边无沿的天宇。

你是我的兄弟，我爱你。

你在你的清真寺里做礼拜，我爱你；你在你的庙堂里顶礼膜拜，我爱你；你在你的教堂里做祈祷，我爱你。你和我本是一种宗教之子，那宗教便是灵魂。这种宗教各分支的领袖都是指向心灵完美的神性之手上相互连在一起的手指。

我爱你，爱你那源自一般智力的真理。那真理，我现在看不见它，因为我盲目；但我认为它是神圣的，因为它是心灵的作品。那真理将与我的真理在未来的世界里相遇，像花的气息一样相互结合在一起，变成一个完整永恒真理，与爱与美一道永存长在。

我爱你，因为我见你在暴虐强者面前那样软弱；我爱你，因为我见你在贪婪的富豪门前那样穷困。因此，我为你哭泣落泪。我透过眼泪，看见你在公正的怀抱中，公正在向着你微笑，蔑视压迫你的那些人……你是我的兄弟，我爱你。

四

你是我的兄弟，我爱你。既然如此，你为什么与我为敌？

你为什么来到我的国家，试图说服我讨好那些教长们？君不见，那些教长用你的话语求取荣光，借你的辛苦获得欢乐。你为什么丢下你的妻儿，去到遥远的地方，为将军们送死？君不见，那些将军们想用你的鲜血买高官，借你母亲的悲痛换取尊荣。难道说一个人杀自己的兄弟能算高尚？如果是那样，我们就为该隐(2)雕像，为亚那(3)颂歌。

喂，我的兄弟，他们说：“维护自我是大自然的根本法则。”但是，我认为野心家的特点在于：

首先使你甘心牺牲自我，以便达到制服你的兄弟们的目的。他们说：“要想生存，必须侵犯他人权利。”我则说：“维护他们的权利，那才是人类至尊至美行为。”我还要说：“假若我的存在必须使他人死亡，那么，死亡对我来说最甜最美。假如没有人让我体面、光彩、清白地死去，我会亲手把自己提前送往永恒世界。”

我的兄弟呀，自私自利会导致盲目竞争，竞争会产生沙文主义，沙文主义会生出专利。所有这些都是争执和奴役生成的原因。心灵主张智慧和正义压倒愚昧和邪恶，而坚决反对那种拿金属锻造长矛、利剑，用武力推行愚昧和邪恶的权势。正是那种权势毁坏了巴比伦，毁坏了耶路撒冷的支柱，摧毁了罗马的建筑。正是那种权势造就了刽子手、杀人犯，而人们却把他们描述为“伟人”，作家依然在宣扬他们的名字，书籍也把他们的战斗记录、保存下来；与此同时，当他们用鲜血染红地面时，大地也不得不把他们背在自己的背上……兄弟呀，究竟是什么东西使你迷恋于欺骗你的东西，依附于危害你的人呢？真正的权势是维护公正普遍自然法则的智慧。假若一种权势能够处决杀人犯，将盗贼打入监牢，自己却又去进攻临国，乱杀成千无辜，掠夺上万财富，那么，这种权势的正义何在呢？对那些让杀人犯去惩处杀人者，让盗贼去处罚小偷的宗派主义者，又该作何评论呢？

你是我的兄弟，我爱你。爱是最高形式的正义。假若我对你的爱在各方面有失公正，那么，我就是穿着爱的漂亮外衣，以掩饰自私自利丑陋面目的诈骗犯。

据传，耶稣被出卖后，首先被带到亚那那里。

跋语

我的心灵是我的挚友：每当日月灾难沉重，总给我以安慰；生活艰辛之时，与我共分忧愁。谁不做自己心灵的朋友，便成为人们的敌人；谁不能自我安慰，便会绝望而死。因为生命源自人的内心，而非来自周围外界。

我来到人间，有话要说；我将要把它讲出。假若在我讲出它之前，死神就把我召去，那么，来日会将之讲出。来日是不会把隐藏的秘密留在没有穷尽的书中的。

我来到人间靠爱的荣耀和美的光明活着；看哪，我现在活着，人们无法使我远离生活。

如果人们挖去我的双眼，我会留心听赏爱之歌和美之曲；如果人们塞住我的两耳，我会因为接触到融合着情侣气息和美的芳香的能媒而感到快乐。

我来到人间，是为了大家，也依靠大家。我今天孤自做的事情，未来会当众宣布；我现在单口说的话语，来日会用许多口舌道出。

————————————————————

(1) 苏格拉底（前469-前399），古希腊大哲学家。

(2) 该隐，《圣经》人物。人类始祖亚当和夏娃的长子，以种田为生。他和弟弟亚伯用各自的物产向上帝献祭，上帝悦纳了弟弟的供物，而未看中他的供物。他出于嫉妒，将弟弟杀害。上帝惩罚他，将他流放挪得。

(3) 亚那，《圣经》人物。犹太大祭司，该亚法的岳父。该亚法后来当上了大祭司，成为杀害耶稣的元凶。

国王

萨迪格王国的人民包围了王宫，群众愤而高呼反对国王的口号。国王从王宫台阶上走下来，一手托着王冠，一手提着权杖，众人看见国王，霎时一片肃静。国王站在众人面前，说：“朋友们！从现在起，你们不再是我的臣民。看哪，我这就把王冠和权杖交给你们。我想成为你们当中的一员。我不过是个普通人，但我想作为一个人，与你们一道劳动，共同努力，使我们的命运更加美好。不需要国王了！让我们到田野和葡萄园去，手挽手地劳动吧！我期望你们给我指出应该去的田地或葡萄园。现在，你们每一个人都是国王！”

人们大惊，鸦雀无声。被他们看作灾难根源的国王，如今交出王冠和权杖，成了他们当中的一个百姓。

之后各自散去，国王跟着一个人走向田间。

然而萨迪格王国的情况并未改善，愤怒云雾依旧笼罩着王国的天空和大地，人们又聚集在广场高呼口号，要求有个人统治他们，掌管他们的事务，老少异口同声喊道：“我们要国王！”

他们找到国王，发现他正在田间劳动，便把王冠和权杖交给他，说：“现在，你果断、公正地统治我们吧！”

国王说：“我将真的果断地统治你们，我也将请天地之神佐助我公正地统治你们。”

之后，男男女女前来控告一贵族虐待他们，把他们当成奴隶。国王下令把那贵族传唤来，对他说：“人的生命在上帝的天平上都是等重的。你既然不知道如何称量在你的田园中劳作的这些人的生命，那么，我就把你赶出去，你应该永远离开这个王国。”

第二天，一些人来告居住在山丘后的一个心地残忍、弄得当地贫穷不堪的女爵。国王下令立即把她带来，判之以流放，并且说：“这些人耕种我们的土地，看管我们的葡萄园，我们吃着他们烤的面包，喝着他们酿造的酒，他们比我们高贵。既然你连这一点也不晓得，那么，你应该离开这块土地，远离这个王国。”

又有男女来控告主教，说主教强迫他们搬运、雕刻石头，建造教堂，分文不付；他们明知主教金银满库，而他们却很忍饥挨饿，食不果腹。

国王下令把主教带来，对他说：“你胸前挂的这十字架，意味着用生命换生命，而你却一味索取，从不付出。因此，你当离开王国，永远不得回返。”

就这样，整整过了一个月，每天都有男男女女前来诉说他们肩上沉重的负担；与此同时，每天都有一个或更多压迫者被驱逐出境。

萨迪格国民惊喜，心中充满欢乐。

一天，老老少少将王宫包围起来，呼唤国王，国王一手托着王冠，一手提着权杖来到他们中间。

国王说：“现在你们还有什么要求？我把你们所希望我拿来的东西再还给你们吧！”

人们高声呼喊：“不，不！你是我们公正的好国王，是你清除了我们国土上的毒蛇、豺狼。我们来为你歌功颂德。王冠的威严属于你，权杖的光荣属于你。”

国王答道：“不，不是我！不是我！你们自己才是国王。当你们认为我懦弱无能、不善治理之时，你们也是不善治理的弱者。如今，国家走上了正道，因为那是你们的意愿。我呢，不过是你们大家头脑中的一种理想，我存在于你们的工作之中，并不是一个叫统治者的人。被统治者会发现自己在统治自己。”

国王带着自己的王冠和权杖回到宫中，老老少少们各自高高兴兴回家而去。

每个人都认为自己是一手托着王冠，一手提着权杖的国王。

两个守护神

一天夜里，两个天神相遇在城门，相互问候之后，开始交谈。

一个天神说：“这些日子里，你在干什么？分派给你的任务是什么？

另一个天神答：“分派给我看守一个罪人，他生活在山谷里，犯了大罪，滑到了危险的边缘。请允许我向你肯定，这是一项重大任务，我将付出极大辛苦。”

第一个天神说：“那很简单，我很了解罪人，不止一次看守过他们。我最近被分派看守一名心地善良的圣徒，他生活在树枝搭成的凉棚下，远避人们，离群索居。我要肯定地对你说，这才是一项极其困难而细致的差事呢！”

第二个天神说：“这纯粹是欺诈！守护圣徒怎么会比看守罪人更难？”

第一个天神回答：“说我欺诈，岂有此理！我说的全是真话。我看你才是个诈骗犯！”

两个天神争吵起来，起初动口，最后终于拳脚相见。

双方正打得不可开交，天神王来了，停下脚步，问道：“为何争斗？什么事情使你俩打了起来？难道你们不知道守护神之间打架是不成体统的，尤其是在城门口？告诉我，你俩之间的分歧何在？”

两个天神同时开口，都称自己的工作比同伴的困难，理应得到对自己功德更大的认可。

天神王摇了摇头，认真思索起来……

最后说：“二位兄弟，我现在不能说你俩之间谁应得到更大荣誉和更大报偿。我既然有权指挥你们，而且你俩都坚持对方的工作比自己的轻松，那么，我给你俩调换一下工作。为了太平无事，确保看守任务完成，并使各自满意，现在你俩就各自承担原来委派给对方的任务去吧！”

两个天神即去执行天神王的命令。然而二天神边走边不时回头怒目望望天神王，暗自说：“这帮天神王！他们把我们这些守护神的生活弄得一天不如一天。”

天神王站在那里，自言自语道：“其实，我们应该小心谨慎，留神看守这些守护神。”

青蛙

夏令的一天，一只青蛙对其伙伴说：“我真担心我们夜晚唱歌会搅得岸上那家人不得安宁。”

伙伴回答：“是啊！可是，难道你不觉得他们白天唠唠叨叨也扰乱了我们的宁静吗？”

青蛙说：“人所共知，我们在夜里唱得太多，而且过分多了！”

伙伴说：“他们白天里高声喧闹，而且过分嘈杂，这也是我们所共知的。”

青蛙说：“牛蛙的咆哮声弄得四邻不得安宁，我们有什么可说的呢？”

伙伴说：“是啊！那些来这岸边的政治家、牧师和学者喧闹不休，声音震天动地，既无音韵，亦无节奏，那你该说什么呢？”

青蛙说：“真的！我们总要比这些人好些吧！让我们夜间安静一些，把歌保留在我们的心中，虽然月亮企盼着我们的歌喉，星宿期待着我们的和声。我们至少该沉默一夜或两夜，甚至连续三夜吧！”

伙伴说：“很好！我同意。我们将看到我们的好心会带来什么结果。”

一夜过去，青蛙未鸣。第二夜、第三夜，也未听见青蛙的叫声。

更奇怪的事情发生了：第三天，住在湖岸边那家的多嘴多舌的女人下来吃早饭，高声对丈夫说：“一连两夜，我都没有尝到睡觉的滋味。我只有听着蛙鸣，才能进入梦乡。我三夜没有听见蛙鸣，准是发生了什么意外事。我因失眠，都快要发疯了啦！”

青蛙听到这话，把脸转向伙伴，使了眼色，说：“我们沉默得几乎要疯了，不是吗？”

伙伴回答道：“是啊！夜下沉默，对我们来说真是个沉重的负担。我现在已经明白，为了给那些用喧闹声填充空虚的人创造欢乐，我们没有必要中断我们的歌声。”

那天夜里，月亮终于盼到了青蛙的歌喉，星宿等来了青蛙的和声。

如此聋妻

富翁有一位年轻的妻子，但却耳聋。

一日清晨，夫妻正吃早饭，妻子说：“我昨天逛了市场，那里货色齐全、琳琅满目；大马士革绸袍、印度头巾、波斯项链、也门手镯……应有尽有，看来都是商队刚刚运到城里来的。现在，你看看我，破衣褴缕，成何样子，我还是知名富翁的妻子呢！我要你给我买些漂亮的东西。”

正在呷吮咖啡的丈夫，立即回答：“我亲爱的！没什么不可以的，你去市场，买下自己想买的称心如意的东西就是了。”

聋妻说：“不，不，你就会说不！难道命中注定我身着破衣出现在男朋女友面前，让家人替我害羞，让人们讥笑你这个阔佬儿？”

丈夫说：“我没说‘不’。你可以去市场买下全城最漂亮、最讲究的首饰和其他装饰品。”

妻子又误解了丈夫的话，回答道：“你是富人当中最吝啬的守财奴，你就是不想让我打扮得漂漂亮亮，而人家的贵妇人三三五五逛花园时，个个珠光宝气，人人艳妆浓抹。”

说着，她大哭起来，泪珠簌簌滚落在前胸，再次高声喊道：“每当我要衣服、首饰时，你总是说：‘不，不！’”

丈夫惊慌失措，站起来，从钱柜里拿出一把金币，放在妻子面前，柔声和气地说：“亲爱的，上街去吧，想买什么就买什么吧！”

打那天起，聋妻每当想要什么东西时，总是眼噙泪水站在丈夫面前；丈夫则不声不响地从钱柜里拿出金币，放在妻子眼前。

后来，这位年轻女人恋上了一个习惯于长途旅行的小伙子；每当小伙子远行，聋女人总是在枕边哭泣，每逢富翁看见妻子落泪，便暗自想：“定是新商队来了，有珍奇首饰珠宝上市！”

这时，富翁便拿出一把金币，丢给妻子……

小序

当爱神用其神奇光芒打开我的眼界，以其火一般的手指第一次触摸我的心灵时，我刚满十八岁。赛勒玛·凯拉麦是第一位以其纯美唤醒我的灵魂的女性。正是她带着我走向崇高情感的天园；在那里，白昼像美梦一样闪过，黑夜婚礼似的消逝。

赛勒玛，正是她以她的美丽教育我崇拜美，用她的柔情让我看到爱情的隐秘，正是她对我吟诵了精神生活长诗的第一行诗。

哪一个青年能不记得第一个用温情柔语、纯洁无瑕、美丽容貌使自己青年时代的疏忽大意、漫不经心为惊魂动魄、触及心神、豁然开朗的觉醒所替代的少女？我们当中谁能不无限思恋那样的奇妙时刻：当他留意之时，突然发现自己的整个身心发生了翻天覆地的变化，内心深处开阔、舒展开来，继而充满激动之情，因不肯吐露真实情况所带来的种种苦涩而令人感到欢快，又因由此引起的泪水流淌、思念及失眠而令人心满意足。

每个青年都有自己的赛勒玛，出现在自己生命春天的疏狂时期，使自己生活充满诗情画意，令自己白昼的孤寂被温馨所取代，夜晚的静寞被歌声所替换。

当我听到爱情通过赛勒玛的双唇在我心灵的耳旁窃窃私语时，我在大自然的影响与书籍、旅行的启示之间感到茫然若失，不知所措。当我看到赛勒玛像光柱一样矗立在我的面前时，我的生活一片空旷、荒芜、凄凉，酷似天堂中亚当昏睡不醒。赛勒玛·凯拉麦正是这颗充满秘密和奇迹之心的夏娃；正是她使这颗心晓知了存在的实质，使之像一面镜子一样竖立在这些幻影的面前。始祖夏娃用自己的意志和亚当的顺从，将亚当带出了天堂；而赛勒玛·凯拉麦则用她的甜美和我的适应性，将我带入了爱情和圣洁的乐园。但是，人类始祖的遭遇也降临到了我的身上，将亚当逐出天堂的火剑就像以利刃寒光威胁我的宝剑一样，在我违背训诫和品尝善恶果之前，就将我强行驱逐出了爱情乐园。

如今，那黑暗的岁月已经过去，用它的脚抹去了那些日子的画面，美梦留给我的只有痛苦的回忆，就像看不见的翅膀一样在我的脑袋四周扑扇拍击，激起我内心深处发出忧伤叹息，使我的眼睛落下失望与悔恨的泪滴……赛勒玛，俊美、纯洁的赛勒玛已走到蓝色暮霭之后去了。她留在这个世界上的痕迹只有存在于我心中的悲痛和位于松柏树荫上的一块大理石墓碑。那座墓和这颗心，只有二者堪谈关于赛勒玛的存在，而那守卫坟墓的寂静，决不会泄露神灵隐藏在棺材黑暗中的秘密，吸收逝者遗体养分的树枝也不会用叶子的沙沙响声道出墓穴内幕。至于这颗心的痛苦和忧伤，它是会说话的，而且现在正随着墨水滴落而倾诉，将爱神、美神和死神演出的那场悲剧幻影公布给光天化日。

散居在贝鲁特城的我的青年时期的朋友们，当你们路过松柏林附近的那片墓地时，请你们进到里面，不要作声，要缓缓行走，以免你们的脚步声惊扰长眠黄泉之下者的遗骸，恭恭敬敬地站在赛勒玛的墓旁，代我问候掩埋她的遗体的黄土，然后叹着气提醒我一句，并且请你们心中默默言道：“啊，在这里，埋葬着那位青年的希望，灾难已将他逐出到了海外；就在这里，他的愿望泯灭了，他的欢乐阴翳了，他的眼泪流尽了，他的微笑消失了。他的惆怅在这无声荒冢之间与翠柏绿柳一道生长。他的灵魂伴着回忆每天夜里都在这座墓上盘旋，与寂寞的幻影一道重复着悲凉、凄苦的挽歌，与树枝一道哭悼一位少女：昔日，她是生命双唇间的一支动人的欢乐；如今，她已变成地心里一个无声的秘密。”

青年朋友们，我要你们凭你们心爱的姑娘起誓，定把花环放在我心爱的那位姑娘的坟上；但期你们放在一座被遗忘的坟墓上的那朵花，就像清晨的眼睛滴在凋谢的玫瑰花瓣间的露珠。

无言的悲伤

众人们，你们想必总是回忆起青春的黎明之时，期望青春画面回返，惋惜它的逝去。至于我，想起那时来，则像获得释放的囚徒回忆起监牢的墙壁和沉重的镣铐。你们把从童年到青年之间的那段时光称为黄金时代；其时，人全然不识愁苦滋味，就像蜜蜂越过腐臭沼泽飞向花团锦簇的果园那样，展翅高翔在种种烦恼、忧虑的上空。然而，我却只能将我的少年时代称为无声无形的痛苦时代；其时，那种种痛苦就像暴风一样居于与发作在我的心中各个角落，随着我的心发育成长而增多，直到爱神进入我的心中，打开心扉，照亮各个角落，那暴风方才离开那里，卷入知识世界的出口。爱情解放了我的舌头，我会说话了；爱情撕开了我的眼帘，我会哭泣了；爱情开启了我的喉咙，我会叹息诉苦了。

众人们，你们想必记得看见你们玩耍，听到你们纯洁心灵低语的田间、果园、广场和街道；而我也记得黎巴嫩北部那个美丽的地方。我只要合上双眼，不看周围的一切，那充满神奇和庄严的山谷和那座座以光荣与宏伟高耸入云的山峰便油然浮现，清澈可见；只要捂上双耳，不听那社会传来的喧嚣声，那条条溪水的潺潺流水声和那千枝万叶的沙沙响声便自然响在耳边。不过，我现在提及并思念的美妙景色只是乳儿对母亲的怀抱贪婪而已。正是那片美景折磨着我那被囚禁在少年时期的昏暗之中的灵魂，酷似笼中的猎隼看见一群群猎隼自由翱翔在广阔天空时所遭受的折磨。正是那片美景在我脑中充满静观的病痛和沉思的苦涩，并用半信半疑、模棱两可的手指在我的心周围织就了一层绝望的纱包。我每到旷野去，总是愁眉苦脸而归；至于悲伤原因何在，我则全然不得而知。我每逢傍晚抬眼远望那被夕阳染成的云彩，总是感到心中郁闷难耐；至于郁闷意味着什么，我则完全猜不出。我每当听到鸟(1)鸣唱或溪水欢歌，我总是悲伤地停下脚步；至于悲伤默示着什么，我仍然不知其中奥秘。

人们说：“愚昧是空虚的摇篮，空虚乃休闲之坟墓。”此种说法对于那些生来就是死人、活着如同行尸走肉的人来说，也许是正确的。但是，当盲目的愚昧居于醒悟的情感旁边时，那么，无知比无底深渊更加残酷，比死亡更加苦涩。一个多情善感而知识甚少贫乏的敏感少年，则是太阳之下不幸的人，因为他的心灵总是处于两种不同的可怕力量之间：一种看不见的力量，载着他遨游云端，让他看到美梦雾霭之外的绝美万物；另一种可见力量，将他禁锢在大地之上，用尘埃蒙住他的眼睛，让他惊恐、迷惘在一片漆黑之中。

愁苦生着丝绸般柔软、神经极端敏感的手，它能牢牢抓住人的心，令其尽尝孤独寂寞之苦。孤寂是愁苦的同盟军，同样也是每一种精神活动的亲密伙伴。面对孤独寂寞作用和惆怅苦闷影响的少年的心灵，颇像刚刚出花萼的白色百合花，在微风前瑟瑟抖动，花心迎着黎明之光开放，随着黄昏暗影的经过而合上花瓣。假若少年没有散心的娱乐场所和志同道合的友伴，那么，生活在他的面前就像狭窄的监牢一样，能够看到的只有四面结满的蜘蛛网。能够听见的只有各个角落传出的蛩虫鸣声。

拖累我的少年时代的愁苦并非源于我对娱乐场所的需求，因为当时我能玩耍的此类地方很多；也不是因为我没有志同道合的友伴，因为好友寻常，行处皆有。那种愁苦是我生来就有的一种心理病症，它使我喜欢离群独处，扼杀了我心灵中对于娱乐玩耍的倾向与爱好，摘去了我双肩上热望、幻想的翅膀，使我在万物面前就像倒映的画面，云天的色彩和树枝的线条，但却找不到一条通道，故无法顺之而下，化为溪流，唱着欢歌而奔向大海。

这便是我十八岁之前的生活面貌。在我经历的岁月中，那一年如同山顶，因为它使我停下脚步，仔细观看这个世界，让我看到了人类所走的路，让我看到了人类爱好的草原和他们所遇到的重重障碍以及他们的法律、传统的洞穴。

就在那一年，我获得了重生。一个人，假若不被愁苦孕育和被失望分娩，继而被爱情放在梦想的摇篮之中，那么，他的生命就如同存在于书中的空白一页。

就在那一年，我看见天使透过一位美娘的眼神望着我；我还看见地狱的魔鬼们在一个罪恶男子的胸膛上大喊大叫，竞相奔跑。在生活的美妙与丑恶之中，谁没有看见过天使和魔鬼，他的心将始终远离知识，他的灵魂里也是一片空白，没有情感。

————————————————————

(1) 鸟，一种鸣禽，比麻雀稍大，羽黑，喙长，呈黄色，啼鸣声悦耳。

命运之手

在那充满奇异事情一年的春天，我在贝鲁特。四月的春风催开了百花，吹绿了城市花园里一片绚丽景象，仿佛那就是大地向蓝天宣告的秘密。巴旦杏树和苹果树穿上了洁白的香衣，展现在房舍之间，活像身着雪白盛装的天上仙子，受大自然派遣下凡，要做诗才横溢、想象力勃发的文人墨客的新娘和妻子。

天涯处处春光美，但最美的春天却在叙利亚(1)……春乃未名神灵之魂，快步巡游在大地上，当来到叙利亚时，便放慢了脚步，回眸后望，与遨游在太空的帝王、先知们的灵魂相亲相近，和犹太国(2)的溪流同唱所罗门的不朽《雅歌》(3)，与黎巴嫩杉树一起重忆古老光荣。

春天的贝鲁特要比其余季节里美丽得多，因为春时既没有冬天的泥泞，也没有夏日的沙尘；处于冬季的雨水与夏令的炎热之间的贝鲁特，就像一位俏丽的少女，刚刚用溪水洗浴过，坐在岸上，正用阳光揩拭她那嫩白丰满的胴体。

在那充满阳春四月的沁人肺腑气息和令人振奋微笑的一天里，我去拜访了一位朋友。他住在远离社会尘嚣的一座房子里。当我们正用话语勾画我们的希望和理想线条时，一位可敬的老人走了进来。那老人年已花甲过五，朴素衣着和多皱的面孔足以表明他的庄重严肃。于是，我立即恭恭敬敬地站了起来。在我与他握手、问安之前，我的朋友走上前来，介绍说：

“这位是法里斯·凯拉麦先生。”

之后，朋友又报了我的名字，并说了句称赞的话。老人凝神注视了我片刻，用手指摸着他那布满雪白头发的高高前额，仿佛想追忆被忘却了的某件旧事的图景，然后微微一笑，绽现出兴奋的神情，走近我说：

“你是我的一位老朋友的儿子，我的青春岁月都是陪伴着他度过的。能看到你，我是多么高兴！我多么想通过你见见你的父亲啊！”

听老人这样一说，我很激动，只觉得有一股无形的吸引力将我放心地拉近他，就像暴风来到之前，天性将鸟雀引领到自己的巢里。我们坐下来，老人便开始向我们讲起他与我父亲昔日的友情，追忆着与我父亲共度过青春的年华，讲述着已被岁月用自己的心裹上了敛衣，并用自己的胸埋葬了的往昔的故事……老人们回忆自己的青年时代，就像江湖游子思返故乡的情感一样；他们喜欢讲述少年时代的故事，如同诗人喜吟自己的得意杰作。他们总是依靠居于往时角落的一种精神生活着，因为现实在他们的面前飞闪而过，从不顾盼他们；而未来，在他们的眼中，好像也罩着一层灰蒙蒙的雾霭和坟墓里的幽暗。

我们在交谈、回忆中度过的一个时辰，就像树荫掠过青草地那样飞闪过去了。法里斯·凯拉麦站起身来要离去，我急忙上前去与他告别。他用右手拉住我的手，左手搭在我的肩膀上，说：

“我已二十年没有见到你的父亲了，但期你常来玩，以弥补你父亲长久远离之缺憾。”

我弯腰施礼表示感谢，并答应儿子尽到对父亲的好友应尽的义务。

法里斯·凯拉麦出门后，我的朋友又用带着某种谨慎的口气，向我讲了他的一些情况。我的朋友说：

“在贝鲁特，我不知道有第二个像他这样的人：财富使他成了公德高尚之人，而美德又使他变得更加富有。有极少数的人能够从来到世上起，到离开世上为止，从不伤害任何一个人的心灵；而这位老者则是这极少数人当中的一位。不过，这些人往往都是不幸的受气者，因为他们不懂得如何用计谋挣脱人们的奸诈与狠毒……法里斯·凯拉麦有个独生女，与他一起住在城郊的一座豪宅里。女儿的性格很像父亲，在女性中没有像她那样温柔娴淑、容貌俊秀的姑娘。不过，她也是很不幸的，因为父亲的大笔财富现已使她站在一个可怕的无底深渊的边沿。”

我的朋友说出这后几句话时，面上浮现出忧虑和惋惜的阴云。之后，他又说：

“法里斯·凯拉麦是位心地善良、品格高尚的老人，但却是个意志软弱的人；人们的伪善领着他走，就像是领着一个盲人；人们的贪婪让他止步，就像让一个哑巴站住。他的女儿虽然心存巨大力量和才能，但却完全屈从于父亲的薄弱意志。这便是隐藏在父女生活背后的秘密。有一个贪婪而伪虚、狠毒而狡诈的人晓知了这一秘密，这个人便是大主教；他用《圣经》掩盖他的丑魂，俨然在人们面前显得像美德一样。他是多宗教、多教派之国中的一教之主，人们的灵魂和肉体都害怕他，都像牲口在屠夫面前低下脖子那样，在他面前俯首顶礼膜拜。这位大主教有个侄子，各种腐朽、罪恶因素在他心灵中相争互斗，酷似蝎子、毒蛇在山洞、沼泽边上翻滚。没过几天，大主教就要穿着他的黑衣长袍，让他的侄子站在他的右边，让法里斯的女儿站在他的左边，举起他那罪恶的手，将结婚花环置于二人的头上，用预言、符咒的锁链将一个圣洁的躯体与一具腐尸连在一起，用腐败法律之掌将一个天魂与一个泥团捏合在一起，将灿烂白昼之心放在昏暗黑夜胸中。关于法里斯老人及其女儿的情况，现在我只能给你讲这么多，你不要问更多的事情。因为一提灾难，灾难就会临近，就像怕死一样，死亡会立即来临。”

说到这里，我的朋友转过脸去，透过窗子向天空望去，仿佛想在能媒中寻觅日与夜的秘密。

这时，我原地站起身来，握住他的手，与他告别时，对他说：

“明天我去拜访法里斯·凯拉麦，一方面履行我的诺言，另一方面表示对他与我父亲友谊留下的珍贵回忆的敬重。”

我的朋友愣了片刻，他的面色也变了，仿佛我那简单的两句话引发他产生了一种新的可怕的想法。之后，他用奇异的目光久久注视着我，那目光中包含着友爱、同情与恐惧，就像先知的目光，看到灵魂深处有一种连灵魂自身都不知道的东西。他的双唇颤动了一会儿，但什么也没说。我离开他，带着杂乱心绪向门口走去。在他向后转身之前，我看到他的双眼仍在用奇异的目光望着我；我始终没有弄明白那目光的含义，直至我的心灵脱离了可以度量的世界，飞向了天国，在那里心与心凭眼神相互了解，灵魂靠相互了解而成长。

————————————————————

(1) 此处特指史书上的大叙利亚，包括今叙利亚、黎巴嫩、约旦、巴勒斯坦等地。因这块地方曾属于东罗马帝国的“叙利亚行省”。

(2) 犹太国系位于死海与地中海之间的古代王国。此处泛指巴勒斯坦、黎巴嫩一带。

(3) 《雅歌》是《圣经·旧约》中的一卷书，属《圣录》。本卷书共八章。卷首云：“所罗门的歌，是诗中的雅歌。”本书如果真为所罗门所作，其形成大约在公元前十世纪。本书文学体裁为诗歌。书中以优美动人的诗句，歌咏了男女之间炽热而又纯洁的爱情。

在神殿门口

几天之后，我厌倦了孤单独处，也看累了书的愁容，于是登上马车，直奔法里斯·凯拉麦家而去。当车子行至人们常来游玩的松树林时，车夫调转马头，离开大路，一阵小跑，拐入一条柳荫走廊，两旁绿草葱茂，葡萄藤架枝叶繁茂，四月的鲜花张着口绽现出微微笑容，红的像玛瑙，蓝的像祖母绿宝石，黄的像金子。

不大一会儿，马车便在一座孤零零的住宅前停了下来。那座住宅周围是个大花园，树木枝条相互搭肩拥抱，空气中散发着玫瑰花、茉莉花和素馨花的芳香。

我刚在花园里走了几步，法里斯·凯拉麦便出现在宅门口，走来迎接我，仿佛响在那个孤零零地方的车马声已经宣布我的到来。老人笑容满面地表示欢迎，随之把我带进客厅，像一位思念心切的父亲那样让我坐在他的身旁，开始和我交谈，细问我的过去，探询我未来有何打算。我一一回答老人的问话，语气中充满美妙梦想和雄心宏愿的音调，这也是青年人在被幻想推上艰苦、麻烦频频而至的实际工作岸边之前惯于引吭高歌的调门儿……青年时代生着诗的翎羽、幻想神经的翅膀，青年人凭之飞上云端，看见世间的一切都像彩虹一样，五光十色，耀眼夺目，美不胜收；他们听到世间生灵无不放声唱着光荣与辉煌的赞歌。但是，那诗情画意一般的幻想翅膀不久就会被严厉考验的暴风撕碎，青年们也无可奈何地落到现实世界上；那现实世界是一面奇怪的镜子，人会从中看到自己的心灵那样渺小，那样丑陋。

就在这时，一位少女出现在天鹅绒门帘前，身着洁白光亮的绸衣，缓步朝我走来。她站住后，法里斯老人站起来向我介绍说：

“这是我的女儿赛勒玛。”

老人道出了我的姓名，介绍了我的情况之后，说：

“许久许久没有见到那位老朋友了，如今岁月让我看到了他的儿子。”

少女走到我的面前，眷恋凝视着我的双眸，仿佛想求我的眼神讲出我的真情实况，从中得知我的来意。然后，她握住我的手；她的手洁白、柔嫩，足以与田野上的百合花相媲美。手掌相接触的那一霎那，我的心中顿生一种奇异的新情感，很有些像作家驰骋想象力开始构思诗句时的心情。

我们默默地坐下来，仿佛赛勒玛把一种暗示沉静、庄重的高尚精神带进了客厅。好像她感觉到了那一点，于是望着我，微笑着说：

“家父常常对我谈起令尊大人，多次讲起他俩青年时代的故事。如果令尊大人给你讲过那些往事，那么，我们之间见面就不会是第一次了。”

法里斯老人听女儿这样一说，眉开眼笑，欣喜不已。他说：

“赛勒玛在爱好和主张上都是精神至上者。在她看来，世间一切东西都遨游在心灵世界中。”

就这样，法里斯老人又全神贯注、无限温情地与我交谈起来，宛如在我的身上发现了一种神奇的秘密，使他重新坐上回忆的翅膀，向着逝过的青春岁月飞去。

老人凝目注视着我，试图追回自己青春时代的影像；我则凝神注目着他，梦想着自己的未来。他望着我，就像布满季节变化痕迹的参天大树，俯视着一棵充满雄心大志、盲目生机的幼苗；大树年迈根深，饱经岁月的酷夏寒冬和时代狂风暴雨的考验，而幼苗却弱小柔嫩，只见过春天，晨风吹来便瑟瑟颤抖。

赛勒玛默不作声，时而望望我，时而瞧瞧父亲，仿佛正在我俩的脸上阅读故事的首章和末尾。

白昼叹着气从花园和果林中走过。夕阳西下，留给老人宅院对面的黎巴嫩高山峰巅金黄色的吻痕。法里斯·凯拉麦向我讲述了他的故事，令我惊异出神；我在他面前尽情唱着我的青春之歌，使他感到欣悦。赛勒玛坐在窗子旁边，用悲凉的双眸望着我们，一动不动，静听我们谈话，一声不吭，仿佛她知道美自身有一种语言，浑然天成，无需口舌发出的声音与节奏；那是一种永恒的语言，包含人类的全部音韵，使之成为一种无声的情感，就像平静的湖泊，将万川溪流的歌声吸纳到自己的心中，使之成为永恒的寂静。美是一种秘密，只有我们的灵魂了解它，为它而欢欣鼓舞，依靠它的作用而成长发育；而我们的思想，则站在它的面前不知所措，虽竭力试图用语言给它下个定义，将之形象化，但却完全无能为力。美是一种眼睛看不见的暗流，在观者的情感与可见事实之间波涌翻动奔流。真正的美是一种光，发自于灵魂中最神圣的地方，照亮肉体的外表，酷似生命源于果核之内，为鲜花送去彩色和芳香。美是男女之间顷刻之间达成的完全互相理解，霎那间诞生的凌驾于一切兴趣之上的爱慕之情，那便是被我们称为爱情的灵魂倾向。

那天傍晚，我的灵魂理解了赛勒玛的灵魂。究竟是这种相互理解使我把她看作太阳面前最美的姑娘，还是一种青春的醉态，使得我们幻想着根本不存在的美妙图景和幻影？莫非是青春使我双目昏黑，使我幻想到赛勒玛明眸放光、粉唇甜蜜、身段苗条，还是那种明光、甜蜜、苗条打开了我的眼界，以便让我眼观爱情的欢乐和痛苦？所有这些，我都说不清楚。但是，我却知道自己尝到了一种在此之前从未感受到的情感；那是一种崭新的情感，它绕着我的心从容不迫地蹒跚晃动，就像灵魂在创世之前徜徉在海面之上。我的幸福与不幸从那种情感中诞生，如同万物按照上帝的意志轮回出现，转世再生。

我与赛勒玛初次见面的时刻就这样过去了。苍天如此想，并且出乎意料地将我从困惑的奴役和少年的烦恼中解放出来，让我自由自在地行进在爱情行列里。爱情是这个世界上的唯一自由，因为它将灵魂提升到一个人类法律和传统达不到的崇高地位，就连自然法则与规律也无法控制它。

当我站起身来要告辞时，法里斯老人走近我，用真诚感人的声音说：

“现在，你已认识了到这家来的路，你到这里来，应该感到有一种把我引领到你父亲家的信心，应该把我和赛勒玛当成你的父亲和妹妹——不是吗，赛勒玛？”

赛勒玛点头表示同意。之后，她望了我一眼，那一眼，类似于一个迷路的异乡客忽然看到一个熟人时闪现的目光。

法里斯老人对我说的那番话，正是我与他的女儿一起站在爱神宝座前的第一曲，也是以痛哭、哀悼而结尾的天国之歌的序曲。那番话又是一种力量，给我俩的灵魂以激励，我们便接近了光和火。那番话也是杯盏，我们从中饮下了多福河水，也喝下了苦西瓜(1)汁。

我出了门，老人一直把我送到花园尽头。我告别了父女二人，心在胸中剧烈跳动，如同干渴者的双唇触及水杯沿时颤抖不止。

————————————————————

(1) 苦西瓜，沙漠中的一种植物，叶子和果与西瓜相似，但很小，堪称袖珍西瓜。极耐干旱，瓜味极苦，阿拉伯妇女为了给孩子断奶，多将瓜汁抹在乳头上。入药，为强烈泻剂。译者刚从科威特沙漠上采得7只苦西瓜，现放在书桌灯下。（2000年11月8日）

盛燃的白炽火炬

四月过去了。在过去的一个月里，我常去法里斯老人家，与赛勒玛见面，在花园里对坐长谈，细观她的美丽容颜，欣赏她的天赋才气，静听她那无声的忧愁，只觉得有无数只无形的手在把我拉向她。那每一次访问，都会向我揭示她的一重新含义和她灵魂奥秘中的一层高深秘密，致使她在我的眼前变成了一本书，我读了一行又一行，背了一节又一节，唱了一曲又一曲，却总也读不完，唱不尽。

神赐予女性以心灵美和形体美，那是既明显而又神秘的现实，我们只能用爱情理解她，用圣洁去感触她，而当我们试图用语言描绘她时，她却远离我们的视野，隐藏到迷惑和模糊的雾霭之后去了。

赛勒玛心灵、形体俱美，我如何向不认识她的人描述她呢？坐在死神翅膀阴影下的人怎么能唤来夜莺鸣啭、玫瑰细语和溪水吟唱呢？一个拖着沉重镣铐的囚俘怎能追赶黎明的微风吹拂？不过，沉默不是比说话更难过吗？既然我不能用金线条描绘赛勒玛的真实相貌，难道恐惧之意能够阻止我用浅薄词语叙述赛勒玛的一种幻影吗？行走在沙漠中的饥饿者，假若苍天不降甘露和鹌鹑，他是不会拒绝啃干面饼的。

赛勒玛身材苗条，穿着洁白长绸裙出现时，就像从窗子射进赛勒玛的容貌美并不合乎人类所制定的关于美的标准和尺度，而是一种像梦一样的奇异之美，或者说像幻影，或者说像一种神圣思想，不可丈量，无可比拟，不能界定，画师的笔描绘不出，雕刻家用大理石雕刻不成。赛勒玛的美不在于她那一头金发，而在于金发周围的圣洁光环；她的美不在于她那一对明亮的大眼睛，而在于明眸内闪烁出的亮光；她的美不在于她那玫瑰色的双唇，而在于唇间溢出的蜜糖；她的美不在于她那象牙色的脖颈，而在于脖颈微微前倾的形象。赛勒玛的美不在于她那完美的体形，而在于她的灵魂高尚得像是一柄盛燃的白炽火炬。遨游在大地与无尽天际之间。赛勒玛的美是一种诗情画意，我们只能在高雅诗篇、不朽的画作和乐曲中才能看到她的影子。才子们总是不幸的，无论他们的灵魂多么高尚，却总是被一层泪水包裹着。

去的月光。她举止缓慢、稳重，颇有些像《伊斯法罕曲》(1)。她的嗓音低沉、甜润，间或被叹息声打断，就像随着微笑波动，露珠从花冠上滴落而下一样，她的语音由绛唇间滑落而出。她的面容嘛，谁能描绘赛勒玛的面容呢？我们用什么样的字眼、词语，能够描述一张被痛苦、平静遮罩着的，而不是由透明面纱遮罩着的面容呢？我们用什么样的语言，能够谈论每时每刻都在宣布心灵秘密，每刻每时都在向观者提及一种远离这个世界的精神世界的容貌！

赛勒玛多思而寡言。不过，她的沉默是富有音乐感的，总是带着她的座客转移向遥远美梦的舞台，使之能听见自己的脉搏，可看到自己的思想幻影和情感出现在自己的眼前。

与赛勒玛品质和性格形影不离的特质是深沉、强烈的忧愁。

忧愁本是一种精神绶带，赛勒玛披上它，则使她的体态更加美丽、庄重、奇异，她的心灵之光透过布丝露出来，就像透过晨雾看到的一棵繁花盛开的大树，忧愁将我俩的灵魂紧紧联结在一起。我俩都能从对方的脸上看到自己内心的感受，都能从对方的胸中听到自己话语的回音，仿佛神灵已经把我们每个人变成了另一个人的一半，通过圣洁之手结合在一起，便成为一个完整的人；谁离开谁，都感到灵魂中有一种令人痛苦的缺憾。

一颗痛苦的心灵与另一颗有相似情感与感受的心灵结合在一起，能找到安慰与快乐，正如在远离祖国土地上的两个异乡客之间感到亲切一样。忧愁、患难之中相互贴近的心，浮华的欢乐是不能将它们分开的。心灵中用痛苦拧成的纽带要比欢乐织成的纽带牢固得多。眼泪洗刷过的爱情总是圣洁、美丽、永恒的。

————————————————————

(1) 《伊斯法罕曲》，一种乐曲，请参看纪伯伦传世经典《音乐短章》中的“伊斯法罕曲”。

暴风骤雨

过了几天，法里斯老人邀我到他家吃晚饭，我欣然前往。我的心灵很馋老天爷放在赛勒玛手中的那种圣饼。那是一种精神圣饼，我们用心中之口吞食，越吃越觉得饥饿；那是一种神奇圣饼，阿拉伯人盖斯(1)、意大利的但丁(2)、希腊的萨福(3)尝过它的滋味，不禁肝肠起火，心被熔化，那圣饼由神灵用亲吻的甜蜜和泪水的苦涩和成的面团做成，专供敏感、醒悟的心灵餐食，以便以其滋味令心灵欢欣，以其效应使心灵遭受折磨。

来到家中，我发现赛勒玛坐在花园一角的一张木椅上，头靠着一棵树干，身穿洁白长裙，像是一位幻想中的新娘，守在那个地方。我默不作声地走近她，像一个虔诚的拜火教徒坐在圣火前那样，在她的身旁坐了下来。我想说话，但发现自己张口结舌，双唇僵硬，只好沉默不语。一种无限深邃的情感，一经用具体语言表达出来，难免失却它的部分特殊意味。不过，我觉察得到，赛勒玛正在静听着我的内心自言自语；与此同时，她也从我的双眸中看到了我那颗颤抖心灵的影像。

片刻之后，法里斯老人来到花园，朝着我走来，照习惯向我伸出手来表示欢迎，似乎也想对我与赛勒玛两颗灵魂联结在一起的隐秘表示祝贺。他微笑着说：

“我的孩子，快来吃饭吧！晚饭在等着我们呢。”

我们站身来，跟着老人走去。赛勒玛用充满柔情的目光望着我，好像“我的孩子”一语唤醒了她内心的一种新的甜蜜感觉，其中包含着她对我的爱，如同母亲抱着孩子。

我们围桌坐下，边吃边喝边谈。我们坐在那个房间，津津有味地吃着各种可口美食，品尝着各种玉液琼浆，而我们的灵魂却不觉地遨游在远离这个世界的另一天地，梦想着未来，准备着应付各种可怕局面。三个人因生活志向不同，故想法各异，但他们的内心都怀有诚挚的友谊与至爱。三个人都是清白的弱者，他们感情丰富，而所知甚少，这便是心灵舞台上演出的悲剧。一位年高德劭的老人，甚爱自己的女儿，只关心女儿的幸福，一个芳龄二十岁的姑娘，对自己的未来总是近看看，远看看，注目凝视，目不转睛，以便看看究竟是什么欢乐和不幸在等待着自己；还有一个小伙子，梦想联翩，忧思重重，既没有尝过生活美酒的滋味，也没有喝过生活的酸醋，一心想鼓翼飞翔在爱情和知识的天空，但因太弱，站都站不起来。三个人在远离喧嚣城市的一座宅院里，围坐着一张精美雅致的餐桌，夜色一片寂静，天上的繁星凝视着庭院。三个人吃边喝，而天命却将苦涩与荆刺埋在了他们的盘底和杯中。

我们刚吃完饭，一个女人走了进来，对法里斯老人说：

“老爷，门外有人求见。”

老人问：

“谁呀？”

女仆回答道：

“我猜想他是大主教的家仆，老爷。”

法里斯沉默片刻，随后就像先知望着天空那样，凝视着女儿的眼睛，以便看看女儿隐藏的秘密。之后，他转过脸去，对女仆说：

“让他进来吧！”

女仆闻声离去，过了一会儿，一条汉子出现了，身着绣金长袍，髭须两端上翘，哈腰问过安好，便对法里斯说：

“大主教阁下派我用他的专用马车来接你，他请你去，有要事与你相商。”

老人站起来，脸色都变了，原本春风满面的脸忽然蒙上了一层沉思的面纱，然后走近我，用温柔、甜润的声音说：

“我希望回来时还能在这里见到你。你在这里，赛勒玛能得到安慰，说说话可以驱逐夜下的寂寞，心灵的乐曲能够消除孤单的烦闷。”

然后望着女儿，笑着问道：

“赛勒玛，不是这样吗？”

姑娘点头称是，面颊顿时稍显绯红，继而用足以与笛声比柔美的话音说：

“我会尽心尽力让我们的客人感到快乐的，爸爸！”

老人在大主教家仆的陪伴下出了门，赛勒玛凭窗而站，望着大路，直至马车的影子消隐在夜幕之中，随着车子渐渐远去，车轮声渐渐消失，马蹄的嗒嗒响声也被寂静吞没了。

赛勒玛在我对面的沙发上做下来，绿缎子的沙发布面衬托着她那洁白的长裙，她就像绿色草坪中被晨风吹弯腰的百合花。

老天有意成全我的心愿，让我在远离尘嚣的住宅与赛勒玛单独相会，更有万木护卫，一片寂静，爱情、圣洁和美的幻影自由徜徉、漫步在房舍四周。

几分钟过去了，我俩默默无言，不知所措，静静沉思，都在期盼着另一个人先开口说话。难道那就是实现相爱灵魂之间互解共通的话语吗？莫非那就是发自唇舌，使心神相互接近的声音与节拍吗？莫非没有一种东西比口说出的更高尚，比声带为之振动的更纯洁吗？那不就是将一个心灵送往另一心灵，将一颗心的低语传入另一颗心的无声寂静吗？那不就是寂静将我们从自身中解脱出来，遨游无边的精神太空，接近田园吗？我们感到自己的躯体不过是个狭窄牢笼，这个世界无异于遥远的流放地。

赛勒玛望着我，眼神里已透露出她心灵的秘密。之后，她用令人心荡神驰的镇静口吻说：

“我们到花园里去，坐在树下，观赏一下月亮爬上东山的壮景吧！”

我顺从地站起来，阻止说：

“赛勒玛，我们站在这里待到月亮升起、照亮花园不是更好吗？现在夜色笼罩着花木，我们什么也看不见呀！”

她回答说：

“黑暗即使能够遮住眼前的花草树木，但却遮挡不住心中的爱情。”

她用非同寻常的语气说了这么一句话，然后把目光转向窗子，我则默默思考着她的话，想象着每个词语的意思，琢磨着每个字的真实含义。过了一会儿，她转过脸来，凝神注视着我，仿佛对自己说出的话感到后悔，想借自己的神奇目光，从我的耳朵里收回她讲出的那句话。但是，那神奇目光的作用恰恰相反，不但收不回那些话，反倒使那些更清楚、更深刻地留在我的胸中，紧紧贴着我的心，随着我的情感起伏涌动到生命的最后一刻。

这个世界的每一件伟大、美好事物，均诞生于人内心深处的一种想法或一种感受。我们所看到的历代的作品，在其出现之前，原本都是隐藏在男子头脑中的一种想法或女子胸中的一种美好的情感……使鲜血像溪水一样流淌、奉自由作为神灵崇拜的可怕暴动，原本不过是生活在成千上万男子中的某位男子头脑中的一种浮想；令宝座倾覆、王国灭亡的痛苦战争，起初也仅仅是某个人头脑中的一个念头；改变人类生活进程的崇高学说，本来也只是才华出众的一个人心中的一种带有诗情的意向。一个想法建造了金字塔，一种情感毁灭了特洛伊城，一种念头创造了伊斯兰光荣，一句话烧毁了亚历山大城图书馆。

夜深人静时产生的一种想法，有可能带你走向光荣，也可能引你步入疯狂；一个女人的一瞥，可使你成为最幸福的人，也可能使你成为最不幸的人；一个男子说的一句话，可使你由穷变富，也可能使你由富变穷……在那静悄悄的夜里，赛勒玛说的那句话，使我像停泊在海涛与苍天之间的船一样站在过去与未来之间。一句意味深长的话将我从青年时代的昏睡和空虚中唤醒，把我的岁月带上通向死去活来的爱情舞台的一条新路。

我们来到花园里，行走在花木之间，只觉微风用它那看不见的手指抚摩着我们的脸面，鲜嫩的花和柔软的草在我们的脚下摇摆晃动。我们终于行至素馨花丛前，在一张长木椅子上默不作声地坐了下来，静听沉睡的大自然的呼吸，在透过蓝天望着我们的天目面前用甜润的叹息声揭示彼此心中的隐秘。

月亮爬上了萨尼山，月光洒遍山巅、海岸，山谷坡上的农村清楚地显现出来，仿佛无中生有，突如其来。整个黎巴嫩山脉出现在银色月华下，就像一位曲肱而枕的青年，盖着一层轻纱，肢体若隐若现。

西方诗人心目中的黎巴嫩是个梦幻般的地方。不过，就像随着亚当、夏娃被逐，天堂被遮掩起来那样，随着大卫(4)、所罗门(5)和众先知的逝去，黎巴嫩的真实面貌也渐而消隐了。黎巴嫩是一个诗般的词语，而不仅仅是一座山名，它象征着内心的一种情感，使人想象到一幅幅奇妙的美景：繁茂的杉树林，散发着袭人的清香；用青铜和大理石建成的高塔，那是光荣与伟大的标志；一群群羚羊蹒跚漫步在山冈和谷地。那天夜里，我看到黎巴嫩宛如诗意般的幻想，像白日的梦境一样呈现在我的眼前。随着我们情感的变化，我们眼前的一切东西都变了模样。当我们心灵中充满神奇的妖丽时，我们想象着一切东西都蒙上了神奇与妖丽的色彩。

赛勒玛望着我，月光照着她的面孔、脖颈和手腕，她就像美与爱之神阿施塔特的崇拜者雕刻成的一尊象牙雕像。

她问我：

“你为什么不说话呢？为什么不向我谈谈你过去的生活呢？”

我望着她那对明亮的眼睛，像突然开口说话的哑巴一样回答她说：

“我一来到这个地方就说话，难道你没有听见？自打进了花园，莫非你没有听见我说的话？你的心灵能听到百花低语和寂静唱歌，也一定能听见我的灵魂和心的呐喊声。”

她用手捂着自己的脸，然后用断断续续的声音说：

“我已听到你的声音……是的，我已听到了。我听到了发自夜的肺腑的呐喊声和发自白昼之心的高声喧嚣。”

我忘记了自己过去的生活经历，忘掉了自己的存在，忘记了一切，只知道赛勒玛，只感觉到她的存在，立即说：

“赛勒玛，我已听到了你的声音，听到了一曲起死回生、引人入胜的伟大歌声，太空中的尘埃为之波涌翻腾，大地之基因之摇晃震动。

赛勒玛合上眼，深红色的唇上绽现出一丝苦苦微笑，然后低声说：

“现在我知道了，有一种东西比天高，比海深，比生死和时光更强有力。我现在知道了那种昨天不知道，也不曾梦想过的那种东西。”

从那一时刻起，赛勒玛变得比朋友更亲密，比姐妹更亲近，比情人还可爱。她变成了一种与我的头脑形影不离的崇高思想，包围着我的心的一种温情和萦绕我心灵的一个美梦。

认为爱情必诞生于长期相处、久相厮伴的人们是多么无知啊！真正的爱情是灵魂互解的结晶；假若这种互解不能在片刻之内实现，那么，即使一年、一代也是实现不了的。

赛勒玛抬起头来，向着萨尼山与天边相接的遥远天际望去，然后说：

“昨天，你还像我的一位长兄，我放心地与你接近，在父亲在场的情况下，我可以坐在你的身旁。而现在，我觉得有了一种比兄妹关系更强烈、更甜蜜的东西。我觉得那是一种超越一切关系的奇妙情感，那是一种强烈、可怕、可爱的关系，使我的心中充满痛苦与欢乐。”

我回答她说：

“我们害怕的、我们的心胸为之颤抖的这种情感，难道不就是那种令月亮绕着地球转、地球绕着太阳转、太阳及其周围一切绕着上帝转的绝对规律的一部分吗？”

赛勒玛容光焕发，眼噙泪花，就像水仙花瓣上的露珠闪闪发光。她用手抚摩着我的头，将手指插在我的头发里，然后说：

“哪个人会相信我们的故事呢？谁相信我们在日落月出的时辰里，我们已跨越了怀疑与诚信之间的一切障碍和隘口呢？谁能相信我们初次见面的四月竟是让我们站在了生命最神圣殿堂的阳春之月呢？”

她说话时，我低着头，她的手一直在抚弄着我的头发。此时此刻，假若让我选择，我会放弃王冠和花环而选择抚弄我的头发如丝的那只柔嫩的手。

我回答说：

“人类不相信我们的故事，因为他们不知道爱情是唯一一朵不需季节合作而成长、发育的鲜花。难道让我们初次见面的是四月吗？使我们站在生命最神圣殿堂的是这一时辰吗？难道不是上帝之手在我们出生、沦为白昼与黑夜的俘虏之前，就把我们的灵魂融合在一起了吗？赛勒玛，人的生命并非从子宫里开始，也不是在坟墓前结束。这个充满月华星光的浩瀚宇宙，不乏以爱情相互拥抱的灵魂和以互解联合化一的心灵。”

赛勒玛轻轻地抽回自己的手，将电的波浪留在我的发束之中，在夜间的微风吹拂戏动下，波浪起伏翻动有增无减。我伸出双掌，捧住她那只手，就像虔诚的教徒抚摩圣坛的帷幔祈祷祝福那样，将之放在我那火热的双唇间，久久地、深深地亲吻；那热吻能用它的高温熔化人心的一切感受，能用它的甜美唤醒神灵中的一切纯真情感。

一个时辰过去了，其中的每一分钟均等同眷恋情深一年。夜色寂静，月光如水，周围是一片林木花草。当我们沉醉在忘掉一切、只晓爱情真实的境界之中时，忽然听到马蹄、车轮声在迅速地靠近我们，我们立即从那甜滋滋的昏迷中苏醒过来，由幻梦世界回到了使我们感到进退两难、困惑难堪的现实世界。我们知道法里斯老爹已从大主教家回来了，于是走出树林，等待他的到来。

马车在花园入口停下，法里斯老人下了车，低着头缓步朝我们走来。老人家如同背负重载，疲惫不堪，走到赛勒玛跟前，双手搭在她的肩上，久久凝视着她的面容，仿佛怕她的形象消失在他那昏花的双眼里。随之，老泪纵横，淌落在那他满布皱纹的面颊上，双唇抖动，绽现出凄楚的微笑，用哽咽的声音说：

“赛勒玛，过不多久……多不了几天，你就要离开爸爸的眼前，投入到另一位男子的怀抱中去了。过不了多久，上帝的教法就要把你从这个孤零零的家里带到宽广的天地中去了。到那时，这座花园将会思念你那缓慢稳重的脚步，爸爸也将变成陌生人了。赛勒玛，天命已经开口说话，愿苍天为你祝福，求苍天保佑你！”

赛勒玛听父亲这么一说，面色顿改，两眼呆滞，仿佛看到了死神的影子站立在她的面前。随即，她抽抽噎噎地哭了，像被猎人射中的鸟儿，扑扑棱棱地落在低洼地上，疼得周身颤抖不止。她用被深深痛苦打断的声音大声喊道：

“您说什么？您说的是什么意思？您想把我打发到哪儿去呀？”

赛勒玛凝视着父亲，好像她想用目光揭去掩藏他胸中秘密的那层包裹里。一分钟死一般的沉寂过去之后，赛勒玛叹了一口气，说：“我现在明白了……我全明白了……大主教夺去了您的爱女……他为这只被折断翅膀的鸟儿准备好了笼子……爸爸，这就是您的想法和意志吧？”

法里斯老人只用深深的叹息做回答。然后将赛勒玛领进厅堂，慈爱之光从不安的面容上顿泻而出。我留在树林里，一时不知如何是好，情感被困惑戏动，如同秋风横扫落叶。过了一会儿，我跟着父女俩进了厅堂。为了掩饰爱打听别人隐私的好管闲事者的外表，我握住老人的手告别，又用类似于被淹死的人望着苍穹顶上一颗明亮的星星那样的目光望了望赛勒玛一眼，然后转身出了门，父女俩谁也没有觉察到我已离开那里。但是，当我行至花园尽头时，忽听老人呼唤我，我回头望去，发现他追了出来。我立即回头迎他。当他握住我的手时，用颤抖的声音说：

“原谅我，孩子！是我使你今夜以眼泪宣告结束。不过，你将会常来看我的，不是吗？当这个地方变得空空荡荡，只留下一个老人度过痛苦的风烛残年时，你能不来看我吗？当然，风华正茂不喜风烛残年，宛如清晨不与黄昏相会，但你将常来我这里，以便让我回忆起我在你父亲身旁度过的青春时光，让我重新听到那不再属于我的生活故事，难道不是这样吗？当赛勒玛走后，只有我一个人孤单单地住在这座远离众人家宅的房子里时，你会不常来看我吗？”

老人说出最后几句话时，声音低沉、断续。当我握住他的手，默默地抖动时，我感到几滴热泪夺眶而出，滴在了我的手上。此时此刻，我的心灵颤抖起来，只觉得对他有一种做儿子的情感在胸中涌动，甜蜜而痛苦，像口渴的感觉一样直冲上双唇，然后又像难言的痛苦一样回到心的深处。我抬起头来，看见他的泪水簌簌下落，我的眼泪也夺眶而出。他稍稍弯下腰，用颤抖的双唇吻了吻我的前额，然后把脸转向宅门，说：“晚安……晚安，孩子！”

满布皱纹的老人脸上那一滴闪光的泪水，要比青年人泪水滚滚给人的心灵带来的震撼强烈得多。

青年人的滚滚泪水溢自泪水充裕的心间，而老人的泪却倾于眼角的残余泪滴，也是虚弱体内的剩余活力。青年人的眼泪像玫瑰花瓣上的露珠，而老人的眼泪则像舞动的黄叶，预示着生命的冬天已经临近。

法里斯老人的身影消隐在两扇门后。我走出了那座花园，而赛勒玛的话音依然绕在我的耳际，她的美貌像幻影一样蹒跚行走在我的眼前，老人家的眼泪也在我的手上慢慢干了。我离开那个地方，宛如亚当离别了伊甸园，但这颗心中的夏娃却没有在我的身边，当然也就不能让整个世界变成天堂了……我离开那座宅院，只觉得那是我再生的一夜，也是我首次看到死神面孔的夜晚。

太阳能用自己的热量使大地充满勃勃生机，同样也能用自己的温度使大地死亡。

————————————————————

(1) 乌姆鲁勒·盖斯（497—545），阿拉伯蒙昧时期著名诗人，七《悬诗》作者之一。

(2) 但丁（1265—1321），意大利著名诗人，《神曲》是其代表作，由《地狱》《炼狱》《天国》三个部分组成。

(3) 萨福，古希腊女诗人。有人曾把她同荷马相比，说男诗人中有荷马，女诗人中有萨福，还有人称她为第十位诗歌女神（在古希腊神话中，司文化的女神共有九位）。她共留下九卷诗。

(4) 大卫，《圣经》人物。以色列犹大族人，在公元前1世纪，生于伯利恒的以法地。他长得英俊，能写诗，会弹琴，又智勇善战。他幼时在家放羊，青年时做扫罗的战士长，后为犹大王。大卫做王四十年，先在希伯仑做犹大王，后在耶路撒冷做统一的以色列王33年。大卫妻妾众多，儿女成群。在耶路撒冷做王初期，大卫强占属下官员的美貌妻子拔示巴，她生下个儿子叫所罗门。

(5) 所罗门，《圣经》人物。大卫之子，古代以色列国王。他重知识，求智慧，人们把他看成智慧的化身。他既是政治家，又是作家和学者。所罗门做王40年。

死神宝座前

婚姻，在我们这个时代是一桩可笑又可悲的交易，完全被男青年和姑娘们的父亲们所包揽。在这场交易中，多数地方的男青年们赢利，父亲们赔钱，而被当作货物从一家移入另一家的姑娘们，则欢乐尽失，如同旧家具一样，她们就被放在房舍的角落里，面对黑暗，慢慢地消亡。

现代文明使妇女的意识稍有长进，但却因为男子们的贪婪之心普遍化，因而妇女们的痛苦有增无减。往昔，妇女是幸福的女仆；如今，她们变成了不幸的女主人。往昔，她们是走在白日光明之中的盲人；如今，她们却成了走在夜幕中的明眼人。过去，妇女们因无知而显得妩媚，因朴实而显得娴淑，因懦弱而显得强壮；如今，她们因娇美而变得丑陋，因敏感而变得肤浅，因知事而变得远离人心。她们能有一日变得美貌与知识、妖丽与德高、身材苗条与心灵坚强于一身吗？我认为精神升华是人类的法则，渐臻完美是一条缓慢的规律，但它却是一条积极有效的规律。假若妇女在某件事上前进了，而在另一件事上落后了，那是因为登上山顶的路上有障碍，那里不乏贼窝和狼穴。在这座类似于苏醒前的昏厥的山中，在这座布满过去时代泥土和未来数代种子的山中，在这充满奇异嗜好和愿望的山中，不乏这样一座城市，那里的妇女正是未来女子的象征。赛勒玛在贝鲁特将是东方新女性的代表，但她像许多生活在以前时代的人一样，成了新时代的牺牲品，就像被急流卷走的一朵花，被迫走向不幸前进的行列中。

曼苏尔贝克与赛勒玛结了婚，二人住在贝鲁特海滨的一座豪宅里，那是个社会名流、富翁聚居的区域。法里斯老人独自待在那座孤零零的住宅中，周围是花圃、果园，酷似牧羊人守着一群羊。喜筵日子过去了，洞房花烛之夜过去了，被人们称为“蜜月”的日子也过去了，留下来的便是醋酸加苦西瓜汁的日子，正像战争的显赫与辉煌，留下来的却是战死者的头颅和尸骨，横布在旷野之上……东方婚礼的豪华讲究把青年男女的心灵高高抛向天空，就像雄鹰展翅高翔云端，然后又把他们像磨盘一样丢入海底，简直就像沙滩上留下的足迹，顷刻便被浪潮抹掉。

春去夏至，接着便是金秋。我对赛勒玛的美渐而从一个青春少年对一位黄花少女的慕恋，变成一种孤儿对长眠地下的母亲英灵的无声崇拜。曾经占据我的整个身心的钟爱之情，变成了顾影自怜的盲目忧伤；曾使我热泪脱眶而出的酷恋之情，已经化为令我心滴鲜血的沮丧；曾充满我胸间的思恋呻吟之声，变成了深沉的祈祷。在寂静中，我的灵魂向苍天祈祷，祈求苍天给予赛勒玛以幸福，赐予她的丈夫以快活，让她的父亲放心。不过，我同情也好，祈祷、祝福也好，统统都是徒劳无益的。因为赛勒玛的不幸是心病，只有死神才能治愈它。她的丈夫则属于那样一种人：不费吹灰之力，便可得到一切，使生活过得舒适、宽裕、快乐，但决不会以此为满足，还常贪图得到本来不属于他们自己的东西；就这样，他们一直受着他们的贪欲折磨，直到生命尽头。我希望法里斯老人放心也是没有用的，因为他的女婿刚刚娶了他的女儿，得到了她的大笔钱财，便把老人忘得一干二净，对他弃之不理，一心只盼他一命呜呼，好把他剩余的财产全部弄到自己手里。

曼苏尔贝克很像他的叔父保罗·伽里卜大主教。他的性格也像叔父。曼苏尔贝克的心灵简直就是其叔父心灵的缩影。他叔侄俩之间只是伪善与堕落之别。大主教在他的紫色教服掩饰下实现自己的意愿，借悬挂在胸前那闪着金光的十字架满足自己的贪欲。而他的侄子，则是明目张胆、肆无忌惮地为所欲为。清晨，大主教去教堂；白日的其余时间里，他则去榨取寡母孤儿、平民百姓的钱财。曼苏尔贝克整天都在被腐朽气息污染透的阴暗的花街柳巷纵情酒色。

星期日，大主教站在祭坛前，一本正经地向信民们宣讲他自己并不遵守的训诫；而在一周里的其余日子里，他就忙于国家政治活动。他的侄子，则利用叔父的权势，把全部时光打发在与那些求职者和追求名利者的交易上。大主教是一个在夜幕掩盖下行窃的小偷，而曼苏尔贝克则是光天化日之下大摇大摆行走的骗子。

百姓就这样在这伙小偷和骗子之间惨死，就像群羊在狼的利爪和屠刀下丧命。东方各民族就这样屈从于心术不正、道德败坏之辈，于是渐而倒退，然后坠入深渊，时代匆匆而过，用其脚将之踏烂，就像铁链一样将陶器砸得粉碎……

究竟是什么让我用这么大篇幅来谈悲惨、绝望的民族呢？我本想记下一位不幸女子的故事，描绘一颗悲伤的、尚未尝到爱情的欢乐便惨遭痛苦打击的心灵……想到那位未曾拥抱过生活便被死神夺去生命的弱女子，我已不再流泪，却为什么谈起遭受压迫的无名百姓，我却泪水夺眶而出呢？难道那位弱女子不正是受压迫人们的象征吗？那位在心灵爱好与肉体桎梏之间痛苦挣扎的女子，不正像在统治者与祭司们之间受折磨的民族吗？或者说那种将一位美丽少女带往坟墓阴暗处的无形情感，不正像用黄土掩埋百姓生命的强烈暴风吗？女人之于民族，如同光之于油灯：若灯油充足，那灯光会微弱昏暗吗？

秋天过去了，金风剥光的树木，戏动着飘飞的黄叶，如同飓风戏耍着海水的泡沫。冬天哭号着走来。我在贝鲁特没有一个伙伴，伴随我的只有梦，时而将我的心灵高高抬往星空，时而又将我的心降下埋入地腹。

愁苦的心灵只有在孤寂中安宁，于是远离人们，就像受伤的羚羊离群而去，隐藏在山洞里，或者得到痊愈，或者默默死去。

有一天，我听说法里斯老人病了，我便放弃了独处，前往探望他。我躲开被车水马龙嘈杂声干扰长空静寂的大道，沿着橄榄树之间的一条小道步行而去。但见橄榄树那铅灰色的叶子上因雨滴而闪闪放光。

行至老人家，我走进门一看，只见老人躺在床上，身体瘦弱，面容憔悴，脸色蜡黄，双目深陷在双眉下，活像两个又深又暗的窟窿，病痛的魔影在那里游荡。昔日那曾经容光焕发、笑颜常驻的舒展面孔，如今紧缩着，愁眉不展，像一张皱皱巴巴的铅灰色纸，仿佛疾病在上面留下的一行行模模糊糊的奇怪字样。昔日那双温暖、柔软的手，如今已变成皮包骨头，瘦弱不堪，活像暴风中瑟瑟抖动的光秃秃的树枝。

我走近老人，问他近日可好。他把清瘦的脸转向我，颤抖的双唇上绽现出一丝凄凉的微微笑意，用似乎是从墙后传来的微弱声音说：

“去吧，孩子，到那个房间里去吧！给赛勒玛擦擦眼泪，让她平静一些，然后再把她带到这里来，让她坐在我的床边……”

我走进对面那个房间，发现赛勒玛瘫坐在一张椅子上，双手抱着头，脸埋在椅背上，屏着呼吸，以免父亲听到她的泣哭声。我缓步走近她，用近乎叹息的微弱低声呼唤她的名字。她就像被恶梦惊扰的睡梦中的人一样，惶遽地一动，随即坐正，用呆滞的目光望着我，仿佛她是在梦中看到了一个幻影，不相信是我站在那个地方。

一阵深深的沉默，仿佛它的神奇影响将我们带回到我们醉于神酒的时刻。之后，赛勒玛用指尖抹去眼泪，伤心地说：

“你看到岁月如何更替了吗？你看见时光怎样使我们迷失方向，我们又如何快步走进了这可怕洞窟了吗？就在这个地方，春天将我们聚集在了爱神的掌中；还是在这里，严冬又让我们在死神的宝座前见面。白日是多么灿烂，而这夜色又是多么黑暗……”

话未说完，她哽咽了。随后，她又用双手捂住自己的脸，仿佛往事已浮现在她的面前，而她却不想看到它。我用手抚摩着她的头发，说：

“来吧，赛勒玛，来吧！让我们在狂飙前像铁塔一样巍然屹立吧！来吧，赛勒玛，让我们在敌人面前像勇士一样挺立，用我们的胸膛，而不是用脊背迎着敌人的刀锋剑刃吧！我们倒下去，要像烈士那样壮烈；我们得胜时，要像英雄那样活着……在艰难困苦面前，坚定地忍受心灵上的折磨，总比退缩到安全、舒适的地方要高尚。在油灯四周拍翅扑火，直到化为灰烬的蛾子，要比在黑暗洞穴里平安、舒适生活的鼹鼠要尊贵。不经受冬令严寒和各种因素考验的种子，是不能够破土而出，快快活活地饱尝四月的美景的……赛勒玛，来吧！让我们迈着坚定的步伐，在这条崎岖小路上前进吧！我们要抬眼望着太阳，以免看见散落在乱石中的骷髅和穿行在荆棘之间的毒蛇。假若恐惧会使我们在半路上站下来，黑夜里的幻影就会让我们听到奚落和嘲讽的呐喊声；如果我们勇敢地登上山顶，宇宙的灵魂就会与我们一道同唱欢乐凯歌……赛勒玛，你不要难过，不要悲伤，擦干眼泪，拂去脸上的愁云。起来，让我们坐在你父亲的床边，因为他的生命就是你的生命，你的微微笑容能使他病愈康复。”

她用充满温情、怜悯的目光望了我一眼，然后说：

“你的两眼里饱含失意、绝望之情，怎能要求我忍耐坚强呢？一个饥饿之人能把自己的面饼让给另一饥民吗？一个急需药品的病夫能将自己的药给另一病人吗？”

说罢，赛勒玛站起来，然后低着头向她父亲的卧室走去，我紧随其后。我俩坐在老人的病榻旁，赛勒玛强作欢颜，竭力佯装平静，老人也装作快慰、强壮的模样，然而彼此都能感受到对方痛苦的脆弱，也能听到对方的心灵在呻吟。父女俩就像是两种彼此相似的力量，正在寂静之中相互消亡着。父亲已病入膏盲，因可怜女儿的不幸而更趋衰竭；女儿深爱父亲，因眼见父亲临危而由衷痛苦。一颗即将告别人世的心与一颗完全绝望的心，在爱神和死神的面前相互拥抱在一起。此时此刻，我被夹在两颗心中间，心中感到无比悲哀，深切体会到那两颗心中的忧苦。天命之手把三个人聚集在一起，尔后又用力紧攥，直至将他们捏碎：老人像一座被洪流冲垮的老房子；姑娘好像一朵被镰刀砍断枝茎的百合花；还有一个青年，就像被大雪压弯了腰的幼苗。我们都像是天命之手中的玩具。

这时，老人在被窝里动了动，然后把瘦骨嶙峋、青筋凸露的手伸向赛勒玛，声音里充满一位父亲心中的全部慈祥和温情，同时饱含一个病人的所有疾苦与病痛，说道：

“赛勒玛，让爸爸攥攥你的手。”

赛勒玛伸过手去，让父亲攥住。老人温情地攥着女儿的手，说：

“孩子，对过去的日子，我感到心满意足，我活了这么大年纪，品尝过了四季鲜果，尝尽了日夜带来的欢乐。少年时代，我曾扑蝶戏耍；青年时代，我曾拥抱爱神；人到中年，我集聚起万贯家财。

在人生的各个阶段，我都是那样快乐、欢娱。赛勒玛，你母亲辞世时，你还未满三岁，但她却能把你当作珍宝留给了我。你像新月那样迅速长大，你母亲的容貌反映在你的脸上，就像星光倒映在平静的水池中。你母亲的品性和道德，见于你的言行里，就像透过薄纱能看见金饰一样。孩子，有你已足以使我深得慰藉，因为你像你母亲一样俊秀、聪颖……如今，我已成年迈老翁，老人们将在死神的温柔翅膀下得以安息。孩子，你不要难过！因为爸爸活着已看见你长成了一个漂亮的大姑娘。孩子，你该高兴呀！因为我死后仍然以你而活着。我现在就走与明天或后天走都是一样的。因为我们的岁月就像秋天的黄叶，将在太阳下飘落飞撒。假若时辰迅速带我奔向永恒世界，那是因为它知道我的灵魂迫切期望与你的母亲相见……”

老人用充满恋情与希望的甘甜语调说出那后几句话，忧虑密布的脸上闪烁着童子眼中闪现出来的亮光。他伸手从头旁边的靠枕间掏出一帧嵌在金边镜框中的小幅旧肖像，那镜框的四边因手掌常触摸而变得光滑闪亮，边框上的花纹也被唇吻得模糊不清。老人目不转睛地望着肖像，说：

“孩子，靠近我一点儿，我让你看看你母亲的影像，看看她留在这张相纸上的倩影。”

赛勒玛靠近父亲，父亲擦去她眼角的泪水，以免防碍她看见那帧模模糊糊的肖像。她久久凝视着，仿佛那是一面镜子，照出了她的精神和面容。之后，她把肖像贴近双唇，热切地吻了又吻，然后大声喊道：

“妈！妈妈！妈妈！”

她没说别的，随后又把肖像放在她那颤抖的双唇上，仿佛她想用她那灼热的气息让母亲复活似的……

人的双唇能够说出的最甜蜜的字眼，便是“母亲”，最美的呼唤声，那就是“妈妈”。“妈妈”，这是一个简单而意义却深广无比的字眼，其中充满着希望、慈爱、怜悯和人的心灵中所有亲密、甘甜和美好的情感。在人的生命中，母亲就是一切：悲伤时，母亲是慰藉；沮丧时，母亲是希望；软弱时，母亲是力量，母亲是同情、怜悯、慈爱、宽恕的源泉。失去母亲的人，便失去了自己的头所依靠的胸膛，失去了为自己祝福的手，失去了守护自己的眼睛……

大自然界的一切，无不象征着和谈论着母性。太阳乃大地之母，以自己的热孕育大地，用自己的光拥抱大地。傍晚，太阳用海浪低吟、百鸟鸣啭和溪水的歌声将大地送入梦乡之后，自己方才离去。大地是万木百花之母，是大地生养了它们，待它们长大之后才断奶。万木百花又是香甜果实和生机勃勃的种子的母亲。而宇宙间一切存在的母亲，则是那充满美和爱的无始无终、永恒不灭的绝对精神。

赛勒玛不认识自己的母亲，因为母亲去世时她还很小。当她看见母亲的肖像时，激动之情难抑，情不自禁地大声呼叫“妈妈”。因为“妈妈”这个字眼藏在我们的心中，就像果核埋在地心里；在我们悲伤、欢乐之时，就会从我们唇间迸发出来，就像玫瑰花香不论晴雨都会由芳蕊洒露。

赛勒玛眷恋凝视着母亲的肖像，热切地亲吻，然后将之紧贴在她那激烈起伏的胸脯上，然后叹息起来，随着每一声的叹息，她的力量便失去一部分。终于，她那消瘦的体躯里失去了活力，瘫倒在父亲的病榻旁。老人双手抚摩着她的头，说：

“孩子，我已让你从这相片上看到了你母亲的影像。现在，你就听我把她的话讲给你听吧！”

赛勒玛抬起头，酷似巢中的雏鸟听到母鸟双翅在树枝间扇动的声音时那样，望着父亲，凝神细听，仿佛她的整个身心都变成了凝视的眼睛和聪慧的耳朵。

父亲说：

“你还是个吃奶的婴儿时，你的母亲便失去了她的老父亲。她为你外公的亡故而悲伤，她像一个坚忍的有理智的人那样哭泣。但是，她刚从你外公的坟上回到家中，便在这个房间里，坐在我的身旁，双手捧着我的手，说：‘法里斯，我的父亲走了，我也就只有你了；有你在，就是我的慰藉。多情善感的心，就像枝杈繁盛的杉树，一条健壮枝杈失去了，杉树会感到疼痛，但不会死去，而是把自己的活力转到旁边的枝杈上，使之成长、壮大，继之用茂盛的嫩叶遮盖住被遮断的枝杈留下伤疤。’孩子，这就是你母亲痛失你外公之时所说的话。赛勒玛，这也是死神把我的躯体投入宁静的墓穴中和把我的灵魂引向上帝那里之时，你应该说的话。”

赛勒玛悲痛欲绝，说道：

“母亲失去了自己的父亲，还有你留在她的身边，而我一旦失去了你，我的身边还有谁呢？外公辞别了人间，母亲得到了一位诚心待她的忠诚、高尚的丈夫的庇护；此外，还有一个婴儿用小脑袋拱蹭她的奶子，用小胳膊搂抱她的脖子。可是，我一旦失去了你，爸爸，还有谁和我在一起呢？爸爸，你不但是我的父亲，也是我的母亲，是我少年时代的伙伴，又是我青年时代的良师益友；你若离去，谁又能替代得了你呢？”

说完，赛勒玛用噙着泪花的眼睛望着我，又用右手拉住我的衣角，说：

“爸爸，我只有这么一位朋友，别无他伴。你离我去时，他像我一样饱受着折磨，我能从他这里得到安慰吗？一个心已碎裂的人，怎么可能去抚慰一颗碎裂的心呢？一位悲伤的女子，也绝对承受不住邻居的悲伤，同样，鸽子不能用被折断了的翅膀飞翔。他是我心灵的伙伴，但我的忧伤使他肩负重担，把他的腰压弯了。我的泪水模糊了他的双眼，使他看到的只有一片黑暗。他是兄弟，我爱他，他也爱我；但他和所有兄弟一样，只能与我共同承受灾难，却无力减轻之；只能以哭泣相助，使泪水更苦涩，令心中火更盛。”

我听着赛勒玛的话，难抑情绪激动，胸口憋闷，只觉得肋骨几乎要崩裂，化成无数喉咙和嘴巴，老人则望着她，他那瘦弱的体躯在靠枕和褥垫之间缓慢下滑，疲惫的心灵在颤抖，活像风中残烛。他张开双臂，平静地说：

“让我平平安安地走吧，孩子！我的双目已看到云外田地，我不会把眼光移离那些仙洞。让我飞走吧，我已用翅膀打碎了牢笼的栅栏……你母亲已在呼唤我，赛勒玛！你不要阻拦我……看哪，海面上风平雾散，船已张起风帆，准备起航了！你不要阻止船起航，不要夺船舵。让我的体躯与那些长眠的人一起安息，让我的灵魂苏醒吧！因为黎明已经到来，幻梦已经结束……用你的灵魂亲吻我的灵魂吧……给我一个饱含希望的亲吻，不要把一滴苦汁洒在我的身上，以免妨碍百花和香草从我身上吸取营养成分。不要把失望的泪珠滴在我的手上，因为它会在我的坟墓上生出荆棘；不要把悲伤的叹息画在我的前额上，因为黎明的微风吹来看见那画痕时，它便不肯把我的骨尘带到绿色草原上去……孩子，我生时爱你，死后也将爱你。我的灵魂会永远在你身边，保护你，关照你。”

老人望了望我，眼睛稍稍合上，我发现他的眼睛已经变成了两道灰色的线条。之后，就连寂静的太空也在窃听着他对我说：

“孩子，你呢，你就做赛勒玛的兄弟吧，像你父亲和我之间的关系一样。艰难时刻，你要守在她的身边，做她的终生朋友。不要让她苦恼伤心，因为痛悼死者是先辈留下的陋习。要对她说些开心的话，唱些生活的欢歌，她就会感到高兴，乐以忘忧……告诉你父亲，让他记起我。你一问他，他就会把我们青年时代展翅翱翔云端的情景告诉你……告诉你父亲，就说直到我生命的最后时刻，我还通过他的儿子表达着对他的敬慕之情……”

老人沉默片刻，而他的声音一直回荡在四壁之间。然后，他望望我，又瞧瞧赛勒玛，低声说：

“再不要医生用他的药面延长我的囚期了，因为奴役期已经结束。我的灵魂已在寻求宇宙的自由。不要让祭司站在我的床边，纵然我有过错，他的咒语也不能为我赎罪；即使我清白无辜，他的咒符也不能送我迅速进入天堂。人类的意志不能改变天意，星相家无法让星斗改道。我死之后，医生和祭司们想怎么办，就随他们的便吧！大海的波涛咆哮不止，而船依旧前进，直至航行到岸边……”

那一可怕的夜已过去一半时间，法里斯老人在黑暗中挣扎着睁开他那深陷的眼睛，那是最后一次睁眼，将目光转向伏在病榻旁的女儿。老人想说些什么，但未能说出，因为死神已吞饮了他的声音，只有几个字眼从他的唇间吐出，活像深深的喘息：

“夜……过去了……天亮了……赛勒玛……赛勒玛……”

旋即，老人低下头去，面色惨白，唇边溢出微微笑意，灵魂离开了肉体。

赛勒玛伸手去摸父亲的手，发觉那手已经冰凉。她抬起头来，朝父亲望去，发现他的面容已经罩上了死亡的面纱。此时此刻，生命在赛勒玛的体内已经凝固，眼里的泪水也已干枯。她一动未动，既没有喊叫，也没有叹息，而是像雕像似的呆滞的两眼注视着父亲那静止的遗体。随后她的肢体就像湿衣服一样松软下来，继而瘫倒，前额触及到地面。她平静地说：

“主啊，求你怜悯，让所有被折断的翅膀强健起来吧！”

＊＊＊

法里斯老人告别了人间，永恒世界拥抱了他的灵魂，大地收回了他的躯体。曼苏尔贝克占据了法里斯的钱财，而他的女儿仍然是苦难的俘虏。在赛勒玛看来，生活是恐惧在她眼前演出的可怕悲剧。

我依旧徘徊在幻梦与忧思之间。日夜轮番扰我，酷似兀鹰、秃鹫挣食猎物的肉。我多么想把自己埋在旧书堆里，以期与先人们的幻影为伴；我又多少次试图忘却自己的现状，借读经典返回古代的舞台。然而这一切毫无作用，却像用油灭火，火烧得更旺。我从先人的行列中看到的只有黑影，从各民族歌乐里听到的只有哭号。在我看来，《约伯记》(1)比大卫的乐声更美；《耶利米哀歌》(2)比所罗门的《雅歌》更动听；“巴门劫难”(3)在我心灵中引起的震撼比阿拔斯王朝(4)的辉煌事业更强烈；伊本·祖莱克的长诗比海亚姆(5)的四行诗更动人；如今，《哈姆雷特》(6)的故事，比所有作品都贴近我的心。

就这样，绝望情绪消弱了我们的视力；除了自己的可怕身影，我们什么都看不见。就这样，失望情感堵塞了我们的耳朵；除了自己那紊乱的心搏声，我们什么都听不到。

————————————————————

(1) 《约伯记》是《圣经·旧约》中的一卷书，属《圣录》，为犹太智慧之书。作者不详。写作时间约在公元前5世纪。书中描写义人约伯坚信上帝的故事。

(2) 《耶利米哀歌》是《圣经·旧约》中的一卷书，属《圣录》。书中描绘在巴比伦王国攻占下的犹太民族的悲惨之景，抒发了作者对耶路撒冷失陷的哀伤之情。

(3) “巴门劫难”指巴尔马克家族悲剧。巴尔马克家族本是一个伊朗血统的家族。巴尔马克兄弟迁居巴士拉，改信伊斯兰教，后在阿拔斯王朝任要职，深得哈里发哈伦·拉希德信任，得势达17年。803年哈里发的宠臣贾法尔·巴尔马克被处决，全家下狱，财产充公。其父、兄皆死于狱中。

(4) 统治巴格达的阿拔斯王朝（750-1258），共经历了39任国王。该时期，是阿拉伯帝国的鼎盛时期，《一千零一夜》中有许多关于这一时期的故事。

(5) 海亚姆（1048-1122），波斯诗人、哲学家、天文学家。生前不以诗闻名，他逝世50年之后才有人提到他写的四行诗。四行诗是伊朗传统的诗体，第一、二、四行押尾韵，类似中国的绝句。我国有郭沫若1928年据英国译本的转译本，书名《鲁拜集》。“鲁拜”为阿拉伯语，意为四行诗。

(6) 《哈姆雷特》是莎士比亚系列悲剧之一，发表于1602年。写一个年轻的人文主义者面对邪恶势力，在怀疑、犹豫之后终于为“重整乾坤”而献出生命。